<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">9/3/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ione Adair, 1976-09-3, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:02:58</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Adair, Ione</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>County assessor, teacher, postal clerk, timber homesteader</occupation>
      <birthyear>1883</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow, Bovill, Fortynine Meadows</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Oregon and Indiana (1893); family lived in the McConnell mansion
         (1900-36)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fishing"&gt;fishing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mansions"&gt;mansions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Psychiana"&gt;Psychiana&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Fortynine Meadows"&gt;Fortynine Meadows&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13603</file_name>
      <mp3>13604.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13604.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Mother was Tubercular; The Family Hack; Family Fishing and Hunting</title>
            <synopsis>Mother preferred convenience of home to woods life: she was tubercular. The girls
               enjoyed woods and wearing overalls. The family hack. Mother usually had a woman staying
               with her. Quiggly the dog got sick after father clipped her. Family fishing and hunting:
               mother an excellent shot, which made father proud.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Outdoor Life in the Summer; Women's Swimming Suits; Fishing Streams</title>
            <synopsis>Pleasures of outdoor life in summer. Collins store served homesteaders. Women's swimming
               suits, bating the Victorian Era - Victorian fashions. Fishing streams with father.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Adair Family History</title>
            <synopsis>Mother raised on a farm near Swan, Indiana. One of Mother's hips was enlarged from
               work. Mother's dresses. Father was an orphan raised by a minister. Dancing and card
               playing were taboo; dates had to leave at ten. Two girls were not allowed to play
               at the Methodist service because they'd been to a university dance the night before;
               dislike of violin music. Bernadine's desire as a child to get under the saloon doors.
               Father had one drink with his hunting friends on New Year's Day. Adair's made a batch
               of dandelion wine during prohibition; the sleuthing of Frank C. Moore, county attorney,
               (continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Decoration Day; Making Wine</title>
            <synopsis>On Decoration Day they buried the wine under the bushes, then cached it in the cellar.
               Father made the wine because he was afraid they wouldn't be able to get any if they
               needed it.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2220</time>
            <title>Methodist Revivals; Arguments with the Sunday School Teacher</title>
            <synopsis>Bernadine resigned from the Methodist Church because of the damnation they preached
               at revivals, and Father let her, despite his dream that she wouldn't go to heaven.
               A boy who swore at his father for omitting the grace before meal. Emotionalism of
               revivals. Bernadine's arguments with the Sunday school teacher; she was independent.
               The parents convinced her by letting her make her own decision.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2580</time>
            <title>Homesteading East of Clarkia; Living with the Abe Frei Family; Living in the Winter</title>
            <synopsis>Homesteading community east of Clarkia. Father knew the locator. She taught two terms
               at Collins to pay costs on her claim, living with Abe Frei family. Locating of homestead
               cabins Strength of Griffin, the drayman. Living in the winter - a homesteader on snowshoes.
               A homesteader who took advantage of others; a trick on her. (continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Homesteading Life; Naming of Adair Creek; Easter dinner; Cooking for Fire Crews</title>
            <synopsis>Scaring a homesteader with a cougar sound. Naming of Adair Creek. Distance between
               homesteads restricted community life. Chicken for Easter dinner. Myrtle's birthday
               party on the cabin roof, with pepper in the boys' fudge; the boys' will on cigarette
               paper. Carter helped them through the winter as a hired hand. How she started cooking
               for the fire crews. She returned to the homestead after the fire because the land
               wasn't burned; she was there three successive summers. How Bernadine was entertained
               on Ione's homestead. Beaus visited the girls on the Collins homestead.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5220</time>
            <title>Loss of Homestead</title>
            <synopsis>Loss of their homesteads after testifying at Wallace, because the government took
               the word of its investigator, who said people couldn't live on those places.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Government Inspector; Price for Timber; Purchase of McConnell Mansion</title>
            <synopsis>Her later meeting with Ashley T. Roach, who confessed he was wrong as a government
               inspector to speak against her homestead. The homesteaders lived up to the law. The
               homesteaders planned to sell to the lumber company. Price for timber. Father's purchase
               of McConnell Mansion.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6000</time>
            <title>Encounter with Frank B. Robinson</title>
            <synopsis>Run-in with Frank Robinson in Bolles' drugstore.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6240</time>
            <title>Riding Stride-Saddle; Quilt Pieces</title>
            <synopsis>To wear divided skirts for riding stride-saddle was most unusual. Getting across boggy
               meadows in spring. Quilt pieces from the conductor at Avery.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Pike's Peak Car</title>
            <synopsis>Father broke his muffler touring with his Pike's Peak car. His love of the Pike's
               motor. How he was converted to a closed car. Bernadine's idea to have the horn inside
               the car.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7080</time>
            <title>Deadly Nightshade</title>
            <synopsis>Hardiness of deadly nightshade which grew at the Mansion.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Bernadine Cornelison. Timber homesteading at Fortynine Meadows; loss of claim.
         Relationship with parents. Victorian manners and dress. Methodist church and revivals.
         Prohibition. Family cars. 9-3-76 2 hr 51p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         IONE ADAIR: She didn't like the homesteading life.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: How come?
         
         IA:  She preferred being at home here in her own kitchen and in her own
         home where she could do things, and had things handy. And when you're
         on the homestead you had to just what you had, and nothing else.
         And she didn't like it. But I did. Youngsters all liked it where they
         could put on overalls wherievery one else was wearing dresses, and they
         could put on overalls and run around and climb qvddo as they pleased.
         They liked it. Mamma didn't!
         
         SS:  Was your mother what you would call a proper Victorian lady?
         
         IA:  A what?
         
         SS:  Was she a proper Victorian lady? Because that was the Victorian days
         back then, they say.
         
         IA:  Would you say she was proper Victorian, Bernadine?
         
         BERNADINE CORNELISON: She wasn't and she wasn't narrow she liked convenient and she
         didn't particularly like the.
         
         IA:  You hurry up and come in here, so I can hear you.
         
         SS:  She said she wasn't.. Your mother wasn't, but she liked
         things convenient.
         
         IA:  She liked everything convenient and that's one reason that she didn't
         like homesteading. But we always went out there just as soon as
         school was out, or very soon after, and came in along in August, along
         about - between the first and the middle of August. And we were al
         ways so surprised when we got in to find that the haying was all done
         and the harvesting was mostly finished, by the time we got in, and we
         hadn't seen it.
         
         BC:  Mother wasn't well. She was tuberculfcif.
         
         SS:  Oh, she wasn't well?
         
         BC:  And she 
         
         SS:  Was she sick much of the time?
         
         SS:  Hardship.
         
         SS:  But, you know, it seems like such a difference in the generations,
         because if in your mother's generation, women didn't care for that
         kind of life, but the children liked it.
         
         IA:  The children liked it. Mothers didn't. It was principally the con
         venience of things. And there was a little store out there that we
         could get things, but we usually packed most everything that we used
         from Moscow when we went out. Dad had a special hack made for us,
         and in that we could pack a good many boxes of different kinds of
         things. And this hack- he had to get a special bodied hack and in or
         der to protect us from the weather and all he had the plumbers put
         posts up and across out of piping and then fastened the top on that.
         And the sides- if we wanted to put sideburns down, we co uld put side
         burns down. And that was a very convenient way to ge t out there. And
         Mother usually had someone out with her during the summertime.
         Mrs. Leighman spent a time out there with her. Mrs. McConnell spent
         some time and we had a hired girl that spent some time with us and
         Mrs. Owings spent some time with us out there. So a great deal of the
         time we had additional company for Mother. And Mother and the company
         and the smallest youngster usually rode in the little single buggy
         and the rest of us rode in the hack. But one time, we had a dog
         named Quiggly, and there was a professor at the University named
         Quiggly, and he had a head of very curly, light hair, and this dog
         was a very curly dog, although she was brown and white, but we called
         her Quiggly on account of the curls. And Dad decided in the summer
         that it was going to be too hot for the dog out there and for the trip
         so he clipped her. And she was so ashamed after she was clipped, she
         crawled back under the big porch over there and stayed til we could
         hardly beg her out or get her out to get her into the convenience to
         take her out there! Well, we got out to what was Little Bear
         Creek, that's this side of Anderson out there, or what used to be An
         derson in those days, and she got to playing in the wat er, in the
         stream. We all went back in under the bridge to eat our lunch in the
         shade and she got to playing in the water and got soaking wet and we
         picked her up and put her in the back of the rig in that wet condition.
         And after we got out to the cabin the old dog began to wheeze and bark
         and wheeze and wheeze, and we didn't know what to do. Dad always had
         a medicine case that he gave Mother to take out for us, for the young
         sters if we needed anything, so Mother got out the medicine ca se and
         she looked up the fever tablets and she forced these fever tablets
         down the dog. And we were out by the- pretty close to the first of
         the week and Dad always came out the last of the week,hunt and
         fished in the stream there,the Little Potlatch. At that time it had
         lots of fish in it. And he fished and he hunted for pheasants and
         there was no limits on pheasants and no limit on fish, you could have
         what you wanted. And there was usually enough to take care of everything.
         he could get. Well, he was supposed to be out there the last
         of the week and here was this sick dog on his hands. So Mother dosed
         him and dosed him until the time Dad got out the dog was able to
         get up and wag his tail and greet him.(Laughter) And so he took him
         hunting and fishing. But that was one reason that Mother didn't like
         the woods.
         
         BC:  Mother was a very fine marksman, she'd any target, and she'd go
         out before breakfast, she couldn't walk very far and she had no trans-
         portation but she'd go out and bring in pheasants.
         
         IA:  Dad got a little single barreled shotgun, and he was so proud of the
         way she could shoot; she could get birds anytime she took a notion.
         
         BC:  That's all the fresh meat we had out there, you see. 
         
         SS:  How did you usually pass the summers out there? What did you do for
         entertainment? Were you a teenager when you first went out there?
         
         IA:  Yes.
         
         SS:  What did you do for your pleasure?
         
         IA:  For pleasure?
         
         SS:  Yeah, to enjoy yourself out there?
         
         IA:  You could fish, you could hunt, you could the streams, and you
         could berry- there were always berries there, o-tt nd huckleberries
         later in the year. And once when we were out there Mother- we
         ran out of jellies or syrups for pancakes; you ate lots of hotcakes.
         They were so easy to fix, so easy to take care of and you could usually
         get some of the larger girls to make the cakes for the rest of them.
         So Mother had a chance there of resting while the rest of us worked.
         Then there was a little store about a mile or maybe a mile and a quarter
         called Collins. If you've been in that part of the country you
         know.
         
         SS:  Yes, I know what it is.
         
         IA:  Well, the old store and the buildings were at Collins, and that was
         about a mile or maybe a mile and a quarter from our cabin. And we
         could go up there and there was usually lots of people around the
         store; homesteaders coming in from their homes back in the Clarkia
         country, and then the people at the town itself, and it took some
         time to walk up and it took some time to walk back, so it kept you
         busy.
         
         BC:  Right behind our cottage, or cabin, we called it, was a stream that
         was deep enough, had it blocked up, to go swimming.
         
         SS:  Oh, really?
         
         BC:  And the suits: describe the swimming suits.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Describe the swimming suits.
         
         IA:  Oh, the swimming suits!
         
         BC:  Be full dress!
         
         IA:  Ashamed of even think of them now! But they were suits! And a swim
         ming suit- they had little under panties-
         
         BC:  Bloomers!
         
         BC:  Bloomers! They were bloomers!
         
         IA:  That came down to your knees, and the little pant was fastened to a
         top vest, well, it would be just like a sweater without sleeves nowdays.
         But it had sleeves down to here on it and practically lownecked
         for that day.(Laughter) And the back- it came clear up across your
         back and over all from the waist down over these small trousers that
         hooked in at the bottom, was a little skirt, made of the same material
         Mine was an old gold skirt and black trousers and a black top with a
         little old gold ring around the top. That was a suit!
         
         BC:  Didn't swim much.
         
         IA:  Now when you think of these bikinis and nothings that they wear, you
         just wonder what the youngsters think. Well, they haven't known anything else.
         
         BC:  It's really sensible. All that clothes.
         
         SS:  You couldn't swim very well with all that clothing on.
         
         BC:  They wore stockings!
         
         SS:  Stockings?
         
         IA:  Oh, yes, you had to have stockings on.
         
         BC:  Black stockings.
         
         SS:  That sounds a little excessive to me.
         
         IA:  Black stockings, and the elastic at the top, and that kept your stoc
         kings up. Black stockings and you usually had swimming shoes of some
         sort. You could either get old shoes and wear them or old slippers
         and wear them, or you could wear these canvas; regular swim shoes.
         
         SS:  That's what I mean, when I say Victorian, because it seems like such
         a different age as far as what was considered proper.
         
         IA:  This was a different age. You may call it Victorian. When I think
         of Victorian, I think back farther than that, farther back than Vic
         torian. Mother was not a Victorian, in my sense of the word because
         Victorian was still farther back.
         
         BC:  Mother was born about 1858, back in the Victorian
         
         IA:  Uh-huh, the end.
         
         SS:  I think the turn of the century, the way I read- look at it, but that's
         from now-looking back at it from here- the turn of the century seems
         like the last part of the Victorian age.
         
         IA:  There was quite a change between the older people at that time and my
         mother's generation and our generation and quite a bit between mine
         and yours.
         
         What do you think of the changes being between her generation and
         yours? Between your mother's and yours?
         
         IA:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS:  How do you think of that change?
         
         IA:  Well, I think it was for the better. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  I mean what was the change?
         
         IA:  What was the change?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         IA:  Well,-
         
         BC:  Hobbles. Long skirts. High button shoes.
         
         IA:  Huh. All shoes, as Bernadine says were high buttoned- or high laced
         shoes came in after that. The high buttoned shoes came on first.
         Then the high laced shoes. And your shoes came pretty well up
         on the leg. And my hunting boots came up to my knees. And my fishing
         boots- I used the hunting boots for both fishing and hunting unless I
         was going with my father and I had a rubber complete overall- a rubber
         suit. And he had one. And we used to fish the streams together. He'd
         work one side of it and I'd work the other and we'd fish the streams
         together. Sometimes we'd get in where the water was so deep that we'd
         have to support each other in order to get- that was the time when the
         Elk River was much larger and deeper than it is now.
         
         BC:  I just thought of something: Mother's better dresses, mutton leg sleeves. Do
         you know what that is?
         
         SS:  What?
         
         BC: Mutton leg sleeves.
         
         SS:  Mutton legs?
         
         BC: They were real big up here then very narrow down here; puffed. And
         bustles.
         
         SS:  Bustles?
         
         SS:  What are they?
         
         BC:  HO, hO, ho! You make me feel so old. They extended your rear!
         
         SS:  Oh, yes, yes. I know. I know what you mean. I just didn't know what
         the word for it was. (Chuckles)
         
         nicest clothes had bustles and mutton leg sleeves. This big puff here.
         
         IA:  What book were we looking at the other day that had the pictures of
         those old mutton leg sleeves in it? I think it was the Time Magazine.
         
         BC:  ffnever had You didn't play cards. You'd read aloud in the
         evening.
         
         SS:  Would she dress up out on the homestead?
         
         IA:  Oh, no.
         
         SS:  At all?
         
         IA:  She was always well dressed but not with the mutton leg and the bustle.
         
         SS:  Did you say they'd play cards and read?
         
         IA:  They read but not play cards.
         
         SS:  Well, you know, I'm interested too in the difference in values between
         her generation and yours. For instance, it seems like your independence
         in going out and taking a homestead yourself was a little bit different
         than the attitude of your parents' generation.
         
         IA:  Mother was raised in the country in a little place that was called
         Swan , Indiana. I think it had possibly a store and a school and
         maybe two or three houses. It was just a little joint, small, country
         stopover. And she was raised- her father and her brother had farms
         out about a mile or a mile and a half from the town. And she was
         raised- and she walked from the home to the school each day. And
         Mother had one large hip- we talk about bustles- she had this one large
         hip, and she had to have a pad made on the other in order to hold the
         dresses out in the shape they should. And the pad was necessity
         this one large hip and she claimed that the hip was - the
         enlarged hip was from two reasons; one was from carrying the milk
         buckets and cream buckets from the barns to the house, which was quite
         a long distance, especially if you're carrying something, and the
         other was carrying her school books. She always carried them over the
         one hip, and she claimed that that was the reason ' one hip was so
         much larger than the other. That was her reason for that. But she
         was not Victorian, but she was that in-between; she still wore her
         dresses that came to her shoetops. You would be surprised if you
         ever saw Mother in anything but a dress that came to her shoetops. And
         she always wore rather dark colored gingham dresses. Once we got her
         a pink dress and it was just beautiful on her. Her hair was turning
         gray and this pink and the gray hair was just beautiful. She liked
         it herself after she got it on and wore it. And a neighbor, Mrs. Shoe
         across the driveway here on the hill,over here where the little house
         is on now, she saw Mother's pink dress and she said she liked it
         so well that she got her a pink dress.
         
         BC:  I remember one dress of Mother's was green taffeta, not a dark g reen,
         a lovely shade of green, with little pink squares in it, little lines,
         just lines. Mother was hat conscious, she wore beautiful hats.
         
         SS:  When she grew up, were her parents farmers?
         
         SS:  So she probably had to work some on the farm herself. Help out a lit
         tle?
         
         IA:  No, she didn't have the health. She was never strong enough for any
         thing like that. And, as I say, she carried the milk- that was her
         job, as the men milked was to see that the milk was brought up to the
         house and put in the cellar. And her mother took care of the things in
         the cellar.
         
         BC:  That generation was quite against card playing. Now, Father, when I
         was little,,he was an orphan, he'd been raised by a minister, but he
         wouldn't allow us to have playing cards, we could have Authors or
         Flinch or something like that, but no playing cards. We didn't get
         to playing cardsfcill we were about in college, and dancing was taboo.
         And when I was in highschool and entering college, there was a very
         strict time limit on when you ended a date. lone would call around if
         I had a date in the parlor, ten o'clock she would rap on the door,
         "Ten o'clock, ten o'clock." my boyto leave. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  That sounds strict.
         
         BC:  Well, they were strict.
         
         IA:  You had a certain amount of discipline, which I don't think the young
         sters have nowdays; or very little of it.
         
         BC:  Well, it wasn't please/your parents,
         you gave up your date at ten o'clock. You'd go to movies. Go down
         and have an ice cream soda.
         
         SS:  Were they religious? Your parents?
         
         BC:  Not especially.
         
         So this was less a matter of religious conviction than of what was
         right and proper.
         
         It was right and proper, and we went to Sunday School.This was the
         same with a great many of the older people. The Methodists used to
         use that old church that's down at the corner of Sixth and Jefferson.
         That was the First Methodist Church in Moscow, and the church people
         were very strict about those things. No dancing and no card playing.
         That was their idea of religion. In fact, we had a superintendent
         at the schools at that time by the name of Mr, Hedley, used to live
         in this big house up on- let's see- it's Hays and B, I believe, possibly
         C, but it was a large brown house up there that was the old Hedley
         home, and Mr. and Mrs. Hedley came to town and they were very well liked
         and he was finally appointed Superintendent of the Schools. And the
         congregation wanted music, and a change of music than what the old
         superintendents liked and all. So someone got acquainted with
         Cuddy - and ummm, I've forgotten the girl's name that was with her, it
         was Beth something, and they were students at the University. Marie
         sang very nicely and Marie - and the friend played the violin. So they
         asked the girls to sing and play at the services that morning. Well,
         the morning came and the girls appeared ready for their part of the pro
         gram. In the meantime, Mr. Hedley had found out that t here had b een
         a dance at the university the night before and both those girls had
         gone to the dance, and he would not allow them to play on that Sunday.
         So the girls want home. Now that was his idea and a g reat many of
         the others had the same idea, of course, but part of the congregation
         were beginning to get the more modern feeling of the church. An ice
         cream social would be alright, but a violin in the church - they played
         violins at the saloons! And you're not going to have violin music in
         the church! That's all there is to it! So Mr. Hedley turned 'em loose.
         
         SS:  The very idea of attending a dance was wrong?
         
         IA:  Yes.
         
         SS:  To go to a dance.
         
         IA:  That was it. And besides, violin music belonged in the saloons. And
         you could hear that every time. We had lots of saloons in Moscow at
         that time, and you would always hear the Violins; the fiddle they cal
         led it, playing in the saloons. Therefore, it could not be played in
         Church. And the fact that the girls danced and ha d attended the dances was just that
         much too much, and that's all there was to it.
         
         BC:  Saloons had swinging doors, they were up about this from the floor,
         I had the greatest desire to crawl under there and see what went on!
         I never did, though. I was just dying to.
         
         SS:  Was your mother opposed- was she in favor of the Prohibition when it
         came in?
         
         BC:  I suppose, I don't remember.
         
         IA:  Prohibition?
         I wondered if your mother was in favor of it or not. If it mattered
         to her one way or the other.
         
         BC:  No,because she never encountered too much of it.
         
         IA:  Well, neither Mother nor Dad ever drank at that time, they did later.
         Dad had a couple of old hunting pals and they would come up to the house
         on New Year's and would celebrate New Year's day with a drink in the
         kitchen, always, but they only stayed just a short time and they had
         their drink and they went home.
         
         SS:  Didn't you tell me once about- did you make some wine and hide it?
         Now what was that? I don't remember that story.
         
         IA:  I was going to tell you, was the fact that Dad- someone told us that
         you could make delicious wine out of dandelions by gathering the blos
         soms in the spring and using it with raisins and orange juice and -th-
         dandelions. You heated the dandelion flowers and thenyou put in the
         raisins and the orange juice and let it ferment and it made a delicious
         wine. Which it did. And Dad was perfectly willing that we sho uld
         gather the dandelions and he'd take us out in the country and along
         the edges of the fields to gather to see if we could make
         dandelion And we could, and we made the dandelion wine. At
         that time
         
         BC:  We never had wine in the house.
         That was during the Prohibition days and we had a county attorney here
         called Frank Moore, and he was a very tall, large, heavyset man, and
         had flat feet and he always walked the alleys downtown to see if he
         could catch anyone that was drunk that he could see that they were ta
         ken care of. And he had just one tune that he could whistle, and he
         whistled that tune from the time he left home, which is that high house
         on the bank on Jefferson Street, it's up high on the bank, and that
         was his home. The old Frank L. Moore home. And he'd leave there whis
         tling, and he'd whistle all up and down these alleys and those old flat
         would go flop, flop.ut had helped us get all these dandelion blos
         soms and Mother got the rest of the material and we fixed it all toge
         ther and we put it in the basement over there and let it ferment til
         it stopped fermenting and then we bottled it. And Dad produced the
         bottles. He had bottles of what . called Winola-
         
         BC:  Munola.
         
         IA:  What? Munola, he called it Winola. Munola. And he got the bottles
         for Mother because he thought it had a tonic in it which was good for
         Mother.
         
         BC:  Probably alcohol!
         And he brought up these bottles, and I guess they'd be gallon bottles,
         they'd be a bottle about like that. They'd hold about as much as a
         gallon. I think they were gallon bottles. At any rate, he brought
         these gallon bottles up and we bottled the wine. And we ha d it in
         the basement, at the back part where there was no heat, and we thought
         we could keep it in there. On Decoration Day, Mother said to me, "I'm
         afraid to have those bottles in the basement. If Old Frank L. Moore
         decides to investigate he could make an awful big thing about Dr. Adair
         having bottles of wine in his basement during Prohibition Days." So,
         she said, "Let's bury them." And out here, where this house stands
         now we had an enormous great, big bridal wreath bush, and we always
         kept it watered in the summertime, and Mother said, "Let's bury it out
         underneath that bush." So I went out and everybody else was out of
         town, out to the cemetery with their decoration and all, and I went out
         and dug a hole. A good, deep, large hole and Mother and I carried
         r those bottles from the basement in our aprons; we could caiy two or
         three of the bottles at a time, carried 'em up and we buried them under
         the bridal wreath bush, where we thought that watering the bridal wreath
         bush would be significant that no one would ever think that there
         was anything buried there. So we dutifully buried the bottles and wa
         tered the bush all summer. LaUthat fall then, just before freezing
         Mother and I went out; dug up the bottles and put them back in the
         woodshed and Frank L. Moore had lost his position- t zas county atto
         rney at that time- or city attorney, which was it? He was attorney any
         way, he was attor 'ney Frank L. Moore. And there was no danger and we
         cached our bottles back in the basement. I still have- that bottle
         wouldn't hold a jigger, would it?
         
         BC:  Half pint.
         
         IA:  About a half pint of that liquor in a bottle. It was a half pint bot
         tle with a leather covering and the screw top. And the thing got tight
         and we never could get the top off, so the bottle is still full of
         dandelion wine! (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  That's the only way Prohibition affected my family. Father was always
         looking ahead- we never had wine in the house- he said, "Well, now
         with Prohibition if we needed some wine, we couldn't get it." So we
         started making wine. And the only time it was ever used - I think I
         used the first of it, we never drank it. One time Mother said, You
         make the fruit cocktail,"it was New Yearns or Christmas,"you make the
         fruit cocktail." So, I said, "Alright." So I got a bottle of wine
         Father said,
         and poured a lot of this wine on the fruit. And "I never
         tasted such a good fruit cocktail. You always make the fruit cocktails
         from now on." (Chuckles) 
         
         SS: When you speak about that-"Tenting to night, tenting tonight
         Tenting on the old camp ground-"
         
         IA:  Sing the song.
         
         SS:  When you say- speak about that"Tenting tonight," Did you remember the
         revivals that they used to have.
         
         BC:  Oh, we had numerous. They made me resign from the Methodist Church
         because these men- they had the sawdust trail in these big tents, and
         then get up and preach hell-fire and brimstone, and they said if you
         danced or played cards you'd go straight to hell, I was about thirteen
         or fourteen, and I knew that I was going to dance and play cards wh en
         I got older. So I just couldn't belong to the-church when I knew I
         was going to do that. So I went and took my name off the rolls of the
         Methodist Church. And then I told my father what I'd done and he didn't
         criticize me. He said,"I'm very disappointed. I wish you hadn't done
         it,but it's alright, it's your privilege." So I resigned. And that
         night or the next night Father had a dream, I went to heaven and St.
         Peter wouldn't let me in! (Chuckles) That's true, because I was going
         to dance and play cards. We had Lowry and Moody and I think Billy Sun
         day was here once.
         
         SS:  I heard a guy named Bulgin came here.
         
         IA:  Yes, we had a Bulgin here.
         
         BC:  Maybe it was Bulgin. Lowry and Moody though, I just couldn't
         take it.
         
         IA:  My father's sister's husband was a very profane man. He was a farmer,
         lived down at Johnson and he was a very profane man.
         
         BC:  Only in speech.
         
         IA:  And he decided once that he'd go down and hear Bulgin speak, he hadn't
         heard him. So he went down and he really was quite with the
         gentleman, and he continued going until the meetings closed. And Uncle
         John then decided that he was going to be a Christian and stop swearing
         and all. So he did try and he eased up a great deal on his cussing. He
         went down to the old home farm after they had moved up here and lived
         over on Polk Street at that time and they sold their place at Johnson.
         But he had this old friend, a Mr, Thompson living in
         Johnson, and Uncle John decided to go down and see how Mr. Thompson
         was, and Mr. Thompson had attended revival service down at the church
         in Johnson and decided that he was going to become a Christian, too.
         So, the two men were conversing and having a very good time talking
         about the changes in their lives and so forth, and Mother called din
         ner. Mrs. Thompson asked the men to be seated and so forth, and Mr.
         Thompson felt just a little bit shy about saying grace; He'd been
         saying grace ever since he'd been converted, but he felt a little bit
         shy about saying grace, so he reached over and started passing the
         plates around for the dinner, and his little boy about, oh, I guess
         he was four years- -between four and five years old- had been accustomed
         to havinggrace the last few days, and he was all ready for it, he had
         his hands folded and his head bowed, but Pappa didn't pay any attention.
         The youngster looked up and he says, "Papa." And Papa went right on
         with what he was doing, serving the dinner. And the youngster looked
         up again and he says, "Papa,pray." And Papa still didn't hear him.
         Finally he just swelled up, and he says, "Papa, pray, damn you, pray!"
         Papa prayed.
         
         BC:  That's a true story. (Laughter)
         
         IA:  Isn't that good?
         
         BC:  You know these revivals preyed so on people's emotions, that at one
         time in Moscow the majority ofstopped the Sunday paper, and the women
         would toss their jewelry into the baskets that they sent around.
         
         SS:  They stopped the Sunday paper?
         
         BC:  Yes, they won't have the Sunday paper and people took off their jewelry
         and give it to the revival I remember that.
         
         SS:  Was the paper the Moscow Sunday paper or the Spokane? They wouldn't
         take it on Sunday.
         
         BC:  Both.
         
         SS:  Was there a real difference of opinion within the Methodist Church
         about this? Were there some people that didn't want revivals? It
         certainly seems like-
         
         IA:  All of the churches in town contributed and had this big- well, it's
         where the old Christian Church stood there. At that time it was the
         post office corner, and they had this large tabernacle was built there
         for it, I think. And all the churches in town contributed, both thet
         congregations and their money.
         
         BC:  Jewelry.
         
         IA:  In having this tabernacle built.
         
         BC:  They had a real sawdust trailfand they would walk down this sawdust
         trail and give their heart to God. Many time. And they'd cry on
         their shoulder, and I didn't like it.
         
         SS:  Very emotional.
         When you say, Bernadine, that you used to argue with the Sunday School
         teacher; over what?
         
         BC:  Well, this one comes into my mind; I never learned anything about the
         Bible, cause she talked all the time. And she thought I was a sinner
         because I'd withdrawn from the church; I still went to Sunday School.
         And she was talking about - Mary(and Martha.. Mary was the
         he did all these things for Jesus Martha did menial
         things, so she wasn't considered as good as Mary. And that made me
         cross, I said, "I think Martha was doing the menial things and Mary
         got the credit for everything and I just don't agree with that."
         I guess I'm always- I mean I think differently, and the Sunday School
         teacher wouldn't accept-"Don't doubt, have faith." 
         
         SS:  Well, it seems to me that you were thinking independently for yourself.
         
         BC:  I was, always have. I don't know why I started so early, but I did.
         
         SS:  Should be a virtue, I think. (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  Thank you.Well, Father brought us up that way he said he
         didn't criticize me for withdrawing, he said he was disappointed. That
         hurt me because I had disappointed my father. But for me I
         had to do it.
         
         SS:  But he didn't try and make you change your mind.
         
         SS:  That's respecting you.
         
         BC:  Well I certainly respected my father. They were quite wise, I think.
         They were wiser than their generation, because if I wanted to do some
         thing, Mother and Father would sit down, "Now, you tell us your side
         and we'll tell you our side, then you do what you want." And they had
         me every time, but they never said so, I didn't want to go against
         their wishes.
         
         SS:  So, they didn't have to say to you, "You can't do it." They let you
         
         BC: I wanted to dance, but Father told me, "When you get to college you
         can dance." So, I waited til I went to college.
         
         SS:  What did your parents think- what did your mother think when you
         decided to get a homestead of your own?
         
         IA:  To get a homestead of my own?
         
         SS:  What did they think?
         
         IA:  Oh, they thought it was the thing to do. Everyone was taking up home
         steads at that time, and lots of the people here in town had taken up
         homesteads in that section of the country out there. There was an open
         ing up of a large area of white pine timber out beyong Clarkia, about
         forty-five miles beyond Clarkia.
         
         SS:  East?
         
         IA:  East, between Clarkia and Avery. I think there's a road now goes from
         Clarkia clear across to Avery, but at that time there was no road, it
         had to be trails, always trails. The Wallaces and the Watkins and the
         Martins and the Paulsens, and the Files and the Wallaces- did I mention
         those?- and the Torsens.
         
         BC:  Druggist And jewelers and doctors-
         
         IA:  And  and all of these were Moscow people that had taken up claims
         in that section of the country. And Daddy knew the old homesteader,
         Matt Miles, who was locating people in that part of the country, and
         he knew Mr.Miles and he knew the family, the Calkins family and
         all, and so he thought - Winifred took up a claim out there; Winifred
         was the youngest daughter of the Caulkins family, and Matt had mar
         ried the older girl.
         
         SS:  Winifred's sister?
         
         IA:  Winifred's sister. And then there was another; she worked in the post
         office.
         
         SS:  Matt- had they taken up a claim, too?
         
         IA:  They had homesteads out there and were quite close to land that
         Mr. Miles wanted to locate me on. And Mrs. Durham and Mrs. Torson
         and all. So we were just a Moscow community out in that section of
         the country. And they thought it was perfectly alright.
         
         BC:  They had no idea of the vigorous life they would have to lead.
         
         SS:  Was it your idea? How old were you at the time? Were you still a
         teenager?
         
         IA:  What?
         
         SS:  Were you still a teenager at that time? Were you still in your teens?
         
         BC:  How old did you have to be before you could take a claim?
         
         IA:  Yes.
         
         BC:  You had to be a certain age before you could take up a claim, lone.
         
         SS:  I think it was only eighteen, I'm not sure.
         
         IA:  I had finished high school, and took the teacher examination and in
         order to pay for the claim, I taught two terms out at Collins schoolhouse.
         And I just had eight students, and I taught the school out
         there for two different terms.
         
         BC:  What was it you got? Twenty dollars a month, or something.
         
         IA:  No, it wasn't- let's see, thirty-eight to forty dollars, and that was
         a big price for those days.
         
         SS:  Where did you stay when you taught?
         
         IA:  I stayed at the Freis who owned the store.
         
         SS:  Sam Frei?
         
         IA:  No, Sam's brother, Abe. Sam at that time was not married and his
         father and mother lived at Bovill. And you go out of Bovill as if
         you were going to Elk River and you take a left hand turn and go up
         the creek, and Sam and his father and mother lived up there. And Sam
         and Anna and Eddie and the rest of the family lived up there. There
         was quite a good sized family in all. Then Sam later moved to town
         and he and his wife bought what used to be the old Washburn eating
         house. And Mrs. Frei later, after Mr. Frei's death turned it into a
         roominghouse; roomings and apartments only, after that.
         
         SS:  Tell me what you had to do- what happened to youlocated on that?
         
         IA:  When we were located?
         
         SS:  When you located, yeah.
         
         IA:  Well, we were located- the man took us in and we had to go around to
         the different corners, the points of interest on the claim, we had to
         take in the corners of the claim of each one, and the man always took
         us- of course, what was said to be the corners- and I suppose it was,
         I don't know, not knowing that part of the country at that time. And
         May Calkins, his sister-in-law, had the cabin on the meadow and they
         were putting up the cabin for her, and my cabin was put within calling
         distance of her cabin. And I stayed; I went out with Mrs. Durham and
         her daughter when they spent the winter out there and we took our pro
         visions in from Clarkia and Herman Wilson, that used to work wheiK the
         Wilson Seed Company down here, the Washburn  Wilson - and Herman Wil
         son was running the store at Clarkia at that time. We bought our pro
         visions from him and they were packed on pack horses from there out to
         the cabin. And Mrs. Toreson had her house and her cabin. It was about
         a quarter of a mile from Mrs. Durham. And we had to cross one of these
         old boggy meadows every time we went out or in to town. Went across
         these boggy meadows in order to get over to my house- my cabin- and
         May's cabin, and Mrs. Taylor's cabin, which was about a mile and a
         half beyond May's cabin. And Mrs. Taylor was a sister of Griffin
         that run the dray here in town at that time. And he was a big man:
         I think of a big man- when my father moved to Moscow all of his belon
         gings for his office, his instruments and books and all, were in an
         enormous great big barrel and they were shipped out by freight and
         Griffin picked up that barrel and carried it up the stairway that
         runs between Bjorklands and Creightons- carried it up that stairway
         to Dad's office all by himself. That's the kind of a man he was.
         Well, it was his sister had the homestead next .May Calkins there.
         There was the three of us in that ring. My cabin and May's cabin and
         Mrs. Taylor's cabin were all along there together.
         
         BC:  Not together, really?
         
         IA:  Well, not together, but we called it together, because all you had to
         do waskput on your shoes and walk one place or the other. You're quite
         some little distance, but you followed a trail across, that is, a trail
         on trees. It hadn't been used enough to - for there ever to be a foot
         trail there- you followed the trail blazes on the trees from one place
         to the other. But we got there.
         And then what were the requirements that you had to meet? Did you have
         to stay there for so many months of the year?
         You had to have a clearing; you had to have a certain amount of land
         cleared and ready for cultivation, and you had to have a garden or a
         crop, and you had to have your cabin, and you were supposed to be there
         all the time. You were homesteading; you were supposed to live on
         your homestead. That's the reason my father had us go out every summer
         on the homestead next to Collins there, was because he couldn't leave
         his office and we took the homestead duties and lived on the homestead.
         And you were supposed to live on the homestead.
         
         BC:  How many months?
         
         BC:  How many months were you supposed to live on it?
         
         IA:  At least six months time. And when you're out there and so far
         away, you don't come to town. You don't have horses or you have to
         send out if you get a chance to have a packer come in with horses
         for you. I had a horse of my own and May Calkins had a horse and
         Mrs. Taylor walked. She was a tall, strong woman and she walked every
         place. It was funny to see her walking on snowshoes. She was tall
         and she brought one foot this way and one foot this way and the snow
         would just fly up across the back of her clothes in the back. We had
         a man staying out there/with us there by the name of Carter and he
         looked down the trail one day and says, "Here comes the Georgia Oaks!"
         The Georgia Oaks was a steam paddle steamer on the Coeur d'Alene Lake
         at that time. You don't hear about Georgia Oaks now, but Georgia Oaks
         was a paddle steamer and worked on the Coeur d'Alene Lake. And he
         looked down the trail and saw Mrs. Taylor coming up on her snowshoes
         and snow was just flying. And he says, "Here comes the Georgia Oaks!"
         
         BC:  Is she the one that used to carry her bacon in her bosom?
         
         IA:  No, that was Mrs. Paulsen. (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  I remember she did.
         
         SS:  She did?
         
         BC:  Yeah. 
         
         IA:  Mrs. Paulsen was a homesteader. How can I locate ? On the road to
         Lewiston, over the Snow Hill, you go past a little wishing well, I
         called it, it's a well which has been enclosed and has the frames up
         over it and it sets back a ways from the road on the left hand side
         as you are going towardsLewiston, and that was the former Paulsen
         homestead. The father took up a homestead out there. Later they
         moved in to town and lived in this gray house, you know where Charles
         Carsow lives down below? Well, it's just beyond that in that gray
         house-two story gray house- and they moved in there. Mr. Paulsen took
         up a homestead down on what was the Creek and her daughter
         Mable, went with her. Her daughter was a very good singer and she
         sang with the Metropolitan Opera for a while. She married Louie
         Devouin a musician and they lived in-
         
         BC:  She is still living, I think, Mable.
         
         IA:  Is she still—?
         
         BC:  Well, she was over to the house a year or so ago.
         
         IA:  She is an aunt of Mrs. Kinzer who lives on Polk-
         
         BC:  Her name is Webber now.
         
         IA:  And she and Devouin were divorced and she married a man by the name
         of Webber that was in Palouse. And Elmer Paulsen was county commis
         sioner- one of the county commissioners for years, up at the court
         house here. And they lived here in town.
         
         SS:  She homesteaded out there with you?
         
         IA:  Yes. She homesteaded. And Mable always went with her mother when she
         went out, cause Mrs. Paulsen that she had to have com
         pany. But this time she didn't go with her, and I don't know just
         why, but Mother was coming out from the homestead
         
         BC:  Our mother?
         
         IA: No. Mrs. Paulsen was coming out from the homestead and it began to
         get rather late in the afternoon and she decided she'd just stay there
         in Collins at night and not try to come on, or go as far as Bovill.
         So, she decided that if she stayed there, right next to the fence out
         side of the woman that run the little restaurant that she would fry
         some bacon for herself, and she carried the bacon in her blouse in
         the front of her blouse, so she had bacon enough for it. Well, so
         she had her bacon and she went in and asked the lady of the house to
         drop an egg in the teapot- teakettle- for her, so she had hardboiled
         eggs and bacon that evening. Then instead of staying all night she
         decided to come on down to our place, about a mile and a quarter far
         ther, she'd make it down there. And she made it on down to our place
         and we were all sleeping- all the young people were sleeping in an
         old log barn, which was across the driveway from the cabin, and so we
         took Mrs. Paulsen in to sleep in the barn.
         
         BC:  I think she was a sponger!
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  I think she was a sponger.
         
         IA:  Yes, she was. (Chuckles) No doubt about it. But she saved money.
         And she saved the farm and she gave a lot of money to Mable for her
         education and to Elmer.
         
         SS:  Did she stay with you for long?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Did she stay for long when she got there?
         
         IA:  No. She stayed all night at our place, but she came on the next day.
         She was headed for Moscow, and was taking it afoot, that's the only
         way she had of traveling.
         
         BC:  This place they called a barn, it's never been used as a barn, it's
         just a log building. And the mattresses- tell him about the mattresses
         boughs boughs
         
         IA:  The mattresses are made of pine fir you know how to
         make a fir bough - and then over the top of that we put a
         layer of hay that we got down at Bovill off of the meadows and we put
         that. But we had nice beds, and we had plenty of roonT sleep-there.
         Well, Mrs. Paulsen had heard some wild tales about the cougars down
         in that part of the country had been bothering the stock on the Bovill
         meadows and on the Frei meadows at Collins, and so she was very anxious
         to sleep in the barn with the rest of us. The boys up at—
         Collins decided that they'd play a joke on Mrs. Coleman, she'd played
         a joke on the old woman that run the restaurant-
         
         BC:  Mrs. Coleman or Paulsen?
         
         IA:  «ate her bacon and eggs outside after boiling the eggs in the teakettle,
         and so they decided they were going to play a joke on Mrs. Paulsen.
         So they got an oil can- I don't know whether you've ever used an oil
         can with aresin string. You take a resin string and put it in an oil
         can; take the top out of the oil can and fasten the resin string in
         one end of the oil can and pull on this resin string and it gives a
         hideous, shrieking noise. Well, they fixed the oil can, and the troop
         up there, there was five or six of these boys altogether, and they came
         down and in the woods just across the creek from our barn pulled the
         stringKon this oil can and made this hideous noise. Well, Mrs. Paulsen
         was wide awake in a moment, because she'd heard these tales of the
         cougars and she was sure there was a cougar. So she was up and get
         ting ready to go into the house with Mother and Mrs. Mc Connell. Well,
         we told her we didn't think that the cougars would ever disturb us,
         and she said, "Well, won't you close your door? Fasten the door so
         that they can't come in?" And she said, "They might come in that win
         dow." There was a window. Well, about that time the boys were pul
         ling that string again, and .here'd be this awful noise. And they
         carried that on for quite a while til Mrs. Paulsen was just beside her
         self. And then it stopped, and they went on back up to town, and the
         next morning bright and early, were they back, to see whether the noise
         had disturbed anybody down at our house! (flhuckles) And Mrs. Paulsen
         got up quite early and after having a little breakfast with Mother,
         she started on down towards Moscow. And she evidently made it because
         she got home alright. But she was so funny.
         
         SS:  Did you girls know what it was that was making the noise?
         
         IA:  We knew what it was so it didn't bother us.
         
         SS:  But you didn't tell her?
         
         IA:  We didn't tell her we knew what it was, oh, no!
         
         SS:  That was part of the joke?
         
         IA:  That was part of the game. (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  You know there used to be an old stream that came down that side, in
         my memory of Bovill, it was called Ruby Creek?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         BC:  We went down into Ruby Creek. That . my place was.
         
         IA:  The what?
         
         BC:  Ruby Creek out by Bovill.
         
         SS:  What makes you say that she was a sponger?
         
         BC:  Because she went outside of the place, she built a little fire and
         pulled out her bacon and fried it and went in the cafe to ask them to
         boil her eggs in their teakettle.
         
         SS:  That's right.
         
         BC:  I think that was poor taste. Worse than that.
         
         IA:  Instead of going in and paying for her meal, she fried her bacon outside
         alongside of the fence. But she didn t want to eat a soft boiled
         egg, so she asked the lady of the house to boil the eggs in the teaket
         tle for her. I don't know whether she boiled them in the teakettle or
         not-
         
         SS:  Were you close to Round Top Mountain?
         
         IA:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Because, you know the name of the creek there that runs south of Round
         Top Mountain is Adair Creek.
         
         IA:  What?
         
         SS:  There is a creek that runs south of Round Top Mountain that's called
         Adair Creek.
         
         IA:  Uh-huh.
         
         BC:  Is that the mountain you climbed and left your name in the tobacco can?
         
         IA:  No, that was at Elk Butte that we left the-
         
         SS:  They must have named that creek after you.
         
         IA:  They did.
         
         IA:  That came after 1910. After 1910, the fires. And we had a neighbor,
         Mr. Flower. And Mr. Flower had an uncle from Iowa that had been spen
         ding the summer with him, and the smoke was getting pretty bad up in
         that part of the country then from those Wallace fires and all the
         other fires, and Mr. Flower decided that he would bring Mr.— oh, I
         can't think of his uncle's name right now- but he would bring the uncle
         down to Avery and put him on the train and send him back to Iowa. And
         in the meantime, the fire fighters had left Mrs. Taylor's creek and
         that branch of the Potlatch where they were fighting the fire then, it
         was time to move on to another location. And while they were moving
         they let us- Mrs. Taylor and I were cooking for these fire fighters,
         and they let us go down to Mrs. Durham's place. And Mrs. Durham and
         her daughter were living there, so we decided when we got there that
         we wouldn't wait for the firemen, we'd wait and let them tell us, they
         said it would take about so many days before they could get set up
         for us, and we would go over to Mr. Flower's. So we walked up four
         miles over to Mr. Flower's place and stayed all night, and Mr. Flowers
         told us he was coming down to Avery to bring the uncle out and we could
         go with him, if we wished. So Myrtle and I decided to go with Mr. Flo
         wers to take the uncle out and Mrs, Durham stayed with Mrs. Flowers
         and the little girl ; they had a small child. So we started out and we
         got down- when we got on top of those long, bare ridges going down
         from- not Round Top, but Debbitt's . Basin- there's a long ridge that
         comes down- we could see the fires off on both sides of us. When we
         got down into Avery we were met before we crossed the bridge at Avery
         by an officer. He told us to turn around and go back, and we told him
         that we couldn't do that, that we had to put this old gentleman on.
         So we were on the train there for two days. And it was during that
         time that they told us that they were going to take us up the line for
         a little ways to see how things were going and we could go up with them.
         We went up with them and they told us then that they we re going to
         call that creek up there, Adair Creek.
         
         SS:  Really?
         
         IA:  Had to have a name, it didn't have any name, so they called it Adair
         Creek.
         
         BC:  Well, that was after you had cooked for these fire fighters then.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  That was after you had cooked for these fire fighters.
         
         IA:  Oh, yes, we cooked for the fire fighters up there. And we came down
         to Avery so that Mr. Flowers could start his uncle back.
         
         BC:  And that's the way you got out.
         
         SS:  Did you live right near Adair Creek, yourself? Or were you fairly far
         from there?
         
         IA:  No. It was twenty-eight miles from Avery back to our homestead.
         
         SS:  What was the creek that you were nearest to?
         
         IA:  Nearest?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         IA:  Just a small stream, I don't think it had any name at that time. Just
         a small stream that run through a meadow. There was a stream by Mrs.
         Durham's place, and we called that just the- just the river, I guess.
         It wasn't much of a stream. We couldn't fish in it; it wasn't large
         enough-
         
         BC:  Where did you get your water when you were on the homestead?
         
         IA:  From a spring. We dug a spring.
         
         BC:  Did you?
         
         IA:  Uh-huh. We had to have water. We dug a spring.
         
         SS:  Was there much of a community life there among you homesteaders?
         
         IA:  No, always so far apart. See, Mr. Flowers was about four miles, and
         Hanson and Larsen were about the same distance, only in another dire
         ction. And Mrs. File was over on Floodwood Creek and Mrs. Taylor and
         Miss Calkins and my place and Mrs. Torson and Mrs. Durham; we were
         all- well, it was about four miles from my place back to Mrs. Durham's
         place, and then Mrs. Taylor was still farther on. So there was not
         very much between us. At Eastertime Bill Griffin, a nephew of Mrs.
         Taylor's spent the winter out there with her, and she wanted to do
         something special for Easter, so she sent up- when Bill went out to
         get the mail, and she sent out for a chicken. And a real, civilized
         chicken. And she cooked this chicken and we had chicken for Easter-
         Easter Sunday chicken. Bill and Mrs. Taylor and Myrtle and myself,
         the four of us. And we got away with the chicken, too! (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  Didn't you have a birthday party once on the roof of your cabin?
         
         IA:  In hers?
         
         BC:  On the roof of your cabin, you had a or something.
         
         IA:  Oh, Myrtle had a birthday. Her birthday was in April, it was either
         the first or the second of April. And Hanson and larsenhad this
         homestead four miles over, just the two boys, Larsen was staying with
         Hanson and Hanson owned the homestead, and they came over, they knew
         it was about time for Myrtle's birthday, so they came over to our
         cabin and said they'd come for the birthday. The only place we could
         think of that would be high and dry, there was still snow all over
         everything out there in April, was the roof of the cabin. And so, we
         took blankets and put up on the roof of the cabin and up with a
         ladder and sat on the cabin while we had our birthday dinner. Well,
         after dinner, Myrtle decided that she'd make candy for the boys, so
         she went down to make some fudge for the boys. And she made part of
         the fudge with lots of pepper in it, so that when the boys bit into
         this candy they got their mouths full of pepper! So she had two bat
         ches, one of the pepper kind and one without pepper, and she and I
         were eating off of the one dish and the boys were eating off of the
         other. Well, they finally got so they couldn't stand it any longer,
         so they had to go down and find some water, and they found the water
         and rinsed their mouths out and tried to get the burning stopped in
         their stomach and all. And about that time, it was time for them to
         start home, and they did. I think they made it by night, although
         they had a four mile trip across country. They had to cross the stream
         and all. Before they left they both wrote out a will on a cigarette
         paper; they always rolled their own because you couldn't carry enough
         cigarettes to keep them going out there, but they could take in the
         tobacco and the papers and roll their own, so they rolled their own.
         And they rolled their own cigarettes and on this cigarette paper each
         one wrote a will, that if they didn t make it home that night, that
         we were to have such and such a thing that was at the cabin. They left
         the cigarette papers with us, and they went on home.(Chuckles) Oh,
         thetf were funny things!. Always something coming up. So many things
         that I couldn't even begin to tell you.
         
         SS:  What's funny- it seems like you really invented things and became re
         sourceful when you didn't have things around you.
         
         IA:  You just had to do things. I told you, I think, about Carter, the man
         that stayed with us that run the trapline, didn't I?
         
         SS:  You told me about '' you told me about him.
         
         IA:  About the man.
         
         SS:  Yes. And about Sylvest-
         
         IA:  And about Sylvester.
         
         SS:  Did Carter stay all winter?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Did he stay all winter?
         
         IA:  Yes, he stayed all winter with us. He stayed until late spring, and
         then he left us, after the snow left, so that he could get out and
         go to work.
         
         SS:  Was it just you that he helped, or was it all- were there other home
         steaders around that he helped out, too?
         
         IA:  No, he only helpedus. My father and Mrs. Durham made the arrangements
         for him to stay with us at so much a month; and he was to stay there
         and to help us with the wood and with the-
         
         BC:  Water, I suppose.
         
         IA:  snow and anything that needed, and had to go out for the mail. He went
         out once a month for the mail.
         
         SS:  To Clarkia?
         
         IA:  Carter.
         
         SS:  Did he go to Clarkia? For the mail.
         
         IA:  Yes. No, Avery.
         
         SS:  Avery.
         
         IA:  Uh-huh. Twenty-eight miles to Ayery. Forty-five miles to Clarkia.
         
         SS:  Well, what about the hardships of that, lone? Were there things that
         you had to do that were hard, that were difficult?
         
         IA:  Oh, only in sawing or getting your wood or anything like that, if you
         happened to be low on it. Nothing especially hard,
         
         BC:  See now, you would consider hardship/ part of the life.
         
         IA:  The man that stayed with us took care of that. That's why my father
         insisted on having someone stay with us, so that if anything happened,
         if we'd get cut or anything like that, that we would be able to get
         word out for help, or to get out ourselves for help.
         
         BC:  She went through the most vigorous young years, and she is the health
         iest of the family. Kind of interesting.
         
         SS:  Uh-huh. During the summer, though, you didn't need anyone to stay with
         you, then?
         
         IA:  No, we didn't. We didn't need anyone especially. There were three of
         us at the one place and we could go back to Mrs. Taylor's the other
         way. But her's was quite a ways, because it was four miles from Mrs.
         Durham's over to my place, and Mrs. Taylor was a mile and a half beyond
         that. And her nephew had left before the fires— before the fire sea
         son started. So, when these fire fighters came through there looking—
         trying to locate some way of getting in to this fire section they wan
         ted to know if the trail went any farther, and we told them that it
         went about a mile and a half to Mrs. Taylor's. So they went on thenwanted
         to know if they could go on, and we said that they could, that
         they could go on over. Well, when we got over, we found that they had -
         they had found the cabin, and they wanted to know when we arrived if
         we would get breakfast for the men. So we got breakfast for those five
         or six men that were looking for trails, and when the rest of them
         caught up, they wanted to know if we wouldn't continue. So we stayed
         on then as cooks for the fire fighters.
         
         SS:  Did you go backafter the fire? Did you go back to the homestead after
         the fires were over?
         
         IA:  Yes. After the fires were over we went back to the homestead.
         
         BC:  Was your place burned?
         
         IA:  No. The fire didn't come that way. The wind was the other way and
         the fires from Wallace came up but they followed the ridges up and
         didn't get into our part of the country at all, in on the Floodwood.
         
         SS:  How many years did you stay on the homestead?
         
         IA:  We were in there from, let's see it was, we went in to stay definitelywe
         were in part of the time during the summer before in 1909, and then
         we were there all the summer of 1910. And I went back then afterwards
         early in 1911 to see how things - the condition of things.
         
         BC:  Is that the time I went with you?
         
         IA:  You were with me in 1909.
         
         BC:  No, Marjorie was.
         
         IA:  Marjorie was with me in 1909.
         
         BC:  I wasn't there the year of the fire.
         
         SS:  What did you think of it Bernadine? Of the homesteading when you were
         there?
         
         BC:  It was a long ride. I'd never been horse back before. We rode in
         from Clarkia, forty-five miles, all in one day, I believe. We rode
         twenty-four hours. And I'd keep saying, "How much farther is it, Pinkie?'
         "Oh, about an hour." Well, an hour was about four hours, that meant
         nothing to me. I thought we'd never get there. And we had to cross
         here one horse had gone down. never did get it out.
         I loved it after I got there. lone was so entertaining. She would
         take me out and teach me different flowers and different kinds of
         pine. And we told you about the b\r± Vnx+X ej And we iearned
         poetry. She had a book of Robert Service. She'd read one line and
         I'd read the next one. We could do it now, I think, but we have to
         be together, because I don't know the line in between. But she was
         very inventive and she's a clever person.
         
         SS:  How old were you then?
         BC Twelve or thirteen. It was quite an adventure.
         
         What did you think of the cabin, itself? Did it seem ample to you?
         Did it seem rude and just real primitive?
         
         Very primitive.
         
         Just a one room log cabin. But when I was just a little
         girl from about two to seven we went to the Collins cabin, so I
         was kind of used to- accustomed to what a cabin could be.
         What about lone living there by herself so long? Doesn't it seem quite
         remarkable?
         
         I can't imagine my father allowing it. Ijust can't. Apparently she
         wanted to do it, so it was alright. He worried about her. That I
         know. Especially when the fire season was on, because many people
         were killed in that fire. We didn't have any word from lone for about
         five or six weeks. That's the only time I ever saw my mother cry.
         
         Just out of worry? For lone?
         
         All these people that had been burned they went into a cave-« Hie Uwkfn
         And that time we had no word at all. And I remember Mother broke
         down and cried.
         
         When she heard the news of these other people dying?
         
         We didn't know she was with the fire fighters. And every
         indication was that that whole area had been burned over. So- then
         Daddy let her go on a trip to Alaska with three other girls, which was
         primitive at that time, the boat they went on. And the one that they
         were to come back on went down and people were drowned.
         lost lone. But they stayed over to go up to Sitka, I think
         it was, and took another boat, so she missed
         
         BC:  Well, she's talking wabbly Sometimes she gets quite confused and
         very, very tired though. Before she was in the hospital she wouldn't
         have done you any good at all. But after the oxygen treatment and the
         antibiotic- then she went back to normal.
         
         BC:  Would you like a cup of tea? You've been talking a lot.
         
         IA:  No, I don't think so.
         
         BC:  Do you?
         
         SS:  No, I guess not
         
         SS:  Orange Pekoe?
         
         BC:  Yeah. In little bags, I'm not very 
         
         IA:  What are you talking about?
         
         SS:  Oh, we were talking about the homestead, mostly.
         
         BC:  I was impressed, because in my younger years the summers out
         here, I knew what to expect when you said "cabin".
         
         SS:  I'll tell you, my wife was a lookout.
         
         IA:  She was?
         
         SS:  Yes, and she was the first woman lookout that they had on Union Dis
         trict in Wallowa-Whitman, which is near Baker, Oregon. And she was the
         first woman in that district. And all these men in that district were
         sure that she was going to quit after the first fire. That she'd be
         down. (recorder shut off at this point)
         
         IA:  Bernadine was on the homestead with me, and we couldn't think of any
         thing to do.
         
         I'll be glad to serve it. very good tea. Pekoe
         
         BC:  We told him.
         
         IA:  You told him about the Service's poems? I'd forgotten that we told
         him that.
         
         SS:  We were just talking about it.
         
         BC:  That we had to be together to recite it.
         
         SS:  You really found it to be an adventure?
         
         BC:  Yes.
         
         IA:  Yes. We enjoyed it. We have had times together there at Collins.
         
         BC:  And I remember as a child, we used to go out from Bovill, there were
         always plenty of beaus around you, like the older sisters, Carrie Bush
         Mc Connell- But the boys would come down from Collins or up from
         Bovill at night. They'd sit around the camp fire and sing. Did you
         have marshmallows then to toast? I've forgotten.
         
         IA:  Have what?
         
         BC:  Did you toast marshmallows around the campfire? You'd all sit around
         and sing.
         
         IA:  Nobody knew anything about marshmallows then!
         
         BC:  There was lots of singing.
         
         SS:  And lots of beaus!
         
         IA:  I didn't know anything about marshmallows until after we got into to
         town after that.
         
         SS:  How did it work out then? The government didn't let you prove up?
         
         IA:  Didn't let me prove up?
         
         SS:  How did that happen?
         
         BC:  They said they hadn't been out there long enough.
         
         IA:  No woman could take it. That we hadn't homesteaded, that we qidn't
         take, it up as homestead;.we just took up for adventure, and so forth.
         And Mr. Ashley J. was sent out from Washington to all the homesteaders in that section
         of the country, and he said
         that nobody could live out there under those conditions. That they
         just weren't living conditions; that you couldnft do it! Actually we
         spent twenty-two months at a time out there, straight through.
         
         SS:  Had you lived there the full time? You'd lived there twenty-two months
         running?
         
         IA:  Twenty-two months. I was only out once in that time and that was to
         the- a hearing in Wallace. The homesteaders were all called in to Wallace
         to give their version of the story, but Ashley J. said his
         version and he'd been sent there by the government, and therefore the
         government took the government's side to it. Mrs. Toreson lost hers.
         Mrs.- now about Mrs. Durham, I'm not sure about Mrs. Durham, because
         they moved in to Spokane afterwards, and I'm not sure whether they did
         or not. Myrtle, the daughter, married a man in Spokane, a Mr. Melchoir
         station, I think it was a repair station and gas sta
         tion in Spokane, and they finally, he had to give up the work and she
         had rheumatism and arthritis so badly, that they had to go into a nur
         sing home out from Spokane. And my niece went out to visit with
         her a couple of times, to see them,
         
         SS:  What about you? They didn't allow your homestead either?
         
         IA:  No, they didn't allow mine. I have a letter from Burton L. French,
         that said he'd gone to certain committees and told them and knew that
         people could live under those conditions;lots of people were doing it,
         and all, but the decree had been handed down and I lost my homestead.
         
         BC:  Did you tell him about the last episode about that?
         
         IA:  The what?
         
         BC:  The last episode? About the man that met you 0U4 Worn OcoVvtf
         
         IA:  The Oxford Station? This same Ashley J. Roach that was.head of the inspection
         for the homesteaders out there, and he had been appointed at
         the head of the Oxford Ranger Station from Orofino. Up past Weippe
         and Pierce and out, and Bernadine and I were spending the summer with
         Mrs. Arnett and Mrs. Mc Bride that used to be here in town, and we were
         spending the summer with her and Mr. Arnett wanted to take us down to
         the Orogrande, to the river, on a fishing trip, and so he packed the
         horse and we got all ready and went over to the Oxford Ranger Station.
         And at the Oxford Ranger Station they were having some sort of a- what
         did I call it?- a party of some kind for the people at the station and
         homesteaders, but Mrs. Arnett didn't know who was giving it. And she
         said that we'd stop there on our way down to the Orogrande and see
         what was going on. And so we got to the Orogrande- or to the ranger
         station and whoshould I meet by Ashley J. Roach, who had been sent out
         from Washington in the first place. And he said, "It's been some time
         since I've seen you." And I said, "It surely has, and I don't think
         any more of you than I did then!" (Chuckles) He said, "I'm sorry for
         that." He said, "Had I been used to the West, or been acquainted with
         the West in any way, I would never have sent in the reports that I sent
         in to the government." I said, "Yes, but you caused me to lose my
         homestead, and numerous others, the same." He said, "I knowit was all
         my fault, because I sent in the reports and the people there were sup
         posed to take the opinion of the man they sent out to inspect."
         
         BC:  He just didn't know.
         
         SS:  Didn't understand the conditions.
         
         IA:  Didn't understand. He didn't know a thing about the West, nor a thing
         about homesteading.
         
         BC:  He still felt a little guilty, I-Ihmllc 
         
         IA:  What?
         
         BC:  I think he still felt a little guilty.
         
         SS:  Well, did you forgive him?
         
         IA:  No. I forgave him, but I didn't forget him. I still have the same
         resentment as far as my homestead is concerned; but against the man
         personally, I can see his side of it.
         
         BC:  That's the way we were brought up. You give your opinion; I give my
         opinion.
         
         IA:  We had quite a talk that day. We just settled in a corner by ourselves
         and let the musicians and the dancers have their fun. And Ashley J.
         Roach and I sat and hashed over old times together.
         
         SS:  Did pretty much everyone lose their homesteads in that area that you
         were homesteading?
         
         IA:  Yes, there were lots of-
         
         SS:  They took it away from everyone? Or from most of the people? They
         took the homesteads away from most everyone in that area.
         
         IA:  Yes, nearly everyone. Mrs. Torson- I think Mrs. Durham and Mrs. Torson
         got theirs. Mr. Flowers lost his, and the boys lost theirs and
         I think Mrs. File lost her's.
         
         BC:  I wonder why that discrimination? Why some would and some wouldn't?
         Do you know that?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Why did some lose them and others not lose them?
         
         IA:  I don't know. I don't know what there was about it. It was his inspec
         tion and his means of reporting it.
         
         SS:  Did you have some land cleared? Did you have some land cleared on the
         homestead?
         
         IA:  Did I have what?
         
         SS:  Some land cleared?
         
         IA:  Some land cleared?
         
         SS:  Cleared?
         
         IA:  Yes, I had some cleared. And then the meadows we were using for hay
         for the horses, and there was lots of the timber; we had to have the
         timber cleared from around the cabinf and all that we could. We had
         lots of brush done. And for the time we were there we had a very good
         showing of living up to it- the law, and doing as we were supposed to
         do.
         
         BC:  You lost a lot of money on that deal, didn't you? Had to hire a man
         and—
         
         SS:  A lot of time, too.
         
         If those people had been able to prove up, spend the five years and
         prove up on the homesteads; do you think most of them would have even
         tually sold the land to the timber companies?
         
         IA:  They would have sold to the lumber companies. Those that were allowed
         to take their claims, keep their claims-
         
         BC:  That's what they took it for. There was a differentiation between ta
         king a homestead and having a claim with mineral rights, wasn't there?
         Maybe that was the difference.
         
         IA:  I don't know.
         
         BC:  I kind of remember something like that.
         
         IA:  There was railroad land right close, just across the creek and up a
         very short ways from my property, and from May Calkin's property.
         
         BC:  Maybe the Union Pacific got it.
         
         IA:  And it could have been that the lobbyists for the railroads were res
         ponsible for that. I don't know.
         
         SS:  How much were the timber companies paying for the timber on 160 acres
         of good timber? Were they paying a lot of money?
         
         IA:  I couldn't tell.
         
         BC:  what Daddy got for his.
         
         SS:  What did he get?
         
         BC:  I think it was about 3,500.
         
         SS:  3,500.
         
         IA:  About 3,500.
         
         BC:  In 1900.
         
         IA:  At Bovill, just at Bovill there. And that, of course, is considered
         the older homesteaders, and those people had been in there for years.
         
         BC:  Daddy sold that claim in order to have the cash to make the downpayment
         on this house, I remember that.
         
         SS:  How much did this house cost him? Total?
         
         BC:  About 5,000, I think.
         
         SS:  So that was most of the money that he needed.
         
         IA:  The property cost him just about what he got for the timber claim.
         
         BC:  But that was this whole block.
         
         SS:  The whole block?
         
         BC:  There was a church up there at that time, I think that was the only
         part not included with this property.
         
         SS:  Well it seems to me then- I think that's part of what the government
         was arguing, that if people wanted or were planning to sell to the
         timber company then they shouldn't be allowed to homestead it, which
         seems wrong to me. I think that's part of the way they—
         
         BC:  There was something about mineral rights that went into that too. I
         remember
         don't remember enough about it, but I Daddy talking.
         
         SS:  Do you remember Frank Robinson very well? That fellow that
         
         BC:  I didn't know him.X a wa tail on the end of a pig or something
         like that.
         
         IA:  Who?
         
         SS:  Robinson.
         
         IA:  What Robinson?
         
         SS:  Frank B. Robinson. Psychianna.
         
         IA:  Psychianna? I have just one recollection of Mr. Robinson. I went
         down to the- what was the Owl- not the Owl- Bolles' Drugstore, the
         drugstore right at the corner of Main and Third Street, and I had an
         umbrella with me, it had been raining when I left home, I had an um
         brella with me, and I stepped into the drugstore to get something, I
         don't know what it was, and they had put out little shelves, like this,
         the counter was up here, and then this little shelf, and they had put
         lots of little odds and ends of things in these different shelves so
         people could see what they had. And I stepped up to the counter and
         asked for what I wanted, and this stranger waited on me and I thanked
         him and turned around and went outside the door. When I got outside
         I raised my umbrella again and a little package, a line of candles- a
         little box of candles about that large, you know those little tiny
         candles that you put on birthday cake , dropped out of my umbrella.
         Well, I turned right around and went back into the store and handed
         the package to the man as he stepped out again, and said, "When I rai
         sed my umbrella this fell out, so it must have caught on the umbrella
         when I was standing here." And he said, "Oh, yes? I can imagine that
         that's the true story." And I turned on my heels and walked out. I
         didn't go in the store for a long time. I told my father about it
         when I came home, and he said, "That's the new man. That's Psychianna
         Robinson. He's the man that's going to build here, and he's going to
         work He Bolles? Drugstore. There's other drugstores in town." And,
         he said, I'm known in all of them." So I didn't go in for a long timequite
         a long time into the drugstore. (Chuckles) I have a very poor
         recollection of Frank Robinson, and also his religion. I never did
         like him. We were speaking about the change in the times; we had
         always ridden horseback. May father had horses that we could ride,
         and we'd always ridden horseback. And Dad decided that horseback with
         a sidesaddle was not an easy way for a person to ride, and that we
         should have stride saddles. And in order to have stride saddles,
         we had to have divided skirts. Well, we got the ladies to make us some
         divided skirts and we wore divided skirts and we rode stride saddle.
         
         SS:  This was unusual for the time?
         
         BC:  Shocking!
         
         SS:  This was unusual for the time?
         
         IA:  Oh, the town! Why, everybody thought it was awful for us to be riding
         stride saddle. Everybody else wore ladies' saddles with a horn on
         'em and a hook on it. And for girls to be riding stride was something
         most unusual!
         
         BC:  And divided skirts shocked 'em!
         
         IA:  My sister and I both rode stride saddle, and we had divided skirts
         that went with it.
         
         SS:  And you didn't care that it was unconventional? It didn't bother you
         girls at all?
         
         IA:  Dad said it was alright, that it was the thing to do, and that's what
         we did!  And we rode horseback all of our lives after that. We rode
         in the timber and we rode on the trails and we rode everywhere.
         
         SS:  How rough was it to get around in the high water of spring out there?
         
         IA:  Out there?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         IA:  When the snow went off, it went off very gradual. The streams across
         these meadows- and the meadows got boggier than they were before, but
         we could still manage to get across them by being ver y careful where
         we walked and all. The horses when they would come to those meadows
         always stopped.
         
         BC:  Shook.
         
         IA:  They just did not want to go in on that boggy land. And the locaterwhen
         we first went out- the locaters had a hard time getting the packhorses
         across the meadows. But as the meadows dried up then the hor
         ses got used to being able to pick their way around and they'd pick
         their way around in the meadows more.
         
         SS:  You mentioned that you used to work on quilt pieces? Out there?
         
         IA:  On what?
         
         SS:  Quilt pieces.
         
         IA:  Quilt pieces?
         
         SS:  Did you do that much?
         
         IA:  Oh, I worked on pieces and quilts because at the time I told you that
         we were from Avery down to TekoGv. coming home-
         
         SS:  You said that man there remembered your quilt pieces.
         
         IA:  Yes, the conductor asked me what we did out there, and, "Oh," I said,
         "we pieced quilts and we do this and we do that." And he said, "My
         mother pieces quilts and she has lots of pieces and I'll see that you
         get some." So when the mail carrier came back out to the cabin he
         brought in a bundle of quilt pieces, and we cut them out and used them
         and worked with the quilts while we were out there.
         
         BC:  Pieced quilts are very valuable now.Vic? flavfc COX%-\c 00r Niece, a/Ow Iivinq
         ,/u
         
         IA:  I pieced quilts after we got in town a good many more than we did out
         in that part of the country.
         BC
         
         SS:  Would you tell me that story about the trouble that you had with the
         car? That your father had with the muffler?
         
         IA:  With the what?
         
         SS:  The muffler on the car. Was that when you were driving down to Lewiston
         that the muffler fell off?
         
         IA:  Dad had just got this new Pike's Peak motor. A car- well, that was
         what the motor was called. It was called a Pike's Peak motor. And
         he wanted to take the family down to Kendrick, and so, he wanted to
         show us the country between here and Kendrick. We got to the top of
         the Kendrick grade and he knew it would be all downhill to Kendrick
         from there. So he snapped off the ignition, and we started coasting.
         And we said,"Dad don't do that, because you might- something might
         happen that you'd want it, and you wouldn't have your engine." "No,
         no, I'll save the gas going down the hill." So he went down the hill,
         clear down to the bottom, and then when he stepped on it, it went, puuf!
         And out went the muffler! Well, we went into Kendrick with this awful
         racket of a muffler. And Kendrick is between two hills, if you re
         member, between two hills and the noise just echoed and reechoed in
         Kendrick. Well Dad stopped at the mechanic Kendrick to see if he
         couldn't get it fixed, and the man there didn't have any muffler and
         didn't have the time-Jfbeing Sunday- he didn't want to go in and fix
         it. So Dad then said, "I'll try Juliaetta." And he went from Ken
         drick to Juliaetta; making the racket all the way up and down that
         little creek that goes down th rough there. He got to Juliaetta and
         the man said, "I don't have a muffler that would fit that," but he
         said, "I can fix it so that you can get home." So he took a piece
         of stovepipe and made a makeshift muffler and put onWof a stovepipe
         so that we could manage to get to Moscow with the stovepipe. Well,
         we got to Moscow, alright, but by the time we got in between the stores
         coming up from Moscow, the old muffler was working just beautifully
         and making all the noise you ever heard. Well, he put his car in the
         garage and he got a man then to send and get him a muffler for that
         and he didn't take that car out until the muffler was fixed. A Pike's
         Peak motor making a noise like that! It was just too much!
         
         SS:  Was he embarrassed driving up the streets of Moscow?
         
         IA:  Was he! He was embarrassed going through Kendrick and equally embar
         rassed through Juliaetta. His brand new car, and making a noise
         like that! It was awful. That Pike's Peak motor- have you ever been
         up Adams Street to the end and looked down over that part of the town
         below? You know how steep that hill is? That Pike's Peak motor could
         come right straight up that hill.
         
         IA:  He tried it. He said he wouldn't buy a car that wouldn't come up that
         hill. And the man that was selling the cars brought the car up the
         hill to prove to Dad that it would do it. So Dad bought a Pike's Peak
         motor.
         
         BC:  But that was his love.
         
         IA:  It was an open car, and everybody wore hats that you could tie down
         with a big veil.
         
         BC:  And goggles.
         
         IA:  Tie under your chin when you rode in the car. And a man pulled his
         hat down low on his head to keep it from blowing off.
         
         BC:  Daddy wore leather gauntlets and a duster.
         
         IA:  We wanted Dad to get a closed car after we'd had this open car and
         closed cars came in, and we wanted him to get a closed car, and he
         wouldn't do it. "No," he said, "the fresh air's good for you. And I
         don't want a closed car." So, we'd been down to Lewiston and were
         coming back and we came in around by Colton and Uniontown and in
         through that way. And on the way home, Mother was sitting on the
         front seat, and she said, "It's just so cold up here I can't take it.
         I'd like to get on the back seat and put a blanket around me." So
         she got on the back seat and Dad slid over and My sister, Marjorie,
         that could drive anything, got on the front seat to drive the car in
         and Dad says, "I'll sit back there with you, Mama." So he crawled on
         the back seat with Mother. And it wasn't very long til Dad pulled his
         handkerchief out and tied it around his neck. A little bit later he
         turned his collar up as high as he could. And he sat back there and
         shivered from about Uniontown on into Moscow. And he said, "Mother,
         it is cold back there. I don't blame you. It's cold on the front seat
         but it's colder back here." So then shortly after that Dad traded his
         little red car off for a sedan that had sidecurtains that would come
         down, that you could putjsidecurtains down it was cold. And we
         always had an enclosed car after that! (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  Did you ever see one of those cars- it was before they had windows in
         cars that you could roll up; it was kind of canvas with little hooks
         that you fastened on the sides of the doors to keep the wind out? It
         was adequate.
         
         IA:  Don't think you ever saw one of those.
         
         SS:  I've seen the pictures, but I've never seen one of them.
         
         IA:  You never the car. They're little turn knobs, you know, we
         used to have, turn a knob and a metal eyelet would fit onto that and
         7turn the knob and that would hold it. And on the next one the same
         way.
         
         BC:  The lights were not electric, I don't think, they were acetylene. I
         think that was the word. And the tank was on the outside and the
         pump was inside, and when the lights would begin to get dim you'd
         have to pump this pump to keep lights bright. I can remember
         pumping.
         
         IA:  There's a good bit of difference between the cars then and the carsnow.
         
         BC:  And I had a millionaire idea once; I was riding with Daddy up to the
         ranch up at Newman Lake, and the horn at that time were down here and
         you had to punch 'em, like this, you know. And I said, "Daddy, why
         couldn't that wire be brought in and put at the steering wheel, and
         you'd have something up here to punch?" I didn't carry on with it
         but that was the beginning of the idea in me that a car could have an
         inside button to punch instead of reaching out and squeezing this horn.
         Taking your hand off the wheel.
         
         SS:  Well, did he take it seriously?
         
         BC:  He didn't mind punching that horn, he probably enjoyed it! I thought
         it was a good idea.
         
         IA:  Did you ever have gout?
         
         SS:  No. No.
         
         BC:  I hope you never do.
         
         IA:  I have gout in my big toe, thatflthe reason—
         
         BC:  The most painful thing.
         
         SS:  Really.
         
         IA:  I've had on three pairs of shoes today and they all hurt. So I got
         back into my old slippers.
         
         BC:  It's faulty metabolism. Your uric acid acid doesn't carry off the cry
         stals and they form on your toe and the pain is excruciating. They
         used to think it was from high living but we
         
         SS:  So you know it's not from-
         
         BC:  Well, I've got a book on it, because I it badly, too. Women don't
         usually have, but my niece has it also, so it's kind of in the family.
         And I got the medical book.
         
         IA:  Cold will bring it on as well as-
         
         IA:  There was a trellis that was covered with this deadly nightshade. They
         were using it for an ornamental vine.
         
         BC:  It's beautiful.
         
         IA:  And the Mc Connells had it for a vine up on this trellis. Well, we
         took it down- my father didn't like it, he was afraid that some of the
         children or someone might get ahold of it and it would prove fatal.
         So he had it taken down. And we lost it for a number of years; didn't
         know what had happened to it. And all of a sudden on the second house
         over, right along the alleyway a great bunch of it sprung up, and it
         covered that fence along there. When Mr. Hallax bought the place and
         I told him that that was deadly nightshade and.be sure that the children
         didn't fool with the bush or eat any of the berries. So he said
         he would be very careful, and he dug it out while he lived there. This
         year there was one of those vines came up on my side of the driveway
         and over the fence between the two places. So I just left it grow, I
         knew what it looked like- it had the red berries on it- so I just let
         it grow there and I went up the other day and picked enough to put in4
         the bamboo.
         
         SS:  Do you think it was the same stock?
         
         IA:  It's the same kind of a berry, probably from the same old berr . It
         could have been buried there for years and then come up. I don't know.
         
         SS:  That's hardy.
         
         BC:  looked it up in the dictionary and it said sometimes it was used
         for a hallucinatory drug, and it was deadly poison, but they had some
         way of refining it. And it is related to the henbane. You know what
         henbane is?
         
         SS:  I've heard of it.
         
         BC:  Well, one time I was in South Idaho, my brother-in-law, was in charge
         of raising sheep. And I was visiting them and there was four or five
         men came out one day gathering this shrub. And I was curious and I
         asked what they were gathering. They said, henbane. They said it was
         related to marijuana, I don't think they were men a£
         all. They had great big cans of it and just it. And that
         was along about 1936.
         
         SS:  So you think they were using it for—?
         
         BC:  I think so.
         
         IA:  I laughed the other day when I picked up the paper and read where by
         the sheriff's office they found marijuana growing just outside the
         steps. And someone had dropped the seed there and it was growing just
         outside the steps at the sheriff's office.
         
         SS:  This nightshade? Now ehere was it growing on the man son- on the old
         house to start with? Where did you find it growing?
         
         IA:  I found it on the fence.
         
         SS:  No, I mean in the old days. Where was it growing?
         
         IA:  It was growing between the little porch on this side- between the
         little porch and the first bay window. And it was growing up
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13603</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Adair1</previous>
      <next>Adair3</next>
      <disp_name>Adair2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
