<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/24/1977</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ione Adair, 1977-02-24, Interview #5 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:30:36</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Adair, Ione</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #5</intnum>
      <occupation>County assessor, teacher, postal clerk, timber homesteader</occupation>
      <birthyear>1883</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow, Bovill, Fortynine Meadows</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Oregon and Indiana (1893); family lived in the McConnell mansion
         (1900-36)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#forest fires"&gt;forest fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#suicide"&gt;suicide&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teaching"&gt;teaching&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#divorces"&gt;divorces&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Fortynine Meadows"&gt;Fortynine Meadows&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Wallace"&gt;Wallace&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13362</file_name>
      <mp3>13363.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13363.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Female Homesteaders; Appearance of Dynamite</title>
            <synopsis>The "colony" of women homesteaders in the timber. Staying with Mrs. Durham in the
               winter; Mrs. Durham's fall from a ladder. Appearance of "Dynamite." 
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>A Hearing in Wallace about the Homestead; Travelling with Quinsey</title>
            <synopsis>Going to Wallace from homestead in winter for a hearing on legality of her homestead.
               Travelling with Quinsey. Evening with Elsie Pfiel and her bulldog in the government
               cabin.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Losing the Homestead; Fighting the 1910 Fire</title>
            <synopsis>Loss of homestead due to report of Ashley Roach, a "patent leather" man from the East.
               Involvement in fighting fire of 1910 as cook for crew headed by Roach, (continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>The 1910 Fire; Returning to Moscow after the Fire</title>
            <synopsis>Cooking for fire fighters in 1910 fire. A man lost with the cooking supplies. She
               got "buck fever" when trying to shoot a deer. A very close call in the fire. Her return
               to Moscow after the fire. Roach's discomfort when fighting the fire. Intention of
               homesteaders to sell to lumber company for a good price.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Pack Trip with A.J. Fleming</title>
            <synopsis>A pack trip with A.J.Fleming, who had a bad hangover; his "discovery" of a bottle
               on the way. Fleming was a remittance man and a poet.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Loss of Homestead to Railroads; Timber Claim on Ruby Creek</title>
            <synopsis>She lived on homestead continuously for almost two years Loss of homestead to railroads.
               Her stone and timber claim on Ruby Creek.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Potlatch Pays for Damages</title>
            <synopsis>A cook offered to testify against Potlatch because of its responsibility for the burning
               of her timber claim, but they agreed to pay for damage.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Adair's Self Reliance; Flu Epidemic</title>
            <synopsis>Father approved of her homesteading. Driving father around during flu epidemic. Her
               ability to care for herself: pulling her own tooth as a child. A dentist who won her
               over with the violin.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Motivating other Female Homesteaders</title>
            <synopsis>She was courageous and independent. Background and motivation of other women homesteaders.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>Father's Background; Running for County Treasurer</title>
            <synopsis>Father's background and pioneering instincts; he grew up in Oregon. She was ahead
               of her time; she always went her own way. She ran for county treasurer.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Father's Last Illness</title>
            <synopsis>Father darkened his eyebrows his last illness. Father's inability to hear Dr. Brosnan
               was misinterpreted as close attention.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>Teaching at Moscow School; Discipline</title>
            <synopsis>Teaching school in Moscow. Strict discipline, responsibility for children. A boy who
               was willing to confess the details of vandalism only when Harry Orchard confessed.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6120</time>
            <title>Impressions of Senator Borah; Stories about the Borahs</title>
            <synopsis>Impression of Senator Borah as "a lone wolf." Correction of some stories told about
               the Adairs. Friendship with Mary Borah. A story Mrs. Borah told of her maid. Closeness
               to her sister, Carrie McConnell Bush. A grandmother who couldn't recall how many children
               she had.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6720</time>
            <title>Mary Borah and the Bush Family; The Stigma of Divorce</title>
            <synopsis>More about Mary Borah and Carrie Bush. Lack of closeness in the Bush family; they
               spent their time with others rather than with each other. The stigma of divorce in
               society.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7080</time>
            <title>The Shooting of Mr. Creighton</title>
            <synopsis>Father witnessed shooting of Mr. Creighton by Steffen.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Sister Margie Quieting Father</title>
            <synopsis>Sister Margie quieted father by reciting "the Golden Text."
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7620</time>
            <title>Dr. Watkins' Murder; Shooting of Steffen</title>
            <synopsis>Father was given Dr. Watkin's sleigh bells by Mrs. Watkins. Shooting of Steffen by
               posse after he killed Dr. Watkins. Dr. Watkins was responsible for judging Steffen
               insane and sending him to Orofino.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8040</time>
            <title>Mrs. Brown's Suicide; Elsie Pfiel raising Carol Brink; Miss Elsie Saving Wallace in
               the 1910 Fire
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Suicide of Mrs. Brown, the Watkins' daughter, rather than face an unhappy marriage
               or divorce; Aunt Elsie Pfiel then raised Carol Brink, her daughter. Carol Brink's
               idealization of her Uncle Douglas. Miss Elsie: her story of the saving of Wallace
               in the 1910 fire by prayer before the statue at the Catholic Church. Carol Brink's
               pony and cart. At her birthday parties each person was given a gift.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Bernadine Cornelison. Women homesteaders in the timber. Experiences of 1910
         fire. Friendship with father. Dr. Watkins family. Carrie Bush and Mary Borah. 2-24-77
         2.5 hr
         59p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: I wondered why there were so many women here.
         
         IONE ADAIR: Why the women went out there. Well, in the first place, the locater
         out that part of the country had a wife that wanted a timber claim.
         A sister that wanted a timber claim; two sisters that wanted timber
         claims. And there was a couple of women here in town that wanted tim
         ber claims that we all knew. So, when the locater had located this
         particular batch of timber out in what was called the Forty-Nine Mea
         dow country, and he took this bunch out to show them the country and
         the timber and if they wanted to locate, then we could all locate there
         with him, a certain distance of each other. Practically a little colony
         by themselves. So that's the way we all happened to go out there. I
         joined the fcunch with Mrs. Torson and Mrs. Durham and Mrs. Taylor and
         Winifred Calkins and Kit Calkins and who else? Oh, following us when
         we located out there was Erwin Hanson and Art Larson went out with him
         just to be on the homestead with him so he'd have company. And they
         were on one side and they were four miles and a half off on one side
         and Mrs. Torson was in three-quarters of a mile from Mrs. Durham and
         my homestead was about four miles over on the other side and Mrs.
         Taylor's was over that way. And so we all got together just as a group
         and would take our trips out together. And it was a saving on packers
         and so forth when we all went together.
         
         SS:  Were most of these ladies as self-reliant as you were?
         
         IA:  I didn't quite hear you.
         
         SS:  It seemed like to be a homesteader, it took a lot of self-reliance,
         you know, you had to depend on yourself and your own resources.
         
         IA:  You had to depend upon yourself. But the others, of course, surrounding
         you that were homesteaders- had took up homesteacfe, all helped if you
         needed any help or anything like that. And Mrs. Durham and I planned winter
         together. I was four miles and a half from her place and
         so we decided that she and her daughter and I would live together that
         winter and I would go back and forth to my place as I wished. And it
         mostly,
         was all snowshoeing of course,.and that's the way we traveled. Then my
         father was afraid that something might happen and that we'd have no
         means of getting word out to the outside of an emergency. So he and
         Mrs. Durham and I decided that we'd hire a man to stay with us that
         winter. And so my father made the arrangements with a man by the name
         Carter. And Bill Carter said that he would trap that winter and would
         try to make up for any additional expenses that he would do- or needed,
         and that he would go out once a month anyway to get the mail and bring
         it to us, and the rest of the time he would spend trapping in that part
         of the country.
         
         SS:  Was he staying at the same cabin that you and-
         
         IA:  Mrs. Durham and her daughter and I- we were the three that were And Mrs. Torson,
         who was a here in town, had a cabin, oh,
         about three-quarters of a mile from out place. But she only spent the
         summers out there, her sister ran the business here in town and she
         went out and spent it on the homestead while the weather was good.
         
         SS:  I was just wondering; when he was there, did he have to sleep in the
         barn? No Barn.
         
         SS:  Did he have to sleep in the house because there was no barn there? He
         could sleep in the house too, then?
         
         IA:  He slept in the house with us; yes. We had, I don't know whether you
         know bear grass or not, but it's a very wiry grass and holds up when
         you made your mattress of it, and we made a full siae mattress. He
         was over six feet tall. (Chuckles) We made a full sized mattress for
         him of : and each day we would roll it up, put a blanket over it and
         could be used as a seat in case that you wanted extra accommodations.
         
         SS:  Just a mat of bear grass?
         
         IA:  Uh-huh. Just a mattress of bear grass. We made the mattress out of
         gunny sacks that we had and then cut the bear grass and made the mat
         tress for him. And that was his bedroom. And we had a bedroom across
         the end of the cabin, and I had a single bed and Mrs. Durham and her
         daughter had a double bed. And during the daytime we had fixed them
         so they would- the double bed would fold up in the wall and out of the
         way and the single bed used as a seat in the daytime.
         
         BERNADINE ADAIR CORNELISON: Didn't you have an attic in that place, a second story?
         
         IA:  Yes, we had an attic, and that's where we kept the flour and sugar and
         things that would- that the moisture might affect. We had an outdoor
         cellar and we kept the canned goods in this outdoor cellar, but the
         cupboard was the attic. We kept the flour and the sugar because that
         would be warm from the heat in the cabin, and it wouldn't get solid.
         Carter, one day, got everything all ready to go out the mail and
         left early in the morning for the we called it twenty-eight miles
         out to Avery by trail, and he didn't go back into Clarkia, because
         that was a longer route, it took forty-five miles to get in that way.
         So, he went out the short way to Avery, and the mail was all sent to
         Avery, and he would go out and get it. Well, he got everything all
         ready and left early and after he left Mrs. Durham decided that she
         had to wash, and the extra soap and stuff that she needed was up in
         the attic. And the only way into the attic was by ladder and a trap
         door. So, we brought in the ladder and opened the trapdoor and Mrs.
         Durham went up to the attic to get the flour or whatever it was that
         she needed and about the time she got up there the ice on the legs
         of the ladder broke off and the ladder went down. Mrs. Durham went
         with it, and as she went down she hit the end of her spine on the lad
         der and dropped off in a faint. Well Myrtle and I didn't know what to
         do, so we just grabbed up bottle of camphor that was there and in
         tending to put it up under her nose or where she'd breathe it, and
         Myrtle miscalculated and put it on her eye- on her forehead that ran
         down into her eye. Well, that brought Mrs. Durham to in one grand
         rush! We grabbed her while she was in that condition and put her over
         on my bed and she laid there all afternoon, just moaning, "Oh, my tailbone,
         oh, my tailbone." And nearly drove us crazy because we didn't
         know what to do about it until Carter got back anyway. We couldn't
         send word out; we couldn't do anything. And we neither one of us were
         going off and leaving the other one alone with the mother on a twentyeight
         mile trp out to town. 
         
         So we just endured moaning and tried to
         keep her as comfortable as possible. Well, when Carter got back then
         he could see that Mrs. Durham was in a very bad condition and would
         have to be taken out to town. And so, we waited for about a week un
         til she got to feeling a little better and then Carter took her and
         started off to Avery. That was a twenty-eight mile trip for a woman
         with her tailbone injured and on snowshoes! So she got along very ni
         cely until about the last mile and a half or two miles of the trip and
         then she broke down. She just couldn't go any farther, so Carter
         practically carried her on to Avery and then they got transpor
         tation from Avery on the train and brought her down to Teko and on
         into Moscow. So we had her in the hospital for quite a little while
         here after that til she began to get better. So Myrtle and I were
         then left alone with just Carter as companion. And so we got along
         very nicely. But the next time Carter went out to Avery to see how
         Mrs. Durham was getting along and it left Myrtle and I alone, and we
         were sitting eating our breakfast one morning and the cabin door opened
         and in walked this grizzly, funny looking, little, old fellow and he
         said, "Oh, you're here." And we said, "Yes, who are yo u?" He said,
         "I'm Dynamite." And I said, "You are?" He said, "Yes, they all call
         me Dynamite." He said, "I'm working on the railroad"and on the tunnel
         and I do the drilling for the holes and putting the dynamite in, and
         that's where I got my name." I said, "You do have another name, don't
         you?" He said, "Yes, I'm Joel/chandler Harris." (Chuckles) And, he
         said, "My mother thought the name of Joel Chandler sounds very nice.
         She'd been reading about him, and so she called me Joel Chandler Harris."
         Well he came in and he stayed- he said, "I'll stay here until your man
         gets back." So he stayed; we couldn't say, "Get out!" We had no means
         of putting him out or anything and so we said, "Alright." So he took
         the bed- unrolled the bed that night and then that was his bed til Car
         ter got back. Well, when Carter got back then Dynamite left and went
         over to Larson and Hanson's cabin and he spent the greater part of the
         winter at the Larson and Hanson cabin. He was a funny looking little
         fellow. Whiskers all over.
         
         SS:  Did he stay there?
         
         IA:  He said, "ive been living in your cabin while you were gone." (Laughs)
         "We knew somebody had been there but we had no idea who nor what." He
         said,"I was in there. But when your man gets back I'll go over to the
         boys." And that's what he did.
         
         SS:  Was he staying there to protect you? Was that the idea?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Was he staying there to protect you? Was that his thinking?
         
         IA:  We don't know. We don't know what his idea was, he was just looking
         a place to land,,, and he just landed. And so we did a lot of blanket
         washing and all when- after he left.(Chuckles)
         
         SS:  You know, he stayed at Elsie place, too. Because I know Carol
         Brink once mentioned that to me. She mentioned this guy Dynamite.
         
         IA:  She spoke about Dynamite, too, did she?
         
         SS:  Yes, she did.
         
         IA:  Well, Elsie was across on what they called another branch of the little
         Norseman, called the Floodwood. It went south and east. It went south
         and east and the Potlatch went the other way, and we were on the other
         side of the ridge from Elsie. She was quite a character. You should
         have known her. (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  She was delightful.
         
         IA:  She certainly was. One night we were going on the trip, my fatherafter
         I'd been out there so long, the government decided I had to come
         in to a trail at Wallace. And in order to get to the trial at Wallace
         I had to be notified to get out there, and there was no one in this
         part of the country that knew where I was or location or anything, and
         so my father undertook to come out and notify me; which he did. And
         he left word that we would need a packer to bring us out, and he wal
         ked out that twenty-five miles from Avery, or twenty-eight miles, and
         told me that I had to come in for the trip, And so they got
         the packer out and the packer, Ira Mc Peek, lived at Clarkia, and
         he had been packing things with the Forest so that he knew where we
         were and how to get to us and so forth. And he brought the horses out
         for us. And he brought a horse out for me to ride that an Indian had
         owned, and he lost the race for the Indian and the Indian was so mad
         that he cut the horse's tailfoff and his ears right close to his head.
         Well, the day that we started out with the packtrain after my father
         got there, they put me on Jim, the horse
         
         BC:  Bob.
         
         IA:  What? What was he?
         
         BC:  Bob. Called the horse Bob.
         
         IA:  Bob, because of his bobbed ears and his bobbed tail. And Mc Peek said,
         "You ride Bob because he is so surefooted." And, he said, "You ride
         out on Bob." Well, I had taken cold a little while before and I was
         subject to attacks of quinsy, and so they dolled me up in everything
         they could find in the cabin that was warm and I mounted Bob and we
         started out. Well, there was one place that we used to call Little
         Lake Thelma, it's a different name than that now on the map, and I
         don't know what it's called now. But at any rate, you had to go up a
         very high, very steep ridge to get up to the top and come on over into
         the Clarkia country, and we always in going up hung onto our horse's
         tail and made the horse pull us up instead of riding because it was
         this way, it was so rough you couldn't ride comfortably on it and we
         always held onto the horse's tail. Well, I was on Bob, which had neither
         ears nor tail, and so I had to stay on the horse and I'd been having
         the quinsy at the cabin and was not in a very good condition to be ri
         ding out there anyway, so we got to the- what was called the- not the
         company, it was the halfway cabin, it was a government cabin, and they
         had blankets and cooking utensils and heating and so forth at the cabin.
         We got to the cabin that night and who was at the cabin but Elsie
         Pfiel. She had heard that-
         
         BC:  Ione's giving a recording, can you come again?
         
         SS:  So you met- So Elsie Pfiel was there?
         
         IA:  Elsie Pfiel had heard through the- well, I suppose it would be the wireless (Chuckles)
         that Mc Peek was coming out to our place and she wan
         ted to come out to Clarkia, so she walked from her place and down to
         this government cabin, because she knew we'd stop there, and she had
         with her a great, big, bulldog, and that was for protection on her ca
         bin that she had this big bulldog. Well, she was at the cabin that
         night when we got in. And I had this enormous head of hair and that
         rain had wet the neck of the turtleneckI was wearing, and the sweater
         was wet and we couldn't get out of the sweater. So Mc Peek took one
         -top side, the one side; Elsie took the other and they took my hair
         down and just skinned this turtleneck sweater up over my head until
         they finally got it off and I was made as comfortable as possible. El
         sie and I slept in one bed that night, those little bunkbeds in the
         government cabin and along in the night came the pack rats. And the
         bulldog didn't like pack rats, so he started chasing them all around
         the house, in the cabin, all around the floor and whenever the pack
         rat - the dog would get too close, the pack rat ended up on the bed
         and the dog up after him! You can imagine how much sleep went on in
         that cabin that night! We couldn't calm the dog down on account of
         the rat and we couldn't catch the rat'and he couldn't catch the rat!
         
         SS:  Couldn't just kick him out of the cabin?
         
         IA:  Couldn't chase him out. They didn't have any idea of going out of the
         cabin.
         
         SS:  The dog.
         
         IA:  The dog?
         
         BC:  Yeah.
         
         IA:  Oh, no, it was cold. Snow deep outside. You don't put a dog out in
         the snow and leave him, especially a short haired dog like a bull
         dog. But we got up the next morning and went on into Clarkia and
         Elsie took the dog and went with us, and we all got to Clarkia safe!
         And that was quite a trip that time.
         
         SS:  Your father had come out all that distance by snowshoe? He snowshoed
         out to the cabin?
         
         IA:  Yes. Snowshoes or walking.
         
         BC:  Which because he person.
         
         SS:  Well, when you got to Clarkia you still had a long way to go to Wallace.
         Did you get on a train then?
         
         IA:  No. Oh, I had a long ways to go. Yes, my father stayed there and with
         me for two or three days til I got my throat cleared out, and then we
         went on up to Wallace and got there in time for the trial. The diffi
         culty was that the railroad had placed- what do you say? entries? Had
         filed on a lot of what was supposed to be railroadlland in that section
         of the country, and they were given by the government certain townships
         and certain- oh, what do you call it?- They had their rights- the rail
         roads had rights over certain townships in order to settle up this part
         of the country. And some of those railroads- townships- or filings
         were over on my place and part of them were on Mrs. Calkin's place.
         So we all had to go in for the government hearing at Wallace. But we
         could take the train from Teko and make connections and get up to Wal
         lace for the trial.
         
         SS:  Did you win that time?
         
         IA:  No.
         
         SS:  You lost that?
         
         IA:  I lost it. I lived there for twenty-two months or more and fought the
         fire and fed the firemen with the help and made the trips back and
         forth. But I lost it.VkDid the best we could and Burton L. French
         was the representative from Idaho back at Washington, D. C, and
         Burton tried his best to have it reopened and a new man put on, but
         they said no, that it wasn't, that I was over on the other- my location
         had gone over; that I hadn't lived out there a sufficient length of
         time. They sent out one of these little- we called them patent leather
         men- from Washington, D. C. Patent leather shoe men, that didn't know
         a darn thing about timber or living in the woods or even living! And
         he'd come in and he'd look over your little cabin and say, "It's not a
         suitable habitation." And I had a little garden patch, and I'd raised
         radishes and lettuce out there and all. He looked at my garden patch
         and says, "It's not sufficient cultivation."
         
         SS:  To your face?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  To your face?
         
         IA:  Yes, oh, yes. He didn't mind telling us. That went on like that, he
         came in and he got Mrs. Durham and Mrs. Torson's place and my place
         and Kit Calkins place right next to mine where she was located on one
         end of the meadow and I was at the other end of the meadow. Our cabins
         were quite close, so that I had company out there. And she lost hers,
         and I don't know, there was a whole bunch of them in through there that
         lost it, on account of this man from Washington, D. C. that didn't think
         people could live under those conditions, although we were living under
         them. Well, during the fire season in 1910, this same man was put in
         charge of the firefighters brigade, that was sent out into that part of
         the country. And at that time, he had sent his report in to Washing
         ton, D. C. and they'd cancelled all of our homesteads out there, but we
         were still on the homesteads, because we didn't know but what it might
         be opened- or reopened, at any time. You never know when you were figh
         ting it. And he was put on in charge of the firefighting brigade that
         went out into that section of the country. And one morning Mrs. Taylor
         
         SIDE B
         
         who lived alone about a mile and a half or two miles from Mi rs. Calkins
         place, and she was a little uneasy about the smoke that had been drif
         ting into the country, so she came over to stay with me. So as not to
         be alone at her cabin in case anything should happen. Well, we werethere
         was a rap at the door, as it was just barely daylight outside,
         and Mrs. Taylor got up and answered the door, and there was this man
         who had reported all these homesteaders, standing at the door and he
         said that he was in charge of a fire fighting crew and that they were
         trying to locate the fire which was causing all this smoke in this part
         of the country. And he wanted to know if there was a trail any farther
         east. So she told him of her trail that went farther east and he said
         he'd take his crew and go over there. Well, we got up and dressed and
         decided that we'd walk over and see if. they had found her cabin and if
         they were still there; which they were when we got there. And the men
         that were camping around the fire on the outside, some of them, and
         some of them were inside of the cabin, and were trying to get something
         for breakfast. And Mrs. Taylor said that she would help the men. So
         she got busy and fixed pancackes and things for the men inside t he
         cabin and outside the cabin. And when they went to move on then to lo
         cate farther to locate the fire, Mr, Roach said to Mrs. Taylor, "Woul
         dn't you ladies like to go on with us a little farther and get a meal
         for us at noon? So we'd have something to eat." And we said we would.
         We got them a lunch of pancackes or rolled cakes so they'd
         have something to eat at noon, and that evening then, they wanted us to
         stay and get the evening meal for them. Well, that was my first attempt
         atCooking outside over a fireplace, and also Mrs. Taylor's first attempt,
         But we managed to get something for the men to eat that night and they
         fixed a bed for us right along by the side of the horses that
         they had taken in there. And the horses kept stomping and chewing and
         stomping and trying to fight the flies all night long, so we didn't
         get very much sleep. But the next morning they wanted us to continue
         on and take care of the men we had.
         
         BC:  How many did you have?
         
         IA:  We had about ten or fifteen that we were trying to fix for them, and
         they had their own provisions, but we had to take care of the provisions
         and the cooking. By the way, it took me years to like potatoes! I
         cooked so many potatoes in waterbuckets over the fire, that I didn't
         like potatoes for a long, long time.
         
         SS:  Were you prepared to go on with them? You didn't have your clothing
         and all your belongings, did you?
         
         IA:  No, we just wore what we had and got along for the time being. Because
         
         BC: A little knapsack.) they had to keep on working and going farther. They had a
         man what
         was his name? Johnny, Johnny, Johnny- at any rate, he was a man here
         in town that we knew of that was a cook and he had gone on a fire figh
         ting crew just for the experience and was a cook. And they left him
         up on the top of what was called the Freezeout Ridge when they camped
         there the night before coming on to our cabin, and they left him up
         there and he said that he would pack things and have «Nieything all ready
         and that the crew coming through could pick them up and that he'd cut
         across country and come over to this part of the country. But, Johnny
         missed the packers and Johnny missed everything when he started out
         across country and he got lost. And so he just kept traveling, he said
         he thought he'd find something sometime. And he finally landed in the
         camp, but by that time they needed fire fighters so bad that Johnny
         wasn't allowed to cook, he was put on the fire fighting and Mrs. Durham and I continued
         cooking. Well then they brought in a- what were
         they called?- they were shorttermers-
         
         SS:  You told me about that. Yeah.
         
         IA:  From Montana.
         
         SS:  Right.
         
         IA:  And they had a camp right next to ours. But they had their own cook.
         And finally Mr. Roach gave Mrs. Taylor and me a man and a flunky to
         so help us out;(we didn't have quite so much work to do after that. But
         at any rate, Johnny was put on the fir line.
         
         BC:  How long did you cook for them lone?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  How long did you cook for them?
         
         IA:  we cooked for over forty days. The government paid us the full for a
         little over forty days, for our services,
         
         BC:  How much?
         
         IA:  for the fire fighters. Oh,I don't know, it was forty something dollars.
         It was about a dollar a day, I think.
         
         SS:  What did you think of the experience at the time?
         
         IA:  At the time?
         
         SS:  Yes, at the time. What did you think of that?
         It was just experience, that was all. Always something new coming up.
         Something that you weren't expecting; like the fire. And one morning
         it was so smokey outside after a perfectly still nightthen the smoke
         would drop down with the, I suppose it was the dampness of the evening,
         that the smoke would drop down. And I heard a noise out on the clear
         ing near Mrs. Calkins' cabin and I got up and Mrs. Taylor said, "What
         are you going to do?" And I said, "I'm going to see what the racket is."
         And so I got up and put on my robe and went outside and took my gun; I
         had a revolver along with me, and I took my gun and went outside and
         just at the edge of the clearing on the other side was abeautiful lit
         tle deer. I never had shot at a deer. I'd eaten the meat and loved
         it. So I thought, oh, gee, that would be good to have some meat. So
         I took old Betsy and aimed at the deer. Well, about that time the gun
         began to go this way and this way and this way and up and down and up
         and down! And I gut "buck fever" and I couldn't shoot! I couldn't
         shoot at that deer. I just had "Buck fever" too bad! So I missed the
         deer and I went back into the cabin and stayed there.! Finally got over
         my "buck fever". (Chuckles) Is "buck fever" what happens when you try to shoot a deer?
         
         IA:  Yes.
         
         BC:  (When you get the shakes.
         
         IA:  You get "'buck fever", that is, you're nervousness, the n eryes of your
         body are all out of control. And your gun arm means nothing! You
         just go one way or the other. I tried holding it with both hands and
         it didn't work or anything, so I just turned around and—
         
         BC:  Did she ever tell you the final chapter of this Mr. Roach?
         
         SS:  Yes, I think so. Yes, he apologized.
         
         BC:  Yes, he apologized. I'd forgotten.
         I was going to ask you when you were on that fire cooking, did you
         ever have to move the camp to get away from the fire?
         Not exactly. We were camped on one side of the river and they decided that that was
         a poor place for our camp, there was a more level
         place across on the other side, so they fixed up a fireplace on the
         other side and moved our camp over. Well, the firefighters were all
         out on the line and one day there was a heavy wind came up and we no
         ticed that the men were beginning to come in off of the fire line,
         both at our camp and at the other camp, the Montana camp across the
         line, and we wanted to know what and they said, "Well, this is as near
         ly a clear place as there is from here up to where the fireline is."
         And they said there is no way of stopping it with this wind. And we
         said, "Well, what do we do?" They said, there1£ only one thing
         to do that we can tell, and that's to take your blankets and go down to
         the stream, and if the fire comes close, get into the water and cover
         your head with the blanket, leaving an airspace and stay until the fire
         is passed over. It may be awfully hot, but if you're in the water, you
         possibly could survive anyway. That would be the only way of doing it.
         So that's what the two men that they'd left us for lackey boys with us
         and the men that had drifted back, all got their blankets and we went
         down to this stream and we sat there on the log at the edge of this
         stream and watched the fire coming. Well, somewhere while we were sit
         ting there, somewhere along, nature took a funny little quirk and a
         wind began coming from the other direction and forced the fire back
         and it was within a very short distance of where we were camped there
         at the creek. But it forced the fire back the other way and it didn't
         come in through our little corner of the woods. So we were very for
         tunate that time. I thought I'd said goodbye to everybody!
         
         BC:  We did, too.
         
         IA:  My father went out to Clarkia and tried his best to get Mc Peek or some
         one to give him a horse and let him go out to our cabin. He wanted to
         know what had happened to us. He hadn't heard from us. He didn't know
         what had happened to us, and he had a daughter out there somewhere and
         the men wouldn't give him a horse, they wouldn't allow him to leave Clar
         kia. He had to stay there at Clarkia and get word, if he could. But
         he stayed there at Clarkia for a few days. He couldn't get any word
         from us because of the fire
         
         BC:  When she came home she was wearing these filthy dirty ienaici clothes.
         Her hair was singed. Her eyebrows were kind of moth eaten and her fare.
         
         IA:  Beautiful looking!
         
         BC:  And she came up the street, and were we glad to see her!
         
         IA:  Oh, dear! Well, I started to tell you this man, Ashley J. Roach-
         
         BC:  You told him that, lone.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  You told him that. About Pierce.
         
         IA:  About what?
         
         BC:  About meeting him at Pierce.
         
         SS:  Oh, she told me-
         
         IA: I did tell you about meeting him at Pierce. But while we were on
         the fireline up there, Ashley J. Roach was taken with the heat of the
         summer and all the responisbilities of the fire and the firemen and
         all and he got a very severe case of diarrhea, the summer diarrhea.
         And he came back into camp looking like a lost sheep. I never saw any
         body look like he did. And I said, "What's the trouble?" And he told
         me. And I said, "Well, I can't go myself because I have to stay and
         help Mrs. Taylor get something for your men to eat tonight, but if you
         will give me man by the name of Ricketts,"which I knew here in
         Moscow- I knew his wife and Jack Ricketts- I said, "I'll tell him where
         to get some medicine in my cabin, and I'll send him back to the cabin
         and get something which I think will help you." Well, my father, being
         a doctor, had given us all kinds of every medicine that he thought we
         would possibly use, and I knew where it was and what it was, and when
         he found Ricketts, and I sent Ricketts back to the cabin and Ricketts
         got some clean clothes for me and some clean clothes for Mrs. Taylor
         on his trip and the medicine for A. J. Roach. Well, A. J. Roach took
         it and within a short time was able to get back on the fireline again.
         
         BC:  Sure were nice to him!
         
         SS:  Yeah, you were pretty nice to him considering that he wasn't very nice
         to you.
         
         IA:  No, he wasn't. But then, the man was in trouble and he had to have
         help. And I had the means of giving it to him, so I got it for him.
         
         SS:  What did you think of him though?
         
         IA:  What did I think of him?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         IA:  I didn't think very much of him. But I had to respect him because he
         was at the head of the camp and all, and disrespect should not have
         been given to him because he was doing the job he was given to do, al
         though he was not trained for it, but he was doing the best he could.
         But I didn't like him. I didn't like him at all.
         
         BC:  Now what's your next question?
         
         SS:  If the homesteaders had been able to prove up on those places, would
         they have sold to the lumber companies after it was proved up?
         
         IA:  Yes. The lumber companies were in this part of the country, all through
         that section of the country, Clarkia and the Meadow country and beyond
         and from there clear up| on into Avery. They were buying the timber
         from these homesteaders. And those that were allowed to prove up sold
         their places. But those others lost it and lost their time and lost
         the money that it took to do theA improving and all.
         
         SS:  I'ould there have been a pretty good profit for the people who proved
         up?
         
         IA:  They thought so at that time. Most of the people out there would get
         all the way from 3,000 to 8,000, depending upon the stand of timber
         on the particular location. And some of them got along very nicely.
         This Elsie Pfiel; I just don't remember rightly whether she sold hers
         or whether she lost it.
         SS; I think she lost it.
         
         IA:  She lost it.
         
         SS:  I think so.
         
         IA:  Mrs. Brown, Delia Brown Griffith, had a claim right close to Mrs. Pfiel
         and I think that she got her claim. Some of them did in that location
         and some didn't.
         
         Remember me telling about Dynamite being at our door; when Carter got
         back he said that- no not Carter, but a man by the name of Fleming
         came. Myrtle and I had been out to Moscow to see Mrs. Durham when she
         was in the hospital, and Carter took us out, but Carter had some other
         business on hand and didn't want to take us back and so my father made -
         called Avery and found that there was a man there by the name of Fle
         ming, A. J. Fleming from Canada that knew that section of the country
         and the trail and would be glad to take us back to the homestead. And
         that's the way we got back to the homestead, was by Fleming taking us.
         But Fleming and Dynamite over at the boys' cabin; Dynamite was staying
         with Hanson and Larson, and they decided they wanted something to read,
         and they knew that Mrs. Brown had left a lot of reading amterial at her
         cabin, so they decided that they would go over and get some of this ma
         terial and bring it over to us so that we'd have something to read, like
         wise. Well, when they went to investigating the cabin they found
         phonograph records, and we had one of these little tiny- the first lit
         tle phonographs with a long morning glory horn and all; we had o ne of
         those. And so they saw these records over there and decided that they'd
         bring us some records. So they brought over a load of records for us.
         We had a great time playing those records we hadn't heard before. And
         they brought the magazines for us. And Fleming spent two nights or
         three nights there with us and Dynamite.
         
         BC:  Was he the one that liked liquor?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Was he the one that liked liquor? Of course it was taboo. And one of
         these two mentaking them out, back there where they were going, as
         they were crossing a little bridge he looked down and he said, "Oh,
         there's a bottle of liquor." Well, he'd stashed it there!
         
         IA:  He climbed down off of the bridge and down onto the and picked it up.
         It had never been opened. Somebody had "lost" a bottle of liquor, and
         he picked it up.
         
         BC:  I thought that was pretty smart.
         
         IA:  And said, "We'll just take it with us. We might need it." Well, he
         was just getting over a St. Patrick's Day booze affair. He'd been
         drunk for quite a while. But the man at the office said that he was
         alright, that he knew the country and that he was over it sufficient
         and he could take us back in. Well, we picked up the bottle of
         4-0 liquor and he started to put it in his bag, inAhis knapsack, and I said,
         "A. J. I think I'd like that." And he turned around and gave me a look
         and handed me the bottle. Well, I put the bottle in my knapsack then
         and carried it. I thought, well, you don't get any unless you take me
         with it! Well, we got the the cabin, to the government cabin, half
         way cabin between Avery and the homestead-
         
         BC:  That was just a lean-to, wasn't it? KBoughs put up to keep the rain. Oh, yes,
         it was just a lean-to, it wasn't a cabin, it was just a lean-to.
         A three-sided lean-to with a rooif oyer it, and you built your fire out
         in front of it and the heat came in, supposedly, to keep you warm. It
         did, but it also melted the snow the roof and the water dropped
         down your back in the middle of the night and scared the life out of you!
         But at any rate, we reached the cabin- had gotten about a mile and a
         half out from the cabin, A. J.'s, oh, what do I call it?- with
         liquor caught up with him, and he got to the point that he just couldn't
         carry his knapsack any longer, it was too heavy. So Myrtle and I divi
         ded the knapsack and put it on our backs and helped A. J. as nearly as
         we could til we got to the lean-to. Well, he curled up at the lean-to
         for a little while and we gathered up a little kindling. Everyone that
         was supposed to use the lean-to was supposed to leave k indling enough
         or wood enough for the following to use. And we started a fire
         outside and got A. J. next to the fire and got him sort of thawed out
         a little bit. And I said, "Would you like a drink?" And he said he
         would love it. So, Mytle and I mixed up- got some hot water from the
         vessels there and we fixed up a drink for each of us. Making it light
         but with heat and the liquor was enough that Fleming soon got -\hft\h
         enough so that he could get up and get firewood enough to keep us for
         the night. And he sat out by the fire and kept things going and we
         sat inside the lean-to and fought the water drippings! (Chuckles)
         But in the morning we all got up; had our breakfast and started on to
         the cabin. We got through the night alright!
         
         BC:  Maybe "finding" that liquor was a good thing!
         
         IA:  A. J. Fleming was a remittance man from Canada. He'd been shipped over
         from England and was a remittance man from Canada, and came down into
         that section of the country and just traveled around to get acquainted
         with the country. So he knew the country he was going into. In the
         meantime, he had gone down into Michigan somewhere, I don't know just
         where, but Mrs. Borah and Mrs. Bush- Mrs. William Borah, and Mrs. Bush
         had gone to this resort andtaere spending a few days at the resort and
         it happened to be the time that A. J. Fleming came down from Canada,
         and he got acquainted with them. So when he came in and said that he
         knew Mrs. Borah and he knew Mrs. Bush and it also helped to give us
         something that we could rely on and we felt very much better about A. J
         Fleming after that. He was a funny man; he wrote poetry and he could
         spiel off poetry by the yards. I have a poem, I think I still have it
         in the basement, that he wrote about the homesteaders out there. And
         he'd write part of it with his left hand and part of it with his right
         hand. And it looks so funny to see the two different handwritings on
         this poem.
         
         BC:  Was he any good?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Were the poems any good?
         
         IA:  Oh, yes, they were good.
         
         SS:  Now what is a remittance man?
         
         IA:  Oh, it is a man that doesn't conform with the way of life in England
         and the family are practically ashamed of him. And so in order to get
         him out of the way, they sent him over to Canada.
         
         BC:  They pay him so much a month
         
         IA:  As a British subject he would be acceptable in Canada. And he was
         accepted in Canada. He had been in one of the wars; had a very deep
         scar across his forehead here and up into his hairline. We asked him
         once- He said, "I suppose you're wondering where I got that scar."
         And we said, yes, so he told us such and such a war, and
         that he was wounded in the war, but other than the scar, that was all
         that he had that showed. And thats why they call them remittance
         men. They pay for them.
         
         SS:  The parents do?
         
         IA:  Uh-huh. Their parents, or their relatives, pay for them to stay out
         of England where they are ashamed to have him known as a cousin of
         so-and-so, or.Earl's oldest brother or something like that.
         
         SS:  Wonder what you had to do to get kicked out of your own country like
         that? Maybe it wouldn't take too much.
         
         BC:  Maybe that scar wasn't from the war, maybe he got into trouble!
         
         IA:  He may have had something beside the war scar. I don't know. It
         could have been a war scar, but we had to take his word for it.
         
         SS:  You know, it sounds as though your father was interested in having
         protection for you and the other women too; would rely on outside help.
         Would you have been able to rely on yourself in tight spots, too?
         
         IA:  We did. We hired men to come in and clear up the clearing and the
         buildings- and put up the buildings for us- we hired a great deal of
         our labor from the men at Clarkia. We had one man by the name of w'
         Courtermarsh- a Frenchman- and the other was named Al Champagne. And
         Al Champagne was the brother of the wife of the man that owned the
         big saloon in Clarkia. His name was Champagne. And Al Champagne was
         one of them. So we had those two men. They got wood for us and Car
         ter would get wood if we needed any. But these men in cutting down
         the old trees and clearing up, put the woodshed full of wood, so that
         we had no trouble with the wood. 
         
         BC:  lone, did you have to have a certain amount of clearing, other than
         for protection?
         
         IA:  Yes, you were supposed to have a certain amount of clearing and gar
         dening, and any other, oh, what do you call it?- improvements that belong on a home.
         I had to haye a barn; 1 didn't haye a horse, but I
         had to have a barn. Which I used for the woodshed and all.
         
         SS:  Was the twenty-two months that you were there, was that in a row?
         Continuous?
         
         IA:  Yes, with the exception of the time I took off and went to Wallace.
         One week I took off about the first of March and Mrs. Durham- Mrs,
         Durham was here at the hospital at that time- and Myrtle and I came
         out with Carter and decided to come on down to Moscow to see how the
         mother was getting along, and to be out in civilization for a.while.
         And they were gardening out here on over the south hill road- people
         were gardening along there and the vegetables were coming up and
         you could see them. That was in March of that year. And it seemed
         awfully good to see all this Und
         
         BC:  lone, would their giving that land to the railroads, would that be
         something like eminent domain? Is that what they call it? They just
         go through and take property because they needed it for a highway or
         something?
         
         SS:  Is that what happened? Did the railroad just get the land?
         
         IA:  Yes. The government just gave them certain sections of land in order to get
         this country opened up. And I don't know what they ever expected to
         do with the land.
         
         BC:  That's the way Southern Pacific and Union Pacific got so wealthy.
         
         IA:  Railroad rights, is what it was.
         
         SS:  If your land, if your homestead had not been on the government- I mean
         on the railroad land, would they have let you alone?
         
         IA:  I presume so, but I don't know, because they tackled so many others.
         
         SS:  So it might have been either way?
         They might have gotten you anyway.
         I couldn't tell how that would have been decided.
         lone, I remember, I think I do, you saying something about stone and
         timber. There was a discussion of that, too. There was a stone and
         timber claim or something that they wanted.
         Yes, but that was down here on Ruby Creek, out from Bovill.
         Lots of stone and timber.
         It wasn't the same thing.
         Did you take up two homesteads?
         Huh?
         Did you have two homesteads?
         This was a stone and timber down here, and I filed on that. I had
         the two sections.
         Did you get to prove up on the stone and timber?
         Huh?
         Did you get the stone and timber?
         Yes, I did, in a way it was funny. The Potlatch- I had this- it was
         on Ruby Creek up from Bovill, between Bovill and Elk River on thatacross
         there. And the Potlatch Lumber Company were
         That no fire shall be started in the timber before a certain date in
         the year. KYou can't start a fire in it. Well, some of those timbermen
         up there got too smart and they started a fire in the timber
         burning brush and so forth. And my father and I went out to seesomeone
         coming in from there told us that part of my land was taken
         by the fire, and my father and I went out to see about it and see how
         much damage had been done. And the cook for the lumber company deci
         ded that we'd have dinner with them; so we had dinner with the lumbermen and the cook
         that day. And while we were sitting there the old
         cook came in and said, "Do you own that timber up there?" And I said,
         "Yes, I did at one time." And he said, "The fire took it, and they
         started the fire out of fire season," and he said, "if you need a wi
         tness, I can be one for you." I said, "You're a cook." He said, "I'm
         a witness also to anything that interferes with my rights as a citizen.'
         He said, "My rights as a citizen would be to tell you that the fire
         was started and that it took the timber on your claim." And father
         said, "Would you witness that"if it was necessary?" "Oh, yes," he said,
         "I'd witness it." So we came back to Moscow and Father and I went
         over to Potlatch to the main timber company office and went in and met
         the president of the company , and he wanted to know what the trou
         ble was, so we told him. That we had been up to see the timber and
         that it was badly damaged and wanted to know what could be done about
         it. And he hesitated for a little bit and then he said, "Don't you
         think that fire liability payment would be sufficient?" And my father
         said, "Yes." was sufficient. So he sat down and he wrote
         a check and I took the check and came home and cashed the check and
         gave up the timber.
         
         SS:  Was it a good payment?
         
         IA:  Yes, it was good, well it was over- it was almost 2,000 for what was
         there, and it only cost me a very little coming and going once and
         twice from Bovill where we spent the summers anyway.
         
         SS:  Did he know that you would be willing to take it to court? Did he
         know that you would be willing to take it to court if y ou needed to?
         
         IA:  We told him afterwards that had it been necessary, we would have ta
         ken it to court, but we thought we'd give him a chance first.
         
         SS:  So he didn't know?
         
         IA:  He didn't know that we would have,Abut there were other people affec
         ted up in that part of the country besides my claim; that had timber
         claims or on Ruby Creek.
         
         BC:  I just remember that stone and timber. I never knew what it
         meant.
         
         SS:  Was that about the same time do you think that the town of Bovill al
         most burned down? Was that in that same fire?
         
         IA:  That was before that. That was before the town of Bovill burned.
         
         BC:  You might have owned a ruby mine. It was up in the Ruby Creek district
         
         SS:  Did you see what the land was like after it was burned?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Did you see what the land was like after it had been burned over? Did
         you go through land that had been burned?
         
         IA:  It was hilly.
         
         SS:  I don't mean just your timber claim, I mean in the woods.
         
         IA:  It was what they called a stone and timber act, and you could file on
         it, and by paying a certain amount for so many acres, you could get
         your claim on it.
         
         SS:  What I was thinking- when you go back through timber, like the land
         that had been burned over, say in that 1910 fire. What does the land
         look like?
         
         IA:  It does, if you go between here and Clarkia by way of Bovill; go to
         Bovill and then from there on across to Clarkia, you pass a lot of
         that land which at one time had been burned over and has come back to
         second growth andf growth timber. It's reforested itself. A great
         deal of that between Bovill and what used to be- well, Clarkia- that
         whole section of the country in through there was lumbered off at one
         time, most of it by the Potlatch Lumber Company. They were at one
         time called the Milwaukee Lumber Company. Then after they got out
         West here they called it the Potlatch.
         
         I don't see how Daddy ever had time to practice his medicine, because
         he was always some place with her.
         
         IA:  Everyone was doing it. And I was teaching school and had money enough
         to take care of these things as they came up. And my father got inte
         rested in getting me connected with the- what was it? Pioneering out on
         the homesteads.
         
         BC:  Can't imagine him letting her go.
         
         SS:  So he approved of the idea?
         
         IA:  Oh, yes.
         c-v 
         BC:  Becausefvmy sister, who is three years younger than myself, he was so
         cautious about every thing we did. Maybe he learned a lesson for all
         the worry she caused him! (Chuckles)." dcn'-h knew.
         But he didn't want us to it.
         
         IA:  I was my father's boy.
         
         BC:  Yes, she was.
         
         IA:  He had no boys. He had no sons, and I used to drive with him during
         the flu epidemic here, I would drive at night for him. He would work
         during the daytime at the office taking care of his patients at the
         office and many a time we'd drive out at night after dinner to visit
         the sick in the country. And Dad would be so tired tht I would do
         the driving, and I'd drive to a certain point and wake him up and ask
         him which way to go, and he'd tell me where the location was and I'd
         drive on and he'd go back to sleep again.
         
         BC:  That's wonderful!.
         
         IA:  That's the way. I fished with him and I hunted with him.
         
         SS:  Do you think he just figured that you could take care of yourself?
         
         SS:  He didn't have any real reservation about you going out on a home
         stead by yourself?
         
         IA:  No
         
         BC:  She always has been able to take care of herself. Any emergency she's
         levelheaded and thinks of some way out of it. She ever tell you about
         the time she pulled her tooth? This was when she was about seven or
         eight years old. Tell him that.
         
         IA:  What?
         
         BC:  When you pulled your tooth. I'll tell you. This was the beginning,
         I think. She had to have a tooth pulled, and at that time there was
         no dentist here. And the dentist had traveled through and told Daddy
         what to do for Ione's tooth. So, I think it was Daddy that to pull your tooth, wasn't
         it?
         
         IA:  Yes. The dentist- I had teeth before youngsters were supposed to
         have teeth. They came through early someway, I don't know how. And
         the front teeth-and they were, I guess they were decayed, I don't know
         what, because I wasn't old enough to really know. Bu t there was a
         dentist came through and my father was telling him about the teeth and
         he gave him a lot of paste and okfic and told him what to do to
         save the teeth until the others are ready to come through. And so Dad
         came home and brought the instruments and worked on my teeth, being
         very careful not to hurt me. And I had those teeth then until the
         others came through. Finally had a tooth down here that was aching
         and Dad said to me, "Come down to the office and I'll take care of that
         for you." So I went down to the drugstore and into the back to the
         office and Dad got his forceps out and I opened my mouth and he pulled
         the tooth, or part of the tooth. He could just get part of it, and
         before he could get the tooth out of his forceps and into the cuspidor
         I was out of the chair and about three block down the street towards
         home! I went just as tight as I could go; noboby was going to hurt a
         tooth of mine like that and hurt me! And away I went! Well, we had
         a little outdoor cellar and above the cellar was a little open loft
         and the children used to play in this loft. That was our playhouse,
         we'd go up a little ladder on the outside and up. So when I went home
         I could feel the edge of that tooth with my tongue, and it bothered me
         terribly, and I went up to the little playhouse and took a shoe—
         what do you call it?
         
         BC:  Hook.
         
         IA:  Where you button your shoes. A shoe buttoner. A shoebuttoner that
         we were using up there and I took this shoebuttoner with the hook on
         it, and I reached in and I pulled the rest of that tooth out. When
         my father came home at night, he said, "How's your tooth?" And I
         said, "There isn't any tooth." "Well, what happened?" I said, "I
         pulled it." He said, "You couldn't pull that tooth out!" I said,
         "I did." And I opened my mouth to show him that the tooth was gone.
         "How did you do it?" "I took a shoebuttoner."
         
         BC:  Buttonhook.
         
         IA:  Buttonhook, and I pried it out with the shoe buttoner.
         
         BC:  I think from then on (Chuckles)
         
         IA:  He just thought I could do anything! After that. Well, we came West
         in 1893- the fall of 1893, that was the year that was so wetAthat the
         farmers couldn't get into the fields to either cut their grain or those
         that had it cut couldn't get in to harvest it. I started out with one
         particular thing to tell you about it- Well, we came West- Now I know.
         We came West, and Dad wanted to take care of my teeth, I had some that
         needed care.,"Nothing doing, nobody gets in my mouth!" And so, he
         said, "Well, we'll see what we can do." We just let them go. So there
         was a dentist here in town by the name of Mc Bride and he had an office
         in the Moscow Hotel. A south office that looked directly . into
         the Telephone Building at that time. And he went to Dr. Mc Bride and
         told him what the trouble was and wanted to know if he could suggest
         anything. And the doctor said','I think we can." And, Dad said, "Oh,
         what?" And he said, "How would you like to come down and have dinner
         with us and bring the gal;" So, my father and my mother and I went
         down and had dinner with the doctor, and I got quite we 11 acquainted
         with the doctor. And the doctor played the violin. And if there was
         anything I loved it was violin music, and he played for me. And we
         had dinner two or three times down at the doctor s and I got (Very well
         acquainted with him and he played the violin for me. One day he said
         to me, "lone," he said, "I noticed when you laugh that you have a tooth
         down here that needs taken care of." He said, "It's going to spoil
         your looks if you don't have it taken care of." I was quite a proud
         little youngster at that. And he said, "Come up to the office and let
         me see what we can do about it." So I trudged down to the doctor's
         office at the Hotel Moscow and the doctor put a big rubber band around
         my neck and a here to cover me and worked on my tooth- teethvery
         careful not to hurt me. And he says, "Will you come back and let
         me do the other one?" And I said, "Yes," And I went back and he did
         the other one. Well, he took care of my teeth from that time on til
         all my back teeth came in, and he filled them all as they needed it.
         And I went to the doctor and had them taken care of.
         
         BC:  the violin.
         
         IA:  But I had them all taken care of. I was down at Dr. Miller's yester
         day and it reminded me, Dr. Miller had the office in the Telephone
         Building which was directly opposite the office- the windows- where
         I used to sit at the doctor's. And I told him, I said, "Years ago had
         my first teeth taken care of directly across here at that window on
         the other side ." And he laughed and he said, "Your doctor did a won
         derful job." And he said, "Your teeth are still in good condition."
         So, I went down to Dr. Miller last night and he was looking in my mouth
         and I said, "Doctor, it's been a good many years that you've glanced
         down into that cavern." And I said, "Are you still working it?" And
         he said, "Yes, I'm still working it." So, he relined my plates yesterday
         
         BC:  So you could eat a hard piece of candy.
         
         SS:  Well, do you think that there were people who would think that Ione's
         independence was too independent for a girl in those days?
         
         BC:  She never inflicted it on anyone else.
         
         SS:  You know how people talk and all.
         
         BC:  Oh, they may have. I don't know. Of course, she wasn't alone, there
         were several people from here doing approximately the same thing. I
         think she's told you how she was one of the first people that ever
         wore a divided skirt. That shocked people, but then soon others be
         gan to wear divided skirts. She was courageous. Nothing daunted her.
         
         SS:  Well some of these other women that were out there- I wonder, was it
         harder on some of these other ladies. Some of these other ladies that
         were homesteaders, was it harder on them than it was on you to be alone
         and take that kind of life?
         
         IA:  Mrs. Durham was a widow, and she had this one daughter, and she thought
         that would be a chance for her to make a little more than she was doing
         dressmaking here in town, and that was her. And Mrs. Torsen was - she
         married the druggist, that had the store down where " Hardware
         is now. And she thought it would help out a good deal if she could
         take a homestead, when this locater was lining up this bunch of people,
         she thought that if she was anywheres near someone else that it would
         be a good idea. So she did that. And Mrs. Durham, as I said, was a
         widow with one daughter. Mrs. Taylor, well, she said her husband died
         but she never seemed to be very sad about it. And we thought that they
         had had a divorce. That was my idea of Mrs. Taylor, any
         And Mrs. Brown, Delia Brown Griffiths, was at the time she took up her
         homestead, the one where A. J. Fleming and Dynamite got the books; her
         brother was a locater, and she was just a young college girl at that
         time, she had finished college, but she married Griffiths after that.
         He was in the construction business. So that we knew him and we knew
         her. And others out there were just about the same. Elsie Pfiel was
         Elsie Watkins, Dr. Watkins' daughter. The aunt of the young lady that
         wrote The Buffalo Coat, the history of her uncle. The Buffalo Coat.
         
         SS:  Did you become rather close friends to any of these women that you were
         with out there?
         
         IA:  Yes, all of them. We'd known them here in town. Of course Mrs. Dur
         ham did sewing for me when we were youngsters and for my mother. And
         Mrs. Torsen trimmed hats for us. And all of the rest of them, we were
         all acauainted one way or another. Some we knew better than others,
         but we learned them we got out on the homestead.
         
         SS:  This Mrs. Durham, was she related to Durham and Coughmans' store?
         
         IA:  No. No, she wasn't.
         
         SS:  What about this woman that ran the hotel at Clarkia? That woman that
         you mentioned to me.
         
         IA:  Mrs. Fertig.
         
         SS:  Was she French?
         
         IA:  F-e-r-t-i-g.
         
         SS:  Did she run a saloon there, too?
         
         IA:  No. She had the little roominghouse down the line between Clarkia and
         the schoolhouse.
         
         BC:  A Mrs. Clark ran it too, for a while. I remember those boys.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Clark, '(hey ran a little boardinghouse there at Collins, too. 
         
         IA: Oh. Yes, she ran a roominghouse at Clarkia- I mean at Bovill.
         
         SS:  I was just going to ask you: Did you think of yourself at the time as
         being a pioneer?
         
         IA:  Think of myself as a-
         
         SS:  Pioneer?
         
         IA:  Oh, no. No, I never thought about it being a pioneer.
         
         SS:  It seems as though nowdays that women will do a lot more, have a lot
         more independence than they used to. It seems like you had that inde
         pendence back then. The sort of thing that a lot of women nowdays are
         striving for.
         
         IA:  You see, my father was born in Iowa, and his father was a doctor and
         went up into Colorado. He got the mining fever. He went out to Colo
         rado where those big mines up around Boulder and Colorado Springs were
         opened up, French Creek I think they called it then. And left my fa
         ther and his wife with a sister of hers by the name of Taylor in Iowa.
         The Taylors moved out to Oregon, down at Amity, Oregon, out from Port
         land. And my father was just ayoungster when4/heytook him out there,
         so he was raised in the West and in that open country down around Port
         land. And so, when he landed here it was still West to him, after ha
         ving been in school.
         
         BC:  Because his father died.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  Our father's father was dead, or died when he was up in this mining
         area. ffe Wdflt otitis ?u doctor with-tfidm. And so that left Grandmother
         alone with two little children. And the little children and grandmother
         they came to Oregon.
         
         IA:  They went with the Taylors down into Oregon. That's how Daddy happened
         to be taken to Oregon.
         
         SS:  So you figure that he was more accustomed himself to pioneering.
         
         IA:  Uh-huh. Well, you take a youngster of about seventeen or eighteen years
         old; been raised in the West and decided to become a doctor, and went
         back East to Rush College on his own and worked his way through the
         college, and he was practically a pioneer in a good many ways. Then
         he came West and Mother's health was so poor in the East that he deci
         ded that he'd come West then to see if it wouldn't help her. So he
         sold out his practice there in the little town and came out to his sis
         ter's at Johnson, down here. And when you're in Johnson, in the main
         town- have you been in Johnson?
         
         SS:  No. But I know where it is, because you told me.
         
         IA:  Well, anytime you're down there on the main street and look straight
         down a long lane that is from the town, and the lane used to go per
         fectly straight and at the end of that lane was a great big house, and
         that was Uncle John's house. So we spent our first months in Johnson.
         Daddy came out and we went w to Johnson to his sister's. And he took
         Mother, Uncle John took mother and Daddy down to Pullman to decide
         whether they wanted to locate in Pullman or in Moscow.
         
         SS:  You told me about that.
         
         IA:  I told you about that.
         
         SS:  Because she didn't like the hills. Didn't like being out of town.
         
         IA:  She didn't the hills there at all. So they came into Moscow, -d bft
         because Third Street was the only hill then that she could see in
         Moscow, except in the mountains.
         
         SS:  Was your mother's family— she grew up on a farm? Was her family a
         poor family?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Was her family a poor family, when she was a girl as farmers, or were
         they fairly well fixed.
         Well, they farmed  Well, he had a farm and he made very good work on
         the farm, and they were not wealthy. No farmer is wealthy.
         
         BC:  Then!
         
         IA:  But they made their living by living on ft farm.
         
         BC:  And they all died early. I think farming must be very hard. I never
         had any grandparents,Nthey were all deadK I was born.
         
         SS:  I wondered what you'd think about this with nowdays with women striving
         to be independent, you know, trying to be independent and have jobs
         and work of their own and not just be a housewife and that kind of thing.
         Now it seems like thatJjwhat you were doing back then, without even thin
         king about it.
         
         IA:  Indiana wasn't very heavily populated at that time.
         
         BC:  It's just her nature, I think. The sister next1b her wasn't of that
         temperment at all. She liked to play with the boys. She liked to play
         with the boys. She was'.adventuresome person, she never would have cared
         to have gone out and done the things that lone has done. She liked
         challenges.
         
         SS:  You think she would see them as difficult or hard going?
         
         BC:  I think the only thing that puts the fear of God in her is the electri
         city. She's afraid of electricity. Electric storms, she doesn't like.
         And anything in the house that looks like it might a little spark
         Just will not touch it. She's afraid of it.
         
         SS:  I donlt know if she understands just what I mean when I try to say it to
         her; but compared to the way the people are today, it seems like she
         was a pioneer in more ways than one.
         
         BC:  She was, yes, she was. Although they didn'ther that. I mean she isn't
         like some of these women that started out- I think that Abigail Adams
         was really one of the first women that worked for women's rights, al
         though they didn't call it that, but she started that sort of thing.
         And I think lone.without realizing it has always gone her own way. She
         will even she'll argue with a doctor but if she doesn't
         think diK she won't take such and such.
         
         SS:  Well, back in those days when she was young, was she interested in women's
         rights at all.
         
         BC:  I don't think so She was mixed up in politics just once and that's
         when she was elected county treasurer and tax collector. And then she
         went into civil service in the post office. But she liked going out
         and giving speeches for electioneering for her office. Daddy went
         with her. I don't know how he got done, because he was always
         looking out for lone and she really didn't need looking out for as much
         because she was so independent
         
         SS:  Was there much of a campaign to run for?
         
         BC:  I don't think so. They had to make all these surrounding towns and
         give talks.
         
         SS:  Did you tell me once that when your father was really quite sick that
         he had you come and make up his eyebrows? I was struck by that.
         
         BC:  Yes. When he was in bed just before his death, I took care of him for
         six months. Of course, I love- I wanted to be a doctor, but I was born
         in the wrong generation. 
         
         But when his beard
         began to turn gray. His hair never turned gray, but his eyebrows
         and his beard were kind of reddish and had reddish gray speckles in it
         and his eyebrows got gray. So one day,Ahe was still quite comfortable
         in bed, he asked me to go to the office and get a bottle of something,
         so I went and got it, not knowing what he would do with it. He said
         there was a toothbrush by it, so I brought it up and he put some on
         was
         his eyebrows and on his beard. He sick in bed but he still was proud.
         
         IA:  Did you think of that professor's name?
         
         BC:  Which one?
         
         IA:  The one that talked about Idaho history.
         
         SS:  Who? Brosnan?
         
         BC:  It was Brosnan.
         
         IA:  Brosnan. How do you know about Brosnan?
         
         SS:  Oh, well, I just knew that he taught Idaho history.
         
         IA:  My father-
         
         BC:  I think you told him this, too.
         
         IA:  Did I tell you about Daddy and his hearing aid?
         
         SS:  No.
         
         IA:  Well,Father was getting a little bit deaf and it bothered him. In
         his profession, he had to be able to hear what everyone said, so he
         got him a hearing aid. It was one of the very first ones that was put
         out, and the battery fit into his vest pocket. And the hearing aid
         came up into his ear. Well, he wasn't sure he was getting good ser
         vice out of that and he would £t heme go into one room and then ask
         us to speak to him and he'd try to catch what we said. And he kept
         on with that by trying the little lever high and low and medium and
         so forth. Well, Daddy belonged to the Chamber of Commerce and one day
         Dr. Brosnan was the speaker at the Chamber of Commerce on Idaho history,
         He was especially interested in the spring up here on Paradise Ridge
         and the monument that's out here where the old- well, it's on A Street,
         1 guess, out at the north end monument out there and he
         was telling about those things and my father decided that he would go
         down and listen to the Idaho History by Dr. Brosnan. So he took a place
         quite close to Dr. Brosnan and went in to 
         out his hearing aid.
         And Dr. Brosnan would go on with his story and Dad would sit here and
         he'd shift the lever one way or- shift the lever the next way and Dr.
         Brosnan would lower his voice and he'd shift it again. Well he watched
         Dr. Brosnan to see what he was going to say or how he was going to
         speak in order to change his hearing aid. And he watched him intently.
         When he came home and we said, "Did you hear Dr. Brosnan?" He said,
         "I couldn't understand what he was saying." And I said, "That's just
         too bad, you'll have to try again." So the next day I was up at the
         post office, the University Station, which was then- what do they call
         it now? The U-Hut and Dr. Brosnan came through the office and stopped
         to talk to me, and he said, "You know, Miss Adair, I didn't know that
         your father was so interested in Idaho history." And I said, "Oh, yes,
         he is." I said,"He's quite a Western man in the beginning and is very
         interested in anything that is historical." "Well," he said, "you know,
         I gave a speech at the Chamber of Commerce yesterday and there wasn't
         a man at that table that gave me the attention your father did!"
         
         (Laughter) And I didn't have the courage to tell him that my father
         came home and said he hadn't heard a word! Now isn't that good?
         
         BC:  Good story. Did you have some special things you wanted to ask her
         about, Sam?
         
         SS:  I wanted to ask her about teaching, a little bit, too. About what
         the experience of teaching was like. Now, you told me once when I
         asked you about teaching, about the time that the supervisor came out
         and you had to bring the class back. But I was thinking about more
         what teaching was like at that time.
         
         IA:  I can't tell you what teaching was like.
         
         BC:  What about in the public schools, lone, you had to do several grades.
         
         IA:  Schools are so changed now. In the early days we had- I had usually
         both high third and low fourth grades, and had all the way from forty
         to fifty youngsters in the two grades in a room. An d you carry on
         your discipline with that many children and your instruetioir and all
         for that many children and you've got your hands full. And now they
         think if they have twenty or possibly twenty-five, they have a full
         room and they have no time for preparation, excepting after hours, and
         in the early days, you did your work yourself and you did it on your
         own time.
         
         BC:  I can remember her coming home with stacks of papers that she was grading in
         the evening. And they would discipline, too. When I was in
         school, which was about the time she was teaching, you had to march in
         and march out of the schoolroom,  marched from the
         walk into the schoolroom and took your seat. And once I was kept in
         school a whole week an hour after school every night because I chewed
         gum in class.
         
         IA:  It was altogether different then. You were responsible for the chil
         dren coming and going to school. If anything happened you were res
         ponsible for them. And so you had your discipline not only at the
         school but either coming or going.
         
         SS:  You couldn't be everywhere at once.
         
         BC:  No, but it was your responsibility.
         
         IA:  No, but somebody would tell on them. There was always somebody to tat
         tle, you know! Which reminds me of the time when Harry Orchard was
         in the- what was it? the WIT? What did they call that?
         
         SS:  The IWWs?
         
         BC:  Before that, I think.
         
         IA:  The what?
         
         SS:  What about Harry Orchard?
         
         IA:  Harry Orchard? Didn't you ever hear about Harry Orchard?
         
         SS:  I've heard about it, but what were you going to say about it?
         
         IA:  Oh, he was instrumental in killing some man down around Boise. He was
         in the union, and they were having this fight for union wages and he
         was instrumental in killing, and I was teaching over here at what was
         then the old Russell School, the building where the- this new building
         is now- and had the fourth grade and a little youngster in it by the
         name of Horton Mc Cauley. His sister was the speech director at the
         university at that time and Horton was in my room, and there were things
         going on that we were trying to get to the bottom of. A little group
         of youngsters were carrying on pretty high for a time and we were trying
         to get to the bottom of it and we couldn't find anyone that would tell
         us. That we could get to give enough of it that we would have anything
         to go by. And I was talking to Horton and I said, "Horton, somebody
         must know, somebody must tell, because we have to get at the bottom of
         this. And he looked up and he said, "Harry Orchard never confes
         sed and I won't either." Well, that was Harry Orchard. Well, it went
         on that way for oh, possibly a week or so, and we were still ferreting
         around trying to get at the bottom of this trouble. And one day the
         papers came out in big headlines,"Harry Orchard confesses!" I took
         the paper over to the schoolhouse with me and I showed it to Horton.
         And I said, "Horton, you said that Harry Orchard never confessed."
         I said, "He did." And, I said, "It's up to somebody to help us out."
         Well, we got a full line on the whole business, and got it taken care
         of.
         
         BC:  What was it? Just mischief?
         
         SS:  What was it? What was going on?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  What was going on?
         
         IA:  There was a house way down at the end of F Street, the big, old house
         still stands way down there, and there was a group of these youngsters
         were committing all kinds of depredations at this old house. The
         house was empty. It had been moved from here on A Street out to F
         Street, where it goes out,, beyond where the schoolhouse is out
         there now, the other school. And we were trying to find out what was
         going on and who was guilty of the depredations that were being done
         to the house, and we couldn't find anybody that would-
         
         SS:  They were vandalizing the house?
         
         IA:  Vandalizing the house and oh, I don't know what all was going on. All
         sorts of things.
         
         BC:  So Harry Orchard confessed, I didn't--
         
         IA:  And fourth grade youngsters shouldn't be doing it. But Harry Orchard
         didn't confess! But when Harry Orchard confessed, we got the whole bus
         iness! You'll find out about Harry Orchard some of these times.
         
         SS:  I've heard about him. Because I remember then they had the trial.
         Bill Haywood and Clarence Darrow came and defended Haywood and Borah-
         
         IA:  And . came in on that, too. That was funny.
         
         SS:  Did you ever meet him? Senator Borah.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Did you meet Senator Borah?
         
         IA:  Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  What do you remember about him?
         
         IA:  Oh, nothing in particular. He was a large man. I wouldn't say that
         he was over six feet tall or something like that, but he was a large
         man in every way. And he had a remarkable face, a face that if you
         saw it you remembered it. serious and all, but the same time
         he was not stern or forbidding or anything like that. He was just a
         man that you were comfortable with.at the same time and you never felt
         like taking any privileges or asking anything of him. He was a- what
         do they call him? A lone wolf?
         
         SS:  Did he talk in a common way, or did he talk in a-
         
         IA:  was forceful His A voice was very pleasing ancj his distinction
         was very good. You could understand him. I could understand
         him but then Idid then anyway.
         
         BC:  Did you tape the talk that Lee gave the other day? He gave
         a talk on. And Mrs. Wood had called me afterward and said
         she contributed some things to Lee's talk. Well, the things she contri
         buted were not correct. I just wondered if you taped it and got her
         She told that Dr. Church came to Mother's door and rapped
         on the door ' ask her if she wouldn't let him live there. Well
         that wasn't it. He was going by Mother was in the and they talked
         gardening and he said, "This is very much like my home in Pennsylvania."
         And he wanted to know if Mother wouldn't let him live there. That's
         the way Dr. Church got into the house. And she said that he came from
         Indiana and knocked at the door. Which, to me, is quite different.
         
         IA:  She has the ideas but they're not always straight ideas.
         
         BC:  What was the other thing she said that was so wrong?
         
         IA:  One thing that she told Lee over here was that we used to take the
         bannisters that go up the stairs and twine the pine boughs on them for
         decorations on them at Christmas. And more things about decorations
         for Christmas.
         
         BC:  She never was in the house.
         
         IA:  She never was in the house! She had her idea-
         
         BC:  She didn't know.
         
         IA:  So you want to check on anything that gives you that has been given
         to him by Mrs. Withers.
         
         SS:  You know, in talking about Mrs. Borah, I was thinking that I hadn't
         really asked you whether you did see much of her or remained in contact
         with her after she went back to Washington.
         
         IA:  Did she make contact with—?
         
         SS:  Did you still remain friends?
         
         IA:  Oh, yes. You see, Carrie Bush, or Carrie Mc Connell and our family
         were very great friends, good friends. And Mfrim would come
         to visit with the Mc Connells and we always saw when she came.
         In fact, picked out a suit for me down at Boise and had it sent
         up to me because Carrie had a suit I liked very much and so she
         found a suit that she thought would be pleasing to me and she sent the
         suit up to me. And she always had so many things to tell about Washing
         ton and the things that they'd do.
         
         BC:  A great imagination and a flair for telling.
         
         IA:  She had a negro maid that she had had I think about ever since she went
         into Washington, and Daisy was just the source of a great deal of in
         flammation for rfory. And Mrs. Borah said that she came to her one day
         and she said, "Mrs. Borah, may I have Thursday off?" And Mrs. Borah,
         said, "Well, what do you want with Thursday off? You've never asked
         for Thursday before. Why do you want Thursday off?" "Oh," said Daisy,
         "Thursday is hecklin' day." And she said, "All the Negroes get together
         down on the street and we heckle the white people try to make
         'em angry!" She said, "Thursday is hecklin' day and I'd like to have
         Thursday off!" So little things like that, they're funny.
         
         BC:  Well, lone, Mrs. Borah's sister, Carrie Bush, was practically a member
         of our family. She enjoyed our family much more than she did her own
         there was no one else, family, becauseher brothers gone and her sisters.
         
         IA:  We were always together. 
         
         BC:  So she practically lived with us.
         
         IA:  Carrie was on a picnic with us if we went anywhere, Carrie always went
         with us.
         
         BC:  Every summer she would go camping with us.
         
         IA:  We were talking about homesteads or selling timber claims. After I
         had the homestead out there and my father decided that he thought
         I should take a stone and timber claim because all you'd have to do
         was pay so much an acre for your stone and timber claim, and so he
         got in touch with some man that was out on what they called Cedar Ridge,
         that's up from Kendrick and out in;the country from Kendrick, and this
         man said that he had a couple of locations out there that he thought
         my father might be interested in for me. So Dad and I hitched up the
         horses and we went out to the old place, and the man was living in a
         two-room cabin, a very nice cabin for out in that part of the country,
         and his little old mother was living with him. He had sent back East
         and fot his mother to come out and live with him. And my father and
         the locater decided that- there was still quite a bit of snow and it
         wasn't a very good idea for me to get out and go over the claims if
         I didn't know any more about the timber than he did. But my father
         had been used to the timber out by Bovill and Collins and Clarkia
         and so he said, "You stay here and visit with Grandma, and I'll go with
         the boy and we111 go over the claim and if I think it's suitable I'll
         come back and we can go over either today or tomorrow. So I stayed
         with Grandma, She was someone in her nineties, and we sat and visited
         about the timber and about the country and all these things and I final
         ly asked her about her son. I said, "Is he your oldest boy?" "Oh, no,
         he's not the oldest." And I said, "How many children did you have?"
         "Well," she said, "I just don't recollect." She said, "it'a twelve or
         thirteen, but I'm not sure which. And so, I saved that for my father
         when he came back. I thought he would enjoy that.
         I think one reason that Carrie was with us so much; we always had trans
         portation. Daddy had good riding horses and good driving horses and
         Mc Connells didn't. Andthere was always something doing around our
         house, so it was natural that she'd gravitate here.
         
         SS:  So she was really at the house a lot?
         
         BC:  Oh, yes. And they lived right down here. We have some pictures of
         Carrie and Mrs. Mc Bride at that time and lone. Who else in front of
         the mirror that Mc Connells had down in that house.
         
         SS:  Do you remember that Mrs, Borah had to say about what life was like
         back there in tae Capitol?
         
         BC:  She was very popular.
         
         IA:  What's that Bernadine?
         
         BC:  Senator Borah.
         
         SS:  I was asking if there were other stories that Mrs. Borah told you about
         Washington. That strange place back there where they make all these
         laws!
         
         IA:  No. She used to tell so many, but they were al just little things
         that would come in in a conversation and its very hard to get them
         all collected so that you could tell them.
         
         She told us about the hecklin' and I remembered that one very well.
         Mrs. Borah called her sister Mrs. Bush, oh, a couple of times a month
         and they'd have a long conversation. And she was very entertaining.
         Tell all these wild things about Mrs. Longworth and somebody else and
         somebody else. And then Mrs. Bush would come and relay .'' conver
         sation to us. She had a great sense of humor.
         
         SS:  Do you think she changed much in the years that she spent in Washing
         ton?
         
         IA:  You mean Mrs. Borah?
         As being a senator's wife for a long time?
         
         IA:  Yes she did. You haven't had a chance to read Mrs.Elephants and Donkeys. You'd
         probably get a lot out of that from Mrs.
         Borah, because Mrs. Perrine was Mary Louise Bush and she spent a couple
         of years or more with Mrs. Borah in Washington. And Mrs. Borah gave
         her this material for her autobiography.
         Would it be a biography when it was given to her?
         And so there'd be lots of that, I'm sure that would tell—
         
         SS:  Well Carrie Bush was married to Ben Bush. Right?
         
         BC:  Uh-huh. He was a forrester.
         
         IA:  What?
         
         BC:  Carrie married Ben Bush. Carrie McConnell Bush.
         
         IA:  Oh, yes. She married Ben Bush, she married him in 1910. And Mary
         Louise was their daughter. She was born, oh, a year or so afterwards
         and then they had one son, young Ben Bush. And he's working for the
         government now in something, and I don't know just what. They sent
         him at one time down to Anatctica and he wrote back and to Id about
         the penguins down there and all the funny things that happened.
         
         BC:  It was a funny thing with that family; there was Ben and Mrs. Bush and
         the two children. They were the most separated family. You never saw
         them together. They never talked about each other and Mary Louise would
         come home to visit and she'd stay with somebody else instead of with
         her mother. We never could understand that because our family was so
         close, and they just didn't seem to have that close tie together. It
         wasn't because they were separated young.
         
         SS:  It sounds like they found a lot of warmth in other families, like in
         your family.
         
         BC:  We did, but I don't think they did.
         
         IA:  What?
         
         BC:  I don't think Carrie and her family, her children were close at all.
         There wasn't any warm feeling there.
         
         IA:  You mean Carrie-
         
         BC:  and Mary Louise and Ben.
         
         IA:  Mary Louise and Ben?
         
         BC:  Uh-huh.
         
         IA:  No, they weren't. Mary Louise married quite young and she married Mr.
         Perrine, who was a musician and lived at the big Perrine ranches, out
         I think, in Twin Falls. And they were only married three or four years
         before his music didn't pay for their upkeep and Mary Louise was tea
         ching and she decided that teaching was just too much, to try to keep
         a house and teach and to support her husband too, and so they were di
         vorced and she came back up and lived at home for a short time and then
         went back to Washington, D. C. a couple of summers to be with "
         and work on this autobiography, The Elephants and Donkeys.
         
         BC:  She taught for years
         
         SS:  You know, when you mentioned divorce; that reminded me of something
         else I was going to ask you about. In the early years, like when you
         were young, divorce wasn't very well accepted, was it?
         
         BC:  Not at all.
         
         IA:  The what?
         
         SS:  Divorce wasn't very well accepted.
         
         BC: Stigma on the family and the person. And the family were as disgraced
         as the people that were getting the divorce.
         
         BC:  Well, the son, Ben, divorced his wife shortly, too.
         
         IA:  Ben was quite a character. He Carrie's husband- he was the head super
         visor of the forest and the land for quite a while in Boise. You'll
         find his recordthere. And they lived up in what was called the Burns
         house on A Street.
         
         BC:  He wasn't here very much, was he Pinky? I never can remember seeing
         them together.
         
         SS:  He was in Boise?
         
         BC:  I don't know. But I never saw them together, Carrie and her husband.
         And I was old enough to remember
         
         SS:  Do you remember when Dr. Watkins was killed?
         
         IA:  Who?
         
         SS:  Dr. Watkins. Do you remember when he was killed?
         
         IA:  When he was killed?
         
         IA:  I wasn't in town at the time. We were out at Collins, Bovill on
         the homestead and my father came out to tell us about it. And that's
         when the story that I told you about my sister saying, "If God be for
         us, can be against us."
         
         SS:  Would you tell me that story again?
         
         IA:  Yes. But my father was over here at the old place and he'd just star
         ted down the street and Was about even with the first house over here,
         when this man on horseback came up the street, or down the street, I
         don't know which, and Mr. Creighton lived in that green house, the se
         cond house down-iRalstons and then the slate colored house and then
         the next is the green house. Creightons lived there and Mr. Creighton
         just came out of the house and started down the street and he saw this
         horse going either up or down, I don't know which way, but he called
         out to the horseman, he says, "What's that shooting?" And the man tur
         ned around and shot at him, and the bullet went through Mr. Creighton
         had his arm up this way across his stomach, he was quite a fussy man,
         and he always walked with his arm across his stomach, and the man went
         on then and Dad said he just stopped perfectly still, because he didn't
         want to get down and get mixed up in that. And he went down the street
         then a little ways and he met some men coming up and they were from
         Dr. Watkins' office.
         
         BC:  How did Dr. Watkins.
         
         IA:  His office was down there whoR oh, who's is it now? I think
         it's been taken down, I'm not positive though. It's a little insurance
         office that- what's his name?
         
         SS:  The Title building.
         
         IA:  A little tiny office building down there. Well, that was Dr. Watkins'
         office at that time, it's now, I think two insurance businesses or some
         thing like that. I never thought to look for it when I was down.
         
         BC:  One is Jfitle office.
         
         SS:  It's right next door to that. Does that mean that your father saw Mr.
         Creighton get shot?
         
         IA:  What?
         
         SS:  Your father saw Mr. Creighton get shot?
         
         IA:  He saw the man shoot at Mr. Creighton, but he didn't go down, not un
         til afterwards.
         
         BC:  After the man rode off.
         
         IA:  After the man rode off. As I say, I didn't know whether the man was
         going up the street or down the street, but Dad missed him one way or
         the other, because he stopped when he saw him shoot. He didn't want
         to get mixed up in it down there. But Dr. Watkins had those offices
         down there. The offices were built for Dr. Watkins and that's where
         the man shot him. Shot him down.
         S3: Tell me that story about Marjorie.
         
         BC:  She'll tell you about Marjorie.
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         SS:  That story about Marjorie.
         Oh. well, when we were on the homestead out at Collins: We always
         went out every summer and my father always came out on Saturday and
         he managed not to be in his office on Saturday, and he'd come out to
         the homestead on Saturday and then back on Sunday and he'd be in the
         office again for the next week. And so the family went out and lived
         on the homestead while my father stayed in town. My sister, Marjorie,
         was about, I imagine about years old when we first started going
         out there, and she always whenever she'd sit down at the table, she
         always had to cry regardless of what was there; what was said, or anything,
         the moment you pushed her high chair lVto the tableAtears began
         to come. One day an old uncle of mine said to her, "Kid, what's the
         matter with you?" And she looked up at him and she says, "I'm just not
         happy." And that's the only reason we ever had for it when Marjorie
         cried. Well, the post office at Troy had a minister on the postal
         route and he served all the towns which were little town then from
         Troy to Deary to Helmer and to all the little towns, and Bovill and
         finally Collins. Collins was the last on the line. And the minister
         would always stay over til Sunday and on Sunday would hold services
         in the schoolhouse for all the homesteaders there. He considered that
         was his duty and a good chance to preach the word, so he always had
         his sermon. Well, he would give the sermon for the next Sunday would
         be on such-and-such a textjhe'd give you the text. And if you had
         your Bibles look it up and read the rest of the chapters. Well, the
         text for the next Sunday was, "If the Lord be for us, who can be against
         us?" And we tried- we thought now that's the thing- we'll teach Mar
         jorie to say that for Daddy when he comes out, he'll be there Satur
         day and we'll just have her say the Golden Text for Daddy. So we tried
         all week long to get Marjorie to say the Golden Text, "If God be for
         us, who could be against us." Do you think the child would do it? She
         just had a blankout for that, she wouldn't say a word, she wouldn't
         try. Well, Saturday evening we were all sitting around the table and
         Daddy pulled Marjorie's chair up to the side of him and after he said
         grace he turned and looked at Marjorie and she was crying. And he said,
         "Marjorie, what's the trouble?" She didn't answer. He just reached
         over and took her by the shoulder and shook her a little bit, he says,
         "Stop your crying." He was getting exasperated because she cried every
         time we sat down to the table. Well, Marjorie looked up at him and with
         the tears rolling down her face, said to him, "If God be for us, who
         can be against us?" That just melted him. She didn't get any puni
         shment after that! She'd . cry all she wanted I thought that was
         pretty good.
         
         SS:  Was that the first time she said it? Was that the first time you got
         her to say it?
         
         IA:  The only time she ever said it, and I don't think she ever said it
         again afterwards. Down here at the Methodist Church, oh, a number of
         years ago they started what was called the Golden Age Club. I think
         you've possibly heard about it, where they meet, I think it's Monday
         evenings, but I'm not sure now because I haven't been to it for so
         long, and the minister, forget what his name was, the mini
         ster knew Mrs. Town and he knew me and he said, "We just have to have
         some help to get this thing started. And I'd like to have some some
         of you people tell little incidents or stories that happened that you
         can remember." (break here for a few words) — well acquainted with
         him, and they never hunted or fished together like he and Dr. Hatfield
         and some of the others, but he knew the doctor and he knew the family, and
         Elsie Pfiel-
         
         BC:  Tell about the sleighbells.
         
         IA:  The what?
         
         BC:  The sleighbells.
         
         IA:  Oh, the sleighbells. Yes, over at the museum they have a string of
         sleighbells. They used them two years ago I think it was on the door.
         We used to always use them on our front door until people got to stea
         ling things off of the doors, and so we didn't put them out any more,
         we didn't want to lose them. But shortly after the doctor's death,
         Daddy was called one day over to the home and Mrs. Watkins always had
         those very severe migraine headaches and the doctor would keep medicine
         or treatment for it, and so Elsie called my father and said, "Mother
         has one of her severe headaches and she would like you to come over
         and see if there is anything you can do for her." So Daddy got into
         the sleigh and he hitched up the horse and drove around there, they
         lived right across from the Presbyterian Church up here, in that 1 ittie
         house that the cupalo, and he drove up in front and Mrs. Watkins
         was there in the room when he went in and she looked up and she
         said, "Doctor I didn't hear you coming." He said, "I don't think you
         would, I wasn't very noisy." And she said, "Don't you have any sleigh
         bells?" And Daddy said, "No, I don't have sleighbells for my horse,
         I just don't have the bells." "Well," she said, "we'll see about that."
         So she sent one of the girls up to the barn or the woodshed and asked
         them to bring in the string of sleighbells that the doctor had used on
         his horse, and she gave them to my father and said, "Now when you come
         be sure to use the bells, so that I can tell when you're coming." And
         Dad always used the bells on the horses everafter that.
         
         BC:  That's where those bells came from.
         
         SS:  That's a nice story. Those bells were- I think they were kind of Dr.
         Watkins' trademark, too, because Carol Brink writes about those bells.
         
         BC:  Oh, they're a beautiful tone.
         
         IA:  Oh, they re nice, they were lovely music, (tinkle, tinkle. J They were
         just lovely.
         
         BC:  Well, that's how Dad got the sfehWlU
         
         SS:  How great a shock was that to the town when Dr. Watkins was shot? Was
         that a really great uproar in the city? Do you think?
         
         IA:  Yes, it was. Everybody was up in arms about it, and they formed a
         posse and followed the man out to his home and he went to an upstair
         window and he would shoot at the men that were dam below and tried to
         kill some of them. But they said that his aim was very poor; didn't
         hit anybody.
         
         BC:  Did they kill him? I don't remember.
         
         IA:  He was upstairs and his little, old mother was downstairs and she came
         out and tried to get the men to disperse and leave. She said, "He is
         not in his own nind, and he is liable to do something thatwould be
         very I do wish you'd disband and go back, and I'll get
         him down and see what we can do about it." But they weren't able to
         dispense, they stayed with it until the man was shot. And it was
         serious and they just had to have him taken care of then. But Dr. Watkins-
         in those days all of the insane people or people that were off,
         as they used to call them, mentally were sent to Orofino. That was
         the place for them. And this man had been bothering his mother and
         bothering some of the neighbors around and they had him arrested and
         took up to the courthouse and at the courthouse they judged him
         insane. And one of the doctors that pronounced him insane was Dr.
         Watkins. And so as soon as the man was able to get out, whether he
         was released or whether he got out of the asylum, I don't know, but
         at any rate, he still had it in for Dr. Watkins because he was the one
         that said that he should be in Orofino, and that's why he shot him.
         
         SS:  But he did go down to Orofino? He was sent to Orofino? This man was
         sent there? He was sent to Orofino?
         
         IA:  Yes, he was sent to Orofino. The doctor sent him to Orofino in the
         first place, and then, as I say, he either escaped from there or was
         released, I don't know which. But, at any rate, he still had it in
         for Dr. Watkins because he was the one.
         
         SS:  One other thing I was going to ask you: do either one of you remem
         ber when Carol Brink's mother killed herself?
         
         IA:  Smith's mother?
         
         SS:  No, Carol Brink's mother. Dr. Watkins daughter. Elsie Pfiel's sister.
         
         IA:  Oh, yes, yes, she killed herself.
         
         SS:  Do you remember that?
         
         IA:  I do. Carol Brink, she became Carol Brink, she was Carol Brown
         
         BC:  Ryrie.
         
         SS:  Right.
         
         IA:  Brown after Ryrie, her husband died, and then she married Brown.
         
         IA:  She married Brown. She married Alec Ryrie and Ryrie worked in one of
         the banks here and was considered a very good man and all, and after
         his death, she- this Brown, Matt Brown I told you was a locater and
         located his sister on the Floodwood out here, and he was- well, we
         called him a rounder; that was all he was, he was just simply a roun
         der. He would drink -
         
         SS:  I've heard the same thing about him.
         
         IA:  And all.
         
         SS:  A ne'er-do-well.
         
         IA:  And he was such a different type entirely from Mr. Ryrie, that I suppose
         that it appealed to the sister. I don't know but that my sup
         position, that it was the extreme change. And she married Matt Brown.
         Well, they got along fairly well for a little while, but it didn't last.
         And finally, she'd come to the point, as you said, that divorce was
         something that just wasn't heard of; it was a disgrace to the family,
         and a disgrace to the people, and she didn't want a divorce, so she
         took what they thought was ground glass and committed suicide by swal
         lowing the ground glass. And Carol was just a small child at that time,
         and Elsie, the sister, took care of Carol. And that's how Elsie and
         Carol happened to be together.
         
         SS:  Do you remember her, the mother? Do you remember the woman?
         
         IA:  Carol's mother?
         
         SS:  Yes. She was a very good-looking woman. Elsie was inclined to be a
         little heavy, like her mother, a little stout. But the sister was tall
         and slender and very light hair, and you really would call her a
         beautiful woman.
         
         SS:  In the book that Carol Brink wrote about her, Snow in the River, she
         seems to present her as a very emotional and moody woman. She played
         the piano, she said, very emotionally.
         
         IA:  She played piano very beautifully, but as you say, emotionally.
         I think that came on, most of it, the melancholy spells and all after
         Alec's death. She was much more so, after that.
         
         BC:  Carol was a young, young girl when her mother died. And Carol, in one
         book we felt that she didn t give Aunt Elsie proper introduction, be
         cause she seemed to be critical of her and not too fond of her and Elsie did everything
         in the world for that girl. She gave parties
         for her and got her a pony cart. Carol, I think resented the fact that
         she wasn't her mother, but still had to take care of her.
         
         IA:  I think in her book that she leans a great deal to Ryrie's brother.
         
         SS:  That's right.
         
         IA:  Speaks very highly of him, and he was the one that the people didn't
         think very much of in Moscow.
         
         BC:  Well, she was a child.
         
         IA:  She was a child and he appealed to her by being good to her and all.
         Douglas, I think was his name.
         
         BC:  That's right.
         
         SS:  But he wasn't very highly thought of.
         
         IA:  No.
         
         SS:  She presents him as a rather controversial man in the book. She does
         love him but his own business affairs were so mixed up in the book, you
         know. He went from rags to riches and back again.
         
         BC:  Didn't she say that he gave her so many lovely things, and Mis s Elsie
         didn't have the money. She sewed for Carol, made her clothes, but
         along this neer do well and brings Carol something beautiful,
         so of course, he impressed her.
         
         IA:  Miss Elsie was a nurse, and she had very little to go on and a Mother
         to take care of and all. And when she had this Carol then, she just
         had to be careful. And they were used to the old style things that
         the mother had for Elsie and her sister and all, and they were out of
         date for little Carol. And this brother, Douglas, was always buying
         and getting things for her.
         
         SS:  Did they call her Miss Carol?
         
         BC:  Miss Elsie, the woman that raised Carol.
         
         IA:  She was quite the talker. We took her with us out to the Stanley's
         cabin. In the summertime my sister would always make an arrangement
         with Stanley, Hubert Stanley was a clerk in the post office, and
         she'd make arrangements with him to rent his cabin out on the- what
         was it?
         
         BC: Chatcolet, was it?
         
         IA:  Huh?
         
         BC:  It was on a lake.
         
         IA:  Yes, it's out, oh-
         
         BC:  Isn't it Chatcolet?
         
         IA:  Chatcolet- no, it isn't Chatcolet. Rocky Point. And we'd always go
         out there. So one summer we took Elsie out with us and Stan and
         Marjorie and I would get in the boat and go way out to where the river
         through the lake for fishing, and we could hear Elsie sitting up
         on the porch talking to my sister and Bertha Hall and we could hear
         her just as clear as could be-
         
         BC:  Never stopped for a 
         
         IA:  Never stopped for anything. (Chuckles)
         
         BC:  She was entertaining.
         
         IA:  Oh, dear.
         
         BC:  She'd tell about different cases that she'd nursed and she always
         something amusing about every one of them
         
         IA:  You'd just laugh your head off to listen to her. She always had some
         thing funny. In 1910, the year of the fires, Elsie was married at
         that time and was living in Wallace, she and her husband,and while the
         fire was all around Wallace, Wallace was practically surrounded by the
         fires of 1910, and they have a- not a Sister's school, but - well, I
         guess thatrthow you would call it a Sisters school- at any rate they
         had a school and a church there for the Catholics. And in front
         of the building was this big statue of Christ and Elsie said that du
         ring the fires that all the congregation, the Catholics, would congre
         gate around this statue of Christ and pray that the fires would not
         burn the town. And she said it didn't. It burned all around it, but p
         didn't burn the town, and she said she thought it was the prayers of
         the Catholics around the statue. She bought Carol a little buggy-
         
         BC:  A pony cart.
         
         IA:  A four-wheeler buggy and a little Shetland pony.
         
         BC:  Maybe Douglas got that.
         
         IA:  And Carol was the envy of the town because she had this Shetland pony 
         and the little carriage. She'd take people out for rides. Loved to
         pick up the children in town and take them out for rides.
         
         BC:  And Miss Elsie used to give birthday parties for Carol, and the only
         birthday parties I ever went to where we were each given a gift instead
         of taking a gift. Miss Elsie would have a little gift for each child
         that was asked to the party. And there was one I remember so well,
         it was a little wooden pail about so big and a little now we
         would cellophane, we wouldn't call it that then, it was a clear blue
         kind of plastic stuff and the little pail was filled with candy. I
         was so impressed.
         
         SS:  Seems like a very nice custom instead of getting presents to be giving
         presents.
         
         BC:  Miss Elsie did things like that for Carol. At that time Carol was my
         age, maybe a year older, so Carol couldn't when she was living with
         Miss Elsie, couldn't have been more than ten or twelve years old. She
         has a childhood, maybe not too accurate.
         
         SS:  I have to be going it's almost six-thirty.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13362</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Adair4</previous>
      <next>Albright1</next>
      <disp_name>Adair5</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
