<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/14/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Helen Anderson, 1974-06-14, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:13:06</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Anderson, Helen Kellberg</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1904</birthyear>
      <residence>Burnt Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Swedish settlers who came via Missouri (1906)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#butchering"&gt;butchering&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sewing"&gt;sewing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#poetry"&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#parties"&gt;parties&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Burnt Ridge"&gt;Burnt Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13365</file_name>
      <mp3>13366.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13366.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Eric Oiler's Barns; one old man hewed the barns and made them smooth</title>
            <synopsis>Eric Oiler's barns. One old man hewed the barn beams and made them smooth.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>180</time>
            <title>Butcher bees for hogs; sugar cured or smoke cured pork and brine cured beef</title>
            <synopsis>Butcher bees for hogs. Sugar cured or smoke cured pork and brine cured beef.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Little stamp money during the Depression; price of groceries and reusing old clothes
               to make new ones
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Little stamp money during the Depression, Got 6 or 7 cents a dozen for eggs and a
               bit more for butterfat, Ernie bought clothes the day after Christmas during the Depression.
               Sewed clothes over for Lois from Marie, Cut up a Sunday outfit for John one Saturday
               night.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Johnson Mercantile Store sold beautiful men's and women's clothes, furniture, hardware,
               and groceries
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Johnson Mercantile store sold beautiful fur coats, wedding dresses and yardage in
               the old days. Also sold furniture, men's clothing, hardware and groceries. Another
               grocery and dry goods store and two theaters in Troy, Went to "Shepherd of the Hills"
               when worried about the end of the world.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Father helped to get rocked roads and rural free delivery; put in a telephone to Eri
               Oiler's; horses fall in
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father helped to get rocked roads and rural free delivery. About 1908 father put in
               a telephone to Eric Oiler's on barbed wire and when Eric Oiler's horse fell in the
               well they saved him easily, Carl Westberg's horse fell in well, Paul Rodin called
               Anna Westberg to ask for a kiss to see if the phone was working.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1860</time>
            <title>Mrs. Joe Carlson dried fruit on roof of the house; would make a big fruit soup; midwifery</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Joe Carlson dried fruit on the roof of the house. Mrs. Carlson would make a big
               fruit soup thickened with tapioca when she went into midwifery. When Moody is sick
               with diphtheria she brought them food and made clothes to bury them in.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2220</time>
            <title>Two girlfriends complained of not having sisters and only having brothers</title>
            <synopsis>Two girlfriends complained because they didn't have many sisters and didn't know why
               the doctor always brought them brothers in his valise. Learned the facts of life on
               your own.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Carleton French lived in Troy and walked to Burnt Ridge school reading; told stories
               to the whole school; learned poems by heart; had highest grades on eighth grade exam
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Carleton French lived in Troy and walked to Burnt Ridge school reading a book. Told
               stories that fascinated the whole school. Learned poems by heart which keened up your
               memory. One year the three highest grades on the eighth grade exam were from the Burnt
               Ridge school.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2820</time>
            <title>Frank Steelsmith rough on the kids</title>
            <synopsis>Frank Steelsmith rough on the kids. Made to stand on tiptoe to keep nose in circle
               and wear dunce caps for punishment. One boy threw a brick through the window and no
               one would tell.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Kitsh mad at one boy and whipped him; mother complained; June Cole and Esther Kristians
               and good teachers
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Kitsh mad at one boy and whipped him and mother complained. Teacher spanks the boy's
               sister for having her dress unhooked. June Cole and Esther Kristians and good teachers.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Parents celebrated 25th anniversary with a surprise gathering which even she didn't
               know about
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Parents celebrated 25th anniversary with a surprise gathering which even she didn't
               know about.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Party games and square dances; church celebrated midsummer picnic day on June 24th</title>
            <synopsis>Party games and square dances. "Old Man Tucker", "Skip to my Lou", "Carl Gustav" and
               one Swedish song. Went to literaries, parties and few shows while courting. Church
               celebrated midsummer picnic day on June 24th and many came.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Good and bad teachers. Neighborhood happenings. Party gatherings. Economizing in
         the depression. Naivete of young. Shopping in Troy. 6-14-74 1.2 hr p LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         HELEN ANDERSON: Done by the same man. And then Eric Oiler, he up here, he had his
         may he about the same time as Carlson's. But he had a beautiful barn. It
         looked real pretty when he got through. The other barns were nice looking
         little bit
         too. But it was just, different than the rest of the barns that were
         built.
         
         LAURA SCHRAGER: Did he hire men to come in and build the?
         
         HA:  Yes. Well I think people wanted work. So people wanted work and this way
         they got a chance to work, on building. Course, he needed quite a few men.
         only had about three men working for us. That worked on our barn.
         
         LS:  Did you help out at all?
         
         HA: No, but we had one old man,Julia Nelson now, she used to be Julia Moody.
         Her father would hew these great big timbers and make beams to hold the
         barn together.And they were heavy beams. That was his job. I don't know
         how in the world he could do it. it was perfect logs. Several big, maybe
         two feet. Square. every bit that and some were biqqer
         than that. And he'd always make 'em smooth, and that was mostly all done
         by hand with an axe and t' en he had this to smooth out beams and
         so forth. Sort of a blade, couple of handles.
         
         LS:  Did a lot of people come to help build the barn?
         
         HA:  we didn't have a barn raising. Y0u know, lots of places they do have
         barn raisings, and that,.. I was going tell when they, butcher bees, they
         have lots in the wintertime. In.the winter time,they had, people butcher
         for the season or for the winter and some would have five or six hogs that
         they'd butcher for their families and they had the wholt neighborhood come
         over help cut up this meat. First butcher and scald, well kill and scald.
         They had scalding vats that they'd roll the, put 'em in scalding water and
         ^have blades or something like that and they'd scrape all the hair off. And
         then after the scraped all the hair off and even took off the knuckles on
         the pig's toes. They save everything. And then they'd open 'em up and take
         the insides out and then they would cut 'em up into hams and shoulders and
         ribs and so forth, and sparerib, stuff like that.And some usea^sugar cure.
         Some of them used the smokehouses. Some people smoked their meat. Other
         would put 'em in sugar cure. But the only way that meat would keep is let
         the body heat of the animal off of them hanging. You should let fem hang
         maybe a couple of weeks wouldn't hurt 'em a bit. Unless it was soft weather,
         you would take it sooner then. But if you were in no hurry, why
         you'd let fem hang in the cold weather.If you just butcher those pigs out
         and cure fem before you get the body heat off of 'em, they won't keep.
         It happened that people, too big of a hurry to get their meat taken care
         of,it spoili Be sure of what you're doing. Everybody had, always butchered
         in the wintertime. We butchered pigs and we butchered beef.
         
         LS:  Would you have parties for butchering?
         
         HA:  No. But the people on American Ridge did. They always had a party,butcher
         bee. Like the quilting bee or anything else. They would all come and have
         a big time at the same time. But here on our Ridge, each family took care
         of their own. That was quite a process, 'cause you'd work from maybe ten
         days to twe weeks to get all the meat taken care of. It wasn't only the
         butchering, it wasn't hard to lay that down in brine salt and stuff like
         that and cure it for 6-8 weeks. And then you could take it out and dry it
         off and you would put it in, about the best thing you could do, we used
         to have oatmeal sacks, they were quite large, you could put a ham in or
         so forth, but that isn't enough.After you get that out all real good and
         tight, then you should have a anothefsack, not necessarily gunny sack,we
         used to get these peas sacks, something like that, white heavy ones and
         you put that around your meat and you tie that loose, you don't want it
         tight on the meat 'cause then it would possibly milriew. And then you
         would hang it, maybe up in the rafters or maybe upstairs, if you weren't
         using the room upstairs,if it was dry. But it be a dry place,
         not too damp. And we had best beef we had ever eaten, I believe was out
         on Driscoll Ridge, we lived in a log cabin.And Jim Pinns owned it
         and his father I think owned it before. He, and that was built in 18 something. But
         anyway, we lived in it for five years. We rented their farm
         And so we hung ours upstairs under the rafters in the window to the east.
         The window to the west would be open most the time. And that way we had
         a breezeway so even at night, when it was a hot day, the upstairs was cool.
         It was quite cool. That wasn't days of seal sport I guess. We lived out
         there and everybody, we went through depression. And you couldn't afford
         to hardly send a letter. There was no money. We could hardly get 6-7 cents
         a dozen for our egg£. And butterfat was a little bit more than that. We
         got cash out of the cream that we sold. But it never amounted to more than
         about five dollars a month,we didn't have that much cream. But with that
         five dollars, we bought sugar, our coffee, our, maybe a pair of shoes or
         something that the kids needed. It always seemed like somebody would have
         to have a pair of shoes. Maybe once a month. First one would wear theirs
         out and then the other one, and lot's of bb* were made out of paper...
         
         LS:  They were made out of paper?
         
         HA:  Yeah. But you wouldn't know it. But we paid five dollars for a pair of shoes
         that we bought from Troy. And they didn't last for more than about a week
         or ten days. Toes were out of em. So you examined them and they were
         practically all paper. So no wonder that they would ©ear out so soon.So
         of course we went on through that. But children's shoes were more expensive
         almost than the grownups shoes. Always were. And lots of times children's
         clothes were more expensive than some of the other things for groyups,
         at that time.Of course you had a little child you always say, well, wouldn't
         that look cute on so and so. And you'll buy it just because you think that,
         but we didn't have that much clothes though. Because the kids used to wear
         overalls and coveralls and shirts. Or else we'd sew 'em shirts out of clothes
         or pieces that we had.
         
         LS:  Did you sew a lot?
         
         HA:  I sewed an awful lot, many years ago when the kids were small. I sewed
         everything that the kids wore. And I sewed a lot til Marie was in high
         school. After that clothing got so much cheaper that, it didn't coat very
         much. For goodness sakes, you could buy a dress for a dollar or two or three
         or four or five. Wasn't too much, but five was priced high, because we
         didn't have a lot of money. But they even had Cresses for thirty nine cents.
         Had panties, I remember that. And they made, but I don't think, well, they
         seemed to be fast colwr so I did have a few of those for every day dresses.
         They looked pretty nice for a while. But you go away in, but like I say,
         the dresses weren't high. And we lived on the Halstead place then, right
         next to where Horton's live now. And bought toys for the kids for Christmas
         and a little bit of something for each one, but the day after Christmas
         then the price of the clothing went down and so went to Moscow, I don't
         think I did. £ut he saw all of these bargains and he'd bought Lois a dress,
         a two piece,rust colored, pleated skirt, nice tap on it for five dollars.
         And he bought clothes for the kids and what not. Marie was in high school
         and everybody thought she had so many nice clothes, but she made her clothes
         and I sewed for her too. But she always looked nice in whatever she put on.
         She knew how to wear her clothes and made it look like she had lots of clothes.
         Well here it comes to being Easter. I bought her a dress and it was real
         cute. It was a jersey, but it was pleated skirt.You know how jersey hangs.
         It was a full skirt, it was real nice. I think she got a pair of shoes, no
         she didn't get a pair of shoes, but I saw a coat for five dollars. And it
         was navy blue with this white stripe in it. And it looked real nice on her.
         But when she got home, she cried. She said she wanted a pair of shoes but
         I bought her the coat instead. Well I said I thought the coat would be better
         for the reason that she needed that too. But she cried when we got home.
         Course sheAbought that coat, I talked her into it. But anyway, I suppose
         then we went into town later and got her a pair of shoes, but it was so
         hard to get clothes in those days. And she took such good care of her clothes.
         Never sear 'em out anyway. Pass fem down to somebody 'else I guess. I
         sewed some of Marie's over for Lois 'cause Marie was the oldest
         in the family and Lois was the youngest. It was kind of fun to make new
         dresses out of old dresses. I didn't feel I was lo sing anything if I made
         a mistake in sewing because it was old stuff. If I got a brand new piece
         it would worry me to death.'Cause if I ciiit that up wrong it would be too
         bad. But these other dresses, I could tell what kind of a dress I could
         make out of it that kind of material and so forth...
         
         LS:  Didn't you cut up a pattern Bnd...?
         
         HA:  Yes. I didn't have anything for 3ohn to wear, he was just a little kid,
         about four years old. I don't know if he was that old. And I didn't know
         what he was going to wear to church. We always went to church on Sunday
         morning. So anyway, I had an old pair of pants that the kids had worn the
         kneas out. And so I used the back part of the pants and some of that you
         could use the knees and it for the bib, but anyway, I got a pair of
         pants. And Mrs. Berg, the minister's wife kind of cmiled at me and here
         John comes a new pair of pants and I'd pressed fem all up and looked like
         new and she said,"Did you make 'em?" And I smiled, I.said I did. But Auntie
         had given me a black fur coat, I would say. It was pretty nice stuff in it.
         And I took her coat and I made myself a coat and bought a pattern for this
         one. It turned out so nice. And I had a hat that I wore when I was sixteen.
         And anyway, I was looking through the rag bag. I found, it was made out
         of velvet. And it was just nice. Dust velvet.Sort of faded. I found enough
         to put a bow on my hatJ. I think I turned the hat around.(laughs)Anyway,
         I did something, I turned up the brim. And I put this bow on the thing.
         And I come to literary, we had literary in^school and so,"I wonder where
         Helen got that?" "Ah, her outfit." And I made it so it looked real
         nice. So then the minister's wife, she wondered where in the world I gotj
         she knew that I'd made it over from something. She thought it was nice
         so she went and bought a pa. ttern just like mine and made her old fur
         coat over. She had it for ten years or more. So she made her coat over
         after my pattern. But it did aake me look real nice.(Laugh) Could afford
         to have a nice looking coat in depression time.It was black fur. Pretty.
         
         LS:  Did you shop a lot in Troy in Ole Johnson's?
         
         HA:  Olson Dohnson Mercatile store I think it was called.It had everything there.
         Everything when we first, well many years ago you could buy lovely clothes
         that come out from New York. Beautiful stuff.All those pretty good price.
         Lots of 'em were eighty dollars and stuff like that. They were really just,
         fur coats and of course now they'd be lots more than that. But you~^r around
         eighty dollars. And wedding dresses. And they had lots of dresses. You buy
         and graduation dresses, lots of 'em would buy graduation dress. And they'd
         cost around fourteen, fifteen sixteen,eighteen dollars. But they were
         real pretty, made out of real silk and they had nice styles to 'em. But
         they had yardage that you could buy knit and silk and aatins. But
         you Could get at the store. Also they had mill...
         can't say it...
         
         LS:  Millinery?
         
         HA:  Millinery and Anna Halson, her name was Westberg at that time. And she
         worked upstairs and made hats. Beautiful hats, all kinds of pretty hats.
         And we also...there was a balcony on this upstairs that you'd go
         the whole building and part of it was furniture and oh, I think they had
         men's clothing down one side too. But you could go clear around and they
         had something up there, mostly furniture though up there.
         
         LS:  Did they sell shoes?
         
         HA: Yes. They had the shoe department downstairs. And theft, they had the
         hardware department, they had everything. And then they had the grocery
         department too and they had a secretary there, it was a full time secretary
         taking care of all their business there. And then, you could buy anything.
         You could buy all kinds of things. Christmas time you could buy all kinds
         of toys and stuff like that. And of course, they had the men's department
         where you could buy all kinds of stuff like. But as far as going into
         tne department, there you bought bananas and things by the barrel, like and anchovies
         or smoked herring or, and cranberries
         and lutefisk. So there was all stuff and candy and so forth. But
         that was a real interesting store. And it was heated. It had hotwater heaters
         and so forth. It felt so good to come in there and sit around those heaters
         and warm up. Then you go up^to the grocery store. The grocery store too
         that was a little bit of a dry goods store too. And Mr. Brohman ran the
         grocery department, and Mrs. Brohman, she had dry goods and notions and
         I think they too probably had hats and clothing maybe some too.Then further
         up the street we had a couple of theatres there, sometimes two and not
         always in the same place either because we had one across the street
         where the bank is now. Above that...
         
         LS:  Would you go to shows much?
         
         HA:  No, just real special. We went to what was called "Shepherd of the Hill".
         About the eighteenth of December and this was the time they prophised this
         was going to be the end of the world. So we were all determined we were
         going to go down and see the "Shepherd of the Hill"and it was a good show.
         It was just really interesting for us kids. But we were worried about the
         end of the world coming. We were supposed to freeze to death I guess, for
         one thing.It was awful cold. And we^ go down there by buggy or hack or
         cutter or something like that. Or sled.
         
         LS:  Who told you it was going to be the end of the world?
         People that prophised it did that. But I've got off from that. We had always
         about two theatres going and for a while we had a theatre about where the
         grange hall is now.That went on for quite a few years too. But that was
         interesting. And they had good shows. Tney had shows all over country^
         too besides...you know, real good shows. Anybody could go in and enjoy a
         good evening and we never had anything to worry about,and I think the
         people were honest and a lot more strict. Because we never had any trouble
         to speak of. Parents looked out for their kids and so forth. Ithink they
         were just easier to manage. And then mostly children were home.They weren't
         like now in car days where they take the car and 30 and they
         could be good kids but something could always happen without expecting
         it, you know. These things happen you know. Something break down on the
         car or maybe you didn't have enough gas in the first place or something
         and drive out of oil or.,something. And we didn't have the roads 'cause the
         recked roads weren't very good for cars. And they started to get 'em rocked, how
         hid rocked roads? Not too awful long. I don't remember
         exactly now, but maybe along in'20 I guess, 1920 or something in there.
         I don't remember though. But my father worked on that to see that we get
         rock roads. We got the Rural Free Delivery before that. It came out at first,
         once a week. Maybe it come twice. Once a week, then it come out twice a
         week and then finslly we got it day.That was really something to
         see. And of course we were thrilled to death to go and get the mail.
         Course, they finally got home for us but we always ran up there to get
         the mail. It was interesting. There were enough people in our family that
         we probably each one would get a turn at it."Can we go get the mail today?"
         And we'd visit it a little bit with our cousins, but we weren't supposed
         to. We were supposed to come right back! (laughs)
         
         LS:  How far did you have to go?
         
         HA: Dust up to the corner here. But and then before that in I think it had to
         be in about 1908 I think was when we got our telephones and my dad started
         that too. And he worked hard on all these projects.
         
         LS:  Did you ever hear about him putting in the telephone?
         
         HA:  Yeah. And my dad. He started out by having a telephone on the barb wire
         fence from our place to our uncle's Eric Oiler. And so we could talk back
         and forth. So then he tried to get these other people interested in wanting
         a phone. And they couldn't see no use why we a telephone. Well
         I think Eric Oiler was the first one to have a hores fall in a well.
         So anyway he called up dad and he managed to get the horse out of the well.
         But it wasn't too awful many years later Carl Westberg had a horse in a
         well. And it broke through last time to oater.Horses from the washtub or
         something like that by the well. But this horse could have been running
         loose or gotten loose or something. Anyway, fell in the well. And it was
         such an excitement because they had to get pulley s and pull 'em up. They
         got him just to the top and then he fell down in again, you know. And then
         of course...
         
         LS:  Did yau run up to see what was going on?
         
         HA:  We didn't. I heard about it. And so then they finally got him out the next
         time that they raised him, be careful so he wouldn't go back in the
         'Cause lots of times horses have been .in the well maybe for several hours
         and the water's so cold that they're kind of stiff when you get 'em out
         and maybe cramps too. Ahd they get 'em out but if you pull far enough from
         the well you walk backways get,'em down in there a gain. So it's quite
         a task to take a horse out of the well. Anyway, the neighbors began to
         get their telephones in and old man, I forgot his name. I know it so well.
         Paul Rodin's father, he told Paul,"You call up Westbergs and see if they
         can hear ."So he rings and Anna answers and he says,"Is that you Anna?
         Give me a kiss!" And ^dad got him he said,"you aid guy, you're always so
         craz$?."And he said,"You wanted to know if you could hear over there. And
         of course, Paul always pulled these pranks anyway and always a ffilown too.
         He was always that way as long as he lived. He'dAeither kid you or tell
         you something else.
         
         LS:  Is this Paul Rodin?
         
         HA:  Yeah, did you meet him?
         
         LS:  No.
         
         HA:  And my name was Helen Marie and he's say Helen Maria. And, didn't like
         being called Helen Maria. Then I called our daughter Marie, our oldest
         daughter Marie. And of course, he called her Maria too. And it made her
         always hate her name because somebody. But anyway telephone line, daddy and different
         ones I think they had to
         have *em, if anybody was sick they could always call on, and then I was
         going to say, Doe Carlson lived on the canyon edge down there and they
         had all kinds of apple trees and fruit trees. Prunes and pears and she'd
         dry fruits, she'd dry this fruit on the roof of her house under cheese
         "A cloth or mosquito net or something. And set on top of the roof and
         dry *em. As hot as it is today, you could see where they dry and she'd
         watch 'em and so forth. Anyway, she was midwife and she went and help
         deliver babies and she'd deliver babies around this whole . maybe...
         
         (End of side A)
         
         HA:  ...fruit soup and I mean big. I suppose about a couple gallons or a gallon
         and a half anyway and here she had prunes and raisins and apples and apricots
         ^or something and this and that would make a big stew out of this here. And
         she'd thicken it with tapioca. And it was good. And she'd make it thin
         because it seemed like, well it was thickened from the tapioca, but she
         mafeie it thin eo by the time it was all gone, it was all eat. up and not
         thick on the bottom or anytoing like that. But it was so good. That was
         a treat to all the kids 'cause if mom was in bed with a brand new baby,
         give it for something for the kids to have for soup or something like that.
         Mother was sick and won't have to worry about soaething 'bout uhat for the
         kids. They'd get bread and milk or something. But this kind of tide
         them over til mother g«t on her feet again. She was a very wonderful
         woman though. She was a^wonderful person. And she was so handy crocheting
         and making clothes for other people. And then, so there were people by the
         name of Moody that lived on the canyon on American Ridge side of the hill
         across the canyon* Burnt Ridge. And when they were sick she'd always carry
         all kinds of good stuff down to these people, course,they knew she had so
         much. They had diptheria. Idon't know how in the world they had diptheria.
         It could have been from drinking certain water or something. And two or
         three of 'em died. And here Mrs. Carlson went over there and she made dresses,
         took some of the dresses that had or somethat her daughter had,
         but she made little clothes to bury them in.find then she'd take,
         flowers hats and put in their hands in their coffins and the father
         had made the coffins in those days 'cause they were so poor they couldn't
         afford to buy coffins. Coffins are so expensive today its terrible. And
         they must have, I don't know where these are buried but some of them are
         buried on Burnt Ridge I think. Or it could have been on American Ridge too.
         They have a cemetery, which is quite interesting, to go through the cemetery.
         I one is buried on Burnt Ridge.
         
         LS:  5he sounds like quite a woman.
         
         HA:  she was. she was always doing something for somebody all the time. And
         then knitting stockings or she always had something to bring to somebody
         that was sick or something like that. And she was quite creative and knew
         how to make all different things. She'd make like a Santa Clause she'd
         bring to some people. Little red Santa Glaus with little cotton around the
         red cap. And the mustaehe and the suit. About 18 inches, it was quite
         large. And then she'd make like they did in Norway. make chickens
         or rooster or she'd make...it was all by hand, he'd use cotton, red cotton
         flannel and stuff and make dolls or Santa Clauses white
         beards and so forth.
         
         LS:  Was she Norwegian?
         
         HA: She was Norwegian. Back in Sweden they have so many customs. They maybe
         have a rooster, maybe that's made out of straw. Some braided straw and
         just stuff out there and just mostly the color of straw. And of course,
         they probably have red like on the comb and different things. And then they
         have what they call, its a goat. And it always brings good luck at Christ
         mas time. And people do have goats in their barns and at Christmastime
         they bring 'em a special treat to their goats. For good luck and joyful
         Christmas or something. Then they have what they call elf.
         
         LS:  Did you take stuff to your goats? gave away and lots of these things she gave
         away. And they had,its just
         elves, where the elves would come at night and do these things. Maybe
         leave a pair of shoes or something. And there's always a good place that
         the fairy godmother, these elves that come.But the Santa elves and the
         reindeers. Now the elves make all these toys for 'em so Santa Claus can
         come with the toys.They do^this in Norway, the elves bring these things.
         Like in Holland they set their shoes on the outside of the doorj and
         receive gifts.
         
         LS:  Did she know ways to help people whan they were sick?
         
         HA:  bhe must have. I don't know why she knew so much. She must have had some
         training in that. And she would make a wonderful nurse. She always had a
         way. There was no no for answer, she couldn't do it. It was just in her.
         Dust loved to do things for them.
         
         LS:  Can you tell me the story of the two friends who were complaining why they
         didn't have the right brothers and sisters and they were going to talk to
         Mrs. Carlson to find out the facts of life?
         
         There were two sisters, they were just good friends. And these girls are
         getting pretty big. And these girls were getting pretty old and of course,
         they didn't know the facts of life. They still thought that the doctor
         come and brought the babies in the suitcases,valises. So they got to
         discussing and walking home together and they were talking about this
         and they didn't think it was fair. It was Edith Carlson and Sally Ruberg
         and they were,Edith had an older sister and she was the youngest. Sally
         only had all brothers. I think about five brothers. And Edith had four or
         five brothers too. And Edith didn't think it was fair that the doctor
         always gave boys,here was always getting"girls. And they laugh
         about it today that they figure the doctor brought the babies in the valises,
         the suitcases. So that's what they always used to say. Course then thay
         got more modern than that, and now you know. This was been about almost,
         I guess fifty years.They'd say,"A stork brought a baby last night."(Laughs)
         And we were to achurch convention and somebody come to this church meeting,
         she said,"So and so said the stork visited their home last night."And
         mother wrinkled her eyes, brows up, you know. Thought this didn't sound
         very nice, the stork had brought that baby.(laughs) So that was supposed
         to be quite aodern. First they come in suitcases, then the stork would
         bring them.It's so funny that they were saying it anyway.That was a secret
         absolutely.lt was such a secret.
         
         LS:  Would you just learn by rumors?
         
         HA:  Yeah, you had to learn on your own. That was all there was to it.There's
         one thing,I wouldn't want to mention it. We'd have a rough time, going for
         a long time. My older sister put me wise and I was worried to death, go
         to town, go to a doctor, you know. I kept everything to myself. Of course,
         that happened.
         
         LS:  Do you remember any teachers from school?
         
         HA:  Burton L. French,he's related to, no, his name is Carleton. Which was the
         senator?
         
         LS:  Burton.
         
         HA:  Carleton French. And we had such a big school. We had a big school, way
         around forty some people. I think we've had around sixty kids too, for
         that.We should have around here, maybe in one of the cupboards upstairs
         the names of everybody that went to school. He lived in Troy and he married
         a French girl, but his name was French, his last name. And, but he'd walk
         from Troy out and so he had to walk five miles out. I think the road war
         longer than it was now. So he walked five miles to school . Sometimes
         he'd take a shortcut and go past Nora Dohnson place through the timber
         and hit the railroad track, that way when the road was good. He always
         read a book. He'd read a book coming out, hold a book like this you know.
         And he'd keep one one the rqad and the other eye on the book. And so he
         did a lot of reading. He told so many stories, of all things from way,
         way back, which was good in a way. But sometimes he'd be telling them to
         the lower classes, they were all grades in one room. So he'd tell maybe
         third and fourth grade, be few sitting up there, and tell all these things,
         bear stories and everything and he'd have the whole school so quiet you
         could hear a pin drop. Everybody listened to him. He said,"I'm reading this
         to the children. The rest of you better get back to studying."But that happened
         day after day. He made it interesting. I think the kids liked to come to
         bad school 'cause it was interesting. There's one thing that I thought was
         for us: I don't know. We probably had that same reader for one or two years.
         And after we had the thing and we finally could read it by heart. 
         
         We knew
         everything by heart.And it was kind of discouraging. And then finally I
         remember going through the third grade, but that was a bigger step because
         I don't remember any second grade book. I don't remember having a second
         grade book.fhe third one wasn't bad. The fourth grade was hard. We had
         the book. And that had about.all these stories and they .all had
         such hard names to pronounce. Great big, and there were always make believe
         stories. But they were interesting. It was a harder book. It was Hercules
         in one of *em. But these other girls, they were like fairy godmothers or
         maybe princesses from far off land or something. So I wish I had the book
         today. And poems and everything. Wev learn poems ail the way through
         up to the eighth grade. Every book that you went through, you learned all
         the poems like the Village Blacksmith and Evangeline and Longfellow's book
         and stories, most all we had to learn, which was good because it really
         cleaned up your memory. You could remember so much better. We learned everything
         by heart. And we had, we took geography we learned all the otates,A to
         draw the maps and stuff like that. When we took physiology, it was all the
         names of all the bones. And cells and everything like that. Which was good
         too, I'm glad we did that. I guess we had time for it 'cause we only had
         reading, arithmetic,grammar, physiology, geography, history,spelling and
         penmanship. I think that's about the course of our school. And it was
         interesting, it was good for us. I liked it. It was easy for me. But
         he was good. We had him I think for about five years.Maybe more than five
         years. And he was good. And everybody got good grades. Not just that he
         gave good grades, but when they took the county exams, or -were they
         state exams in school? I think they were state. And the three highest in
         the county were Elmer Dohnson and he had 94 or 96 and 98, they were the
         highest in the county.
         
         LS:  On Burnt Ridge?
         
         HA:  On Burnt Ridge. And then Smith, he was a funny old guy.
         hot headed.It's just the way he felt or sewed his oats. But he had
         it in for everybody. He knew better, more thaa anybody else, although I
         dontt think he did.Their sons are living on American Ridge. They're fine
         people. He'd punish us kids. And he'd probably have them standing up at
         the blackboard, maybe make a ring up there where you'd have to step on
         your tiptoes and put yosir nose inside a ring, for punishment. I remember
         he thought he, a kid couldn't learn anything well then he'd put a dunce
         cap on him and set 'em in the corner of the room. And soeetimes kid would
         want to know how to work a problem or something, he'd probably hit his
         hands down like that and so they didn't get much help that way.'Cause,
         I want to tell about this but not mention names. And even the eighth
         graders, the big ones, some of the boys were pretty big before they got
         through the eighth grade. One of the boys threw a brick through the window.
         And so then he called school session and he wanted to know who threw that
         brick. And we, the littlest heard it. And there were quite a lot
         Hit of Swede people going there, but everybody knew, but nobody squealed. Not
         A one soul squealed, not even little kids. So he got away from there,
         Saanson. He's caretaker of Burnt Ridge Cemetery. It was Swanson's
         older brother. I guess he had. But he chased them, I think it was Gustav
         Carlson, maybe Lars Larson and Terry Dohnson. I don't know what happened,
         but he chased them down the side of Burnt Ridge and they were going to go
         through the fence. The boys cleared the fence and they ran clear to this
         house up here. He dropped everything and was after those three boys. But
         he got tangled up in the fence and tore the bottome of his pants out. And
         of course, he couldn't go no place(laughs). 
         
         He was such a funny guy. I think he was teaching the eighth grade certificate.
         Course, you could do that in those days, but he had it in for the kids.
         It was terrible so they were all scared. My brother come to school one
         morning, wfe had one of these styles where you could take, come here and
         drive, wet weather or^ too much snow, we had styles, box up like this and
         steps here and steps here and steps going to school this way. When they
         come with a sled or a wagon, they could driue~ on the side of the road
         there, children right down on top of this style and then you go into the
         schoolhouse. But otherwise if you walk in from the north end of the ridgfe
         you walk in this side, and if you walk in south we'd walk up this side and
         come into school. That was kind of interesting. My brother come to school
         and he said,"Good morning" and he got mad and spanned him and broke a
         stick off see, he was out of sortSj or sWoiN Wis bi$nessA ancj nere
         he just tried to say good morning and kind of spoiled it for him. So he
         didn't use good sense* And then the next teacher we had, her name was Kitsh.
         We had some rough kids and they would fight and wrestle. They didn't get
         along. 
         
         This Boise boy wouldn't pick a fight, but they were just determined
         he was going to pick a fight;^Fight and wrestle. Anyway, whatever this one
         boy did, I don't know what he did, she got awful mad. And she tried to hold
         him in after school for three days. And so then the third day she got«o»e
         of the older kids to hold both doors, she went down and got some willow
         sticks and whipped that kid. He cried bloody murder. She beat him on the
         legs and all over the whole body. I don't know what she did, whether he
         took off any clothes or not, but she spanked, just bloody murder
         andvcried. So next morning his mother come and she was pretty mad about
         it. I don't blame her. I suppose she told her,"You better...." I don't know
         what he told her, but that was awful. Then his sister, poor girl, I
         guess she didn't have much clothes and they didn't have much. Lived in an
         old house. It was up in the cemetery kind of on the hill there, around
         there. I think it's closer to the fence. Anyway, its gone.And she was
         raised, only girl, youngest and she had four or five big brothers. And
         she was the only girl. And of course, she boys, raised her around
         boys and always got a kick out of things. Why she picked on this girl I
         don't knew. This girl, she sat there and her blouse, it wasn't hooked
         together and I don't suppose, she didn't have very good pants.Anyway, she
         showed the skin on her back and she was sitting in the front seat. I think
         people were kind of laughing at her because her dress was open, could see
         part of her bottom. 
         
         We kids I guess were too young, were too scared. We
         were always helpless. And she took that kid and pulled down her pants and
         beat her in front of the whole school. That's cruel.Then from there, I
         remember teachers. And then we, when I was in seventh grade, I
         had Esther Kristiansand. She was a good teacher, but, no, we had Margaret
         Smith's sister. Dune Cole. And she was a good teacher and she was kind of
         a person and she was the one when we got to have reading afternoon hours
         just to settle the kids down and she was a teacher for all eight grades.
         And she'd read Uncle Tom's Cabin or, these two boys that run away from home.
         And then the Pepper Familyand Anoe of Green Gable. And Tom Sauver and
         Huckleberry Finn.Mostly, Mr.Mystanq that's a book too. And of course, that
         was more for boys, but we all got a kick out of these stories that she
         would read because $he were good and everybody obeyed her because she
         good teachers^ naturally obey. And she was interesting. We had her for
         quite a few years. Then from that, then we had Esther Kristiansand. Iwas
         in seventh grade when Ihad Esther Kristiansand. And she was good. We took
         our tests, I think two subjects. We could take physiology and I thinh it
         was geography. You could take those two and the next year you ^^ ^
         your subjects. And so Esther Kristiansand Iguess Ihad for my eighth
         grade too. Then I was out of school. That year. And I think it was that
         year that mom and dad celebrated their 2Sth anniversary.
         
         LS:  Was that a big...?
         
         HA:  Lots of the church people came. It was down here in the living room. They,
         and my sister knew about it nobody told me and even the school
         teacher or anybody told me. 1 couldn't understand why they wouldn't have
         told me because I was, I could have been about around fifteen years old
         or something. Anyway, I don't know why they didn't tell me. And that night
         I talked to, we were really friends with our teacher. Oh, we had Miss Smith
         too, she was^always you could just really pal with. But with Esther
         Kristiansand we'd talk and.she . have time to talk. And she always
         didK too, she'd sweep the big schoolhouse. And so that night she
         was busy and nobody said anything to me and I thought it was so funny my
         older sister wouldn't say something to me about it, but they were afraid
         maybe I'd talk. Because I was around my toom anyway. Anyway, *ididn't find
         out about it. come home and Oscar and Helmer had boughten mother a nice
         silver set for their anniversary. And I remember, and they got lots of
         silverware from the church people. And they had Alvin^here, they were just
         little kids, about four years old, twins, to carry in the gifts. They couldn't
         bring the silver or anything. So they had 'em out here and.had to carry
         them through into the living room. So it was a nice evening, had nice cake
         and whatever they had. I'm,,sure there was more than cake though.-They
         clear out, generally would have cookies and sandwiches and cookies and
         cake. All of it. Lots of times they would have desserts, but not at too
         big a gathering like that, couldn't hardly do it.
         
         LS:  Can you tell me about the party games?
         
         (End of side S)
         
         HA:  ...played games, party games and stuff. Lot of square dances and folk songs
         but we never thought more than they were just games more or less but they
         really were folk dances and square dances.
         
         LS:  do you remember any of the songs?
         
         HA:  Yeah, (sings SEE TAPE FOR SONG) Anyway, we'd change so some was going this
         and some was going that way. And we held ahanger around it and go
         around this WWy we were inside, singing about this old house.(Sings)
         Let's see if we can't get more of that(sings)
         
         LS: They had movements that went with them?
         
         HA:  Yeah. I've got another one. I don-H remember them all but there's lots of
         
         LS:  You'd go to...?
         
         HA:  Yeah, we went over there and played all those songs and we'd do so many
         of them that we practically took over. Well, were, young people.
         Course they got in the ring too, but they sat and watched us. They were
         more what you call American people that probably didn't do what
         been brought over from the old country. Now they have folk dances in Sweden
         on Midsummer day. That's like our Independece day. Our Fourth of Duly.
         And we attended them. Had all these folk dances and they were in circles
         and, or in square dances and they wore Swedish costumes. And the Norwegians
         wore their Norwegian costumes fop all celebrations and for weddings and
         so they don't have to buy another dress for another wedding or something
         like that. That's what Mrs. you uant to hear lots Norway
         Mrs. lives out and she could tell. So would Torvod
         is his name, her name is Herlov.
         
         LS:  What kind of things would you do?
         Well, I'll tell you, mostly we went to sometimes parties at peoples homes
         have parties. But I didn't go to many shows, very few shows. Few
         more after we got married. But he was always gone working. He was home a
         little bit in the summertime. I mean in the wintertime. But he was always
         farming for somebody else out around Moscow. We didn't see too much although
         we'd see like a Midsummer picnic day we used to take the 24th of Dune was
         a big picnic from our church. But everybody came from Moscow and Deary and
         this way^because there was something, gathering. And then of course
         there was Fourth of Duly celebration, people go right to Lewiston
         to watch the firesorks and something like that, or Moscow. That is uncommon
         now. People aren't interested that much. But have you been to the rodeo
         
         HA:  in Lewiston? You ought to go on...
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13365</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Anderson_Helen1</previous>
      <next>Asplund</next>
      <disp_name>Anderson_Helen2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
