<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/14/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ernest Anderson, 1974-06-14, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:33:38</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Anderson, Ernest</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1902</birthyear>
      <residence>Burnt Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Arrived in 1907, two years after emigrating from Sweden</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Burnt Ridge"&gt;Burnt Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13358</file_name>
      <mp3>13285.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13285.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Harvest work on uncle's farm paid 65 cents; very seldom went home while working for
               uncle
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Harvest work at uncle's as a teenager, and 65 cents pay for the season. Very seldom
               went home while working for uncle; and found on returning that many people left the
               country. Managing uncle's farm.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Working as roustabout for Blain Thrashing Company; marriage cake from the baker</title>
            <synopsis>Working as roustabout for Blaine Thrashing Company. A marriage cake from the baker.
               Getting scalded by hot coffee when the hack was hit by a pick-up.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Harvest crews were largely loggers who wanted to get out of the woods in the summer;
               troubles harvesting in Canada in late fall
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Harvest crews were largely loggers who wanted to get out of the woods in the summer.
               Troubles harvesting in Canada in the late fall. Playing poker in the harvest crew.
               A horse trainer loses his team in a storm.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Hard work on homesteads; locals worked at small sawmills for money</title>
            <synopsis>Hard work on homesteads. A man tells of his mother's tears coming to her new homestead.
               Local people worked at small sawmills for money.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Wife's family usually more accepting of husband than husband's family is of wife</title>
            <synopsis>Wife's family usually more accepting of husband than husband's family is of wife.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Farming Joe Carlson's place; donating labor to build road; thrashing on Burnt Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Farming Joe Carlson's place. Donating labor to build road; pleasure thrashing on Burnt
               Ridge. He and his wife got up at 4am to start work today.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Depression self-sufficency and cooperation; took ten years to recover from depression</title>
            <synopsis>Depression self-sufficiency and cooperation. Giving a hog to a neighbor. (People died
               on the farms instead of hospital in old days.) After two years of leaving the car
               on blocks, he got credit from Dinsmore's gas station. Raising cows, buying a separator.
               A frozen bean crop. Local creamery kicked out by big concern. Took ten years to recover
               from depression. Storing wheat on the farm during the Depression. Hauling wheat to
               Troy in the winter, he got cheated on the scale, and caught them.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Chores at home, doing wash; Rotating shoes</title>
            <synopsis>Chores at home, doing wash. Rotating shoes.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Strictness of Sunday school; had to learn English in school; rule of the whip; well
               behaved children in Sweden; good and bad teachers
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Strictness of Sunday school. Had to learn English in school, which was also strict.
               The rule of the whip. Well behaved children in Sweden. The will to learn. Good and
               bad teachers. Importance of love for children and learning. Fighting at school. Superiority
               of country over town schools.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5160</time>
            <title>Consolidation of school districts because of lack of youngsters; problems with transportation
               
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Consolidation of school districts because of lack of youngsters. Problems with transportation.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Depression trials. Rural schools: strictness, teachers, decline. Harvest work as
         roustabout. Early sawmilling. Chores. 6-14-74 1.5 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>No transcript available.</transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13358</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Anderson_Ernest1</previous>
      <next>Anderson_Helen1</next>
      <disp_name>Anderson_Ernest2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
