<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/26/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Axel Anderson, 1974-07-26, Interview #3 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:01:43</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Anderson, Axel</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #3</intnum>
      <occupation>Assistant logging superintendent, camp foreman; employed by Potlatch Lumber Company
         for 44 years
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1886</birthyear>
      <residence>Bovill, Elk River</residence>
      <origin>Arrived in 1907, two years after emigrating from Sweden</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumber"&gt;lumber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bootlegging"&gt;bootlegging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#armed forces"&gt;armed forces&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager;Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13353</file_name>
      <mp3>13280.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13280.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Jacks fought after baseball games between logging towns</title>
            <synopsis>Jacks fought after baseball games between logging towns.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Logging during the Depression; growth of blister rust</title>
            <synopsis>Logging in the depression - white pine only, company pressure to do it cheap. Growth
               of blister rust.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Horses to donkeys, then back to horses; steam donkey settings</title>
            <synopsis>Horses to donkeys, and then back to horses as well. Steam donkey settings.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Before railroads there were drives on the rivers and creeks; flumes and chutes; danger
               of speeding logs
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Before the railroads there were drives on the rivers and creeks. Flumes and chutes:
               danger of speeding logs. Slowing down chutes. (Continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Slowing logs in chutes; cleaning snow out of chute; grease caused fires; used donkeys
               and horses with chutes
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Slowing logs in chutes. Cleaning snow out of chute in morning. Grease caused chute
               fires. Using donkeys and horses with chutes. Fire danger stopped use of donkeys in
               summer. Why chutes were used.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Trouble wit first cats compared to horses; use of helicopters and cats now</title>
            <synopsis>Trouble with first cats compared to horses. Use of helicopters and cats now.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Selective logging looked much better than clear-cutting</title>
            <synopsis>Selective logging looked much better than clear-cutting.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>IWW's prevented him from getting men on train in Spokane for Potlatch, so he enlisted;
               need to change conditions in camps
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>IWW's prevented him from getting men on train in Spokane for Potlatch, so he enlisted.
               IWWs trailed him. Need to change conditions in camps.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Desire to enlist in army in WWI; letters of recommendation to get into forestry unit</title>
            <synopsis>Desire to enlist in army in World War I. Letters of recommendation to get into forestry
               unit. Training before going overseas.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Lack of education compared to others in troop; practical ability and their book knowledge</title>
            <synopsis>Lack of education compared to others in troop. His practical ability and their book
               knowledge.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Building cabins in army camp; location of camp; members of 20th Engineers, 36th Company</title>
            <synopsis>Building cabins in army camp. Location of camp. Members of 20th Engineers, 36th Company.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>Armistice Day and night; drinking with the major while men drank and worked hard</title>
            <synopsis>Armistice Day and night. Drinking with the major. Men drank, and worked hard. His
               best chum was a black first lieutenant. Coming back one day late on a pass. Don't
               make excuses in the army. Dealing with captain after a drink. Drinking with the captain.
               Getting sick on wine.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Baths in barber shop; Wobblies got showers in camp; washing in creek; controlling
               moonshine
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Baths in barber shop - you had to put up with rough conditions to have a job. Wobblies
               got showers in camp. Washing in creek. Other Wobbly achievements. Some didn't show
               appreciation for improvements. Controlling moonshine by firing men who were drunk
               Monday morning. Wood-Em-Up-George's wit in firing men. U.S. Pelton told his boys they
               should log at work instead of in camp. Pelton family operation.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5520</time>
            <title>Family drive on Sunday, ice cream for kids, bootleg for him</title>
            <synopsis>Family drive on Sunday: ice cream for the kids, bootleg for him. A drink after a night
               on the snowplow from a deputy in the bootleg joint. He'd drink with the men in town.
               Advising an old friend to give up bar.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5580</time>
            <title>Irishman Pat Malone in Duluth; two lumberjacks poured the evidence on Pat</title>
            <synopsis>Pat Malone was one of the Irishmen in Duluth. Two lumberjacks poured the evidence
               on Pat. Potlatch brass.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Serving in forestry unit in France in World War I. Drinking and liquor control in
         camp. Log chutes; donkeys and horses. Depression logging. 7-26-74 2 hr 40p
         SS&amp;LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         AXEL ANDERSON: I see now where, I believe it looked like it could've been some
         kind of a fence post or something piled up there. I seen it was torn all down.
         They don't have any more ball games up that way. It was a pretty good diamond.
         Course every time they knocked it across the creek it was a homerun.(chuckles)
         Maybe a little bit's growed out a few stumps there and made a little ball
         diamond about—they had in Elk River. That wasn't very big. Oh, they must have
         graded out just about a block, you know. I guess the field was big enough. Had
         a little grandstand. They must have played there for ten-twelve years, I think. As
         long as the mill ran, I ki
         all them students from the University come up there and they took
         about adozen at amill, puu ?em to work in the mill. And in the yar
         there in the summer-time, so that made a pretty good team.
         
         SS:  So they'd play( the game then they'd have the fight afterwards?
         
         AAA:  Oh, yes. Afterwards, that's when they had the fight. Not the team.
         But all the 'jacks around. If Bovill played down at where the Blackwell mill was at—not
         Blackwell, but the other town there.
         
         LS:  Santa?
         
         AAA:  Ho.
         
         SS:  Fernwood?
         
         AAA:  Fernwood, where the Blackwell rail! was, you know. They had a crew
         there as big as Elk River mill. About the same size. And lots of
         loggers. You know, all kinds of camps there, you know. And them
         loggers and lumbermen, you know they, they're the one that had the
         fights afterwards, 'course, they had a lot of moonshine with them
         and home-brew, and they jot lit up before the game was over, then
         the fight started. We had a scaler there, Jack Dunnaman, he was the
         umpire, mostly. But they never knocked him out. Someway, he got
         by. Course, you know the umpire.; some like him and some don't. And
         he was the only one. They only had one, you know. One at the home
         base, that's all.
         
         SS:  Well, was it a league then, or was it just the teams get together and
         play?
         
         AAA:  Well, they— I guess they had some of 'em— in charge of it.
         The basketball team, only the school didn't have nothing, 'cause this
         was all outside, you know. And they were not high school, there was
         the mill crews and the lumberjacks, out Bovill, they had two
         to now or three that worked on the railrood, they were good brakemens,
         they were damn good. They in their twenties. They fit right
         in with them students that come from Moscow, just right. Same in
         they Potlatch, you know; they had a bunch of students, too. I think
         used to take, oh, a couple a dozen or more students every summer,
         and put to work, you know, some in the woods, and some around the
         mills. But they had a promise that every year they took a bunch of
         them students arid let 'em go to work through the vacations. There
         was a lot of 'em was in the forestry school, and they had to be more
         or less in the woods.
         
         Biu you play Elk River and put Bovill and Troy together
         beat Potlathh?
         
         Oh, yes. Bovill and Elk River, they beat them all the time. The
         pitching was the worst to ret somebody that (chuckles)- they had a
         conductor there in Potlatch , Benson, he died three-four years agohe
         was pitching for Potlatch there for, oh, ten years or more. Tall,
         lanky fellow, he done pretty good. There were no practice, you know.
         They come right off from work, and went playing ball, and kept on
         working until the next game and put on a glove and played a
         ball game. Jo practice. I never seen 'em practice any.
         
         What was camp B like? Working there camp B? You were there before
         the war.
         
         Oh, it was like the rest of them,I guess, it wasn't mucji different.
         between the camps. Camp B , let's see, during the war, U7, when
         I left. Oh, there — we were . pe only two miles from town, up
         creek, that's all. In '17, you see , we had the first, they logged
         out towards Neva, or thirds Bovill on the railroad, where they didn't
         own the grouna. They owned the timber and not the ground. They
         had to log that, pick that first and up Elk Creek , the creek
         you know, they borrowed the old, n timber and all, so theythere
         was no hurry with that timber, that was left to the last, just
         before the mill went down. The last logging up there, we cleaned it
         up and they bvoHfto Potlatch Hauled it to Potlatch, in f34 and '35.
         them logs 193l and '35 We logged two summers up there and.hauled them to Potlatch,
         and they cut 'em there. The mill went down in '30. And then
         in '32 we logged— Potlatch mill was down— we logged two camps there
         on the Potlatch side, they didn't log any in Clearwater. We had Camp
         11 and Camp 2. And all them logs went to Lewiston to Lewiston
         ton. Down Palouse, and up through Moscow, and down to Lewiston.
         And they said those were the cheapest logs they ever had cut in Lewisyoti
         know
         ton. Labor was cheap. : everybody had to work. Forty seven cents a
         half an hour, labor. That wasn't very much, 'course we gyppoed a
         little, but—oh, they could make five-six-seven dollars—some of 'em,
         some of 'em didn't. It was hell to be a foreman, I tell you. 
         when (chuckles) The management. Hold 'er down, hold 'er down. I leuh .one camp there
         and my brother
         in another one, and I think we put in better than three million feet
         to the camp all summer. About six million. I forget— in the fall
         when we got through there, I believe we had something like thirty mil
         lion feet of saw logs, that we put in at the two camps; with horses.
         
         SS:  Which camps were these? What was the names of these camps?
         
         AAA:  I think there were two and eleven, Camp 2 and Camp 11. I was in two.
         They were out— let's see, I was camped on Clove Leaf Creek, and my
         brother he was up on 0mic+- Meadow. That's between Park and Elk
         River. We took them logs, you know where I was seven miles from the
         Elk River mill and hauled 'em to Lewiston. Down to Bovill, Potlatch,
         Palouse, Pullman, Moscow, Kendrick and down to Lewiston. Only white
         pine, no other species. Just picked out the white pine. 
         in there and picked out the rest of it. There was yellow
         pine standing there four feet on the stump and we couldn't touch *em.
         They wouldn't let us. White fir and red fir and tamarack. Just white
         pine only. That was in the Depression, 32. All the mills were
         down, most of them. Potlatch was down. Elk River shut down for good.
         
         LS:  When you first went into the woods, was there any blister-rust at all?
         
         AAA:  Well, I don't know, it might have been, oh, I suppose there was, but
         they hadn't started that. I don't know, really, when they started
         that. But that was started after— I think that started after the
         war, the First World War. I don't think— I never heard of the blisin
         it then
         ter rust before that. The government hadn't started anything 'til
         later years. No I never heard of it. But through the
         twenties, there, they had— through the twenties, and in the thirties,
         you know, they had a lot of blister rust camps, you know. Them kids—
         my kids worked in it. And during the CC camps, you know, they were
         blister kids. Yeah, that Have you ever seen it? Have you ever
         seen that rust? On the trees?
         
         SS:  Terrible now.
         
         AAA:  Is it?
         
         SS:  Oh, yeah.
         
         AAA:  Now, they don't seem to pay no 'tention to it, do they?
         
         SS:  They've almost given up on it.
         
         AAA:  It looked like it.
         
         SS:  They're trying to grow a specie that'll be resistant to it, in these
         little plantings. And they're trying to plant them out and see if
         they'll
         
         AAA:  Then, the white pine then will disappear. Won't it? If they don't
         take care of it. If they don't even try to.
         
         SS:  I think in the East, what happened was, they got down so there wasn't
         many white pines left, and then the rust died out, and now the white
         pines are coming back. And maybe that'll happen here, too.
         
         AAA:  Could be the same thing in Idaho. Maybe. I never know there was so
         much of that being on Marble Creek, in the old slashing there, and
         the new growth come up, you know, and they were just- they were just
         covered, thick, them limbs, with that rust. That's the first time I
         ever really paid any 'tention to it.
         
         LS:  When you were logging there in the thirties and just taking out white
         pine, did a lot of that pine have blister rust?
         
         AAA: Didn't see any, huh-huh, no, that wasn't affected a bit. No, there
         was— up around Elk River they had camps there, they had one camp
         there usually every summer. They had little small strips that they
         took care of there. It didn't bother so much. The first place I
         seen it really tough, was in there on Marble. In that young growth
         you know, come up after the '22 fire. And the young pine that was
         up in there, that killed 'em off pretty much.
         
         SS:  When you were at Camp B before the war, about '15 there '16, '17,
         was the logging methods the same? Did they use the same methods as
         you did when they first— when you first came to Potlatch? Or had
         they changed?
         
         AAA:  No, they— well, the only change they had— the only change theiPotlatch
         had in 1907, I think in the fall, they sold pretty near all the
         horses, and turned into steam donkeys. Then they worked them for -
         'til after the war, I think, or somewhere in that— then they come
         back to horses again. And we used horses and donkeys together. They
         had some camps, you know, and usually three of them steam donkeys and
         the horse camp would be, probably, from fifteen to twenty teams, in
         each one. Up at Elk River there- well, wse: had one horse camp, and
         two donkey camps for a while. Then we start to mix 'em up. Had both,
         horses and steam in each camp. That worked pretty good. You'd set up
         a donkey, you know , for a long haul, a mile haul, you know, and use
         horses and skid to it, and they haul 'em into the track and load 'em.
         That worked pretty good.
         
         LS:  When you just had donkeys, did you have to put in a lot more line?
         I mean, did you have to put in more line? In order to cover the whole
         area.
         
         AAA:  Each donkey was separate, see. And each one had a if there was a short line,
         they took a circle about half a mile,
         and if they had one of them high lines, what we call with supports
         on, you can cross two-three ravines, you know, or hills, mile with
         line, you couldn't do that, except you'd have to have
         a gradual slope. You couldn't go over a hill with a ground line. But
         the high line, you see, when they come up the hill, you know, they
         pick the whole load up, and broke over the hill, you know, well, then
         we had to moreor less just keep the donkey running, check it with the
         brakes, so it didn't run away on you, 'til you got to the next hill,
         you know, then you had to use more steam again, then you had to just
         about lift the load up off'n the ground and go on over the hill with it,
         With the ground line, you coulnd't do that. We had a spool laying on
         top of the hill for the cable to go on, otherwise, you know,
         the cable pretty hard. Well sit on the ground
         to save the cable. When the load come over there, there was a hanger
         there, and they lift it up, they go over all right. See, when you
         come to that shoe up there on the hill, it was uphill, when you dropped
         over, then it was downhill again. Brought the slack over behind you
         and there'll be a swale 'til you get towards the next pole, then you
         go up hill and drop down. That load, you know, sometime be a half a
         carload hooked on, twelve-fifteen logs, or more. They're pretty heavy
         tons of it. If they was any slack in that tight line, you know be
         tween the engines it bear down. Yeah, that was the days of real
         sport. And when you get out of town there away from the noise of the
         mill, you know, you could hear them donkeys and them three locomotives
         in the side hills, you know, back in all directions.
         Potlatch and Winton and Blackwellj they were the big loggers on
         the St. Maries or Elk River line. One time there I counted
         twenty-one free locomotives going from Elk River to St. Maries. Pul
         ling logs into the mill line for the Milwaukee to take out. Pretty
         see
         near every log rails, you know. Let'a at Elk liver we had
         three of them, Bovill, they had six, I think. Then they got down to
         Rutledge, they had four or five, and then you got down to Fernwood
         and there was Blackwell, they had a bunch of them, six or seven. And
         they had one. about the time they all passed, they
         come by you know, they always1 down there and set out logs and pick up
         empties and go back in the woods again before evening.
         
         SS:  About when was this, that there was all this operation going on? at once.
         
         AAA:  After they got the rails in there in 1910, from '10 on, that's when
         everybody started to log. Well, they drove the St. Maries River a
         little, clean from Clarkia down. Dumped 'em in the river, or in the
         creek there up beyond the Clarkia meadows, and they had dams here and
         there, and up towards Emida they had dams. And onSanta Creek, you
         know that ran into St. Maries River, and they logged in the winter,
         they logged with horses and when the spring thaw comes, they had
         water, they used the water in the day time, you know, closed the dam
         at night and hold it for next morning. And they drove millions of
         them there, but after the railroad come in, you know, then the drives,
         that all quit. Was no more of that. The first few years, you know,
         they drove that quite a bit until they got that was the idea with
         the Rutledge, you know, they had the. drive into St. Joe River and then
         get 'em .to Coeur d'Alene and and tow 'em into Coeur d'Alene. But
         after they had that fire, you know, then they had to so
         they built the incline, that ended the drive— no more
         so they built the hill over,down all them creek down Norton and Russell
         and they bring the flat cars in there and load 'em. That ended the
         log drives on the Marble Creek. They put in the chute there firstthere
         was another chute by the flume. The' y had flumes in there and
         that burnt up, that all burnt up durigg the '22 .So everything
         they done in the beginning that all went In that fire, and after that
         then they had to put the incline in to get the rails in there.
         
         SS:  Why didn't more creeks than Marble Creek have flumes on them? Was
         Marble bigger than the others.
         
         AAA:  Well, that's the main one, you see that's — all the smaller creek
         they had chutes, you know, and trailed 'em down to the river, and
         there)[aams here and there. So they just used that all summer down
         into Marble flashfloods, you know, let down. But after that Marble
         is the main one, and all the other creeks don't run in, just feeders,
         smaller ones. Yes, I think they had more flumes there. The Diamond
         Match, no, Winton, I guess built that mill at St. Joe. They had
         flumes up there the first creek or two up river. And over at Mica
         Creek by Calder, Between Calder and Herrick, they was a flume. That
         was running there In i thirties. There was flume in there. They
         had a little railroad up around the Mica Meadows. Little narrow
         small trees. I don't know what they run- oh, probably twenty tonsome
         twenty-twenty five ton trees, little steam engines on rails —
         small rails they packed in. And hauled to the flume there where thyy
         had the dam. I know, when I was with the CC camp there at Herrick
         they were fluming then. We built the road—-A built the bridge over the
         flume, under our road, on the lower end. Near the St. Joe River. And
         on Marble Creek, the Potlatch had a long flume— not Marble Creek but
         oh, back of there- back of there- vjciciao mine, what the heck did
         they call that creek.
         
         LS:  Swamp Creek?
         
         AAA:  Swamp Creek. They had a flume. Big one, that must have been miles
         of it. Two- three dams. Between the dam$, you know, they had — you
         know the water splash out, when the logs come, you know. And they
         had feeders, little dams, you know, and they make a little chute or
         flume-like, and pick up the water out of the creek and run it back in
         the flume again, to help out. Otherwise, you know, they— the logs
         sometime catch up, you know, and they be three-four together, and no
         water run through it, splash behind them. And the flume get dry ahead,
         no water. They hold all the water back, you see, splash it out, you
         see, so that's why they had them little feeders all along there to
         help out, and get the water back in the flume again. The log'd go a
         lot faster in the water., after it get started.
         
         LS:  I'd like to see one of those operation.
         
         AAA:  Yes, we had chutes. I never worked on the flume, but we had chutes
         running chutes, you know, — by golly, you know two mile long up
         the hill there coming down. Had to have a look-out man, you know,
         holler, "Look out, below." when they were coming. And, I tell you
         they were coming, and I mean they were coming, down there. They
         were dangerous, though Lot of 'em get killed down there, they get
         get going so fast, you know, they won't stay in the chute, they just
         take off. Leave the chute, it's a curve you know, they take right over.
         Oh, a lot of people got caught there. We had goose-necks sitting on
         both sides the timber. By golly, you know, that high as that
         tree when they the log shot through, but that slowed 'em down quite
         a bit. Couple hundred feet, and another pair of 'em or two set there
         you know. They were made out of inch and a half square steel, what
         they'd bore we call a goose-neck. They were in the side of it, you know
         and they were made just like a goose-neck, and set down there to hold
         'em. And a long shank, you know, against the side to hold so they
         wouldn't shove back. By golly, you know, that there'd be a pile of
         bark there ten foot high, on the side of 'em. Down to the rails.
         
         LS:  I've heard that one of the reasons that they put goose-necks in was
         because the logs would get going so fast, and start a fire.
         
         AAA:  Too fast, No, well, that could happen, I guess. But they got too
         fast and when they get too fast, you know, why they won't stay in
         the chute. You had to slow— and you had to have— where the
         was- you had to slow 'em down so they come in there, so they work
         there. I had- at one chute landing there, we had, I think I had
         sixteen pairs of those, to slow them down so they just come running
         when they come down to the- one got stuck, the next one knock 'em
         loose. "Course, we had a crew of men down there, you know, by God,
         else we couldn't keep nobody, couldn't stay there. Had to go down
         slow. We had to slow them down somewhere. In the winter time it was
         rough. I had a two mile one there, a chute, and the first thing in
         the morning, put four horses on, and pick out the biggest log you
         could find. Start from the top and prod the snow out. Snowed a
         foot every night, you know. And just pull that clean down to the
         landing, then the chute was clean, they were all shoveled out. So
         when they were through then let 'em come. If they got going too fast
         you had to put in a goose-neck, and slow them down.
         
         LS:  Would that chute— would it ice up?
         
         AAA:  Oh, yes, you know the frost, you bet they get icy. And the more ice
         it got on It, you know, the faster the logs would go. When the sun
         come up, you know, that's all leave, and they slow down themselves.
         And in the summer-time, you know, in order to help 'em, we put in,
         they were always near the creek, you know, to get the water in to 'em,
         a little water that was just like grease, better'n grease.
         Lot of places where there was no water they used grease and that was
         dangerous. Then they could caught fire.
         
         LS:  The greagewould catch?
         
         AAA:  Catch fire, you bet. You bet.
         
         SS:  Did youhorses to bring the logs up to the chute? (outside noise)
         
         AAA:  Uh-huh. Did it with horses. Places, you know, where the chute was
         flat, rf we trailed with horses, shove 'em with horses. Take
         a big log and you could shove fifteen twenty logs ahead of you, and
         get em over the hill, then they runback and get another one. Back
         and forth. You know, there'd be a lot of flats, you know, the chute,
         it would be level, you know, for probably three-four hundred feet, and
         they won't run over 'self, and you had to help 'em. Had a team there
         and push 'em over. And some places they used the donkeys to hold
         the cable and they had a chute and pulled em with the donkeys. You
         take a string though, fifty logs, more or less.
         
         SS:  Would they hook onto the first log, and pull the first log?
         
         AAA:  No, it'd be about the last one. They push 'em, see. No,the first
         one wouldn't do any good, they only had one; you see, go back and
         get one, that's pretty heavy, then probably, you could go back, you
         know on the donkey there you had several hooks, and go back and get
         another fifteen-twenty logs, and go back and get another fifteen- twenty
         and then start. So you come in with a hundred logs, or something.
         More or less.
         
         SS:  Well, what kind of terrain would make you decide to use the chute in
         stead of just the donkey line?
         
         AAA:  Well, if you didn't have the donkey. Lot of 'em didn't have the don
         key, to spare. If you had a donkey there, you'd have to have water
         and in the summer-time there was the danger of fire. You got to burn
         wood  y°u know* Spark , sparks set a fire any place. In the summer
         time they didn't want to use the donkeys much. Just used 'em in the
         winter.
         
         LS:  Were you at that camp, were you working at that camp on Swamp Creek?
         
         AAA:  No. No, I was up there a couple of times; no, I never worked there at
         all.
         
         LS:  Do you know why they decided to put that chute in?
         
         AAA:  Well, they was Yes. It was the only way they could get the logs
         down. There was no trucks them days. The trucks just started to
         come in. I think the last logs from up in that country, too, they
         Hauled 'em down— they had Camp Y there above Dent or above Ahsahka.
         So, I think the last logs in from Swamp Creek I believe they trucked
         'em down there to the mouth of Elk Greek and dumped 'em in the river.
         No chance ofa railroad up in there , you know, too far. Had to build
         a road from Orofino up to Swamp Creek to get in there. In the first
         place that'd cost more than the logs were worth. The next creek up
         there, Robinson Creek and Gold Creek; Diamond Match logged that and
         took the logs over to Cusick. Up here in Newport, on the...After the Potlatch mill
         went down, they hauled more logs out of there-
         I think they hauled more logs out of there since the mill went down
         than what they cut when the mill was in there. I don't believe they
         cut a billion feet of lumber on that mill as long as it was running.
         I've heard it, too, I don't remember the exact thing, but I don't
         think they went up to a billion feet. And they hauled out more since
         the mill went out than what the mill cut when it was sittin there.
         So, you know, really, that mill should have stayed there and they'd
         been sawing there yet. But they got all the timber.
         
         SS:  Was it harder when they didn't have any horses? Was it tougher to
         log with just the donkeys? I would think that the horses would be
         real convenient to pull those logs down to the donkeys.
         
         AAA:  They were. Horses, I think the horses coming back again. I think
         they gonna start. The Forest Service trying to get horses in now
         to save timber. Save the smaller trees. And motor
         power is too much power— you take a team, you know, get a team, we
         used to get the team for two hundred dollars, four hundred dollars
         something like that, where the gol-darn cat, at that time cost six
         thousand, or a little better. And a lot of places, you could do more
         with a team than you could do with the darn cat after you got
         'em. And look at the difference in investment on 'em ,them days.
         It was pretty discouraging there when they first took the horses away
         from us and gave us them cats. They'd be stuck there sitting in the
         rain, you know, and steep hills. 
         
         A cat can't go, stuck, sitting there
         mired. And they go get another one pull 'em out. Get 'em going
         again. I was thinking there the first winter, when I had them cats,
         you know, if I only had horses, could have run circles around them cats.
         But, you goton further up where they couldn't reach with the rails,
         you know, and they had to get something to— longer haul. The horses
         couldn't go. They tried the chutes and they tried the flumes. But
         it ain't like now when they got the cats and trucks and — and no
         matter where it is, you can always build a road up to them, come up
         there with the truck and get 'em. Now they use helicopter.. And
         I've set and looked at the- up aboi+ Halsey, not Halsey, but Elsie
         in Oregon. I saw that happen inthere— just like this one you've
         got here, the Rubber companies down here at the Fair? It's up every
         night, or every day— That was sitting there and it was going back
         and forth, and so I stopped the car and there finally was a patrol
         man come along, so I stopped him, I said, "What in the heck is that,
         Awhat's that doing over there?" Said, "They're logging." (chuckles)
         You know it stayed on the same level and it pick up the logs, you
         know, and go over to the landing, and go back up- He said, "Its so
         rocky up there," he said, "they can't build no road. There's nothin'
         to get up there, so they bought one of them AplmS . but now I
         see they're using helicopters. Now they're using them. They really
         can do It. They got a winch on them, you know, they can lift up —
         they can lift the log off of the ground and go set 'em down, bring
         that hook back and hook on some more. And an the rough timber, you
         know, if they don't want to cut a tree, you know, they leave it stand
         ing there. This wouldn't hurt any, 'cause they pick the log up and
         go over it. (chuckles)
         
         LS:  How did you log in the summer-time if you couldn't use the donkey?
         
         AAA:  Horses, horses. Horses, til the cat come. First you cut the long he
         double logs, you know, and later again you put winches on the
         cat, you know, lust take the old trees now. Top them and take four-fivesix,
         you know, whatever they can and go in with them to the landing
         and spread them out and buck 'em off at the landing where they load
         ing them. Now, they don't even have to have checkers, they got a
         clamp there on the back end, power to go get a tree and get another
         one and yard 'em up, five or six together, and back the cat over it
         and took all of them bundle and 
         The operator on the cat does all of it. One man can do— when they
         fall a tree, you know, they top them off, cut the top off, and leave
         it to the cat skinner to get the rest of it. They don't limb 'em,
         they come top ahead, and by the time they get to the Im* they
         ain't no limbs on 'em, they're off, pull 'em off.
         Did you clear cut most of the time? Did you take everything?
         We took most everything. And we did selective logging, too, a little
         bit. Not too much. We done it on one place there, forty acres, I
         think, or eighty acres, whatever it was, I don't remember. When we
         got through, it looked like a park. Before we got done again, two
         years later, had to go back in and clear and it look like hell.
         Take it off. Why, I dont know. Management. Then they let the river out of there, ai
         the fire got into it, got away when,theyburned
         the brush, or something. Just killed off everything. Well, we logged
         measure in Sweden, they used bnasf they the trees By
         golly, you know, every six-seven years they could get a pretty good
         yield that way. Go in with horses and pick them logs out of there,
         you know and saved the trees growing, saved the underbrush, you know
         the second growth coming up. We just thinned 'em out, you might say.
         
         That's selective logging. But every few years, you know, they got
         a little sell off some more. Well, when I was in France, you
         of course, know they had selective logging. We took what theymarked for us, and
         by golly, he could tell you, if you stole a tree on him. When the
         next time he come over and he'd go look, and he'd say, "What happened
         here?" "That one's missing." If he had that in his mind, or if he'd
         counted 'em, I don't know. He laid it out in strips, you know, and
         like for skid roads, etc they logged first one and then another. By God,(tape noisy)
         Once in a while we had to knock out a tree, you know, and blow to
         get the stump out of there to get a road in .. By god, he knew
         it. And when he come up the next timeTwe'd stole one on him.
         
         SS:  Do you think that one way's better than the other? You think the sel
         ective' s better than the clear cut or—?
         
         AAA:  Oh, I don't know, I couldn't tell you that. Just depends on the management,
         whatever they think, 'course, the little feller out in the
         field, you know, don't make much difference what we thought of it.
         Now, the main idea now is to save timber; save it. And, I don't know
         right now, it don't seem to make any difference what— years ago,
         there was the cast Now, it don't seem any different on cost
         'cause, if it costs more they raise the price on it. Years ago they
         couldn't do that. You had to hold down. Now, it don't seem to make
         any difference what it costs 'em, people buy it anyway. Nobody care
         about prices any more. Lumber's sky-high, you know. We put that
         little room on there. You know what that cost us? What it cost me?
         That wing on there?
         
         SS:  Three thousand?
         
         AAA:  What? Eighty five hundred. Dollars, to put that on. Ain't that
         something? Ain't that terrible?
         
         SS:  Don't look like much.
         
         AAA:  Yes sir, that's what I paid. I gave 'em a check for eighty five hund
         red dollars.
         
         SS:  You know, Axel, how did you come to go into World War Ii? You told
         me before that you went up to Spokane to hunt up some men for operat
         ions? Can you tell us about that?
         
         AAA:  Well,going down there on the train I bought a paper. My
         name was in it for the draft. But then, still I wouldn't had to go
         I was not a citizen, you eu I wouldn't had to go at all. But the
         way the things looked, you know, they were in a strike. Nobody work
         ing. So, I said, "To hell with it, I'm going to enlist." I started
         looking a little bit. First there was the railroad i— that's
         the one I wanted to go in. But when I got to go dont and look, they'd
         moved to Portland So here come the lumberjack.
         
         LS:  Say, Axel, wasn't there a story about— you tried to hire some guys
         and they wouldn't — and the Wobblies wouldn't let you go on the train?
         
         AAA:  Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:  Tell us about that first, OK?
         
         AAA:  Well, that' the same time. Before I enlisted I was irti- Oh, I must
         have been in there three or four weeks before that. I tried. Some
         time— One time, I must have had about thirty of them. And then we
         got down into the Front StreetAor Trent- front of the Milwaukee depot
         and By God, they won't let us go across. Hell, there were hundreds
         of 'em. No use to fight about it. they won't let us get out
         of town.
         
         SS:  Who sent you to get the men? Who were you getting the men for?
         
         AAA:  Potlatch Lumber Company. They were the Potlatch Lumber Company then.
         That's before they mergered, '10, '12. The merger was in '31 and this
         was in '17, see. txIt was the Potlatch Lumber Company then. Now
         my superintendent sent me in there.  See if I could get a crew,
         just stay there til I could get one. And I didn't come back for
         pretty near three years, before I come back yet, to Elk River.
         Oh, they followed me,that employment office man there, he told me,
         said, 'You watch tonight when you go home." I stayed up on St.
         Nicholas, I think it was up on First, He said,"You just step 
         side the door," he said, "youTp just get inside, stay in the lobby, go and
         sit down and watch," and he said,"watch and there'll be two men
         walking, and they'll look all over for you." And, by God, they did.
         It was right. They had me spotted you see. They were watching me.
         I couldn't get no crew, hell, no.
         
         SS:  What month was this, now?
         
         AAA:  That's in July. I was sworn in the army the sixth day of August.
         This was in July. We had the strike in June. Well that kept on, I
         don't know when they stopped it. I don't know. 'Course they went
         out there, they agreed that to a change in the conditions in the
         camp. I think that would stop it, the strike. Oh, it was a good
         thing they needed it. After that we had nice clean camps, you bet.
         Clean blankets, sheets and pillow cases, (chuckles)
         
         SS:  You gave up the ghosT then, huh? Decided there was no point in
         trying it.
         
         AAA:  Well, no, I could have stayed there then, but— I never felt right
         if I hadn't gone. I said, "By God, I want to go." I never regretted,
         I had a good time. Plenty hard work, but then, outside of that it
         was all right.
         
         SS:  Was it tough for you to get in? Hard to get over there?
         
         AAA: No, no, I didn't havetrouble. Not at all. Went up to Coeur d'Alene
         and talked to them and at the Forest Service. I was working in the
         Forest Service. Got a physical. Had to have five years of recom
         mendation letter; two of them to get in. And that was easy to get-
         I'd worked on the same place— I'd worked seven years up there almost
         at Elk River, so I had plenty— lots of recommendations. And done
         avarything that anybody could do in the woods, that anybody else
         ever did. I had done it. No, I had no trouble getting in. My only
         trouble was that I should have been a citizen, then I could have made
         something out of it.
         
         LS:  Didn't you have some trouble getting those letters, if I remember,
         'cause you were up there and they sent the letter to the wrong place.
         
         AAA: What was that?
         
         LS: Didn't they send the letter of recommendation to the wrong place?
         
         SS:  No, he just had to get 'em fast. Wasn't that it? You had to get
         'em (the letters) fast? They had to come quickly?
         
         AAA:  Yah, that was— oh yah, they sent 'em down to that office in St.
         Maries. 'Cause, you know, that was in the St. Joe Forest. And I
         didn't go there, I never thought of— I didn't think of that. You
         know, that was in the St. Joe Forest, and I didn't go there, I never
         thought about that. I didn't think of that, so I went over to
         Coeur d'Alene to the supervisor's office in Coeur d'Alene Forest and
         he didn't have anything, he didn't have nothin'. I couldn't figure
         it out, so I said, "Well, by golly, that must have been," I said,"I
         had wor," I said, "Ihad the letters and sent them two letters, one
         from Mr. Laird and one from Mr. Bloom, One come from Potlatch and the
         other one come from Elk River." Try to get call St. Joe Forest call
         Vcvj got a phone, I said, "Call the office there at St. Maries, see
         maybe they got it." He called, and they said, "Yes, there's two of
         'em laying here. Been here for a day or two." Well, they said, "You
         gotta go and get 'em." And, I said, "No, I'm not gonna get 'em."
         "I made up my mind I'm gonna enlist tomorrow morning", and I said,
         "my mind is made up, so, no, I'm not going to St. Maries, I'm going
         into Spokane and enlist." Well, they said, "You can't enlist here."
         well, I said, 'I certainly can elist, "I go in the army or artillary
         or anything. Any damn thing," but I said, "I made up my mind I'm
         gonna enlist someway." So, I said; "If you want me to wait for you
         you call that supervisor." And tell 'em to open them letters and
         read them to you, read them, over the phone. If you're satisfied,
         OK, then I 11 stick around with you a little bit, and they don't have
         enough there, then it's all off. But I'm gonna enlist anyway, to
         morrow.' And, by God, you know, he did that and;' "Hell, yes," he
         said, "You bet." He said, "I got three more setting there-yeu know 'em
         they haven't got their's , yet," he said, "would you recommend them?"
         And he asked me their names, and I said, "Sure, you bet your life,
         I know them for more than five years. They're good men, you betcha."
         He said, "I'll give you their ticket for the recruiting office."
         So, I got them with me too, into Spokane. No, they're all right.
         
         LS:  Where did you go then after? Where did they send you after you en
         listed?
         
         AAA:  Washington, D. C. We went to Washington, D. C. for a month, almost
         a month, after I left Spokane. Done a little training there. Did
         squads east and west a little bit. So we could know the right foot
         from the left. Just about all. Byqt we were on the boat, you know,
         I was sworn in there the sixth of August and the ninth day of Sept
         ember I was on the boat, going to France, so we didn't have much
         What little we did have there, was 120 degrees and no shade.
         and ahundred and twenty. That pretty hot. That's the hottest place I've been
         into.Over there at Tucson there the other night The first gamewhen
         they started the game there at eight thirty, it was 103. They
         said when they come into the ball diamond it was 106. When they
         started the game it was still 103, at eight in the evening.
         That pretty hot, aint it? We had 85 and said it was warm, (chuckles)
         
         SS:  Your unit was all foresters? Forestry people?
         
         AAA:  Yeah. (end side 1)
         
         Later, after we got across, you know,
         they increased it with a hundred more-two hundred and fifty to the company. But when
         we first went across,
         you know, all of the was college students, not me. (chuckles) I just
         went through rade school, and you know, it was kinda embarrassing a lot
         of times. Put me in charge of that bunch, get some work out of 'em.
         It was embarrassing, I tell you, sometime 11+ liked to be some
         place, any place, only not where I was. But, I made it all right.
         L3: You probably knew a lot more about the woods—
         Well, I did, I knew all about the woods. But, you know, you take—
         they were all college and all in their twenties- men. They had the book
         education and I had the practical experience. I knew what I was doing,
         and they had no idea what the hell it was all about. That's the only
         thing that helped me. u-KX lowevry hotyto do it, and could do
         it myself, and tried to teach them how to go about it, so they didn't
         get hurt. We never had anybody hurt there in France with that outfit,
         outfit I was with, we were all right. 
         
         And any darn thing they asked
         me to do, I could do it. I could go ahead and do it. No matter what
         it was. Road building or no matter what they was in anything that had
         anything to do with Iggging, or roads or anything, I could do it. Go
         ahead and do it without any help from anybody. 'Course, I couldn't get
         any help from them officers we had, you know, they were most of them
         from colleges ana forestry schools. Deans, first captain I had, you
         know he was a dean of the forestry office at the University of Missoula.
         Montana. He was tue dean of forestry there. The first captain we had.
         The other with D Company, he come from, oh he'd been up in
         Canada and come on aown. his name was Lebeaund. Dan Le Beaund. He
         was pretty good, pretty good man, but, you know, they knew the book, but
         they didn't know anything about logging, or anything. So they left me
         alone, too, they never bothered with me. I could go ahead.whatever I
         did was all right. Sometime I asked 'em, some time I didn't. Most of
         the time I didn't. Just go ahead. Use my own judgment. We had mules
         and wagons to haul logs mi and that was pretty slow. The mills- the
         mill crew, they were prstty damn ood, a good crew. One of the sawyers
         used to saw up.at Harrison. I don't know, I can't tell you the name
         of the company where he worked, but, at that time there were five big
         sawmills up at Harrison, on the Coeur d'Alene River there, on the lake.
         They had rails and boats there. His name was Dill. And the other
         was ? I don't remember where he come from, I think he come from
         the South, somewhere. Sabers, you know, tiiey had circle saws, not band
         saws, we had circle, two circle, one on top of the other. If they
         needed them. The timber wasn't very big, you know, I think they were
         five foot saws. Five foot circle saw, that's a big one.
         
         LS:  Were there any camps at all set up? Where they sent you to?
         
         AAA:  Oh, no, no, no. There in France?
         
         LS: Yeah.
         
         AAA:  No, no, we built that. Oh, no, we had little pup tents we slept in
         first. Just under canvas. Each one of us. Oh, not all of us. We
         had a tent, we go three-four into each one, or half a dozen, I guess.
         was a bunch of Canadians in there ahead of us, where we oome to, and
         they gave us all numbers. So we got numbers. It didn't take long to
         build a camp, you know. There was timber there pretty much like our
         white fir. Fast growiugbtuff. You know, and they built them. Wc
         only had half inch lumber, cut half inch, for the walls. Had two
         by fours for the studdings. And two weeks after they put them out,
         you know, it looked like a picket fence. That lumber shrunk, so damn
         much, yon know, made tae cracks, damn near had to go put double that
         in, put something over them cracks. Tar paper. And that lumber was funay,
         you know, you could cat a piece out of the heart of the log, and throw
         'em in the water tank, out Lucre, and they sunk like a rock. When it
         was green, it dried out float —and you cut it
         out of the middle of a logand throw it out there in the water pond and
         down she went just like a rock. (chuckles) It was that heavy.
         
         LS:  how did yon decide where to put tiiat camp, then?
         
         AAA:  where there was water. We had to have water, you see. We had to look
         around, find a place where there was water. Water is the main thing,
         you see. We couiu always get wood, we tried 
         Then close to where the timber was, close to where the timber was. 'cause
         they'd bought the timber before, you know the government, long before we
         left the states, they'd acquired the timber. And the places to go for
         each company. We were scattered all — before they were through, we had
         twenty, we started in with six, and before they were through, there were
         thirty camps. We got to be there, they started with twenty after
         that. We were in the tents. And they started the 20th Engineers, and
         they come over, then they put us in with them instead of being D Company
         the last yearTin '18, we were the 36th Company. 36th Company. We were
         company when we went across the water and we come back the 36th Company.
         20th Engineers. They cut out the tenth, see. And we had two hundred
         and fifty men to each company. There were a lot of people. Oh, tuey
         needed the lumber awfully bad, you know. They needed lumber more than
         they needed soldiers or ammunition, either. Lumber was what they were
         after. 'Cau they had to build, everything had to be built. The Ger
         mans had blowed out everything there was, so everything had to be started
         from the beginning, built docks, built railroads. They built a railroad
         from Bordeaux clean up there to the Alsace-Lorraine, clean across France.
         The Americans did. Put up new depots and big yards s Yes, you bet,
         that was something. But it takes for barracks, to build. I was near
         one of their big camps there on the const when they would come home. I
         just went tar enough, i didn't— I was left on the dock. Take care of
         the wagons there for the company. So I never got to the barracks. But
         I looked in there, they hau a hundred and twenty five thousand people
         tnere, soldiers. That take a lot of room. Ana them were built pract
         ically over night, you Know.
         
         SS: Do you remember what town that was? On the coast?
         
         AAA:  See, we landed it's on the English Channel.
         
         SS:  What we're more interestea in is the town where you were near in the
         camp. Where the camp was.
         
         LS:  Where the lumber camp was where you working.
         
         AAA:  We were in close to little where we were camped the last
         one. An the mill was at Piorteau, fifty kilometers from there,
         from the mill up to my woods camp, where I was. Mill was at Morteau
         on the main line, you see. And I was up fifty kilometers up on a branch
         line. Narrow gauge, thir+y nine— I think it was nine inch gauge,
         narrow gauge. And we loaded the logs on the railroad cars and send 'em
         DOWN at La Roche. When Armistice was signed, you know, the captain
         was with me, we were out looking over some timber, they blew the whis
         tles and bells were ringing, all the church bells were ringing that morn
         ing and it was the 11th day of November. He said, "What the heck is going
         on?" And I said, "I'll betcha the war is over." And he said, "How'll we
         find out?" And I said, "We've got to go back into town. They got a
         communique on the police station, there. Blackboard but there
         so, we'll find out." So, we went in, and boy, when he saw that, he
         said, "I gotta go." And he left me. He had the car, you see, and the
         driver and I was on foot, (chuckles) He said, "I got to go down to
         the company."A I had just as many men as he did. I was in this town,
         just outside of it. So, I went over and I hired a saddle horse when
         I got to camp, and I took that and I went out, and I met them, they were
         coming in— there were four horse mule teams, four horse teams come in
         and saw logs. Iasked them drive to one side, Head for camp." And, I said, "You'll
         have til tomorrow morning.
         ovp ;tomorrow morning, better be in camp, but tonight you take off."
         And I went and got the whole crew in and I told 'em the same thing.
         "All right, you're free til six o'clock tomorrow morning," but, I said,
         "When the bell rings for breakfast tomorrow morning be here, or I want
         to know the reason why." By God, they were all there, too. And they had
         one hell of a time there that night. There was two Swedes, the Larson
         brothers, they didn't drink any, they were from Montana, and I gave them
         the wheelbarrow and a couple of more, I think I had six on them three
         wheelbarrows. 
         
         And, I said, "Take them with you, and go downtown, see
         if anybody is laid out. Take 'em home. Take 'em home." They did, they
         got a few, they must have made five or six trips. A few of 'em laid
         out. And I got mixed up with the mayor of the town, but you know, he
         was— you know the mayor of a townnhe's quite a man. Boy, he had that
         stovepipe hat on and a long straight-tailed coat, you know, and vest,
         and a nice, white, big collar around the neck, and oh, boyI And he
         was pretty good, he was pretty good. We were drinking champagne, _"
         that night. And when I left in the morning at five o'clock he was unc|er
         the table. He was laying out— he was laid out. So, our captain come
         up a few days after that. So, I asked him if he want to meet the mayor,
         I said, "I'll introduce you to the mayor of the town." And, boy, how that
         mayor praised us. He said he never saw such a fine bunch of men in his
         life, to the captain. Boy, he praised us. And how we were behaving,
         and he was sleeping underneath the table, (chuckles) I told the captain,
         I said, "When I left him, he's a pretty good talker',' I said. "That
         don't mean much." I said, "When I left he was laying there sleeping
         under the table. And we were drinking champagne, i he paid for it."
         And the champagne's pretty good first time when he come in, you
         know, we could get a bottle of champagne for a dollar. We hadn't been
         there two days, twenty five francs then, five dollars. Five dollars a
         bottle. But the first night we were in there we got 'em for five francs.
         One dollar.
         
         LS:  Did the men at the camp do a lot of drinking, when they were there?
         
         AAA:  Oh, well, you know, they couldn't do a hell of a lot on thirty dollars
         a month. Oh, they done their part whenever they could. You bet. They
         had a good time. I think we all did. All of us. I had a good time.
         I didn't mind it a bit. Lot of work. And I got a hell of a lot of
         work out of them/(students. They worked. But I was right with 'em, I
         worked right along with 'em. I was no better'n they was. We were all
         there for the same cause. We had a spy camp there one time, that's
         the first  "Hu we were on. Ihad a 4«wt cr cabin of my own,
         where I slept all alone. So, one Sunday, I was there and there come a
         soldier up, he was trailing— he had a rifle on his shoulder and an
         other rookie walking with him. This fellow was sent up there for pun
         ishment. He was restricted to the camp for three weeks, compliment
         from the captain, you know. So, I returned the favor, and I said,
         "OK, you can go back." And Ilooked this fellow, he was overjrrom
         Metalline Falls, north of Spokane there, his name was Wood. And, I
         aaid, "You son-of-a-gun," I said, "you think that I'M gonna sit home
         here because you come up here?" And, I said, "No." And he said,
         "What you going to do?" And, I said, "You're gonna go_with me." I
         said, "You and me we go out together."A And I said, "There's a cafe
         out there'" A little place just out of town, "We go out there and have
         a feed, and we get a bottle of beer, maybe a glass of wine." But, I
         said, "Don't you leave me. You stay right with me." I said, "That's
         all the punishment there Is." So we were pretty good chums after that,
         (chuckles) After the war he come up and worked with me , for me for a
         year or more. After I got back there, the first, in '19, and 1920, I
         think I must a had two dozen or more of them soldiers come and work
         with me,, on the mill.
         
         SS:  Did the officers mind the fact that the men would go out and around on
         the town? The captains?
         
         AAA:  No I don't think so. No. No, I wouldn't think so They did it themself.
         Had to. We were all in the same boat. If you stopped to think
         about it. They were no different. One had a drink and the other
         The best chum that I ever met there was a nigger. Well, when we were
         coming home, we were laid there on the dock there for a month and I took
         a hike out of town, out of the dock, got in a cafe out there. He was a
         first lieutenant. We had a drink, and after that he bought all the
         drinks. I never did see him any more. We left about, I think it was
         about two o'clock that night. I had to go back home, where I was and
         1 think he had to go to barracks. 
         No they were all right. One time there were— I stayed over on- I
         met a chum of mine. I'd been up for a commission then— for an eye
         examination then, and I didn't get it. Coming back and I stopped at a
         town and I met a fellow there, we enlisted together over
         here, and I hadn't seen him. He was in E Company, and I was in D, and
         he was in the hospital there, but he was downtown. So I went with him
         to the hospital there. We had a feed there that evening and he got a
         pass, a overnight pass. I had one more day on mine left, and he o+*
         an overnght pass and we forgot all about It and we stayed two nftj.hts.
         So he had an explanation to do when he got back to the hospital what
         happened. And I had to do a little something when I got home to my
         camp. So, just when I got there, the first sergeant come and he said,
         "The captain want see you." And there was a first lieutenant took my
         place, you know up in the spy camp, and his name was Hodgeman, and
         I'd been gone eight days, and see Ihad seven days, and Iwas gone eight.
         So, he says, "Arney, what happened?" He said, "You're late." Well,
         I told him, I said, "Nothing happened, really," I said,"you know, I
         french missed the train." I said, "My is no good, I can't talk
         very much." Yes, yes . "So, I got on the wrong train," and I said,
         "I had quite a time to get back again." Yes, yes. I said, "I'm here,
         and sober, I'm all right."A" Hes, all right, all right", he said. "You
         better get to the captain as soon as you can-sald
         "He don't like it." 
         
         And that was all that was said about it. But I
         took, it was only a day over. He come home under guard. I know that.
         I know that. One time that he was out, you know, and he couldn't find
         the place, he was lost altogether. I don't think he could talk any french.
         And he couldn't find any train, and he didn't know anything, so they
         picked him up, you know, and brought him back home. And he come home
         under guard, too. Two soldiers brought him home. And I knew that, so
         I thought I'd work on that train business, just a little bit.(laughter)
         It worked. Yeah, in the army you never ask for an excuse. Never tried
         to excuse yourself, just tell 'em-sure, sure, thing/;, Igot pretty well
         liquored up one time there with the Canadians, and there was a pay master
         come around, and I got home. In the morning, you know, the first thing
         in the morning,you had to come to the captain- what's the use. OK. I
         had my fatigue clothes on, you know, not the uniform, I had my, just
         tne old overalls and the jacket on. But washed up probably and went
         over and he said, "Sergeant," he said, "I expected the sergeant to set
         a better example for the men." "Well," I said, "captain", I said, "You
         referring to me, Now?" Yes, yes . "Well," I said, "I tell you, captain,"
         "I drank more champagne than any four of your soldiers put together,
         last yesterday", I said," I just drank every damn thing that come my
         way." But, I said, "I made it home, all right, under my own power."
         Yes, yes, oh, he said, "Go on." And every time I met him he says, "Go
         on, go on." And every time I saw him after that, you know, he said,
         Oct "Go on, you S.O.B.". No, never any excuse, make it worse than it was.
         I learnt that much in the array. Trying to excuse, you know, that never
         workea, cause they'd fiud_out anyway. So,Ahe said about drinking, you
         know. But I made it home. Yes, yes. But I put him to bed, drunk.
         That was later, though. we were out scouting, looking 
         the country, you know. No place to go. And we were at the hotel there,
         you know, we e+ in the dining room, and -supper—when they fed,
         you know, Frencluaen never drinks water,neVer drink water. They put a
         bottle of wine or a pitcher of wine on the table, first thing. And
         then you order, and get your meal, and that pitcher never get empty
         until you leave. That's full til you leave, they'll fill it every time.
         
         So I kept a fillin' his glass fill his glass, and he said, "We
         didn't order that wine." And, I said, "No, hell, no I said','that goes
         with the meal, that part of the meal." I said, "Whether you drink it,
         or you don't drink it", I said, "you pay for it just the same." But
         I guess that is the custom. So, I guess he liked it, and I kept a fillin'
         it. A And the waitress there, you know, just as soon as that got down a
         little bit she was right there and fill it up to the top again. And
         when he started to walk from the table, by God, his legs wouldn't carry
         him. So I got the helper there and we got him up to the room. After
         tnat, you know,Apretty good— no trouble with the captain after that.
         There was only him and me, that's all there was. When I done the same
         damn thing there in the camp, on the river  three sergeantswe
         went over to the cafe after retreat. We were laying down in the camp,
         and tne man there at the cafe said he just got in a load of wine from
         Bordeaux, and he said, "That's good wine". So we bought a bottle a
         piece, and you get three glasses out of a bottle, three ordinary water
         glasses out of a bottle. So they opened one, we each one had that glass
         and drank that, and each one bought a bottle. We were fine. Went home
         and we all slept in the same barrack, you see, they— all the sergeants
         were together. And along about midnight, or so, I heard something, woke
         up and I looked and there was the mess sergeant, he was one of 'em, his
         name was Kavin, and he crawled on the floor and out through the door
         he went, but he was on the hands and knees, I thought that was funny
         that he walk, but I thought he had to get out anyway. A little
         bit, you know, I heard it again, and there was the other one,his name
         was,- he was out there from Centralia, Hubbard; he got killed. The
         Wobble him out there in Centralia, after he come home. And
         he took off, and by God, now, I had to take off
         I had to go tc I want to heave. And my legs were no good. I
         took and you know, we set out there til reveille, six
         o'clock when they blew reveille. We never got back in again. And we
         heaved everything— and I haven't cared for wine since. That done me
         on wine. The head was clear, we were sober judges, when we come home.
         But it just took my stomach and boy, all three of us acted the same way.
         We just had to throw up everything that was in us, and we sat three from
         two o clock to six—four hours, I guess, we sat out there. That was, on
         I think that was sweet wine. If I remember. But, when they order wine,
         I say "No." "I don't want no wine, none." We forgot the Watergate. 
         
         SS:  Well, that's just as well.
         
         AAA:  See what they gonna do. I think they just talk too much. It seems like
         they just sittin' there atalkin' and doing nothing. Chewing the same
         thing over and over.
         
         AAA:  Or we find a creek that was deep enough to jump in.
         
         LS:  Where could you take a bath in June?
         
         AAA:  Barber shop. The barbers havebath tubs. No showers. The kids used
         to say, "What did you do for a bath?" Well, we didn't, didn't get any.
         "Oh, Iwouldn't a stayed there." I said, "You'd stayed, you bet you'd
         stayed. You had to eat." And, I said, "If you didn't stay any place
         you didn't eat, either. The way it was with me anyway. My folks was
         seven thousand miles behind me. So I couldn'g go home. I wasn't like
         you kids, you could go home to your dad and sit at the table and eat."
         Isaid,I had to eat, and Istayed." Sleep in astraw stack, out
         threshing. The creeks wasn't deep enough so you could take a swim in.
         But that's what Wobblies did, yo In 1918, that was a good thing.
         got But that's what Wohbll did, you know, they showers in the camp.
         
         LS:  Were those hot and cold showers? Or was it just cold showers?
         
         AAA:  Oh, no, oh, no. They had hot water. Oh, they had a little boiler.
         Oh, no, it was hot and cold, so you could regulate it. And an extra
         car, put it up in the washroom, tubs, you know, so they go in there
         and wash their own clothes, you know, and hot and cold water. Before
         that time, you know, you had to go to the creek. I tried it one time
         and tried to wash it, and when Iwas through my thumbs
         went through all of it, it was nothing but holes, it was like a sieve.
         Nothing left. And it wasn't clean either. Didn't have no wash board
         or anything, you know. There were no washing machine, those days.
         That was at Helmer, so I went down and found a washer woman, one Sunday
         and she did my washing for me.
         
         You ought to stop there and talk to Clay Gustin,A that is a good
         old tolotet » could tell you lots about Latah County. And about the
         Potlatch. I was around him from '26, I guess to, oh, in the 40's. I
         think, after that Ibelieve he worked on the highway or something, didn't
         he, or for the county? Didn't he work on the road out to Park? I think.
         
         SS:  I know he goes out, even now in the spring, and summer.
         
         AAA:  Oh, does he?
         
         SS:  You mean Carl Plank?
         
         AAA:  Carl Lancaster, too?
         
         SS:  When you came back, after the war was over, was in the
         camps besides the conditions?
         
         AAA:  Yeah. Eight hour day. Hourly day, then. It wasn't daylight to dark any
         more, or ten hours, it was eight.
         
         LS:  Was that the Wobbles doings, too?
         
         AAA:  Yes. During that big strike they got the eight hour day and then they
         got clean sheets and blankets for the beds.
         
         SS:  Did it make your crews happier, to have this stuff?
         
         AAA:  Oh, yes, Oh, you bet. Sure it did, but a lot of them took— it was in
         the moonshine-homebrew days, you know; they didn't show their apprecia
         tion too much, that's for sure. Get with their muddy cork (caulk) shoes
         get up and crawl into bed with shoes and clothes and all, in the clean
         sheets. That don't show too much appreciation, but that's something you
         had to expect. You had to expect that. It wasn't all roses.
         
         SS:  How was the moonshine out there, in those days?
         
         AAA:  Oh, they paid ten dollars a gallon. They brought it to the camp, and
         some of it was strong and some of it was diluted, I guess.A They watch
         for the foreman to go and leave Saturday evening and they'd come in
         from Deary, somebody from Deary, probably. And Sunday when I come
         back to the camp, sittin' 'round the stump there singing to beat hell,
         (chuckles) On a jug of moonshine. But there was a cure for that, too.
         One morning- one Monday morning I took seven teamsters down the road,
         and after that you could see a jug of moonshine in every manger in the
         barn. There was twenty teams, nobody drunk, everybody on the job Mon
         day morning. I told 'em, if they had to have that,"down you go -that's
         all there is to it, no monkey business." The only thing you could do to
         scare 'em was to send 'em out. Send 'em down the road.
         
         LS:  You fired them 'cause they were drunk Monday morning?
         
         AAA:  Yeah, they couldn't go to work. They wasn't able to go to work. So that
         was all of it. We had an old foreman there for haul)or tne next
         one time,
         camp to me there, They called him 'Wood 'em up George' He had a saloon
         there in Spokane, later. He said, "Raise your wings, and flee for the
         valley" at the office, "Raise your wings, and flee for the valley."
         He was a witty old bastard, I guess. He'd come out and say, "Say, you
         got a partner?" "ya, sure, sure." "Take 'em ]and 'head for the office."
         wants to see you". Oh that Old Wood 'em up, he was quite acharacter,
         I think.
         
         I think Iheard he got his name because he wanted to always get that last
         log on top of the car. Uh-huh. We had Pflton, U.S. Ptlton, the Old Han Plton, Homer's
         Dad, he
         run Camp 8, there a long time, when I first got to know him. But later,
         you know, he come up with us there at Elk River, and Igive him agyppo
         job on the donkey. U.S.- Ithink, he blew the whistle, he was pretty
         old then. And Todd or Adrian, he run the donkey, run the machine. Homer
         was the hook tender and Lutus, I think he was hoisting. Had a little
         steam gilly out there and picked the logs up and put 'em on the car. And
         there was one more, Iforget his name. Ican't think of him. Well, any
         way, you know, they- Adrian was married, and I put up shacks for 'em so
         they all-we called it Pfltonville. They had another
         shack to eat in. The cookhouse with all the supply and right there near
         the creek so they dipped their water out of the creek-
         nice stream of water. Nice cool water. But anyway, they start at night
         you know, they were logging down the creek and so forth. And the old
         man he told 'em, "If you do half as much logging when you're on the job
         as you're doing in the camp", he said, "we would make lots of money."
         He says, "You're doing all the logging in the camp", and he said, "that
         f you see don tbring in any saw logs." They was all his boys,AI thought that was
         a pretty good He said, "If you do more of that logging in the
         dayttoe,", he said, "and+jTto bed when you get home, we make lots of
         money." They made so much a thousand, see. For each thousand feet on
         We the car. . called that Pltonville.
         It was just a spot where the family had their operation.
         Yeah. Close to where the donkey sat. She was doing the cooking for the
         family, see. Adrian's wife, she done the cooking, for all of 'em.
         There were five or six. The rest of the crew stayed in the camp.
         There were twenty one men to that crew.
         
         SS:  They put in a lot of timber there, didn't they? Lot of wood?
         
         AAA: Oh, you bet, you betcha. Some days they had good luck, and some days
         they didn't, nad a breakdown or something, you know. Lot of time, you
         ten or
         know they start on a new road, you know, they pick up six to twelve
         carloads. Then when they got farther out, longer out toward the mile haul,
         you know,4kCtfu'uh!4~get so many. That for sure, take too long to make the
         trips,when they were short time to the donkey they'd pick up a lot of
         'em.
         
         SS: During the prohibition day, then there were no saloons open? Right?
         So guys would have to drink
         
         AAA:  Yes, yes, that's right, there were no saloons. I had a family; I had a
         car, and I drove around if I had a Sunday off, or something,-that I
         didn't have to go some place or have to do work. I took the family
         and we drove out, you know. One Sunday we went down, I think we went
         down around Harvard, yeah, down to Deary and Harvard and we come back
         back up towards St. Maries River, went down to Potlatch, and come up
         to Harvard and come at Emida Fernwood, and I stopped in Clarkia
         another Sunday afternoon, and it was pretty warm so, they had an ice
         cream joint there, so I went in, and I asked the kids what they wanted
         and the Atfd .it out to them. I knew there was a bootleg joint.
         I didn't take the kids in, I brought it out to them, and they sat in the
         car, and now, I said, "The family's took care, now I need something."
         He said, "What do you want?" "Whiskey or beer?" noisy....
         Ana he didn't know me from Adam, I said, "I'll take one of each. I'll
         take a drink of whiskey and a beer for a chaser." "OK". And, one tim
         there in Elk River, you know, we'd been out with the snowplow, winter
         time, it was cold, oh, that must have been about one o'clock, xthat must
         have been in '14, or ia '13, somewhere in there, Well, they had this
         feller, they called him Hamburger Smith, he was an old cook, he built a
         little hotel, he musta had a few rooms up there, I never was in there,
         and he had a bakery and a restaurant underneath. And I knew he was sel
         ling moonshine and drinks, and I come in cold, I'd been on that open snowplow
         in the night, my knees were shaking. So I got itkhrough the door
         and here was the Goddarned deputy sat on top of the counter, I stood there
         with my mouth open like an old fool you know, kid » So the deputy there
         said, "What do you want?" "Well," I said,"you know what I'm after, I'm
         cold." "Ok." He stretched over this way underneath, and he said,
         "Here it is," yourself." But he didn't take
         no money, he didn't take no money. I took drinks out of it, but
         I never will forget It. But, you know, that deputy sheriff set
         that on the counter I thought I was in the wrong place. But, I told
         him I was cold, and I said, "You know what I need." He just leaned over
         the shelf
         and reached underneathand come up with that quart of whiskey.
         
         SS:  Did you drink with your men, at all?
         
         AAA:  In town, yeah. In town. Oh, sure, why not? You know, I thought I was
         just as good as they were, so why shouldn't I drink with 'em? And I
         figured they were just as good as me, and when we were in town we were
         all alike, we're not on the job. That's why, when you were talking about
         the Jackets brothers down there, Mike and Joe. If I come in there, I
         know everybody in there and, by God, I couldn't hardly ever get out of
         there. So the last few years there, I didn't go near it. Too many.
         I could just down there at the counter there and, by God, there
         sitting all round me. And I couldn't a counted 'em. I saw him
         two years ago, Joe, and he was telling me that the saloon business was
         no good. He said, its no good anymore. Said make no money, make no
         money. And I said, "You got a lot of money, don't need it." "Yeah,"
         but he said,"can't sell." And, I says, "Give it to the bartender,
         give it to 'em. Turn it over to 'em. They got no money. He said,
         "Nobody got any money, they can't pay." And, I said, "Turn it over to
         'em, and let 'em pay you so much a month. Let 'em pay you whatever he
         can." I said, "You don't need the money, can't take none of it with
         ya when you die." So, by God, three weeks, later, he did turn It over
         to the bartender. I haven't seen him since. Don't know where he is.
         Let's see, we were over at some funeral
         But, I heard he got married.
         up on the north side there, that's the last time I seen him.
         
         SS:  Liu you know Pat Malone, Axel?
         
         AAA: Oh, you betcha. Bat your life. Iknow Pat. vuite alad. He was deputy
         sheriff there in Uovill forjjl guess 'til he died. He must have been
         tnere for twenty years or more. He was telling me he used to be apolice Duluth.  
         
         you Know, there they, Irishmen, near all of them. You could see their head above all
         the
         people walking on the sidewalk when you looked up the street. You see
         them black helmets. And Pat was one of them. Pat Haloue.
         
         LS:  id he ever tell you how he came to come out here?
         
         No, no. No, I don't know, why he did. I guess he was like the rest of
         us. I aon't think— see he was— he didn't follow the lumberjack or
         anything like that. He was a law officer. I imagine he just come out.
         And stayed.
         
         SS:  Was Pat as big a drinker as they say?
         
         Icouldn't tell you that. Idon't know. Inever see him take a drink.
         No, I don't know that. He might have been. I imagine that he would
         take a drink. I know there were two Swedes come in there one time—
         with tne sheriff, you know
         he always you know, when they went and looked up a still.
         then in Moscow. But, anyway, the two Swedes
         Charley Young and Lundstrom, or something, the other one. They had a
         gallon of moonshine, you know, wherever they got it, and they were
         staying there at the Spokane hotel overnight. 'Course, Iguess they
         were talkin' loud. Pat had aroom thereat the same place, so he
         opened the door and come in, and he says, "Now, Igot ya," he says,
         "I got ya, with the evidence." Arid they says, "Yes, Pat, you have."
         "Sure, we'll give it to you." they said, "We'll give it to you, you
         got us. So they they laid 'em on the bunk, on the bed,
         ana they pulled the cork out and they- Pat always wore Malone pants
         and a mackinaw you know, heavy wool pants ana he had wool clothes on. And they
         emptied every drop of it on him and his clothes. They said, "Ok, Pat,
         now you got all the evidence, you got it, we haven't got nothin".
         Ana he stunk, he stunk like abrewery, (chuckles)
         
         hey Yean, they held him tuere andemptied all that was in the jug, and
         poured that on his clothes and in his clothes, and that wool and all
         soppea it up. But, usually he didn't bother anybody. Not too much.
         Iguess if they give him adrink, you know, he probably wouldn't said
         a word. But they took and held him and give him all of it. And that
         was quite astory, he couldn't very well pinch 'em.  Coutdn-h tor evidence
         and he couldn't tell 'em that he carried the evidence. And that they held
         him and he had all of it. (chuckles)
         
         Did most of the lumberjacks come down from Spokane? Did most of them
         come in from Spokane?
         
         Oh, I think so. or less, whenever- if they have anything left
         over to come in with. Enough for car fare.
         Were you working under Andrew Bloom?
         
         AAA: Yes, uh-huh. What was he like he was like to work with?
         
         want shis name now owns it? lie bought out the Red
         Collar. They had tug boats. They over from St. Marias
         Sown to Coeur d'Alleennee. his name? Imet him .
         times. He was an Irishman. And I think Mr m think Mr. Bloom and Deary must a
         come, Ithink they come out here together from togetfter from the East. They worked
         for the Weyerhaeuser in Minnesota.
         
         But they come out here cruising, and Bill Helmer. They all come out
         the same time. 1900. out (noisy) Yeah, he was an old cruiser. He used to cruise in
         the woods. Cruised
         the timber. (tape shut off)
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13353</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Anderson_Axel2</previous>
      <next>Anderson_Axel4</next>
      <disp_name>Anderson_Axel3</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
