<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/5/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ernest Anderson, 1974-06-05, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:32:39</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Anderson, Ernest</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1902</birthyear>
      <residence>Burnt Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents emigrated from Sweden and settled in the late nineties. Helen Anderson's
         husband
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#butchering"&gt;butchering&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#knitting"&gt;knitting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumber"&gt;lumber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Burnt Ridge"&gt;Burnt Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13356</file_name>
      <mp3>13283.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13283.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Parents came to America in 1888 to Ashtabula, OH; returned to Sweden to marry in 1892;
               return to Duluth 1895
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Parents came to America about 1888 to Ashtabula, Ohio, for two years. They returned
               to Sweden to marry in 1892, returning in 1895 to Duluth, where life was hard. Family
               moves to Blaine, near wife's sister, and then to Nora to work at the mill; mother
               agrees to cook at mill.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Moving to Troy in 1905; mother died in 1911; had to learn English in school; unhappy
               with war being declared
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sister's finger caught in a trap. While moving to Troy in 1905, a neighbor came out
               with lemonade for the family. Mother's death in 1911. A housekeeper. Had to learn
               English in school. Unhappy with war being declared. Decided to become a horseman and
               farmer from being on uncle's farm as a boy. Father starts farming on Burnt Ridge because
               of health in 1919. Burnt Ridge school center of social life.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Starvation and depression in Sweden made people come to America; Uncle Charlie got
               one meal a day for delivering groceries and eventually made a partner in the grocery
               business
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Starvation and depression in Sweden made people come to America. Uncle Charlie got
               one meal a day for delivering groceries in Duluth. Eventually he was made a partner
               in the grocery business, just because he had labored for free and was trustworthy.
               He was impressed by Ernie's knowledge of butchering.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Father splices loading rope which broke, shutting down waterfront work in Duluth;
               father had one month of school, but worked many skilled jobs
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father splices loading rope which broke, shutting down waterfront work in Duluth.
               Father had one month of school, but worked at many skilled jobs, and even knit stockings
               for his children.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2100</time>
            <title>Many Swedes stopped in Ashtabula; people didn't believe they had freedom of worship,
               with one state church; present government support in Sweden
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Many Swedes stopped in Ashtabula. People didn't believe they had freedom of worship,
               with one state church. Present government support in Sweden.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Hot day in Nora; father yells at him playing in log pilel man killed by log geing
               rolled into Burnt Ridge canyon
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Hot day in Nora. Father yells at him playing on log pile. A man killed by a log being
               rolled into Burnt Ridge canyon.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Horse teams hauling lumber to Troy Lumber Company in winter</title>
            <synopsis>Fascinated by horse teams hauling lumber to Troy Lumber Company in town in winter.
               Kids hitched onto the rear with their bobsleds and sledded back down the hills. Horses
               riding on six feet of snow. Teams made up of one horse and one mule. Building the
               kind of barn he wanted. He disliked cows because they jumped fences.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Drunk men stumble up the hill behind a horse; playing ball and skating on the creek</title>
            <synopsis>Seven drunk men stumble up the hill behind a horse. Boys pick fights with him and
               his brother in Troy, and he makes a bullwhip. Playing ball and skating on the creek.
               Year round fishing, with springs feeding the creeks in the hills.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Sawmills sold lumber to Genesee area; logging big timber in canyons within the last
               twenty years; origin of Burnt Ridge's name
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sawmills sold lumber to Genesee area, and hand hewn ties for railroads. Logging big
               timber in canyons within the last twenty years. Burnt Ridge named because it was burnt
               over, separated from American Ridge because people got lost trying to locate the area.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Farming on Burnt Ridge ridge was good until depression</title>
            <synopsis>Farming on Burnt Ridge. First years good, until Depression.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>Falling into a hog pen as a boy in his Sunday best</title>
            <synopsis>Falling into a hog pen as a boy in his Sunday best.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>Joe Wells appears at farm on the ridge, where does the chores for shelter and meals</title>
            <synopsis>Joe Wells appears at a farm on the ridge where the wife is alone, and gets shelter
               and meals as he does the chores. Mr. Settle is given trouble when he comes to Moscow,
               and tells them they are black inside, while he is black outside. Wells family said
               to be best in Deary community.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>Father stacks grain for the first time on his farm; quality of construction and craftsmanship</title>
            <synopsis>Father stacks grain for the first time on his farm. Quality of construction and craftsmanship
               in the early days.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Starting a farm; being good to others</title>
            <synopsis>Starting to farm. Being good to others.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Hard times in Sweden and Duluth. Play and fights as a boy. Getting started as a
         farmer. Canyon logging; horse team hauling. Joe Wells. Father's craftsmanship. 6-5-74
         1.5
         hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>No transcript available.</transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13356</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Anderson_Axel5</previous>
      <next>Anderson_Ernest2</next>
      <disp_name>Anderson_Ernest1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
