<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Winney Trout Baker, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>0:46:25</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Baker, Winney Tout</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm Wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1886</birthyear>
      <residence>Texas Ridge</residence>
      <origin>Moved from Illinois with family as a child</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farmers"&gt;farmers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#students"&gt;students&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#ranches"&gt;ranches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crops"&gt;crops&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#harvesting"&gt;harvesting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#one-room schools"&gt;one-room schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pregnancy"&gt;pregnancy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
                  
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
             
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Texas Ridge"&gt;Texas Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Illinois"&gt;Illinois&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13368</file_name>
      <mp3>13369.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13369.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Introduction</title>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Personal background, moved to Idaho</title>
            <synopsis>Born in Illinois near Redmond, 1886. Came by train to Moscow, uncle followed after with big wagon and horses.</synopsis></point>
         <point>
            <time>120</time>
            <title>House in Idaho, hunting game</title>
            <synopsis>House was built of lumber, decent sized house. Lots of game there; there were deer and birds and her brother went out and shot deer and birds any time they wanted. </synopsis></point>
         <point>
            <time>180</time>
            <title>Picking fruit; hunting game; relationship with Native Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Had lots of fruit. Picked berries with mother and she canned them. Brother would get deer, hang and skin it. Native Americans found out and came on horses and waited for brother; brother would sell the deer skin. Mother was afraid of the Native Americans, didn’t like them. Mother hid her under the bed when they visited. There was never any trouble though.  
            </synopsis></point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>Home was located not far from present day Deary</title>
            <synopsis>Home was located not far from present day Deary.  
            </synopsis></point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Remembering school</title>
            <synopsis>Remembering school. Not very big, two rows with benches.  
            </synopsis></point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Friends Leo and Josie</title><synopsis>Friends Leo and Josie.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>School book description</title>
            <synopsis>School book description. With capital letters on the first line and then the small letters underneath. Copied lines. Read from them.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Description of her school teacher</title>
            <synopsis>Description of her school teacher. She taught many years.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Built a new schoolhouse, stories of walking to school, typical school day</title>
            <synopsis>Built a new schoolhouse on the main road, where she went. Most of the children had to walk. Sister was always with her in the mornings. School at 9 am. Turkeys were there on the way to school, children ran away from them.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Sister taught at school for one term</title>
            <synopsis>Sister taught at school for one term.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Lots of rain; stories of wading, finding a snake</title>
            <synopsis>It had rained a lot. Some places a yard or two. She liked to always go barefooted in the summer. Everyday she went out and waded into the water. Sister went out one day with her and caught a snake. She got out of the water very quickly.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Owned a pony; stories of riding with friend</title>
            <synopsis>When she was older she got a pony. It was a very good riding horse. She had a good friend Jessie Shawl, they would ride everywhere. They would jump into trees from horses. Never fell off.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>840</time>
            <title>Describing pony saddle</title>
            <synopsis>Describing saddle.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Summertime stories</title>
            <synopsis>Father would work in summer. She ran around a lot during the summer. Didn’t know anything about.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Mother made clothes; price of fabric; father enjoyed singing</title>
            <synopsis>Mother made clothes. Remembered Calico was five cents a yard. Father was a good singer, he sang base. Would get up in winter and go singing for the sick.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Nephew Ralph would walk near the bridge, leave shoes</title>
            <synopsis>Nephew Ralph, sister’s son, would walk and go over the bridge. Sometimes take off shoes and go barefooted and leave their shoes under the bridge until evening. Would walk back at night to get her shoes.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Description of school; her education; typical school days</title>
            <synopsis>Description of school, it was bigger. She doesn’t remember how far she went through school, maybe to the eighth grade. Went to school for three months at a time. People would gather in the schoolhouses for literature. They had programs where they would sing or have entertainment at the school.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1260</time>
            <title>Big porch at home; thunderstorms would roll in</title>
            <synopsis>At their house they had a big porch, there was a thunderstorm. Rain ran down the roof and onto the porch. She had a tin cup and went on the porch, was knocked out of her hand by the rain.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Water supply from well; carrying water</title>
            <synopsis>Where they got their water. Dug in the yard for a well. Carried water to washboard into tub.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Garden at home; raised cabbage</title>
            <synopsis>Describing the garden. Always had a big garden. Sister and mother took care of it. Raised cabbage. Would collect cabbage, put two in a bag and let them hang over brother’s shoulders.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Took wagon to get groceries every two or three weeks to big city</title>
            <synopsis>Take wagon with groceries. Every two or three weeks. Looked like a big city to her.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1620</time>
            <title>Native Americans liked her red hair; sometimes scared</title>
            <synopsis>Lots of Native Americans. They liked red hair, she had lots of long read hair as a girl. Scared her as a girl that they liked her hair. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Bought flour. Used elevator and tramway.</title>
            <synopsis>Bought flour. Used elevator and tramway. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>First car was a Model T</title>
            <synopsis>First car, Model T, second hand for her and her husband.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Husband</title>
            <synopsis>Husband.  
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>First thrashing on the ranch</title>
            <synopsis>Remembers first thrashing; horses drove it. Afterwards had an engine. Mother and sister cooked for them. Had a large ranch. Thrashers would be there for a week. Produced lots of grain. Lots of men.
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2100</time>
            <title>Picked strawberries in the summertime</title>
            <synopsis>Picked strawberries in the summertime. Take daughter and she would play, was no trouble. Usually they walked. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Christmas tree in the schoolhouse; Christmas holiday traditions</title>
            <synopsis>Had a Christmas tree in the schoolhouse. Hang the presents on the tree. Watched children pick there presents off the tree. Had her own tree at home. Put Christmas card paper and children would make chain for decorations. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Her aunt and husband came to visit</title>
            <synopsis>Had aunt, her father’s sister. She and her husband came to visit. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Family garden</title>
            <synopsis>Family garden.            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Second family home</title>
            <synopsis>Second place where they lived. 
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Moved from Illinois with family as a child. Rural childhood experiences.</description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>Transcript not available</transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13368</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Bacca</previous>
      <next>Benge1</next>
      <disp_name>Baker</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
