<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">4/27/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Dick Benge, 1976-04-27, Interview #4 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>3:38:50</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Benge, John (Dick) &amp; Ella May</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #4</intnum>
      <occupation>Lumberjack; Farm wife; sawmill worker; cook</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894;1901</birthyear>
      <residence>Hatter Creek, Princeton</residence>
      <origin>Dick: Moved from Nebraska with family in 1913; Ella: Moved from Winchester, Idaho
         area
         (1924)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#tractors"&gt;tractors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#working conditions"&gt;working conditions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gyppos"&gt;gyppos&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#foremen"&gt;foremen&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#blacksmiths"&gt;blacksmiths&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#alcohol"&gt;alcohol&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mills"&gt;mills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooking"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fraternities"&gt;fraternities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sororities"&gt;sororities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#plays"&gt;plays&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Hatter Creek"&gt;Hatter Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Princeton"&gt;Princeton&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13372</file_name>
      <mp3>13373.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13373.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Life in Nebraska, farming; family moved to Idaho due to illness</title>
            <synopsis>Father's consumption caused them to come to Idaho; he
               treated it with German medicine. Dick had to work, but got
               a wagon of his own. Early tractors were no good for farming.
               Decline of population in Dick's old Nebraska neighborhood;
               over dependence on machinery. With diversified farming,
               they had cash-in-hand the last year in Nebraska.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Differences in farming between Idaho and Nebraska; equipment, wages, cost of living</title>
            <synopsis>Shock of using a 12 inch plow because of stumps here.
               Need to ask questions in a new country to find how things are
               done. He got $1.50 a day instead of $1 in Nebraska, but
               prices were higher. Working in harvest: long days and fun. High
               wage demands by labor.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Preference of working in the woods; IWW strike caused improvement in conditions; gyppos</title>
            <synopsis>He preferred woods work to farming. IWW strike caused a
               remarkable improvement of conditions. The men hurt themselves
               by gyppoing; he stopped working after a carload, to keep the
               prices up.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Recovery from being hurt on the job at Soap Lake</title>
            <synopsis>Foreman saw to it he'd get a high price. After hurting his kidneys
               on the donkey, he went to Soap Lake to recuperate for a month.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Gyppos work schedule; foremen worked them hard; Shorty Tribble</title>
            <synopsis>Gyppos wanted to work during lunch, so they gave up hot
               lunches for lunch buckets. Foremen worked the men hard, as
               a rule. Foremen had pets. Tom Kelly taught Shorty Tribble
               to bake bread.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Workers who returned; Shorty Tribble</title>
            <synopsis>Men who quit and later came back because of the chuck. Shorty
               Tribble's ability as cook and meat cutter.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3360</time>
            <title>Breaking a horse</title>
            <synopsis>Breaking a horse whom they'd tried to whip break unsuccessfully
               before, (continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title></title>
            <synopsis>More history of Cap and Prince (team of horses). First logging cats were poor.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Stories of men who returned home in the evenings, what they missed out on</title>
            <synopsis>Staying at home, a man can't care for his team as well. With
               one team Dick could have corduroyed a road to Seattle and
               half-way back. Black, the clerk, was great at figuring; he
               didn't want to go to town to order new chain.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4200</time>
            <title>Bill the blacksmith; relationship with Dick</title>
            <synopsis>Bill's skill as a blacksmith. How he had Dick make a
               caulking compound for horseshoes. Bill's training. His
               particularity about the condition of tools. He made Dick a
               gift of a canthook. He wouldn't let a sloppy copper take the
               new tongs he had reserved for Dick. Replacing an incompetent
               top loader.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>Dangerous situations in the woods; Laird</title>
            <synopsis>Laird crowded a logger and learned a lesson. The bosses missed
               a dangerous situation.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Potlatch as company town; who lived in town, relationships</title>
            <synopsis>Potlatch was " a one man town," which won't work. Even
               now people can't cooperate there. Working men couldn't live on Nob Hill.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Potlatch had to unionize; workers brought property and lived in Princeton, commuted
               to work
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Potlatch had to unionize. People owned property in Princeton
               and worked at the mill. Princeton fair.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5640</time>
            <title>Princeton store owner Bill Wilson generous with credit during the Depression; not
               everyone had good credit
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Credit from the Princeton store during the Depression. Some
               couldn't get credit. Borrowing money to set up after marrying.
               Some depended on commodities.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6000</time>
            <title>Father followed the almanac for slaughtering and planting; mistreatment of Native
               Americans in area
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father slaughtered and planted by the signs. Importance of
               moon and tides. Indians lived by signs. Mistreatment of
               Indians, who defended their land as we would.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6780</time>
            <title>Working while raising a family of five kids; son's arrest </title>
            <synopsis>He raised children to mind at home. His son's arrest for a
               traffic violation; he fought it in court, because they'd taken
               down the signs. His son chose not to farm.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Cutting down timber on the creek</title>
            <synopsis>(May Benge and Peggy Schott, their daughter speaking) Staying at camp for free. Cutting
               down the timber on the creek.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7380</time>
            <title>Housework completed by May (gardening, water, selling produce)</title>
            <synopsis>May's daily work. Burning slash and stumps to clear land.
               Packing water. Raising a big garden. Selling produce to
               Guernsey's store at Onoway.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7620</time>
            <title>Family hiking to Princeton to sell goods; Life during the Depression</title>
            <synopsis>Hiking to Princeton to sell eggs, to Potlatch with cream during
               the Depression. Rewarding the kids with candy for helping.
               Dances during the depression. Drying mud off the tires
               inside. A family had the neighborhood for a party when she got
               coffee.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7920</time>
            <title>Christmas during the Depression; bartering food and wood</title>
            <synopsis>Making a Christmas feast and presents in the depression. Finding
               a way to sell wood in desperate straits in the depression.
               Trading chickens to peddlers for fruit. Canning hundreds of quarts. Duthie in Pullman
               would always trade for wood.
               Eating "government beef" (deer).
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8640</time>
            <title>Building the house a bit at a time</title>
            <synopsis>Building up the house from two merion shacks a bit at a time.
               Dick was unemployed, being a logger.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8820</time>
            <title>Hiking to Potlatch to visit family</title>
            <synopsis>A very rugged hike to Potlatch with her sister-in-law.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9000</time>
            <title>Neighborhood parties; drinking; dancing</title>
            <synopsis>She tells a young man that a man can handle a quart of liquor,
               and he gets drunk. Every Saturday night was a dance or party for
               the neighborhood. Her fear when Peggy stayed out all night
               dancing; another time her car broke down. She expected her
               children to work.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9960</time>
            <title>School experience with lice</title>
            <synopsis>Fighting greybacks at home. The itch at school. Head lice.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10200</time>
            <title>Women working at Potlatch; women's life in mill</title>
            <synopsis>Working at the Potlatch mill - she packed boards for resawing,
               and kept the work area clean. She got help when the wood was
               too much to handle. The women had their own room. How she
               began to cook at fraternities and sororities. The work at
               Fernwood became too difficult after she was sick. She did
               well at the Potlatch mill.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10800</time>
            <title>Built house by working at mill; Dick an excellent logger but not farmer</title>
            <synopsis>She built the house by working at the mill. Working for yourself
               versus working out; Dick wasn't a good farmer, but he was an
               excellent logger.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11400</time>
            <title>Clearing land with help from the kids</title>
            <synopsis>More about clearing land. The kids pitched in too.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11640</time>
            <title>Courtship between May and Dick</title>
            <synopsis>Where she lived. How she met Dick. What Dick wore on their
               dates.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11820</time>
            <title>Family and religion; family spread out across distances</title>
            <synopsis>She hoped that her children would find the Lord, and they have,
               closeness of the family. Johnny protected his younger sister.
               Difficulty for family to get together because of distance.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12360</time>
            <title>May working with schoolchildren, raising money</title>
            <synopsis>Her work putting on dances and plays with the school kids to
               raise money for Hatter Creek School and the school bus. The
               full-length play: Object Matrimony.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Peggy Schott (daughter) Depression experiences: hardships, selling produce,
         parties, canning, credit. Her work: sawmilling, clearing land, cooking. Woods work.
         Home
         improvements. School plays. 4-27-76 3.5 hr 75p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         The first part of this interview was with DickcBenge, the second with his wife, ELLA
         MAY ARDEN BENGE, and her daughter, PEGGY SHOTT. The interview took place
         at their home on Hatter Creek, near Princeton, Idaho, on April 27, 1976.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: -- how your parents raised you.
         
         DICK BENGE: Raised?
         
         SS: Yeah, how they raised you.
         
         DB: I was raised in Nebraska, on a farm.
         
         SS: You told me that, but I was wondering about how they did. I mean,
         how-- whether they were strict with you, or lenient, or made you toe
         the line, or what.
         
         DB: Oh ^hey were lenient, but, Ihad to work. Dad, he wasn't very healthy,
         he had— them days they called it consumption. Well, the old feller,
         you know, he seen an advertisement in the paper— lung Germine
         
         SS: What?
         
         DB: Lung Germine. Made in Germany. Medicine. He had to send to Germany
         to get it. So, he took that for six months. And the glass, everywhere
         he took it up to, in four weeks, it just crumbled that glass. So it
         must have been pretty powerful! Well, he got all right.
         
         SS: That did it for him?
         
         DB: Huh?
         
         SS: That cured him?
         
         DB: Well, it got him a lot better anyhow. So then, a doctor told him, he
         said— we was down and he was atalkin' to him, and he said, "I believe
         if I was you, I'd^get out of here." Said, "You can't stand it here
         long. Now, if you'll go to some mountain region, you might be good
         for a long time." Well, he did. We come out here. And that's how we
         come to come. Yeah. Oh, Dad, he was very lenient with me, 'course,
         he made me mind, yes. Had to work six days a week, but Saturday night
         and Sunday was mine. (Chuckles)
         
         DB: I had a horse to ride and got a little older, I had a buggy. Got a
         brand new buggy for me and a good drivin' horse. Well, what more could
         you ask? Nowdays, they get 'em an automobile.
         
         SS: What was the work that he was having you do when you were a kid?
         
         DB: Farmin'.
         
         SS: All farm work?
         
         DB: All farm work. Diversified farming. He raised— well, I'll give you
         the layout; he had ten milk cows. He had eleven brood mares. And
         he had fifteen sows for pigs; and he bred 'em all every year. Well,
         that was when the tractor first come out, and so, he had five good
         teams to sell. They run 'em one year and the next year they run 'em
         in the fence corner and the next year they all went back to hor
         ses and mules. Yeah, they wouldn't monkey with the damn things. They
         couldn't get 'em to start of a cold morning.
         
         SS: They run 'em in a fence corner? What do you mean?
         
         DB: They just quit 'em. Yeah.
         
         SS: Was this in Nebraska?
         
         DB: Uh-huh. Yeah, we was sixty-five miles south of Lincoln. We was right
         down, oh, we was only- what?- about twelve, thirteen miles from the
         Kansas line.
         
         SS: Did you have many neighbors there, like here?
         DH: Oh, that was thickly settled, you know. There was a house on every—
         well, half section, a hundred and sixty acres, anyhow. But I was back
         there last fall, a year ago this fall. Well, now, there's a mile
         through there that they was— well, I'll have to count up and see now-
         There was one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight houses at
         that time. Well, when I was back there^-, the house that we lived in
         when we left there— nothing there. A nice ten acre is gone. A nice
         mapie grove, it was gone. Farmin'I The house set up on a little
         raise, that is, well, here, I don't know what they would call it,
         just kind of a level place. So, I just walked up over the hill where
         the house used to be,ytjust over a little slope, and I don't know, I'd
         say, there sat two million and a half dollars worth of farm machinery.
         Corn planters, corn huskers, everything. Five tractors.A No wonder
         the country's into it, is it? No, no wonder they're going belly up!
         Automobiles and machinery's put 'em into it, too.A You put it this
         way: you know, when I was growin' up, we tried to get ahold of a
         piece of land or something when we'd get a job, but now the kids get
         a job, they stop on his road home, after he gets his job, buys him a
         car!
         
         SS: Were the people there, your neighbors there, were they at all differ
         ent? Was the neighborhood any different from the way it was over here?
         Yes, it was. They was more of a clan. Over there? Uh-huh. What was that ?
         Well, they all, you know, knowed one another, and, you know, neighbored
         afoot back and forth, Go Saturday nightr and see their neighbor,
         and stay til midnight or one o'clock, and have supper and play cards,
         and be sociable. Now, they don't do that, you know. They was all
         sociable there!
         
         SS: Were they that way over there than they were like, say, around here?
         Yeah. 'Course, now, this country here was a good deal that way when
         we come here; but not so much as it was back there. But, it's a slip-
         
         SS: I'm thinking back in them days, I wonder why they were closer back
         there? Maybe 'cause they'd been there longer?
         
         DB: Well, I'll put it this way— to my notion, there's a different class
         of people. You know, more sociable. Wanted to get out, have a lit
         tle fun, be sociable and not be out much. Yeah. Maybe I'm wrong, I
         don't know, but that's the way I always looked at it. Dad and I
         talked it over lots. About the difference in the people. Yeah.
         
         SS: There was mostly farmers there? Right?
         
         DB: All farmers. Nothing but farmin' there. And stock raising.
         
         SS: Maybe that had something to do with it, too.
         
         DB: Course, they all had a farm. Had a bunch of stock on it. Bunch of
         milk cows, a bunch of brood mares, a bunch of brood sows. Well, you
         know, that made their livin'. I know there, one time, a year before
         we left back there, yeah, — We had— milking the ten cows, churning
         the butter, feeding the buttermilk to the brood sows and little pigs,
         we were two hundred and seventy-four dollars ahead of the store that
         spring, when we started a farmin'. Well, two hundred and seventyfour
         dollars run us pretty much through the summer, at that time. Of
         course, we raised our eggs and butter and had our milk and meat. But,
         we went down to the store and everything we wanted, clothes and
         all, for the summer. So, you tell me somebody now that's ahead of
         the store.(Chuckles)
         
         SS: When you sold out, did you get out ahead? Did you get much to bring
         over here to start out with?
         
         DB: Oh, I don't know; we had ten, twelve thousand dollars when W got here.
         It cost us a hundred and fifty dollars for a car to ship out here on.
         We brung a team and wagon and a buggy and a whole lot of house furni
         ture and such as that with us. We didn't sell out there, you know.
         The way this old world turns over!
         
         SS: The way it does what?
         
         DB: Turns over! (Chuckles)
         
         SS: What did you think about leaving, at the time? Were you sorry to go?
         
         DB: No. No, I'll tell ya, I was glad to get away for Dad's sake. The
         doctor told him he'd have to go. And we knowed some folks lived here
         at Princeton, so he wrote out to 'em and found out, so we come. We
         come out.
         
         SS: Was it easy for him to start up farming here, again?
         
         DB: Well, you know, comical; We went to Potlatch and got a brand new plow,
         walkin' plow. Half regular, twelve inch, 'cause we only had the lit
         tle team. Dad started aplowin' on it with the twelve inch plow, and
         Dad come on around and I said, "By God, if that's all that'll turn
         over, we never will get done." We was used to them gangs and all
         that, you know, it took four, five, six feet at a shot. And that way
         you'd have to make that many rounds with this one. But, we didn't
         have much to plow.
         
         SS: Was that all you could use here? A twelve inch plow?
         No, we just had one team. We just fetched the one team with us. So,
         that's why we got the twelve inch plow. Well, they're nice in stumpy,
         too. They're light, theyVe woocUvx keftm^ they're nice to get around
         the stumps. Of course, we went around and talked to all these fellers
         that'd been raised around here and all, you know, AVsd .which'd
         be the most suitable. We didn't know. You got to learn, you go in
         to a new country, you gotta ask a few questions and learn a little.
         Who is right up to date. You know, I worked out some there after we
         got our work done: Dollar a day! Twenty-five dollars a month and
         board, or a dollar a day and board, or, I mean, yeah, a dollar a day
         and board. Geez, we come out here and they give me a dollar and a
         
         DB: half a day. I thought I'd make money. Come to find out, it took it
         all for clothes and tobacco, that extra fifty cents. Just that much
         higher here. I wasn't ahead.
         
         SS: Not ahead, at all. Just the same.
         
         DB: Just the same thing, she just leveled off.
         
         SS: Where did you do most of the working out that you did, when you did
         work out? Before you started in the woods? Was it mostly like for
         harvest and that?
         
         DB: Yeah, harvest. Well, I worked down there in the flat, this side of
         Princeton there for Bert Roe. I worked for him. He give me a dollar
         and a half a day. God, I thought I'd make 'er! Come to find out at
         the end of the month, I was just as far behind as I would have been in
         Nebraska at a dollar a day. I found out, you're gonna pay a lot more
         money here than you did back there. So then, out here we took in har
         vest, I did; two and a quarter a day, boy, that was money! Jesus
         Christ, uh, up 'fore daylight in the fall and summertime in the threshing
         season; stayed with her til dark«A That's the hours we got in,
         in the harvest rig. Boy! And we was with Baine  Mc Farland and
         they were pretty light on the men. A lot of 'em blow their whistle
         to go to work, and he'd blow his whistle for us to get up. I don't
         know, he was a good threshing machine man, and he got more threshing
         than the rest of 'em. That first year I was here, we put in sixtyfive
         days on that threshing machine. Boy, you'd get kind of tired of
         that. But, I was workin', good money. Well, that was good money
         then, you know. Jesus, the hours!
         
         SS: You must have been feeling like a dead dog at the end of the day.
         
         DB: No. You was outdoors all time, slept out of a night. You know, four
         or five hours sleeping out under the stars done you as much good as
         six or eight in the house. Yeah. Pretty good.
         
         SS: What about the crew? Working with all these other men there in the
         harvest? Was that kind of fun? Working together?
         
         DB: Oh, yeah. Well, there's one morning I'll never forget. There was two
         sleepin', John Burton and George Basler and George wouldn't get up.
         John'd try to get him upland he wouldn't get up. John come down by
         me one morning, he said, "I'm gonna set that Goddam bed afire, one
         of these mornings." Next morning he got up and he said, "George, get
         up." "Nope." Said, "George, get up." "Nope." He said, "Ive told
         you the last time; I'm gonna set this Goddam bed afire, and I'll bet
         you do get up!" The next morning he did set her afire! George» he
         was in it. It was half his bed and he just stuck his hands in his
         pockets and went down towards the cookhouse whistlin'. (Chuckles)
         George come out of it. It was his bed, half of it was his bed and
         half of it was Old John's bed. Yeah, they was a good outfit to work
         for they didn't work us like some of 'em.
         
         SS: That was the end of it? He just jumped out and the bed burned up?
         
         DB: No. He beat her out. Yeah, they had straw under the bed. He took a
         quilt or a blanket or something and got a handful of burning straw
         and rolled her out. (Laughter) Next morning, he got up. That God
         dam son of a bitch, he'll get up in the morning. He did.
         
         SS: You say some of these outfits really did work the men, eh?
         
         DB: Ohhhh! work 'em. Yeah. Some of 'em, you know, in the fall; blow
         that whistle for 'em to go to work just at daylight, and work 'er
         just as long as they could see.
         
         SS: Did they pay much more?
         
         DB: Two and a half a day for pitchin'. And boy, that was hard pitchin',
         too, 'cause we went on up the river. Most of us stacked grain and hat was hard pitchin'!
         We had a 36-60 separator to try to keep a
         goin', you know. That old girl'd eat a lot of grain, and eat it in
         a hurry!
         
         SS: Did you have a cookhouse with you, or did you eat at the farmer's
         place?
         
         DB: We had a cookhouse. No, that's one thing— oh, once in a while we
         couldn't get the cookhouse close to the machines, as a rule we had —
         never had to go over a hundred yards, anyhow. And that helps.
         
         SS: Yeah, I heard that women in the cookhouse worked plenty hard, too.
         
         DB: Oh, my God, did they work! Yeah. The last two years I was — Baine
         and Mc Farland.moved the cookhouse, me and another (coughing spell)
         boy- they worked. We had a lot of fun, but, you paid for it-AYou
         know, the laboring man right now- they got the fellers working in the
         woods, they wouldn't get out and work the way we worked for forty
         dollars a day. No,they wouldn't. Now, you know, theyAhave forty,
         fifty, sixty dollars a day now. Well, it's no wonder our lumber and
         everything's going up, is it? That's what's a doin1 it. Labor's a
         driving it up.
         
         SS: One thing I was gonna ask you about, along this line about working.
         Did you, yourself, have much ambition to be a farmer? Or did you pre
         fer to work in the woods?
         
         DB: Well, you know, I liked woods work the better. 'Course, it was a littie
         more dangerous. Had toAwatch^everything. But, when you was workin'
         in the woods, when you got your day in, you was done. And when
         I went to work, see, they was workin' ten hours, that was before 1917,
         before the IWWs struck. Well, they didn't strike for more money,
         all they struck for was better conditions. And at that time, you know,
         we was all packin' our own quilts. we called 'em. And,
         I was workin' in the camp, working in the kitchen, and I took two
         weeks off and I come home and I went back. And it was way late when
         I got into camp that night. Had to walk about seven or eight mile.
         Well, I pooped around down in Bovill it got dark before I left there,
         and I heard some little motor running, and I thought, "Well, holy God,
         somebody get hurt?" And they got the speeder up there ahaulin' 'em
         out, or what?" Well, I was going along up there and they had a copthe
         strike was on then— and they had a cop out there and he met me,
         and Jesus, before I got to camp, why, I looked and see the whole woods
         was lit up. Electric lights. And this little motor running. It
         was in the washroom. So, I asked the cop what was the matter, what
         was goin' on? "Oh, by God, Dick, you won't know the camp."
         He said, "She's all painted. Got steel bunks. They're furnishin'
         the blankets, and they're furnishing the mattress." Steel
         beds and everything! He said, "You're lost." So, he took me in
         the little shack that he had there, and he had a steel bed, sheets,
         blankets and everything.
         
         SS: It was the IWW that done that?
         
         DB: Yeah. Well, they had another good rig that I didn't like— they
         didn't like this gyppoing and contractin' —A they didn't like that.
         Well, it's all contracting. That's one way the company had a getting
         around 'em, see. I could see what wasRgoin' on.
         
         SS: How did the company take advantage of that?
         
         DB: Well, they went to contracting.
         
         SS: To get you to work harder?
         
         DB: Well, I don't know as you worked much harder, cause the most of them
         old foremens, they give you the whiplash, anykow. And, when they went
         to gyppoing, you see, well, then— always before the company hauled
         hot dinners out to us. And when they went to gyppoing, well, the
         working man , didn't have sense enough himself to take care
         of it. What he done— he worked the noonhour; gyppoin' you see.
         Making more money. Well, the boss and I we were pretty well acquaint
         ed; I was running the slide and taking off the corners, so the first
         day we was working out there, why, there was three of us, and we got
         three carloads out and loaded by one o'clock, so we quit. I was gowe
         in' down the track and « met the foreman and he said, "What's the mat
         ter, Johnny? You broke down?" And I said, "Nope." "What's the mat
         ter?" "Well," I said, "we got three carloads out and loaded. We got
         a car apiece. Isn't that enough? Well," I said, "we quit." And, I
         said, "As long as we can get a car apiece— whenever we get 'em load
         ed, we're going to camp." "Well," he said, "You'll hold the price up
         if you keep that up." And he was a brother to the woods superintend
         ent. So, he wasn't a bit afraid to tell the truth of- who it hurt.
         
         SS: In other words, cut the price on it.
         
         DB: That's right. The workin' man cut his own throat right in the woods.
         Yeah. Just by not havin' sense enough to — Well,AI got all the cor
         ners skidded out and loaded out and then he give me a nice, big team
         he had to skid with, and my brother-in-law went swampin' for me. two of us, and come
         along one time just before quittin txme, and
         there I was sittin' on a log a smokin'. He come right up behind me
         and he said, "Say, Johnny, you broke down?" And, I said, "Nope."
         He said, "What's the matter?". And I said, "Bob, we got enough logs
         today, the two of us, to make her pay," I said, "we made about forty
         dollars apiece, today. That's enough, for one team." He said, "It
         sure is." And, I said, "I'm not agoin' above that. I'd rather go
         below it. Hold the price up." "Well," he said, — his brother was
         woods superintendent— "brother Tom's gonna cut the price on you fel
         lers anyhow." "Yeah, let him cut it." So, it wasn't but a few days
         til Tom come up, and he come out where I was and he said, "What you
         gonna do? Keep on a skiddin' logs?" I said, "I figured on it."
         He said, "There's three skinners here in camp-- that is teamsters—
         he said, "I'm not agoin' to cut the price on you," he said, "you're
         takin' better care of your horses than the rest of 'em— these three
         skinners," and he said, "long as you take that good care of your hor
         ses. I'm gonna hold the price right up." "Now, listen," ' said,
         "there's another question—" "As long as you stay in camp. And when
         ever you quit and leave, when you come back, you'll go to work at the
         same price as the others." So I found that out. He did. But, his
         brother, Bob, I was working for him, he said, "We can get around
         that. By God, I'll fix her." So, he slipped the price up a little,
         see, so I could make good money.
         
         SS: This is when you come back to camp?
         
         DB: Yeah. I was gone three, four weeks. You know that's one thing I lik
         ed working in the woods them days; you'd work in camp and something
         fix you up a hike happened, you'd quit. Tell the boss. Yup. You'd go in and he'd^
         hand it to you. "Now," he says, "when you go spend that, come back
         and go to work."
         
         SS: Fix you up a hike?
         
         DB: Yup. That's what we called gettin' your pay. So, when we went back
         to camp,Awe always had a job.
         
         SS: Did you like to do that? Take off for a couple of weeks or something
         like that?
         
         DB: Oh, yeah. Sometimes. Snow got right deep there; I took off for three
         months, one time. Well, I went and I'd a been a runnin' a donkey, and it was agittin'
         my kidneys.
         
         SS: Working on a steam donkey?
         
         DB: Uh-huh. So, I went in and told him. And, he said, "I'll tell you
         what you do. You go to Soap Lake. Stay up there for twenty-eight
         days and see if it don't help you." So, I did. Give me a check.
         "Well," he sa^d, "When you go to Soap Lake and come back and feel
         good, come up and go to work." Well, I didn't get back. I come back
         from Soap Lake and I pooped around a couple of weeks and I wrote my
         brother-in-law, he was working; I wrote him a letter. I shouldn'ta
         done it. Of course, he had to tell Old Bob about it. And in the next
         day or two I got a special delivery letter from Old Bob to come up
         and drive team. (Chuckles) They don't do that now. Uh-huh.
         
         SS: They try to get one man?
         
         DB: Yeah. He wanted me to come up and drive a team he had. He had a
         team that was hard to drive, and he had a lot of trouble gettin' work
         out of 'em. I never had a bit of trouble with 'em.
         
         SS: Was that Prince?
         
         DB: Uh-huh. Old Cap and Prince.
         
         SS: Well, why did working on the donkey jar your kidneys up? What was—?
         
         DB: Well, I'll tell you— they got 'em on cables and they was fastened to
         stumps. There was six or eight lines run out from 'em, to hold 'em
         while they're pulling. You know they're stout. If you git coming
         around a stump or something, and she hangs up on you, you'll open
         her up once or twice to see if you can't get her around, well, when
         that comes around, that old donkey's a pullin' her best, and that
         comes around loose right quick, your donkey'11 just go that way,
         you know, and, boy, does that shake you. And that's what hurt my
         kidneys.
         
         SS: So you were running a donkey, then?
         
         DB: Yeah.
         
         SS: You were standing right on it?
         
         DB: Standing right on it. Yeah.
         
         SS: Had you been working on it long? When it got to your kidneys?
         
         DB: Oh, I'd been working on it, I guess, two months.
         
         SS: Well, what was Soap Lake like? Was that a nice place to go?
         
         DB: Very nice. I went over there. You see— that water— you go over
         there and take your baths, and it changes your entire blood in twen
         ty-eight days! And, he had been there, the boss had been there, and
         that's why he told me to go over. Course, I went. I'll never regret
         it.
         
         SS: Did you spend a lot of time in the bath?
         
         DB: No. I'll tell you, that water was so strong that you take your bath
         in— I had a room just about as long as this'n, I guess, and the north
         side of it was all bathtubs. So, there was a feller right in there
         all time,look after 'em. So, he come to me the second day. And
         he said, "You never took baths here before, did you?" And, I said,
         "Nope." "Now," he said, "I'm gonna tell you something— I'm in here
         all time, and if you can't get out of the tub, lep me know." So, the
         second day— you're supposed to take ten minutes— it just weakens
         you that fast. Didn't use soap, just rub yourself, and it'd foammm
         you know, and by gosh, whenever it'd quit foamin' you're clean!
         
         MRS. BENGE:NGE: How you comin?
         
         DB: Alright, why?
         
         MRS. BENGE:NGE: I wondered.
         
         DB: If I can quit coughin! I can't quit coughing. I'll see Brooks and
         see if I can get something to stop that. I'll tell her, when she's
         here. She'll be here after while.
         
         MRS. BENGE:NGE: I already told her. She said she would see if she could'nt get
         you an extra digitalis.
         
         DB: I've been atakin' two right along, now.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Just one a day. Just one a day.
         
         DB: Two. I've been takin' two every day, that you didn't know nothin'
         about.
         
         MRS.B: You can't do that all the time, though.
         
         DB: I know it. They're poison. Did you know that?
         
         SS: They're strong.
         
         MRS.B: You get those and I'll call 'em in to the drugstore, so they'll be
         filled.
         
         DB: They're poison. Ya get too much of it.
         
         SS: You said this guy was going to— told you to let him know if you
         couldn't get out of the bath. After you were in there for ten minu
         tes. Did you need him?
         
         DB: No. I made it. But I had to roll over and get on my hands and knees
         to get out. It was just that—
         
         SS: Strong.
         
         DB: went in there and I wondered, you know— they had two tables in
         there, and I don't know how long trey was - they must have been fortyfive
         feet. And they was full, all time. Jesus, I walked in there
         the second morning— a feller he'd be eatin' away and drop everything
         ,went to the toilet. Oh, she does clean you up! nmimmmm.
         
         SS: So you come back pretty much as good as new, then?
         
         DB: Oh, ya. Felt good and limber as a cat. Slept well of nights. Before,
         when my kidneys bothered me, had to get up about ten or twelve
         times of a night, you know. That weakens a fella.
         
         SS: But you didn't go back on the donkey after that, did you?
         
         DB: Huh?
         
         SS: You didn't go back on the donkey, then?
         
         DB: Yeah. Yeah, I went back and finished the job. It didn't take but a
         little bit.
         
         SS: You know, this talking about gyppoing— you said the IWW, they was
         against gyppoing.
         
         DB: They was.
         
         SS: Were you ag#_nst it, too.'
         
         DB: Well, I didn't care for it. I knowed— we didn't gyppo a week til I
         could see what was going to happen. The lumberjack was gonna cut his
         own throat. Working noonhour, and all. Well, before, you know, the
         company always brung us out a hot lunch at noon. Well, Then they all
         ordered— when they got to gyppoing, they all ordered lunch buckets.
         Well, they sent and got half a carload of lunch buckets and give 'em
         all one.A In about two weeks, why, the cook said, "There's no use in
         making lunches any more."
         
         SS: Was a hot lunch better?
         
         DB: Oh, boy, yeah. Brung her out there, you know, covered up and wrapped
         up, smokin' hot. If it was rainin' or something, it taste awful good!
         There one time, and they hadn't taken the hot lunch away from 'em but
         a few days and it was rainin'. And they was settin' out there under
         a tree eatin1, and this one feller^was agrouchin' about it. He liked
         the hot lunch. And another feller was a settin' there by him, he says,
         "You son of a bitch, I hope you starve to death on it." Says, "You
         wanted it, you got it! ^Eat her, Goddamn, you." (chuckles) Yeah, them
         old buzzards, you know, they come ^straight out with it. They didn't
         beat around the bush. I liked to work in the woods. God bless it.
         There was lots of fun.
         
         SS: You're saying though, that the foremen kind of drove the men some
         times.
         
         DB: They used to, yeah.
         
         SS: How did that work? I would think the men wouldn't care for that very
         much.
         
         DB: Well, they was all used to it the early days. You know, them old
         foremens, they used to— we had one over here on the steel gang, and
         lots of times they had the logging gangs and then they'd bring the
         steel gangs in. And Mc Quarlan run the steel gang. Now, he'd go ev
         ery morning, or at noon, kick your door open and,"Roll up and roll
         out!" Well, that was it. You'd either roll your soogans and get
         ready to travel or go to work. It was that way at morning and that
         way at noon. So, a man was used to it. They never thought nothin'
         about it. IWW took it over and they kinda changed things. But,
         then, you know, the gyppo then he kinda taken over and he'd get up
         from the table eatin' his last hotcake). before he got to the barn
         to get his team, so he could get to work.
         
         SS: It sounds like some of these guys like T.P. Jonts' brother, Bob Jones,
         it sounds like he was a little more—
         
         DB: Lenient.
         
         SS: Yeah.
         
         DB: Lenient with the crew.
         
         SS: But most of these guys would try to get everything out of you they
         could.
         
         DB: That's right. Yep.
         
         SS: Did that do anything for them? Did that give them more money? Make 'em look better?
         Why were they pushing the men like that?
         
         DB: Oh, that, I don't know. But, you take every camp; I worked in sev
         eral of 'em, all the foremen,they got their men. They got their pets.
         And they favor them. Well, all you can do, is let it go, I guess.
         Or, that's the way they did. Yeah.
         
         SS: Would the foreman's pets be their personal friends?
         
         DB: Oh, yeah. Had one, Tom Kelly, I worked for him over at Camp 5. I
         worked in the kitchen there for eighteen months.A I never did like
         it. Then, I come down home, had two carloads of wood to haul out,
         down to Princeton, cordwood, we'd cut that winter and so I was gettin'
         that out. And T.P. sent me a letter to come up; had a new job for
         me. He knowed I didn't like it, so I went up and he put me to scal
         ing, out in the woods. That was good. That wasn't hard work; easy.
         So, there was nothin' to that.h One winter there, he was down to Camp
         6, and I was scaling down there. There was seventeen saws to scale
         after. That makes lots of logs, in good timber, that is, it don't
         make as many logs^to scale. Yep. He'd drop the work right onto you,
         don't think he wouldn't. Well, I'll tell you what he was, he was an
         old railroad cook. He was cooking on the line when they put the In
         land through to Moscow from Spokane. Well, he cooked on that. And
         the feller that was cookin' there then had flunkied for him down here
         at Palouse, when they was amakin' that cut there. Shorty Tribble.
         Hersheil's brother was cookin'. He was working on the kitchen, there
         and Tom learnt him to cook. That old Tom was a good cook.
         
         SS: That's where Shorty Tribble learned? From Tom Kelly?
         
         DB: Tom Kelly, yeah. .It was along one fall, we was workin' there; Shorty
         could not make any bread worth a darn to eat. He tried it for four
         or five days andRKelly^had a certain place to eat— they all had their
         certain place to eat at the table—every time I'd go by Tom he'd grin
         and he'd shake his head and point at the bread. So, one morning he
         come in there and he said, "What's the matter?- he always called the
         cook Palouser—
         
         SS: What did he say?
         
         DB: Called him Palouser.
         
         SS: Palouser?
         
         DB: Yeah. Said, "What's the matter, Palouser? What's the matter with
         your bread?" Shorty said, "I don't know, I've done every damn thing
         I can think to do to it, and I can't make it come out of it." "Well,"
         Tom said, "I'll tell you what I'll do. I'll go turn the crew on out
         the rest of 'em, and see that they're all workin', then I'll come back
         and wash and put on aclean shirt and show you how." So he did, he
         back in about a half an hour or an hour. He worked the bread
         down and he throwed it up on the— Now, he said, "just let that go.
         Don't touch it. That bread," he said, "don't work it down." Said,
         "You've been aworkin' it down two or three times, but don't do it on
         this." So, Shorty did. Gee* we had good bread for supper. He come
         in, looked at me and winked, and he said, "Hey, Palouser, how'd your
         bread come out?" Old Shorty said, "Alright, I guess." (Chuckles)
         He knew damn well Tom was tryin' to get a raise out of him, and he
         seen that wasn't going to happen.
         
         SS: He wouldn't let it rise?
         
         DB: HUH?
         
         SS: He wasn't lettin' it rise?
         
         DB: Yeah. Now, I'll tell you what had happened: It was along, oh, right
         after the first of the year and there was newAwheat, and Tom said
         that new wheat, you couldn't work it like you did the old wheat. If
         you did, it wouldn't rise up. Well, after it set a while, Shorty
         done like Tom done, from then on, he mixed her up, worked her down
         and throwed her up on the bread rack and let her go til she started
         to run over the edge of the pan and „then take her down, rolled her
         out, put her in a pan and let her raise again, and bake 'em. He
         had good bread. So, I learned something, too.
         
         SS: I heard that the men were pretty particular about the food.
         
         DB: Oh, you take a bunch of old lumberjacks is the hardest layout to cook
         for that there is. One time they didn't have— oh, they had— it was
         iust after the strike and they was kinda settlin' down, and they had—
         boy that was comin' back in, and so they talked to a bunch of 'expand
         they said "Well today was thet
         last day. What's the matter?" Well, they said, "We're going down
         tomorrow." "What's the matter?" "Well," said, "We can get ten cents
         an hour more over at Blackwell and Rutledge." Well, of course, they's
         a regular old-time bunch of jacks. I didn't pay no attention to that.
         But I knowed there was something and I couldn't figure it out. Well,
         they drawed all their money went into Spokane and blowed in and come
         back. I think they come back to Rutledge's, there at Coeur d'Alene.
         Well, they worked there one payday, and here they come back. "What's
         the matter? I thought you fellers was going over there to make big
         money?" "Well," said, "the money was alright, but they the goddam
         chuck, we couldn't eat her." There it was. 'Course, they could al
         ways bla^e it onto the chuck, you know. Yep, you could always blame
         it onto the chuck! He was a good cook; Shorty was a good cook. He
         always cooked everything good and done and good flavor, good taste
         to it. And the best meat cutter I ever saw. Well, he had a butcher
         shop of his own, and he could get you a good steak right up around
         the horn. (Chuckles) Boy, I never seen a man could cut meat like he
         could and save it. Save on it, see.
         
         SS: And you were talking about being a teamster and with this team of
         horses that was a tough one to handle, and you were telling me about
         that when I was here last time, but I couldn't figure why you could
         handle 'em when these other teamsters like this good one couldn't.
         Why was it?
         
         DB: Well, it's the way I treated 'em. You know, a horse is like a human
         being, you got to treat him good if you get anything out of him. And
         what happened to this feller— they tried to whipbreak him and
         couldn't. So, I went to put the harness on him that morning and,
         boy,^went behind him and he kicked at me,; both feet! "Well," I said,
         "that won't work, so I'll try it the other way." Well, they had a
         place built up between the horses, and I got over next to the »rf
         and went up to the front end, and he struck at me. "Well," I said,
         "this won't work." And I had the blacksmith, and the barn boss and
         bullcook and all of us, and we couldn't get the harness on. He said,
         "What're you gonna do?" I said, "I'm going "h go get some sugar."
         So I went and got a cup of sugar; give him a bite or two, you knowm-
         m-m-, that was good. Right there's where we got in friends! I
         didn't know then what had happened to him. I knowed there was some
         thing, but I just couldn't figure it out— what they'd done to him
         that made him that bad. The third day, the other team, he drug out
         a log, and oh, they was a limb on it, eightj ten feet long and it
         was layin' in the road and I didn't want to get the old feller tangled
         up in it and get him to kicking at me out there, so I walked around
         in front of him and picked it up, and when I picked it up, here he
         come with mouth open and apawin' the air! And I said, "Oh, I know
         what's the matter with you now. They tried to whipbreak you, didn't
         they?" And the breaking went the other way. So, we got along pret
         ty good from then on.
         
         SS: This deal— you told me about this deal that the foreman made. He
         said he'd pay you and that you also could get—
         
         DB: Ye I got day's wages out of it besides.
         
         SS: And you got money for the scaling, you got gyppo for the scale" Is
         that right?
         
         DB: No. Yeah, I got the scale out of it, but then I got a day's labor
         for driving the team— for driving 
         
         SS: How much of the scale did you get?
         
         DB: Oh, just whatever we could get a day. It was a good team, and I was
         careful about breakin' 'em. They'd fell every time you asked 'em.
         And that's what helps, you know. So, I come out alright. An old
         foreman, Tracy, Art Tracy, he come around in a day or two and I was
         workin' the old feller, and he said, "You and Old Hogle jobbed me,,"
         "No, who jobbed who." And he said, "You two."
         I said, "If you think you can handle him, go ahead. Just pick you
         up a little switch and pick up the lines and see how you come out."
         "Oh, no, he said, "I won't do that." "Well," I said, "what're you
         hollering about?" "Well," he said, "I still think you fellers jobbed
         me." "Well, alright.If that's your belief, go ahead." But I did,
         I worked there, oh, I worked him, I guess, about two months and a half.
         So Old Nogle.he come down one day and he come out in the woods and
         he was standing there at tfefc skidway and he said, "Dick," he said,
         "don't you think that we've pulled Old Tracy's leg long enough?"
         "Well, , you're arunnin' it." "Well," he said, "I'm gonna
         give you back your old team. And, I'll put Jee Pierson with that team."
         Says, "He's a nice easy skinner." So Nogle asked me what was the
         matter with the horse, and I just up and told him. And when Joe
         left there, Joe was there about eighteen months, when he left, Nogle
         the give him team. That was the last of old Cap and Prince in the
         woods. He took 'em home. Nogle did. I said, "Why in the name of
         God, did you do that fer?" "Well." he said, "if somebody else gets
         him beat' him, and he's too good a horse for that." I know Joe
         won't. So, Jee didn't, and Joe kept him til he died. Went out in
         the woods one day and the old feller just started up the hill, and
         he got about half way up it, and Joe he wanted to give 'em a rest;
         hollered "Whoa," and the old feller just fell over dead. Yeah.
         
         SS: Ihe name was Cap and Prince?
         
         DB: Uh-huh. Yeah. Boy, they that black horse. Had an awful
         good skinner from Palouse, he brung 'em down to Bovill. He unharnes
         sed the bay, but I knowed him, I knowed the team was acomin1 that
         day, and he said, "Dick, I brung a team down fer you to work." And
         I said, "Old Cap and Prince?" "Yeah." He said, "Prince still got
         the harness on him." I said, "I thought you was a good skinner."
         "Well," he said, "not for that one." And I said, "Well, what's the
         matter with you?" Red Lucas, was his name. "Well," he said, "I don't
         know, I don't want to undo him." "Alright." "Well," I said, "we'll
         wait til after supper. I'll go up and pull the harnesSfvof him." I
         went up, walked in, and called him by name, and he just looked rigght
         straight at me, laid his head right back again his rib and looked at
         me, right in the face with those eyes. I got a little closer and he
         commenced ahuntin' sugar. Just nuzzled me under the arms and all
         over! Well, I didn't have any, but soon as I got the harness off of
         him, and got him curried, I went down and took out some sugar and
         give him. The old feller hadn't forgot, and neither had I.
         
         SS: Did you like working with horses better than the other kinds of work
         in the woods?
         
         Well, yes. See, I was raised on a farm, and I liked horses better'n
         I did Cats. 'Course now, I coulda had— well, the company got the
         Cats in 1918, put 'em in there at Camp 6, and Morgan and I was asawin'
         logs, and they brung a Cat out where we were workin'. They had
         no rockrails on 'em, you couldn't keep 'em on the track, run over a
         little stickyand she'd run off of the track, and Oh, boy! Have to
         hunt another stick and unhitch it, back it up, run it out and get it
         out and get you a pole you could lay under it and run that one
         side so's you could climb back on again. Ahh!A That was the old Holt.
         You know, coming home and getting a chance to stay at home, would be
         real
         
         DB: Well, down below here, now, the folks lived down there— two mile
         and a quarter, right down the creek there, well, that was long before
         I was married. When I come down here I stayed at home. And save
         that dollar — what was we paytathen? I believe we was payin' a dol
         lar and twenty cents a day board— save that. Yup. But, a feller
         staying to home, he's not with the crew, and there's lots of things
         he can do with his team up there of an evening; dress 'em up and curry
         'em up, kinda slick 'em up. Take good care of 'em. So, I had one
         team there, a bay team I drove, oh, about five years, I guess 
         Wtter And Old Nogle he came out one day and he said, "You got any
         idea, Dick, how many logs that you've skidded with that team?" "NopeV
         "Well," he said, "you've skidded enough logs with that team to cordu
         roy a road to Seattle and half way back." And, I said, "Jesus Christ,
         you done a lot of figuring, didn't you?" "#ope," he said, " didn't do
         that. Said, "Black did." Well, he took, I think, four hundred logs
         and figured up the width of each log— course, it was right on there,
         could get it right off of the scale book, and he just figured it
         up. God, he was good in figures. I wish I was as good as he was.
         be talkin' about something, loggin' or somethin', he'd stand
         there and listen, and he'd have it all figured up when you got done
         talkin'! You know a feller like that's pretty good.
         
         SS: What did he do there?
         
         DB: Huh?
         
         SS: What was his job there?
         
         DB: Clerkin'. Ya, he done all the figuring for the camp. But, he got
         told there— Boy, I never got so tickled in my life: we was always
         Kelly breaking our decking lines, they was all old- And said, "Dick,
         I'm going into camp." "What you going into camp for?" I broke my.
         decking line twice, while he was there He said, "I'm gonna get
         you fellers some new deckin' lines." He said, "I'm gettin' tired a
         the way you're breakin' 'em." And all this and that, and he 5--Hd, KV^t:
         gonna stop it. So, he said, "I believe I'll go in right now and have
         Black"— that was the clerk, the feller that was good with figures-
         Well, it was only one more day to payday; end of the month. Kelly
         told him,Asaid, "Black, I want you to go to town"— we didn't have no
         phone out there— "and phone out to Bovill and order a barrel of chain:
         decking line."
         
         SS: What kind of chain?
         
         DB: Deckin' line.
         
         SS: You said, barley chain, did you say?
         
         DB: A barrel of chain.
         
         SS: A barrel of chain.
         
         DB: It come in barrels. Oh, the barrels was, I don't know, I guess they'd
         hold fifty, sixty gallon. And that was full of chain, they was hard
         to handle. And Tom went in the office, he told me and he said, "Black,
         I want you to go to town." He said, "What's the matter?" He said,
         "I want you to go on down and order a barrel of chain and stay down
         there til Van comes down, that was the bull cook, and help him load
         it, and get it up here tonight." And Black said, "I can't do that."
         And Tom said, "Why?" He said, "I got my payroll made out." Tom said,
         "I'll tell you what I'll do. I'll make a deal with you." He said,
         "You go order the chain and I'll pay for it. And the next month if
         we have to get another barrel, you can pay for it." So, that was shoot
         ing it pretty straight at him. (Chuckles) So, he got the barrel of
         chain down there. Yeah, he sure got her down there. Well, Tom was
         awful good for riggin'. Well, him and I was talkin' one time, I was
         down to the office chewin' the rag with him; rainin' and we couldn't
         go out and he said, somethin' about riggin', I don't know, and I said,
         "Tom, you're the best foreman I ever worked for for riggin'." He. said,
         A man can*t log unless he's got it." Said, "it takes good riggin'
         to log with." Well, he was right there.
         
         SS: When you said he was good with the rigging. Do you mean—?
         
         DB: Get good riggin' fer ya.
         
         SS: He kept the stuff in good repair?
         
         You betcha. If he had a blacksmith, and if he didn't keep that rigrin'
         up he didn't stay. He had one blacksmith, he was here with 'em
         most of the time, Bill Seii*3 . Boy, he was a good blacksmith.
         Built anything. Anything that he wanted to build, he'd build it right
         there in - at- the blacksmith forge. Used to be rainy days, well
         I d help him.^ Just help him to kill time. Boy, that old feller could
         work anything out, figure it out, you know, and she'd work. He was
         quite a hand to drink. 'Course, I was stayin'^to home then and I
         had an old Dodge car, and I missed the bridge, course, I was a little
         full, alright. So, I was supposed to come and get him the next mor
         ning and take him to town so he could get some; well, he come out to
         the barn, and he said, "Where the hell is your car?" And, I said,
         "It's down home." He said, "What's the matter?" I said, "I missed
         the bridge last night." "What's the matter?" I said, "I broke every
         leaf in one front spring." "Well, why didn't you bring it over?"
         And, I says, "I don't know." He said, "You go get it and I'll fin
         ish taking care of your team, and run her right in the shop, and we'll
         tear her up and I'll weld 'em together." My God, he welded all them
         springs, and I drove it three years after that and it was still a movin'.
         So, he knowed what he was doing when it came to welding. So,
         one time there, we didn't have no welding compound; one of my horses
         pu!lol a shoe. I was talkin' to him the night before, he said, "I
         can't put it on. ." I said, "What's the matter, Bill?" He says, "I
         got no welding compound or toe corks." "Boy," I said, "what am I
         going to do?" "Oh," he said, "come up in the morning and we'll strai
         ghten it out." Went up in the morning and he said, "Why can't you
         build some welding compound?" I said, "Outta what?" "Well," he said,
         you go down to the creek and get you some nice clean sand and wash
         it. Just small stuff. And bring it up; chop her up right fine,
         with the hammer on the anvil." And he said, "When you get that done,
         go get you a pint bottle; glas^; break it up, chop it up fine." And
         so, he said, "When you get that donethe two of 'em together."
         So, I thought— uh learnt something. So, he said, "You
         know," we shod the horse and he put the toe corks  Well, the
         toe corks held just as good as if he'd had welding compound.
         
         SS: Toe corks?
         
         DB: Toe corks. Uh-huh. So, he told me, he said, "Dick, you know, that
         was my first job in Wisconsin." He said, "We was eighty mile from
         town, up on the river. That was my job, I was only fifteen, sixteen,
         that was my job, gathering sand and bottles and making compound for
         the blacksmith." And, he said, "I'd help him here and there," and,
         he said, "along towards the last, I was doin' pretty good helping him
         and all." So, he told Bill one day, he said, "You comin' back next
         year?" "Yeah." "Alright," he said, "if you come back," he said, "you
         can have his job, he's not acomin' back." Said, "That'll stick you
         up one notch." So, Bill, he went back up as helper. Blacksmith's
         helper. And, he said, he was a good smith, so he said,"I helped him
         two years there." And he said, "Then I took over."^ And he said,
         "He was a better blacksmith than I was." And, I said, "I don't see
         how." "Well," he said, "he was." So, he learned Old Bill all he knowed,
         Course now, Bill picked up a lot of it hisself. And he was good,
         very good, figuring out anything. You go in and tell him what you
         wanted, and he's one blacksmith that I've seen—you'd be workin',
         he'd come out in the woods to see how your riggin' was. "How are
         your peaveys, and^your cant hooks, tongs." How everything was work
         ing. And if you had something that didn't look just right, "Say,
         don't you suppose you'd better bring that in tonight, we'll work her
         over." "That's workin' alright, Bill." "No, it's not good enough."
         up tell you, if he made you a cant hook and you throwed it to a log,
         if you didn't want to catch that log, you'd better move back, because
         you'd have it before you knowed it. That old hook'd never let go!
         
         SS: That's something. Sounds like he really looked after his work.
         sending
         
         DB: Oh, he did. Well, I went to up out there in the woods. Bill
         come out and he picked up the cant hook that I was using. He said,
         "Where did you get that?" And, I said, "It was here when I come.
         That's what the other feller was using yesterday." So, Old Nogle, he
         come along about that time, and he said, "Say, you got any so-and-so
         iron up there?" "Yeah." He said, "You go up and send me down"— I
         think he wanted forty feet of it— Clairfe said, "What in the hell
         are you going to do now?" He said, "I'm gonna make these boys some
         cant hooks of my own." Well, he made 'em. Well, you know, M knowed
         what he was doin'. Yup. So, I got a hook out here yet that he made
         me. He made me two; I used one,, all the time I was sending up. Care
         ful with it. Never sprung it nor nothin'. So, he said, - when we
         got done— he said, — I was staying to home— he said, "Do you know
         where that old windfall red fir tree is?" "Yup." "Well," he said,
         "when you go home ,"Khe said, "go on the lower side of that
         and look, and there's some brush and stuff piled in there," and he
         said, "you dig under that brush and there's a brand new cant hook
         under there that I built." He said, "I want you to take it home, to
         remember me by." I got it out there yet! 'Course, Peggy caught a
         log, when she didn't aim to catch it, but she did, and boy it throwed
         her and kinda split the handle outta the cant hook, the top end.
         
         SS: He wasn't supposed to give it to you, so he hid it in the woods? Is
         that it?
         
         DB: He hid it so I could find it and take it home with me to keep.
         
         SS: That's nice. Sounds like a nice man.
         
         DB: Yup. He always went overboard for me. He made me a pair of skidding
         tongs, that was made over two years and I never used 'em. So,
         there was a feller there, he was breaking a pair of tongs about ev
         ery day, and I just happened to be in the shop, and I see them new
         tongs layin' en the floor. So, he said,^"Let me tell you something,
         Dick has used them pair of tongs he's got right now a little over
         two years, I know. He never breaks 'em." So, he said, "I've an idea
         you better hang them new tongs back up, they don't belong to you.I
         left them for him nearly two years ago to have 'em ready for him."
         Said, "He takes care of his riggin', and that's the fellers I take
         care of first. less trouble to me." So, he walked out, by God and
         never said a word. About all he could do, cause Old Bill woulda made
         him.
         
         SS: I wonder why that is that some guy like that would keep breaking it?
         And you'd never break it.
         
         DB: Didn't understand the woods, see. He might take a tong and thr :ow it
         right around a stump, you know, and leave the crook in there and try
         to roll his log out, pulling straight agin the stump. You can't do
         that without breaking something directly. Boy,^he was toploading,
         and he wanted to know if I wouldn't send up, and the feller that was
         good sending up, Powder Puff Johnny, he's hook man, he was sending
         up, but he worked at it one day and Envl was on top, and that night
         Johnny said,"I think I'll go down." And the boss said, "What's the
         matter?" "Huh," he said, "what do you think?" "You think I'm gonna
         work out there and him a sending up." He said, "Me a sending up
         or a man like that on top that never worked on top before?" "Well,"
         he said, "you'll have to get somebody else." Old Nogle come in the
         door about that time.A So him and Jack talked a little bit, and they
         come on back where I was currying the team and Nogle said, "Do you
         'spose you can send up?" I said, "I can try it." He said, "I know
         you have." Said, "You might be a little out of practice; it'll come
         back to you. So go ahead.' So, I did. I worked with him one day
         and I went in that night, and I said, "That all you got for a man on
         top?" "Yup." "Well," I said, "count me out." So, the next morning
         we went out and he said, "Who you going to get?" And, I said, "D'm
         gonna get my pardner, Andy Kidwell." He only weighed about a hundred
         and twenty pounds, but, boy, you ever got a log^up them skids, that
         was his. And he never let his chain get away from him. Old Nogle,
         he come up after Andy and I had been workin' there about an hour, I
         guess, that next morning, and Nogle looked over and he said, "That
         little bugger, I didn't think he could work on top." I said, "You
         don't know him like I do." So, he said, "Alright." Well, Andy and I
         had worked together then two years before. So, he said, "Well, I
         have to make it up to Andy some way." "That's up to you." So we
         finished the job.
         
         SS: You said to me before that Laird would come out and he would check
         the men on the job, too? Would he do that?
         
         DB: No, uh-huh.
         
         SS: No.
         
         DB: No. I never seen Laird in the woods but once. That was the last time
         I ever seen him in the woods. He was up there at old Camp 5, and I
         was workin' in the kitchen and we got our work done after dinner and
         Marian we went out and theA was loading logs, oh, I'd say, probably a
         hundred and fifty feet above camp, and it was rainin' a little and
         Old Laird and four or five of them was there and they had umbrellas
         and Bill Bailey, he was running the Marian, and he was good with it.
         So, we was skiddin' a few long logs, so they kept crowdin' in, crowdin' in, Bill looked
         at me and winked, and I knowed somethin' was gon
         na happen, but I couldn't think what. Old Laird, he was standing
         there, oh, boy, he was so interested, you know, leaning holding
         his umbrella, you know, and Old Bill he swung the log around, grinnin'
         and looked at me and winked, you know, and he just let 'her
         down on the umbrella, easy, eased down, eased down. Old Lairdyhe
         didn't know what was happenin', and pretty soon the handle was slippin'
         in his hands, and he tried to get it up and he couldn't. And
         he looked up and he seen that log, BOY!, he left, umbrella and all!
         (Chuckles) But, he took the hint. He knowed Old Bill was just ask
         ing for room. Why, he shouldn't abeen in there. Nope. He seen some
         body else in there, I suppose he'd a thought, "Well, hell, he'll get
         killed and we'll have to pay for him!" Some of them fellers, you know,
         they was awful wise, and still they don't know nothin'! Jim 0' Connel down there,
         I was a unloadin' trucks and/[had the long trucks in
         there, you know, and once in a while they'd break a cable- loadin'
         cable— well, whenever they broke one and had that trailer about
         rig,": where she belonged, she'd go down that ramp and the tongue'd
         snap a couple of times and when she would straighten out, she'd just
         break and go right on. Jim and this other feller — Billings from
         Lewiston— they was down there watchin' 'em aworkin' and they was
         follerin' that trailer right up. So I stopped the trucker and I
         said, "Fellers, I don't believe I'd foiler that trailer any further."
         "Why?" I said, "If he breaks that loadin' cable, that trailer'11 go
         back there so fast that it'll catch you both, and you wouldn't have
         a chance to get out of the road." Boy, their faces turned white and
         they got out of the road and stayed out. You didn't have to tell 'em
         a second time.
         
         SS: I was going to ask you, too, about what you thought of Potlatch, the
         town, when it was a company town there. You didn't live there much
         did you?
         
         DB: I wouldn't live there at all.
         
         SS: What did you think of the place? A company town?
         
         DB: Well, it was a company town; one-man town. And that don't work. A
         one-man^ if you've been raised out in the country, that don't suit ya.
         They used to always try to get me to move to town. I was workin'
         down to the mill, unloading logs. They wanted me to go down there
         and live. Uh-huh. I couldn't see it. Havin' a hard enough time
         gettin' along up here. They've never got over it, the town's never
         got over it. Here this spring, you know— both ministers, one of
         'em retired and the other one^quit, from the Lutheran Church, and
         so— yeah, they was gonna have one minister for both churches. I
         said, "Look, that ain't agoin' to work, either. It's been a one-man
         town too long for that." And they got all the old heads in there
         and that's just what happened. And it didn't work! They blowed up
         a time or two and had two or three ministers in there. Well, when
         the Presbyterians, they finally gave up that they weren't handlin'
         it right. Give both churches a little say in it and they been agettin'
         along a little better ever since. But it hurts 'em.
         
         SS: x don't quite understand, what that means. I mean, if you got a oneman
         town, that means that people can't worfc together? Is that it?
         
         DB: No. One man abossin' the whole thing. There's just one man bossin'.
         And, that don't work.
         
         SS: They used to have a Nob Hill. All the brass used to live up there.
         Yep. That's on the southside. That's on that hill just as you come
         into town.
         
         SS: Kind of like there was two classes in the town, huh? One up on Nob
         Hill and the other ones down.
         
         DB: a Well, you see, all the ones that had the good jobs, they lived on
         nob Hill. 'Course, the other fellas - just a common man^they would
         n't rent him a house, either. Well, that made it bad. Well, now
         they incorporated the town, all these fellers that bought the property^
         I don't know what's the matter with 'em. Afraid to get up and speak
         their piece or say anything, or what. But I know if I had, I'd get
         up and speak my piece.
         
         SS: Wasn't it a lot harder to get a union and organized in the sawmill in
         Potlatch than it was out in the woods?
         
         DB: No.
         
         SS: Wasn't any harder?
         
         DB: hard. (End of a cassette)
         
         DB: Yeah.
         
         SS: You in favor of it?
         
         DB: No, I was not. Neither was the company. So it hung fire for about
         a month, six weeks, so they sent eight carloads of lumber from Lewiston
         to Chicago, and I woke up one morning and they was asettin' down
         here on the track in Lewiston. Well, they got her back here, and
         they wouldn't unload it. Why wouldn't they unload it? Wasn't union
         loaded. So, we all joined the union, alright. (Chuckles) Boy, they
         sent four or five of 'em out of the mill, all around, signing us up!
         Well, I guess, you couldn't blame 'em. It was either sign up or they
         was gonna have to shut down or get another crew. Well, I don't know.
         The unions may be alright, but I don't go for 'em.
         
         SS: I was thinking about Princeton and the town. Did you have much to do
         with the town when you lived out here in the early days. Was there
         much going at the town, then?
         
         DB: Yeah. Well, we lived there six weeks when we first come here. Then
         we bought a place, and then, after that, why, fellers kept buying a
         little property in Princeton and work at the mills. They drive back
         and forth, but they didn't want to live there in town, so that's the
         way they worked it. Buying a little piece of property here.and drive
         back and forth.
         
         SS: Did they used to have anything on Fourth of July?
         
         DB: Oh, boy, did they!! Boy, you betcha. They used to celebrate!! A
         feller lives over here on the flat, Bert Roe, he always scraped around
         and got a little fairAin the fall. Had a fair, and he'd sell this
         and sell that and give money for small prized, you know.A Well, he
         sold out and moved away. Well, when he done that, that fell out.
         Oh, well, she had to change. Yep, everything changes, you know.
         
         SS: Did you used to do most of your trading at Princeton?
         
         DB: Yeah. Wilson, down there, he run a store for several years there.
         That was all, ran two years. And that was right after the Depression.
         From the company. And I went to work for the county, on the road,
         Carl King and I. And, God, I owed him nearly five hundred dollars.
         Every time I went, tell him, "Well, Bill, I ain't got no money."
         "I know it. What'ya want?" Tell him. "Now, you're sure that's all?"
         Well, a feller like that, pretty nice. He said, "I know you'll get
         your money sometime." So when I got my money, why, I went in and
         paid him off. And I appreciated it.ft Had five kids at that time.
         Come pretty handy, feller get all his groceries.
         
         SS: Had he known you for a long time before that?
         
         DB: His father had, he run the store there first; his father had run a
         store there. Well, I kind of think the old feller was implicated
         in the store then, too. But, nobody never knowed that he was, nor
         he wasn't. But I know he hung around tne store lots.
         
         SS: Do you think that everybody that needed credit got it then? Around
         Princeton? Or was there some people that couldn't get it, like you
         could?
         
         DB: There was some that couldn't get it. They know 'em. If a poor devil
         don't keep his credit up, he hasn't got much credit. Yeah, I know
         that, well, when I first got married, I only had fourteen dollars
         left. I bought a feller out there, bought all his— what stock he
         had and his house furnishings, and his lease on the place for a year.
         Well, I went down to Potlatch to get the money and I told him, I saia,
         I had to go to Potlatch to get the money. Jesus Christ, went down
         there and they wouldn't let me have it. And I'd done business with
         them for years, and I said, "Alright, that's fine." So, Old Lennons
         there in Princeton, he used to let lots of money out, you know. I'd
         borrowed money off of him three or four times. So, stopped to see
         him. "Hope," he said, "I haven't got her, Dick, but I'll tell you
         what to do . You come down tomorrow afternoon, bring your car, I'll
         take you where you can get it." And, he said, "I'll see that you do
         get it." Well, he took me down to the Old National Bank there in
         Palouse; so we went in, he give me an introduction to him, and
         we talked there for a little bit, and pretty soon Mac said, "What's
         your business?" I told him I'd like to geta— needed a hundred and
         fifty dollars pretty bad. Said, "What you going to do with it?" I
         explained it. First time I was ever in a bank. But, of course Old
         Lennons had been in there, that's where he done all his banking busin
         ess. So. "Yeah," he said, 'let him." I got it on a straight note,
         beings Old Man Lennons was with me.
         Lennon told him, "I know he's good because he's borrowed money off
         of me several times." And, he said, "He always paid it back, a little
         before due, some of it." Well Mc Pherson said, "We'll let that go,"
         he said, "I'll give him the money, don't worry." So, I got the money
         and come on home.
         
         SS: What happened with people like them that couldn't get money if they
         needed it, say, during the Depression, and couldn't buy food, couldn't
         buy what they needed at Wasson , what would they do?
         
         DB: Well, I don't know how they did get by. Got by, a lot of it, on com
         modities and stuff that Uncle Sam put out.
         
         MRS. BENGE:NGE: We didn't get too many of 'em.
         
         DB: Well, we didn't need it, all time and I'd rather let have 'em
         that I knowedAneed 'em. I'll tell ya, some of 'em got down pretty tough. Ya, some
         of 'em got pretty tough.
         He wouldn't kill a hog or a beef or anything til the sign
         was right. And then you take— I've seen him kill hogs- Oh, he said
         there was nothing to it alright, he says, "You have it your way and
         I'll think as I damn please." Old feller was a little rough anyhow.
         So, he got a great big hog, oh, she weighed about seven hundred and
         we skinned her. Well, he kept her for ten days til the sign got right
         and then he said, "I'll have Mom to cook some of that side pork to
         day noon for us," and he said, "you see if there ain't a difference."
         So, she fried it, done a good job; set it on the table. All the grease
         was out of it, just fried nice, but still just as thick as when
         she cut it. Well, we got half done eatin', and he said, "See any dif
         ference in the meat?" Why, it's nice, holds it shape good, and he
         said','That's why I waited til today to kill it." Yeah. He planted
         everything. Well, I know there in Nebraska we had a three corner
         fence come in there on the line, like that, and Dad planted this lit
         tle three cornered strip in spuds, and the other feller did. So,
         that s fine. So, boy, that other feller's vines got up high as that;
         bloomed andxas nice lookin' spuds as you ever saw. So, we was down
         there one day hoeing and he was out a hoeing. He said, "Yeah, Dave,"
         he said, "what'd I tell ya? Do you figure these spuds is gonna be any
         good?" "Well," Dad £aid, "they're alright if they don't all go to
         vine." Dad's little old vines was about that high, you know, and
         they was bloomin' and growing to beat the devil, and we got way over
         double the amount of spuds that he got, and his vines was up, oh,
         that high, and our's was about like that.% ht. asked him, "Why is
         that?" "Well," he said, "you planted yours the wrong time of the
         moon." "What difference does that make?" He said, "Mine is growin'
         under the ground and yours are growing on top." So, I don't know.
         
         SS: Do you know how he figured when he ought to plant? What was guiding
         him there?
         
         DB: Well, he went by the almanac. It's all marked out in that, you know.
         I never could read it.
         
         MRS. BENGE: I asked him one time how he judges the pork.
         
         SS: Judges the what?
         
         MRS. BENGE:NGE: How he knew when to butcher. And he said, "Well, when there was a
         moon, a moon. When the moon ^ heoo and growing." '^ was just almost
         full. And then butcher. But if you wait untilAit's full and
         starts on the decline, then it'll all fry out to grease.
         
         DB: Well, I'll tell you, it's got something to do with it. I don't know
         what. The moon even controls the tide of the ocean. Now how it gets
         that, I don't know. But I know it does.
         
         SS: Well, go ahead, what were you going to say?
         
         PEGGY SCOTT: We raised rats for a while. You know, well, for experimental
         purposes; universities, you know. Sold rats. We had two, three thou
         sand at a time, you know. And, we noticed according to the moon, we
         kept records, and according to the moon, the conception was almost
         three times as good during the growing part of the moon, as it was in
         the declining part of the moon. We would only have to breed about a
         third as many rats, I mean— don't ask me why, I don't know. But it
         was very true. And the litters were bigger. Now science will— oh,
         go fly a kite. But it proved out over a period of years, and it is
         really true.
         
         SS: That is really interesting. I don't doubt it.
         
         PS: This was just according to our records. Certainly nothing offic
         ial, but we did keep He had mentioned it to the kids at the university, and they says
         "Well, this is when you start keeping records. This is when you prove
         a theory. Where you have the equipment to do it with." And we start
         ed keeping records, and it did prove out.
         
         DB: Well, I do know when I was down there to Johnny's one day, and we
         wanted to go clamming. And he said, "Nope, not today, nor tomorrow
         or next day." "Why?" Said, "The clams won't come in." "How?"
         "Well," he said, "the moon brings 'em in." So, we waited three days
         and we went down there, and boy, we just a little late that morning.
         Boy, all the sand was just bubblin', this way, you know. Oh, I don't
         know. How did the Indians get by? They went by the moon. And they
         could tell ya what the winter was gonna be, what the summer was gonna
         be. All the seasons, they knowed what they was. They had no books;
         no nothin'! There was one old feller— Indian there, I was working
         at the sawmill there, and I had four Indians working for me, and
         three of their dads— their father come up and lived with 'em, and
         they was Spokane Indians. And that's where I got a lot of my advice,
         was off a him. He was ninety-six. Still peggin' around in pretty
         good shape. And he told me, "Dick," he said, "we got an awful prob
         lem." "How's that?" "Well," he said, "they made us sign up, I'm a
         Spokane Indian, and they made us sign up and they give us a reserva
         tion around Spokane. Well," he said, "we had it two years and they
         took it away from us." Said they didn't have no fish, no place to
         fish in or nothin'. "Then," he said, "they sent us over to Coeur d'
         Alene. Sent us over there two years." And, he said, "That was no
         good for us," he said, "then they sent us down to—"
         
         SS: Nez Perce, Lapwai?
         
         DB: No. That place near there in Spokane— ah—
         
         SS: Yakima?
         
         DB: No. It's right on 95, between here and—I thought that was the Coeur d'Alene Reservation.
         Uh-huh. No. He didn't belong to the Coeur d'Alene Reservation.
         
         SS: Plummer—
         
         DB: Ahhhhh—
         
         SS: Well, it don't matter.
         
         DB: Plummer. But what's the name of the— that ain't what they called
         it. It's a mission, see they got a mission there.
         Yeah.
         
         So, away she went.
         
         So, he wasn't happy about it?
         
         Oh, boy! It burnt him up, when they took the Indian Reservation there
         in Spokane, the Whites- and moved 'em over to Coeur d'Alene. That
         burnt him up. And from then on he was upset and backwards. Yeah.
         Nice old feller. He wasn't nasty about it, but how
         the whites treated 'em. See.
         
         SS: That was pretty bad.
         
         DB: Wasn't it. Well, they blamed the Indians for fightin'. What would
         we do if the Roosians come in here and 4w to overhaul us like we
         did them? Ain't we all gonna fight back? Huh? And right now.
         That's the reason I don't go for that gun law. They could; they're
         liable to. The Roosians are not too dependable. That's their busin
         ess, I guess, not mine.
         
         SS: You know, Dick, I was going to ask you something about the difference—
         Did you raise your kids about the same way your parents raised you?
         Or was it much different?
         
         DB: Well, there might have been little difference. I made 'em mind
         And I told 'em when they got away from home, I wanted 'em to do the
         same way. If they ever got into anything or done anything that wasn't
         right, well, they'd have to pay for it one way or the other. So,
         made her fine and dandy. The boy he got arrested once. Boy, I laugh
         ed til I cried over that; he was trying to go with a cop's daughter
         down in Palouse. Well, I knowed that old feller and he was pretty
         grouchy. So, Johnny he aggravated the old feller then with his car
         down Palouse of a night. Well, I kinda figured there was some
         thing going on, and it went on and went on, and we was settin' eatin'
         breakfast, and I could see, boy, there was something bothering him.
         We was both working down atAPotlatch sawmill. I'd bought him a good
         car and we was using rf to go back and forth, and so I could see in
         his face— we got about half done eatin' and he said, "How much mon
         ey you got;in the bank, Dad?" I knowed then that they'd picked him
         up. So, I told him. "Well," he said, "I give a check for you on your
         name." His is J. H. Benge and mine is A. L. Benge. So he just wrote
         it A. L.. And he told me what he'd done. I said, "That's alright."
         Well, he give 'em a check for his fine and come back home that night.
         What he d done, went to Palouse and crossed that^highway and made his
         U-turn there. You can't do that. And, he said, "Dad, I know I
         shouldn't a done it, but I did." And, I said, "Well, what you gonna
         do about it?" "Well," he said, "I have to go back Tuesday night.
         Gonna have a hearing." I said, "Alright, I'll go with you." So we
         went down and we went down across a aerial highway." No
         aerial sign up. Well, when we come back up the other side, there
         wasn't none over there. "Now," I said, "let me tell you something—
         you ask 'em why they haven't got their signs up. It takes two signs
         one over on that corner and one over here." I said, "They're just
         using that now to pick up people that don't know 'em." So, we went
         in. So, they asked him why he done it. He said, "I didn't see no
         sign up that it was a aerial highway." Said, 'You're supposed to
         have a sign up there. How would a stranger know?" He said, "I should
         a knowed, but it just slipped my mind." Well, they talked around
         there a while and finally they give him back twelve dollars. Turned
         him loose. "Now," he said, "I'm acoming down tomorrow night, and if
         you fellers ain't got them aerial signs up; two of 'em, one over here
         and one over there, I'm gonna see what I can-do with the city." So,
         we went down the next night and they was up. One over there and one
         over here. Well,Athey'd tore them down just apurpose.to catch people.
         Well, you know, that's the way the cop there in Palouse, that's the
         way he gets his money, most of it.
         
         SS: Your son was going with his daughter, huh?
         
         DB: Tryin' to. The old feller didn't like him and he was just aggravatin'
         the old feller. Well, you know, you cross the railroad track up at
         this end of Palouse. Johnny turned in one time and come down the
         railroad track on the rail with his car, down there; cop caught him
         at that. Well, that didn't help. I didn't know a car would stick
         to a set of rails like they do. Ever see that tried out? They'll
         stick right on 'em! Yeah. You just let your^steering wheel go,
         she'll stay right on the rail. Oh, them kids, they learn lots of
         stuff that us older people didn't know.
         
         SS: So you really never wanted to farm very much, yourself? Or did you?
         
         DB: Not after I got to loggin' Nope. Johnny, he, that's the boy, he
         worked over there for Hugo Walter; he worked over there three years.
         He was just a kid and Hugo, he wanted to lease him his whole place
         and furnish all the machinery. He wouldn't do it. I was running a
         camp at the time when Hugo offered him that, so he come up, well he
         was workin' at the mill, too, parttime—and he come up and asked me
         what I thought about it. And, I said, "Listen, you're eighteen
         a little ovt*~.. You're old enough, you ought to know what you want.
         I don't. You suit yourself." So, he said, "I believe I'll tell Hugo
         to take 'er." So, he come out and went driving skidding Cat for me.
         Well, he could make as much in one month as he could for three for
         Hugo, see. Well, you couldn't blame him, for wantin' to work up there
         where he was makin' more money. So, he worked up there til camp went
         down, then he come down and he worked at this little sawmill here.
         Frandsen went out in the woods with a loggin' crew. Well, his brotherin-
         law wasflrunnin' it. ^The other feller thought Johnny wanted his
         job. Well, he coulda got it, yes. But,— so my boy come up from Cali
         fornia and he said, he was talkin'— no, it was my nephew— and he
         was talkin' to Johnny about it. And, he said, "Come and go back with
         me. I've got a danged good job for you." And Johnny said,' What is it?"
         "Running dozer. Making road." Johnny said, "Well, I never run a
         dozer." They got a better loggin' road than this highway is down
         here Princeton. He's two tanks there that he heats his oil
         in, two stir fires, three road graders. Five dozers. And if the
         road gets too bad he can,get in part of the loggin' crew. Old Timson's
         got to come and help him. Which helps.
         
         SS: Six hundred miles of road.
         
         DB: Lot of road.
         
         SS: One thing I was thinking about when you were raising a family. Was it real
         hard for you to not be home for a good part of the time, working out?
         
         DB: Well, I was home most of the time. You see, all the time the camp
         was around here, I stayed home and go back and forth. And the boss,
         he took pity on me one winter there, and he said, "Dick, it's a little
         too hard on you . Running up and down that railroad track night
         and morning. You come up to camp and stay and I won't charge you a
         cent board." That was Old Kelly. So, I just went up to camp and
         stayed. Yeah, she's sure, sure changed. Boy, the timber when I first
         come here was sure pretty. All the hills in here, all around, big
         old yellow pine and tamarack. We cut her down and hauled her down on
         the truck and loaded her up and took her to Potlatch.
         
         SS: When Dick was gone, you really raised the family.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, I had cows to milk and my day consisted of packing his lunch
         pail and sending him to work and going out and milking the cows and
         getting the kids up and getting 'em off to school. Then there was
         certain times in the year that we did clearing, and that was the hardest.
         And just as soon as the kids were gone and the separator wash
         ed— and to heck with the dishes! (Chuckles) And take off in the
         woods and fix up all my fires and pick up and burn and I had a pair
         of coveralls.. Working in black wood, you'd just get terrifically
         dirty; just black. And then I'd work until I heard the four o'clock
         whistle blow. And then I'd come down and the kids'd be coming home.
         The girls were old enough and they'd wash up the dishes and sweep the
         floor and I would do other things and get the meal ready, and then
         they'd wash the supper dishes and I'd take off back up the hill and
         Dick would be there and the two of us would work til dark. Burning
         the stumps out; a lot of 'em. Maybe six weeks at a time, almost.
         Have to take a day off now and then to wash.
         
         PEGGY SCHOTT: And pack water and wash by hand.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Packed water and washed on the board. And if you didn't think the
         house got to be a mess! At such a time. Course, the two older girls
         did a lot of it. And Peggy helped. She was pretty good to pack
         water in a gallon bucket. That is one of the things I did! And then
         I always raised a big garden, which was nothing small. We didn't
         have irrigation. We had it over on the creek and we had a steam en
         gine, and we'd hook the hose down into the creek, you know, and wat
         er it that way. And that's just about all, I guess.
         
         SS: Did you grow enough of a garden to pretty much take care of the vege
         tables?
         
         MRS. BENGE: For the family of seven, potato wise, perhaps and some of the
         other things. I canned everything I could. And cabbage, I always
         pitted, and carrots, I pitted.A I sold quite a lot of stuff to Roy
         Guernsey's store. He had a store in Onaway. I even had head lettuce
         that I took down one year, and then take it out in trade. Oh, and
         we always had eggs. And during the real Depression, if I got those
         things to town, I had to pack 'em.
         
         SS: Walk 'em in?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Walk 'em in. Yeah. And take two water buckets full of eggs, and a
         couple of kids with me, and they could pack a gallon of cream. Some
         times two gallon and they'd switch back and forth. And drop the eggs
         off at Princeton and I had to take the cream on to Potlatch. And,
         get— we got four cents a dozen for the eggs.
         
         SS: That's a long walk.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah.
         
         SS: A real long walk!
         
         MRS. BENGE: And, I don't know, maybe we'd get a dollar and a half a bucket for
         the cream. And, oh, yeah, I always bought the kids something if they
         went and helped. Sometimes the older girls would take the two buc
         kets of eggs and go to town. And they could always buy a penny can
         dy bar. Which was bigger than a dime one is now. (Chuckles)
         
         PS: We didn t feel abused, because everybody avr\£ the same thing.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Everybody done the same thing. We used to have quite a lot of dances
         during those times. Well, we had an organ that worked pretty good;
         they had a lot of 'em here, and Dick had a violin and several others
         had a violin, and they'd all come and bring some food; you know, what
         ever they happened to have, and we'd dance until midnight then we'd
         stop and have coffee and whatever there was to eat and then we'd dance
         til daylight on a one-by-twelve board floor with cracks in it. You
         know, you can't get them if they're rough, oh, they lacked that far
         of being together. The men when they were logging, hauling wood, you
         know, during Depression, used to get out in the mud and get their
         tires all muddy, you know, an awful mess, and I didn't object and
         they'd bring them in and put 'em behind She heatin' stove and let
         'em set there a day.
         
         SS: What?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Their tires. And then get right out here and bounce 'em up and
         down to get all of the dirt off of 'em. And then they'd sweep it
         down the cracks. (Chuckles) If they swept it up good, I didn't
         mind. I never complained, because I knew how hard it would be with
         no place to work outdoors with the mud on 'em.
         
         SS: The dances sound like real togetherness. Real neighborliness.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes, it was.
         
         SS: Do you think that the Depression made people draw closer together?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, it sure didn't drive 'em apart!
         
         PS: One particular instance— I guess I can talk—
         
         SS: Oh, sure. Yeah.
         
         PS: Well, one particular instance I remember. We didn't have any coffee.
         Course, I was just quite small, but, they didn't have any coffee, 
         and our neighbor lady down there in this first house. So she sent Catc.t
         word up saying they had gotten some coffee and she had a cup of
         sugar, so she made a cake, and they invited everybody down. You know,
         big deal! You know, it was really togetherness and gung-ho, just like
         you were having a fiftieth anniversary now. Big deal! ^Cake and a
         cup of coffee! Went down, and they drank coffee all afternoon and
         nobody slept for three days, because they hadn't had any coffee and
         the caffein kept them awake for about three days! Now, I mean, this
         is togetherness. You drank together and everybody suffered together.
         I do remember that.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And one Christmas during the Depression we didn't have any money at
         all, but we sold two cord of wood at Potlatch and got it hauled down
         and they measured it up, and we didn't have anything left at all.
         Just macaroni and flour and oh, some sugar. And I had to get stock
         ings for the girls, they were going to school, and I just squeezed
         every penny I could get out of it. And bought a fifty cent doll for
         Peggy.A And then come Christmas in a couple of days. 'Course, I
         made 'em doll clothes and things like that, but I didn't know what
         to have for Christmas dinner, and I didn't have any chocolate; I
         thought I could make a chocolate cake. And we hadn't had anything
         except, you know, just plain cake, and so, I went down to the neigh
         bors and asked her if she had any chocolate. She had just gotten a
         great big box of chocolate, and she give me a cup of cocoa. And I
         come home— and see there was five of us— and I killed two old hens
         and stuffed 'em and cooked 'em, and we had potatoes and gravy and a
         canned vegetable and I made a chocolate pie, and put whipped cream
         on it for supper. And we just had the loveliest Christmas dinner that
         you ever saw. Just real nice! With nothing else, and I don't know,
         I think I had something that I give her in place of the cocoa. And
         that's the way it went. And, sometimes here would come a peddler
         from down in the Palouse country and he'd have, oh, grain or potatoes
         or something like that that he'd want to trade for wood and we'd trade
         him that for wood. Traded for a pig or just anything. But, the only
         time, and I'll tell you about that, -HmlV I was ever really worried;
         we didn't have any flour. We didn't have any sugar. We didn't have
         any spuds. We had some peas, but they was weevilly, and I soaked 'em
         overnight and tried to pick all thatAweevils out of 'em, and they
         weren't worth cooking, so I put some wheat on to cook. And Dick and
         I went up on the hill, it was in the summertime. "Just what are we
         gonna eat? AWhat are we going to do? If we kill the chickens, we
         won't have any eggs or any money. If we eat the eggs, we won't have
         anything at all to buy anything with. We got milk. We gotta save
         that cream for a few pennies." 
         
         And Edgar Adair, a man who was in
         Princeton and he had a truck; and we was settin' up on the hill just
         a talkin'- "What the heck we gonna do?" I hadn't had any soap for
         three weeks; I didn't have any baking powder; I didn't have anything,
         you know, as far as commodities was concerned. And Dick and I both
         just run down over the hill right over the logs and everything and
         got down there. "Oh, boy, am I glad to see you!" He said, "I sold,"-
         I don't know how many cords of wood it was- "but", he said, "I gotta
         take four cord out in groceries. And if you'll give me eight cord,
         I'll let you have the groceries." Well, my goodness, you know, beg
         gars can't be choosers, so we got up there, and we had an awful lot
         split, and we just blame soon loaded that car full— a big truck load.
         And, Dick went to town with him and he brought back— He took two
         cord down, and then I think Edgar got groceries with the other two
         cords. But, you know, for two cords, you could get quite a lot of
         groceries. We got a barrel of flour, and we got twenty-five pounds
         of sugar and we got, oh, boy!, we got a lot of soap and we just got
         everything. And when he came back by, he came back by Flannsberg,
         Adown in Palouse, and he had an old sow that had pigged that year,
         and she'd been running out in the pea field, and she was just real
         nice. Not all of that terrible fat. And so Dick bought that, traded
         her for wood, and Flannsberg come and got the wood. We brought the
         sow home with us. Made a whole fifty gallon barrel full, and it was
         awful nice meat. Then they come by— oh, I can't think of the name
         of the guy at Palouse— but he never turned anybody down that went in
         there. And you'd take a load of wood in there and he'd let you have
         flour and feed and a tank full of gas, and you got your money's worth
         for the wood. Edgar took two cord of wood down for us.
         
         SS: So you got two cords worth of groceries, and two cords worth of buying power.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah.
         
         SS: From that wood. And that's because he just made the sale.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Oh, boy! You know, sometimes we get awfully discouraged, but when we
         look back on it, when we're doing the best we can, and saying a little
         prayer, and you don't know where from which way, and you don't expect
         the least, that's where it comes from. And we used to raise quite a
         few chickens, and the peddlars would come by. Had those great big
         Rhode Island Reds, and they'd trade me a box of peaches for a chicken.
         And apples and tomatoes, and that way I could can my Oh, I
         canned everything I could get my hands on.
         
         SS: They would kill the chicken and just take it with 'em.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Just take it with 'em. As a rule. And I canned about six to eight
         hundred quarts; not all at once, but, you know, when some of the jars
         were empty, well then in the fall of the year^there was carrots and
         cabbage to can, and all that stuff, you know. Just everything I could.
         And that's kinda the way it helped out, too. 'Course, when he went
         back to work, you know, after the Depression— at the end of the Dep
         ression, why, then, it was considerable easier going.
         
         SS: When you said this place in Palouse which would trade—
         
         MRS. BENGE: It wasn't Palouse, it was Colfax, wasn't it?
         
         PS: Pullman.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Pullman, yeah. Whai was his name
         
         SS: I wonder if that's part of the same that came from Troy?
         
         PS: I don't know.
         
         SS: But, if he was always there and you could trade with him, how come
         you were in such desperate —?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, sir, we didn't have a truck at that time. I don't remember
         how it was, but we didn't have a truck; no way of hauling anything.
         There was nothing to do but just make wood.
         
         SS: Was Dick walking to Potlatch when he had work?
         
         MRS. BENGE: He wasn't working then, there was no work at that particular time.
         
         SS: That's why you were walking into town?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah. I didn't have no way to get there.
         
         SS: It's too bad that
         
         MRS. BENGE: It was about the same time as they put out this work—
         
         SS: WPA work?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah. WPA work. They'd go work a couple of months— a week, a month—
         and they got nineteen dollars a week. That was the beginning of the
         letup.
         
         SS: Did Dick get on with that?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Uh-huh. And, of course, you hated to kill your beef, and there was
         little "government beef" running up around the country, sometimes it'd
         fall and break their neck and we'd use them! (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Government beef?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah.
         
         SS: They had cattle running around.the country?
         
         PS: Government beef are wild critters.
         
         SS: I see, win, I see. I get it.These wild animals do die!
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes, yes. Nothing to waste, though. it, and I don't know
         whether it was any good or not, but thenAI'd can it. But, anyhow,
         I canned a lot.
         
         SS: Did many people think of leaving from around here, during the Depres
         sion? Or would it have just been too rough to go anyplace else?
         
         MRS. BENGE: We never thought of leaving. Never did.
         
         SS: I meant trying their luck somewhere else.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Some of 'em did. Some of 'em did, but we never thought of such a
         thing. And, you know, my house didn't amount to much, well, it was
         two thickness of one-by twelve boards, inside, with tar paper between
         it. And then I had another pasteboard thing that had gottenfour
         times, it had gotten so hard, and put on top of that; tacked it
         all over. But it was heavy like that.
         
         SS: Was it pasteboard?
         
         MRS. BENGE: I don't know what it was. We had that on the house, and then two-byfours—
         and there was nothing on the outside. And then, there was
         just a door here, and steps up to that. You know the little shacks
         we bought to build it out of in the first place? All the windows
         we had was in them. And, you know, they're little squares like this,
         you know, and we had one here and one here and two back there. And
         boy, when I first got my windows in, I felt plumb naked! I'm tellin'
         ya! I really did. But I'd had it without any—
         
         SS: So, you'd had it withoufckny windows in it.
         
         MRS. BENGE: But, we got our place paid for, then we got a well dug, and we gotlifted
         the old house up and put it on a foundation.
         
         SS: This right here? This house?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Lifted it up and put it on a foundation, and then built on, and fin
         ally built a good barn. Just inched it up a step at a time.
         
         SS: Do you think that most everybody else in the neighborhood here was
         pretty much in the same boat during the Depression?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Everybody was in the same boat. There was a few men that managed
         to work at Potlatch, considerable. But Dick was a logger, and so
         there wasn't much work for him. We managed to get a payment down
         on a truck and he went and took it and went over to Joel and around
         over in there and hauled, to pay for the truck. Hauled grain all
         one fall.
         
         SS: I imagine walking into Potlatch and back must have taken you most
         of the day.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Oh, I was young then, I didn't mind it. There was only one time that
         I remember that it kinda laid me low. But, my sister-in-law was
         going with me, Lola Tribble, and so I got ready to go and it was mud
         dy, oh, my goodness, it was muddy, and going down that road it was
         the hardest walking you ever saw, and I was tired when I got there,
         and she come to the door and said, "I got lunch all ready for u
         why don't you come over?" And, I said, "Lola I'm tired already, and
         I don't want to come over there and then walk back. I think I got
         a lot to do down there and we'd better get a goin'." So she come on
         down across the bridge, and we went to Princeton. And about when we
         crossed the river bridge, somebody come along and give us a ride in
         to Princeton. And we had some business to tend to in Princeton, and
         then we walked on to Potlatch. All the way, and when we got just
         past the graveyard, down there, somebody come along and give us a
         lift on into Potlatch. Then we had to go to Onaway. We walked over
         the hill. And then we come back and-there was a lumberyard down about
         where Carter's is, and we had to walk down there and then we had to
         go back to Onaway and come back over to Potlatch. And, I'll tell ya
         I was purty tired when we got there! (Chuckles) We walked every
         step of the way from Potlatch to Princeton. And I got to Princeton
         and I went in and I sit down like this and Bill was sitting fn a chair
         on the other side of me. And the man that was teaching school up
         here, I can't remember his name.
         
         PS: Douglas.
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, it was the one after him. And he said, "My goodness, you girls
         look all in." And, I said, '^1 sure am." And he said, "I'll bet you
         walked all the way to Potlatch and back, and didn't get much ride."
         And we said, "We sure did." And he said, "Well, how many groceries
         you got to walk home? I said, "So many, that I don't think I'll
         take 'em." "Well," he said, "go get them, and I'll take you girls
         home." So, he brought us home. And I sure appreciated it.
         
         SS: I guess that ordinarily you really couldn't figure you could ask a
         neighbor to give you a ride, that had a car?
         
         MRS. BENGE: There wasn't any of 'em passed us, None of them passed us, they just
         didn't happen to be going our way at the right time. (Chuckles) Not
         a £He of em passed us! But thatj,, either Lola or I will ever forget.
         I made more fuss about it than she did, but she stayed in bed all
         the next day and I didn't. Oh, yeah, I walked to Potlatch and back
         many times. But that was just real hard goin'! And the extra we
         had to walk. I don't remember, it's been so long ago, I think we
         
         SS: would get together for dance after dance.
         
         MRS. BENGE: I don't know if this is fit to put in there or not, but— I felt just
         like dancin' and having one heck of a time, and Mosses lived at the
         house, and you go down here to that turn, and go right straight back
         it's up the hill Athat little log house up there. Maybe you've noticed
         it, have you?
         
         SS: I think I've seen it, yeah.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And they lived there. Well, we went to the dance, and I went in and
         we went right to dancin' and pretty soon I come out to the sink and
         this Gale Leroux, oh, he must have been about sixteen, and he lived
         just up the road there. They done the house over a lot. And he said,
         "May, how much it take to get a man drunk?" "Oh," I said, "anybody
         that's any kind of a man can stand a quart." "Really?" I said, "Ya,
         you 11 feel pretty good quart, you'd better not try
         more than that." And, I think he'd never had a drink in his life.
         And hid uncle and another fellow had managed to get about three quarts
         of whiskey, and they'd had a drink when they first got there, and the
         kids had found their cache. And Gale downed a quart, and the other
         kids got rid of the other quart, and there was only about that much
         left in one quart! And were those men ever mad! Oh, blow me down!
         (Chuckles) And, Violet, Gale's sister come in.and she said, "Gale's
         deadly He's dead." And I went out there and he was just out like
         just out like a light. He never come to til the next morning. So
         help me! And, oh, Violet was mad. (Laughter) And Larry was mad!
         
         SS: Did you know that he'd never even had a drink before?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes.
         PS: Did you know he had the liquor when you said that?
         
         MRS. BENGE: I had an idea he'd-Coodd Ben t .cache, cause if n could get
         and he'd figured on taking the men out, maybe after sup
         per and giving 'em a drink apiece. Him and the man that run the comranch, his name
         was Hans Peterson. And they're the ones that
         had the liquor. Oh, boy.
         
         SS: How often, May, would there be dances in those days?
         
         MRS.B.: Well, there was a couple of winters there was either a pinochle party
         or a dance every Saturday night. Costs nobody anything except may
         be a little food.
         
         SS: How far up and down the creek did the families come from?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, let's see; Gages wasn't here at that time, were there?
         
         PS: No, on the hill, which is two miles, two miles that way and two miles down.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah, that's about all.
         
         SS: And about how many families would there be, usually?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, let's see, there would be Rozells, and Schweiders, and they
         didn't come very much, and two families of Lerouxs, and Weavers,
         and Brownings, and Mc Veys, and Mosses, and Tibbies and Twogoods,
         and Carrs, and Carrs didn't always come. And Rosses. I believe
         that's all. OH, Jonses. But they all had young people, you know,
         like Jonses had six kids up here. And then other people'd float in
         from here and there, too, you know. So, that was lots of fun. Oh,
         Joe Pierson and his family; off over there by Baleses. They used
         to come. There two girls and.three boys.
         
         SS: You said a little while ago that you kind of helped raise some of
         the neighbors' kids, too.
         
         MRS.B.: Oh, I always had kids and the other kids 'd come and stay a week.
         
         P.S.: This wasn't at that time particularly, though.
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, but later on, yes, and then, too. There was always kids around
         here. Always kids around. But, as for to take any of 'em and keep
         'em, I never did. Oh, Wests lived upAthe creek, too. There were
         quite a few families.
         
         SS: Do you think that parents, when you were raising kids, that parents
         acted very differently than parents do nowdays with their kids?
         
         MRS.B.: I haven't been around how they act. Been out of circulation too
         long. But the girls was going to the dances,A and maybe she'd changed
         twice, that is, she danced with 'em and she ate supper with 'em and
         she came home with us. But they were going together, just the same.
         Or they thought they was. They were making eyes atewe Another, We was
         and holdin' hands, and that was it. a little older, we
         didn't have so many dances here, when Peggy got old enough to grow
         up, we used to go, oh, what creek was that on, where we used to go
         up to
         
         P.S.: Kinmans?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Kinmans.
         
         Side I
         
         And go to this Flat Creek schoolhouse.
         
         P.S.: Grouse Creek.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Grouse Creek schoolhouse, yeah.
         
         P.S.: It wasn't a schoolhouse, it was a logging—
         
         MRS. BENGE: I know, but then we did have 'em on Flat Creek schoolhouse. Two or
         three dances I went up to up there with you.
         
         P.S.: It was the Grange hall.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Was it the Grange hall? But Peggy was old enough, at least part of
         that time to pick her own boyfriend and he'd come and get her. Many
         times she worried me to death.
         
         SS: I think it's interesting how, you know, nowdays it seems like parents
         give their kids a lot of latitude about going on dates and all that.
         feeling And I have the ,. that in those days a lot of courting was carried
         on under the watchful eyes of the parents, by comparison to today.
         
         P.S.: Well, there again, we didn't have cars even when I was in high school.
         There was no gas available during the war. I mean, if you did have a
         boyfriend and his folks had a car, once a month was all he could ever
         get it, so six, or eight or ten kids went together. It was very,
         very different. There's no getting around' . There's an entirely
         different aspect on the whole thing. Now, if a child, even at thir
         teen to fourteen can't get in a car and go from here to Spokane to
         see a show, they just aren't living. Where us, we could go to one of
         these parties, and that's all— just to run off our energy. My boys,
         we were very fortunate, they lived out here and they all had horses,
         and after they graduated from horses, they went to cycles, but we in
         sisted on an offhighway bike.. So even I don't understand this.
         But mamas working— I shouldn't mention this, this is my hangup—
         mama's are working; she comes home from work, she's got her own work
         to do, she is tired; the kids are out of sight, out of mind, to heck
         with it! In fact my son-in-law— my daughter-in-law doesn't like to
         stay home— and he says her home- their home- they live in Moscow, and
         mama works and daddy works— she took care of the kids from the time
         she was a firstgrader on- the younger brothers and sisters— she got
         'em ready for school, and he said their home was a place to come to
         when you got hungry and "* to sleep. And it was
         just a house. There was no point in coming home 'cause mama wasn't
         there. There was no home there!
         
         MRS. BENGE: One time Peggy give me some bad time , and we had a car and there
         wasn't too much gas available, but this Ernest Hayfield lived up over
         the hill this way, and he'd been trying to get a date with her and
         she wasn't too crazy about it. But, there was two other girls and
         two boys come and she said she'd go, and she didn't know whether to
         or not, but she finally went. And, I expected 'em to be home; Dick
         was workin' nights, and got home at two o'clock, and I woke up and
         she wasn't here and I went out— it was summertime and it got daylight
         pretty quick— and I set on the steps and I didn't know whether to
         take off and go just straight up or just what to do, or whether the
         car'd broke down or they'd run outta gas, and it was just daylight
         when they came home. I went out there abawlin'. "Whatever did you
         do this to me for?" "Well, Mother," she said, "the dance stayed, and
         we danced til daylight." She said, "You said you used to dance til
         daylight." It probably must have been about five o'clock!! But
         all six of 'em were there yet. They were all together. Oh, boy!
         
         SS: Were you mad?
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, I wasn't mad.
         
         SS: Kind of glad to see her again, eh?
         
         MRS. BENGE: And then another time, she was going with this Curley Plumly, and
         they went to the show in Palouse, and they got back as far as Kennedy
         Ford, and they run out of gas. AThey had quite a bit of time
         left, and Peggy said, "Daddy gets off at two o'clock." And so they
         played around so much and finally had toAhurry because it was get
         ting close to that time. They got there and was running right out
         to try to stop Daddy, and he went right on by! Well, Giesa, our
         oldest daughter was married and lived in Onaway and she went over
         there. But, anyhow, I worried^ And Curly brought her home the next
         morning.
         
         P.S.: We didn't have telephones, then.
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, we didn't have telephones .. So, people do have times rais
         ing their kids. Not that at either time had she really done anything
         so wrong, except that I walked the floor. That's all. And I wasn't
         mad. You're too scairt to get mad!
         
         SS: When your kids were just little babies and children, were there things
         that you were supposed to do or not supposed to do with the kids?
         You know, when I was growing up, a lot of mothers were raising their
         kids by— according to Dr. Spock, you know. He had come out with
         some books about child raising and that's how a lot of mothers were
         raising their kids, when I grew up.
         
         P.S.: We didn't have social problems.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Uh-huh.
         
         P.S.: Really. What we done, we done together, which didn't leave the children
         on their own hardly anything— like the parties and this type of
         thing. I was playing pinochle with veterans when I was a first grad
         er. Because you grow up with it and you learn.
         
         SS: Did you try to break the kids into working, pretty young?
         
         MRS. BENGE: You betcha! (Chuckles) Just recently I had a girl come and stay
         and— with me. And they said, "Will May make her work? Will she
         make her do anything?" And Judy said, "Huh, I'd just like to see
         you be around Mom and not do any work!" Yes. My kids worked. Always.
         "You better get up and get busy." (Laughter) Yes, they worked
         and they're all good workers, every one of 'em.Johnny worked.
         
         P.S: But there again, we didn't work alone. We weren't sent to do a job
         ftirhculfirif
         we went to help with the job. I mean, there's a difference send a child out to hoe
         in the garden for two hours, it's pretty rough,
         and works for two hours. There's a difference.
         
         SS: Uh-huh. There really is a difference.
         
         P.S.: I mean if mama goes out to work now, and tells her child to stay home
         and do the dishes and the housework, it's very different, than if
         Mom says, "I'll wash, if you'll dry."
         
         SS: Yeah. Well, you said that you had a run in with greybacks. He said
         that when I was over talking to Dick last time, and I was wondering
         about that time you had a run in with greybacks.
         
         MRS. BENGE: We had a cousin— he had a cousin- Johnny Sparks from back East, and
         he'd been out on the road, and he'd worked a little here and a lit
         tle there and he'd slept out on the railroad track, you know, and in
         blankets, just where he could, and he got greybacks; which is not unusual. And he
         was here a week and he slept in our bed^ and I did
         wash his clothes. And I saw those funny looking bugs on his clo
         thes after I'd washed 'em. They were dead and -he took a bath.
         But, boy, we had greybacks. And, you know, I had to wash all the
         quilts and all the sheets and all the pillow cases
         and give everybody a bath in lye soap. We used homemade
         lye soap. And, I'm tellin' you that was something.
         
         P.S.: I still have homemade soap that I made.
         And anotherithing that we did, that might be interesting, got the
         itch in the school down here. And if you think that isn't hard to
         
         MRS. BENGE: get rid of! Because, you'd get your kids cured up and the others
         aren't cured up and they're just, well, wash their hands in the same
         pan and they got it again! But I used to give 'em a bath in lye
         soap, and mix sulfur and lard and rub all over their bodies, and it
         got rid of it. You know, you go through a lot of things. Well, I
         think years and years ago, they used to have hair lice, but I never
         had anything to do with that.
         
         P.S.: Oh, yes, we did.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Did you?
         
         P.S.: When you were in Spokane working.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And you washed it in coal^ Grandma come up and helped.
         
         P.S.: Daddy made us— well— we were going to Princeton to school, I know
         the report got out, I don't think I ever had any. But he made us
         saturate our hair in mineral oil, and we had to wear it that way for
         a week. He wouldn't let us wash it out, and wear a scarf around it.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Peggy was a senior in high school.
         
         P.S.: No, I was going to school in Princeton, at the time; eight grader,
         maybe, seventh or eighth. And this cloth would become so saturated
         with oil, you know, during the day and it would run down your neck.
         I think the lice might have been simpler.
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, honey, you couldn't have been in the eighth grade.
         
         P.S.: I was going to school in Princeton at the time.
         
         MRS. BENGE: No, you was going to school in Potlatch. You went to school in Potlatch
         before I went to work at the mill.
         
         P.S.: You worked at the mill and then went to Spokane, remember? So, it
         was during this period of time. When you came back, I was going to—
         
         SS: I was going to ask you now about— you mentioned this a little bit
         before about working at the mill. And I was wondering. Now the rea
         son that came about was because there was a real shortage during the
         war? That's why the women could go and work in the mill? And what
         did you think it was like to work there?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, I don't think it hurt me any. Some^women claimed it did, but
         I didn't think so. Peggy worked there a year. I don't think it
         ever hurt you, did it?
         
         P.S.: No. Worked a lot harder at home.
         
         SS: What was the main work that you did?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, Peggy never done anything except pick lath. But, I used to
         pack lumber back over to the green— from the grader back over to
         the resaw. Or get it there somehow, shove it or pull it. Anyhow,
         I done it and clean up the mill. But I worked there four years.
         There were quite a lot of women working there.
         
         P.S.: All defense plants pretty much had women working. Remember the song,
         ROSIE THE RIVETER? You know, they had women.
         
         SS: Was most of the lumber that you were handling stuff that you could
         carry, or did you push a—
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, it come down on chains. It come from the edger down on chains.
         And as it went through the trimmer and then over onto the graders,
         and the grader found some board that needed to be cut down, and he'd
         pull it off, and then I had to get it back over to the edger. And
         I didn't have too much trouble. I didn't manhandle 'em, I got me a
         hook and hooked into it and drug it over. But, once in a while—
         and I never had any trouble getting along with men— because I done—
         you know, I worked hard— but there would be a plank, a tamarack
         plank, maybe four inches thick and twenty foot long and green,-and
         do you know anything about timber at all?
         
         SS: A little.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, you know how heavy tamarack is; and I couldn't even budge it.
         I relieved the men on the trimmer, so I knew how to do that, you know,
         straightening the boards on the trimmer, and I'd go over there and
         I'd say, "I think you're awful pretty. Gee, I think you're real nice."
         And they'd say, "Now, what do you want?" "Oh, there's some boards."
         And so, I'd spot while they went and packed the boards back. But,
         they never complained, or anything. But it just was too much for me.
         That's all. Sometimes there'd be weeks that there wouldn't be any.
         
         SS: Did the women working at the mill pretty much spend a lot of their
         time together? Like their break time?
         
         MRS. BENGE: We had our special room. And there was a bed in it. If we wanted to
         lay down at noon, we could, or ten minutes at lunch, you know. If
         we got in there early in the morning, or something, but, there was a bed in there
         for us to lay Pretty^comfortable bed.
         And we had water and lavoratories and a table and earthing. And as
         far as I know, or at least speaking for myself, the men were good
         to the women. I never had any trouble with the men anyhow. I
         worked over in Moscow eleven years; three years for girls and the
         rest of the time for the boys in fraternities and a sorority. And,
         I don't thim T lnk Xever had I had hashers in the sorority. And my hashers were just
         as cooperative
         as could be. No trouble at all.
         
         SS: You were cooking? How did you find that to be? That job; cooking
         for the college kids? Was that enjoyable work?
         
         MRS. BENGE: I had been up to Fernwood, and I'd been working in the mill up there
         and then my daughter got ill and it was the end of the season; she
         had another baby. I went down there and when I come back, well, I
         thought, "I'll just draw my unemployment this winter." And, I had
         cooked in a camp two years up there. I'd cooked in camps before.
         "And what do you do?" And I told 'em. And they said, "Well, we've
         got a job for you. The Pi Phi Sorority up here wants a cook." It
         was just right after Christmas. Well, you just about got to take it
         you know. So that got me started. But my kids were all grown then
         and I'd went up to Fernwood where Dick was working, the next summer
         and worked up there. And then in Moscow in the winter. I worked in
         Moscow eleven years. I was up there and I had surgery, and they told
         me I could go back. And, boy, I went back to work, and I thought it
         was gonna kill me. And I come back home and Doug Schofield was here
         and wanted me to come over there and cook. And, I sure did take it,
         because, I'll tell you, handling them boards up there was more than
         I could— well, it was just about to kill me. I just thought I
         couldn't take it.
         
         SS: At Potlatch or Fernwood?
         
         MRS. BENGE: At Fernwood, yeah.
         
         SS: Was that heavier work than at Potlatch? Or was it about the same?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, it was about the same, only I had to pack about eight boards,
         just literally pack 'em up four steps and pile 'em for. guy to
         resaw 'em. Which wasn't very good. Or I thought it wasn't.
         
         SS: Doesn't sound very good to me.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, not when you just got out of the hospital.
         
         SS: Well, I was thinking about sometimes— I've wondered, if say, some
         times those men at the Potlatch mill would have had any idea that
         women couldn't cut the mustard for doing the kind of work that men
         usually did. Do you think there was much of that thinking?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Right at first there was. But, as long as a woman done her work—
         and nobody kicked because I asked 'em to pack that, because they
         knew that was too much for me. And, al ways, even if I was busy and
         the lumber got to comin' awful fast on the chain, well, I'd just fly
         right in and help 'em. Get 'em straightened out, you know.. All
         those things. And I kept the place clean, slick as a whistle.
         P.S.: And most of the women were local people that lived on stump ranches.
         That means a lot of hard work; clearing land,Ait's very hard work.
         So most of them did know what hard work was.
         
         SS: Do you have an idea of about how many women there were working in
         the mill at a time? Say, during the war.
         
         MRS. BENGE: About as many as there ever was, when you was working there. How
         many was there? About?
         
         P.S.: Thirty, thirty-five. In that area. Between twenty-five and forty.
         
         SS: And-
         
         MRS. BENGE: Peggy got laid off. And she took her money and went to Moscow and
         spent it all on a suit and a hat and shoes and got married.
         
         P.S.: Furniture. Grandma, I bought a lot of furniture.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And, furniture, yeah.
         
         SS: Did many women not stick with it? Or did most of the people stick
         with it, when they started at the mill?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah, the most of 'em stuck with it. A few of 'em— oh, like one
         girl I knew— she wanted a rug, and she was a good worker, and boy
         she come up there and she just worked to beat the band, and then she
         got money enough to buy her rug and a new dinette set.
         
         SS: The wages were
         
         P.S.: We got men's wages. Which was unheard of, you know. Wait tables
         for sixty cents an hour and we went down there for— must have been
         less than that— I started at sixty-five cents an hour?
         
         MRS. BENGE:: I don't know.
         P.S.: Eighty-five. Which was really top wages, the same as five and a
         half or six and a half now.
         
         MRS. BENGE: A dollar sixty-five, you mean.
         
         P.S.: It may have been a dollar sixty-five.
         
         SS: You said you just about built the house by working there.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yeah.
         
         P.S.: So you can work pretty hard, you know, work extra hard for that
         much money.
         
         MRS. BENGE: That is, I dug the well, and put in the water, and then fixed the
         bedroom and the bathroom, in here, and then went forty-two hundred
         dollars in debt and built the rest of it.(Chuckles) But it's paid
         for. There was more than that went into it, too. See, it is from
         that there on over, and it startedAfrom the middle of the house and
         went out. So, see, I have lots of room upstairs. I used to get so
         tickled at my husband; when I first went to work at the mill, "Soon's
         I can get enough money ahead I'm gonna put a great big window in here.
         And I'm gonna put the door on this side." "Oh, no, you do that and
         the house'11 fall down for sure'" And the other day something hap
         pened and he told me, "Well, see there, now the house is all going out
         of shape. I told you it would." I put that in first, and put the
         windows in, you know, and the bathroom, and all that. And then I
         built on out, and the foundation around it, and the up
         stairs and the fireplace. The fireplace cost six hundred dollars.
         I wonder just what it would cost now.
         
         SS: A great deal more.
         
         P.S.: Two thousand.
         
         SS: At least.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Because it is a nice fireplace. And Dick just loves the windows,
         especially this one. He calls it his huntin' window! And, I like my
         house. Every bit of it!
         
         SS: A beautiful house.
         
         MRS. BENGE: It's not as good as if it had all been built at once.
         
         SS: Hardly notice it. I'd have never known if you didn't tell me, really
         that it was in parts. A lot of houses are like that.
         We were talking a little bit about whether you worked for yourself
         or worked for somebody else. And some people like one or the other.
         You were saying pretty much you think that you're just kind of bet
         ter off not working for yourself.
         
         MRS. BENGE: I don't know. Dick always worked out. Now, Herman's father
         work^out^. And Herman didn't work outAtil he got his place paid for
         and^his kids raised. Isn't that right, Peggy?
         
         P.S.: Uh-huh.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Very, very little. Maybe just a little^in a great while.
         
         P.S.: The world thought has changed, too. The general attitude of people.
         It is terribly expenseAto get set up in any kind of a business.
         When we first started farming, and that's not so long ago; we didn't
         have any money, so we used old bed springs. We'd go along in our
         pickup and spread the seed, we'd use old bedsprings a harrow.
         Well, nowdays, this would be out of the question. It would be impossible. So, it depends
         on how bad you want to work for yourself.
         If you can stand the guff, starting out. It's very difficult. There
         ian't any of our children ^do, they could have taken over the farm.
         But it wasn't in the cards.
         
         MRS. BENGE: How much land do you have now?
         P.S.: Four hundred and forty. But that's beside the matter, it's the in
         dividual person. My husband is just such a sort of individual that
         if somebody else can run a business, there's no reason why I can't
         But this has changed now If you were into business for yourself, it would be very,
         very difficult. Even
         without interest, to find the money to back you. So, I think our
         young people have turned to education, to improve themselves rather
         than to start their own business. Not that it's impossible, but
         far more difficult than when we were getting started.
         
         SS: Did you say that Dick did farm once for a few years?
         
         MRS. BENGE: About two years. He's no farmer. I know the last year he farmed,
         he went eight hundred dollars in the hole. He is just not the farmer.
         
         P.S.: It's a matter of working for yourself. When you work for someone
         else for so many, many years, unless you have a dream of doing some
         thing for yourself, it's a matter of putting in the hours. Then you
         get your money, and after you've done this for so many, many years,
         you come home and unless there is someone to oversee you and to tell
         you to go ahead, it's hard to get the job done. You put in your
         twelve hours, but the job isn't done. And this is not being criti
         cal; no way. This is the habit you've developed.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Johnny farmed one year, and he raised a good crop. But, I bawled
         Dick out once. He had a '30 Cat, and it takes a lot of gas, and he
         had a team here, but he had three sections df harrow which the team
         would have drug. And he was going over the ground with that Cat.
         It just didn't pay.
         
         SS: Well, when we talked about it, Dick was saying he preferred the woods
         work.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Oh, yeah. He always liked it. He thought he liked to farm, but he
         didn't. And we was milkin' cows and when he started farming, "I
         ain't got time to fool with them." And he turned 'em all out. I
         was working at the mill at the time, and he should have been able to
         make it good, but he didn't.
         
         PS: In my opinion, it all boils down to the theory if you're working for
         yourself, you take care of all the little jobs, see that all the
         little jobs are done. The big jobs'll take care of themselves. When
         it« time it gets done. But the little jobs; fixing the fence,
         the little jobs,^you take care of them, the big ones'll take care of
         themselves. And someone that works out for wages or really don't
         see the little jobs, take care of the big jobs, and the little jobsit
         collapses the big jobs.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Dick was, he was a master logger. He was very, very, very good at
         his job. Excellent logger. And people always come— oh, in late
         years, when it's changed so much, he probably wouldn't be so invaluable— "Come and
         look over this timber for me, lay where you think
         I should put the roads." And do this and do that. And he was a very,
         very excellent farmer.
         
         SS: So Dick really had a fine reputation. That doesn't surprise me at
         all. Because he certainly seems to know logging from one end to the
         other.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes, he's a good logger and he understands it, and he knows how to
         take advantage of it. He knows what logs is. He's just real good
         at it. That's just the truth.
         
         SS: Would you tell me a little more about this land clearing that you
         would do together? It was quite a job and one that would never end.
         
         MRS. BENGE: After we got this steam engine, it wasn't so bad. But, I'll tell
         ya, this hillside up here, I know, I worked at it all one spring.
         And, Like I say, I put on coveralls— cover, you know, completelyand
         then when I'd come home,AI'd turn 'em wrong side out and come in
         and put cold cream on my face. I couldn't wash my face, because there
         was so much black, you know, so much of that lye in there. But that
         was hard work. Pick up and pull it over, and pile it together, and
         chop it up. AI think one spring when it got— when I had to quit be
         cause it got too dry, I counted sixty-three stumps that I could stand
         on and they would come up to here. It was getting kinda hot one Sat
         urday and some other boys was over there on the creek$layin' and I
         had all the kids up there picking up sticks and the older girls was
         in the house doing— gettin' supper and doing the ironing and things
         that had to be done, and Johnny'd stop and he'd look over at the
         creek and Dick was up there with us because it happened to be on
         Saturday, "Come on, here, pick that up. You get busy." And Peggy
         never had to be told. She just plowed right into it. And he looked
         over there and he said, "Oh, dear,"— and there was a dog a layin*
         in the shade of a log, and he said, "I wish I was a dog!" (Chuckles)
         "I wish I was a dog! " But, he learned to drive the Cat when he was
         quite young, and he then went to work for other farmers. Two years
         he worked for Walsters. Hugo Walster, down here. And, made good
         money.
         
         SS: Before you married Dick and came up here, where was it that you lived
         before?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, I was born in Pomeroy, Washington. And then, my mother died
         when Iwas eighteen months old, and then my grandparents took me to
         Winchester (Idaho). And I was there til I was about seven. Then
         we moved to Lewiston. And I was in Lewiston til I was eighteen—
         seventeen. Then I was twenty-two when I married Dick.
         
         SS: What did you think of this area when you first moved over here?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, I come up and got a job as a hasher— working in a logging camp
         in the cookshack, you know. Waiting table . And, oh, I was just
         busy as a bee, you know. Just aflyin' around there. And this guy
         settin' over there, see. And he smiled at me so nice and said, "Is
         there any warm hotcakes?" And, I looked him over— and he was thirty
         and I thought, "Huh, boy, I'll bet he's good to his wife." Then I
         had a blind date, and it turned out to be him. And, I looked at him
         and I said, "Oh, so you're the one they call Dick Benge, are you?"
         He said, "Part of the time." And, my goodness, I couldn't get rid of
         him! I couldn't get rid of him, he was right there every time I
         turned around.
         
         SS: He must have taken a liking to you.
         
         MRS. BENGE: He evidently did, because, he was right there all the time. He was
         more lumberjack style. He didn't have anything the first two times he took me out
         except anew pair of bib overalls and aclean shirt.
         And one time he wore a pair of Malone pants. And the next time he
         come to get me he had a brand new suit, and his tie was on crooked!
         Bless his heart! Yep. His tie was on crooked.
         
         SS: I was gonna ask you about church, too. Around here when you were
         first married and with the little kids, was there a community church
         here in Princeton at that time?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, yes. But then they went mostly to the Nazarene Church. cause the
         Nazarene minister would come out and get them, and I didn't
         go. Wasn't that terrible?
         
         SS: Not at all.
         
         MRS. BENGE: I wish I would have. But I didn't. Then after I became a Christian
         I prayed so hard — my kids went to Bible School. They weren't com
         pletely ignorant. And they went to Sunday School,— that they would
         come to the Lord, they did. Peggy joined the Catholic
         Church, and Judy joined the Lutheran and Johnny joined the Baptist
         and (kitha joined the Christian. Johnny's a Mason now.
         
         P.S.: And we have one sister that is a Mormon, and one's a First Christian.
         Religion is very seldom discussed with a family, that way.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Cora Belle joined the Mormon Church.
         P.S.: Mormon, Catholic, Lutheran,. Christian, Mason.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, that should be a lesson for me, shouldn't it? Yeah. It doesn't
         matter where they come, as long as they belong to the Lord. We just
         don't discuss it too much. We don't avoid it. No.
         
         PS.: But no discussions about it.
         
         SS: Sounds like the family, though, is still kind of close.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Oh, you'll never find a family that's closer. You never could find
         a family that was any clos(t)er. Or that stick together when anything
         happens to one. They're right there.
         In fact, my sister is probably the best friend I've ever had. Judy
         the one that was here, when you were here before. We're just real
         good friends. I don't think I've ever had a better friend. Sister?
         It doesn't make abit of difference, she's my friend. We've always
         been real close. And my husband and her are especially close. Now
         this sounds ridiculous, because they're not related. Imean, but
         they're just exceptionally close. I don't think that if either one
         
         P.S.: of them ever needed help, I am sure that's just right where they'd
         go. And this is great! He's far closer to her than he is to any
         of his sisters and she is far closer to him than her brother. We're
         close to my brother, but family wise, we don't know him any more as
         a friend, let's put it that way; he's a brother, sure, we love him,
         but we don't know him as a person because he's been in California
         for fifteen years. And as a friend— we know he's there if we need
         him. But distance has lessened this friendship-type thing.
         
         MRS. BENGE: When Judy was growing up, you know, and starting to go with the boys,
         she was a few years younger than Johnny, and Boy, he kept an eagle
         eye on her. I'm tellin' you. (Chuckles) One time in Princeton the
         lavoratories was out behind the house, and she come and asked me if
         she could go out, and I said, "Come right back." And I was helping
         back in the kitchen, you know, and I guess she didn't even get that
         far because there was some boys out there started a hollerin' at her,
         you know, and Johnny just went and grabbed her around the waist and
         brought her in the house and sit her down! She bawled a while, and I
         just thought, weii, let'em—Alet him handle it. And pretty soon I
         looked around and they was out on the floor dancin'. And if she was
         goin' with a new boy that he wasn't sure about, he'd follow 'em all
         the way home, and back his car up back of their's and wait til
         she come in the house. (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Do you think families are as close now as the families used to be in
         the early days? Seems to me the families used to be a lot closer
         than the average is today.
         
         MRS. BENGE: We're all close together when we're together, but the three of us
         are here, and then Clair's clear down in lower California and Johnny's
         up around Arcadia, and we don't see Clair so very much, she'd got
         six kids and she's got about all she can handle.
         
         P-S: I think the difference is that , we strive so much to become individuals,
         they st^Lve for this from the time they're in the first grade
         on, to become an individual; do your own thing, you know this type
         of thing. And families are close but when they get in school and
         each individual goes their own way. And we used to all go the same
         way. Another thing that's good or bad, but I think it has done a
         lot to destroy— not destroy— it doesn't encourage this family unit
         closeness. Of course, we were just very fortunate, and the boys are
         so very, very close.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And they're all together, yet.
         
         P.S.: Yeah, they're all home at least once a week, and even when I'm down
         here, they all come at least once a week and sometimes twice a week.
         
         SS: Do you think that maybe the most of families were tended to be real
         close, like back in the early days when you were growing up? Do you
         think families were a lot closer then than most of 'em are nowdays?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Well, see, I only had one half sister. And my grandparents raised me.
         
         SS: That's right.
         
         MRS. BENGE: And, of course, in the summer when school was out, we'd go around
         and visit all summer to each one of the boys, you know. And she had
         seven sons and a daughter. And, my father married again, and we'd
         go and visi t every one of 'em. Oh, stay a week, ten days and maybe
         with my Aunt than that. So, I got to know all of my cou
         sins real well. And I guess the family was close. They never had a
         great many family gatherings; there were nearly always some of 'em
         there. And, then, the ones that lived close would come for Christ
         mas dinner, but they never come very far to come to a big dinner. I
         try to have Thanksgiving dinner. I have pretty good luck, they pret
         ty much come, and you can't insist on— if it was your kids, but
         your grandkids kinda get tired of going up to the old folks. They
         don't act it, but then, they pretty much come, don't they Peggy?
         
         P.S.: Yes. Transportation in those days did alter the fact that they moved
         away. That they weren't as close then.
         
         MRS. BENGE: Johnny has been up here he came up in August, wasn't it?
         P.S.: He was here in January.
         
         MRS. BENGE: For a reunion? And he's been up once since.
         
         P.S.: I meant when you were growing up, do you think transportation did
         alter the ?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes.
         
         P.S.: The family togetherness type of thing?
         
         SS: Did you have much to do with the school? Did parents become much
         involved in it?
         
         MRS. BENGE: No. The only thing is that I gave dances down here in the schoolhouse,
         About four of 'em, to get money to buy— when we had the log schoolhouse
         down here.
         
         SS: To get money to buy what?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Seats, and some more blackboards and things for the school. And then
         the only other thing I done was when they were consolidating and the
         board said we cannot afford a bus, we just can't. And Peggy was married
         then, weren't you?A And I put on a small half hour play, and
         two smaller ones. And then had a basket social and a dance. And
         then when we had that I got up and announced that if I could get
         enough volunteers that wanted to be in it, that we would put on a
         full length play, and maybe we could raise the rest of the money for
         the bus. We put it on three times. But I never worked with a group
         of children, or a group of young people that was so willing and
         worked together so good. And then, another thing, they were all high
         schoolers, and they would stop as they came home on the bus, most of
         'em was on the bus— and Iwould be there and have the hall warm,
         and we'd practice until about six-thirty or seven. And then they
         took turns bringing food, you know, and we'd eat our dinner and wash
         our dishes. And then practice until nine. And that wasn't so late
         but what the kids could go home and do some homework if they had to.
         About three nights a week. And we put it on three times.
         
         SS: Do you remember what play it was?
         
         : 0h yes Object Matrimony. And they was twelve children in it. I
         don't know, the one down hereVas a two and ahalf hour play and we
         had something in between each play, you know, there was three acts,
         and it was all one scene, but—
         
         What was Object Matrimony about? Sounds like it was about marriage.
         Object Matrimony. Well, there were these girls, these six girls,
         and there was no boys around or anything, and they was wantin' boy
         friends, and they didn't know, so one of 'em— one of the boys come
         in, that was a reporter there and he said, "Well, let me put it in
         the paper." Idon't remember what the ad was, but then, he put it in
         the paper, and then these guys showed up. And Clair was the cook,
         and she was an older girl, and Johnny was the old soldier— dressed
         up in an old soldier suit— that come courtin' her! Everybody got
         married in the end. (Chuckles) All six of 'em! And it was cute,
         wasn't it honey?
         
         P.S.: Yeah, it was. Lot of work.
         
         SS: And it{quite a bit of money then?
         
         MRS. BENGE: Yes, it raised the money.
         
         SS: What hall was this? Was this in the schoolhouse?
         
         MRS. BENGE: It was inAPrinceton Hall.
         
         SS: The Princeton Hall?
         
         SS: Sounds really like fun.
         
         P.S.: That isn't the first time you had done it. Other high school kids
         wouldn't have anything to do in the winter, you know, and gas was
         at a premium; it wasn't available, during the war; we had stamps to
         get gas, and when the stamps were gone, that was it.
         
         END
         
         Transcribed by Frances Rawlins, August 15, 1976
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13372</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Benge3</previous>
      <next>Benscoter</next>
      <disp_name>Benge4</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
