<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">8/15/1973</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Arthur Bjerke, 1973-08-15, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>0:31:05</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Bjerke, Arthur</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer; carpenter; logger</occupation>
      <birthyear>1886</birthyear>
      <residence>Brush Creek, Deary</residence>
      <origin>Came from Norway with family, who homesteaded in 1891</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#funerals"&gt;funerals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13607</file_name>
      <mp3>13608.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13608.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
      <!--   <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Family moved from South Dakota to Genesee in 1890; land clearing; difficult to get
               food
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father takes homestead. The first clearing of
               land. They eat eggs all the time.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Childhood memories; wolves; African Americans in school; Joe Wells</title>
            <synopsis>Childhood memories: wolves around the sod shanty;
               sights on the journey out. The first class at Wells' school.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Father worked in Sweden timber</title>
            <synopsis>His father worked in Sweden; he meets a man he
               worked for 40 years later in Troy.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Early homesteaders by name; Eric Larson killed by brass button</title>
            <synopsis>Litany of early homesteaders. Some couldn't
               afford to file on homestead. Eric Larson killed
               by a brass button. Early visiting and dances.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Joe Wells; African American family</title>
            <synopsis>The black family of Joe Wells.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1620</time>
            <title>First settlers in Deary; "Seven Devils"</title>
            <synopsis>The first settlers around Deary ware seven Germans,
               giving country name of "Seven Devils". Large
               group of South Carolinians, among early settlers.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Native Americans nearby</title>
            <synopsis>Indians came through often, (continued)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Arthur helped Native American with his wagon; blacksmith parts;</title>
            <synopsis>Arthur fixes an Indian's wagon tongue, and he
               appreciates it. Arthur likes to be with them.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>Arthur herded cattle; becomes a good shooter</title>
            <synopsis>Arthur herds cattle from range to range. He
               becomes a crack shot, he has a good dog.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Trading horses with Native Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Arthur trades horses with an Indian and gets a
               tough one.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Interactions with Mox Mox (Native American)</title>
            <synopsis>Mox Mox didn't like timber to be cut. Signs of
               Indians: rock for grinding camas; round bare spots
               where tepees stood.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>-->
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Note: This is a partial recording of the first interview. Parts of the audio have been lost. However, the full transcript is available for download.</title>
            <synopsis>Arthur understood four languages as a boy, even
               German. His parents didn't speak English well.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point> 
		 <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Arthur knew four languages as a child (Swedish, Danish, Norwegian, and English)</title>
            <synopsis>Arthur understood four languages as a boy, even
               German. His parents didn't speak English well.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Arthur's father hurt while hunting; father deeds Arthur the farm upon his death; Jorgeson
               store and caskets
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>One side of father's face blown off while hunting
               wolves in Norway. Place deeded to Arthur when
               father died. A bargain on a good casket at Jorgeson's store. Jorgeson underpriced
               the
               other Deary store by buying by the carload.
               Arthur recognizes Jorgeson's boy forty years
               later.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Building the Cornell railroad; dangerous situations; murder and explosions</title>
            <synopsis>Building the grade for the W. I. M. rail
               road through Cornell. Italians murdered and
               buried along the grade. An explosion. Arthur
               works on a high trestle. Italians were good
               people, some stayed; Sam Piwash became a
               successful logger.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Herding cattle in meadow rangelands. Experiences with Nez Perces. Family
         homesteading. Neighbors. Construction of WISM. Father's accident and death. 8-15-73
         1.5
         hr 19p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: So ya just been sitting around, huh?
         
         ARTHUR BJERKE: Oh, getting around, getting so dang stiff and stumbly that I
         can't get around much.
         
         SAM: Yeah, I wanted to go back and ask you some things, the way we was talking
         last time, about the old days. How did your parents come about coming out
         here and getting the place that they got?
         
         AB: They homesteaded it. You know, we come here in 1890 to Genesee from Dakota.
         And dad worked on tha railroad when they built it through Troy. And he got
         acquainted with some people that homesteaded down here on Bear Creek, right
         down below Deary. So we moved up there, and then he come up here and he took
         this homestead, and we moved up here. And that's about all there is to it.
         And we moved on the place the 17th day of March, 1891. And our neighbor
         over here, Martin Olson, he moved on his place the 18th day of March, 1891.
         He stayed with us 'tils he got the cabin built over there.
         
         SAM: Were there people here at that time?
         
         AB: Oh there was a few. Well, Louie Halseth and M. S. Perry and them up
         around Helmer was here, and the Lawrences.
         
         SAM: What was the land like then?
         
         AB: Well It was pretty heavy timbered. But the Indians had kept it burnt off
         so it wasn't much underbrush. You could drive pret'near anywheres you wanted
         to in the open timber.
         
         SAM: What did they do, your parents, to start homesteading here? What did they
         do on the land?
         
         AB: Well, they started in cleaning it up a little, and breaking up a little
         land. Then they slashed down a bunch of timber on the flats here, and
         burnt off the logs. It was all black pine. And then they grubbed out the
         brush roots that was, and then seeded it to timothy and cut hay with the
         scythe to keep a few cows.
         
         SAM: Was it hard? Hard living? Was it hard getting by?
         
         AB: Oh yeah. Well the first year, you know it was pretty hard to get any
         groceries or anything. We had a few chickens, and by gosh we lived pret'near
         on bread and eggs. And I got so that I believe it was 30 years before I'd
         eat an egg after that. And I don't care for an egg now. I can eat an egg,
         a time or two, and I don't want another egg again.
         
         SAM: You got plenty sick of it.
         
         AB: Well had a few chickens, and they laid awful good.
         
         SAM: What do you remember from when you were a little boy?
         
         AB: Oh, I can remember quite a few things all right. You know, I remember when
         we was in Dakota. We lived in the cellar back there, that is, in a sod
         shanty. And there was quite a lot of wolves back there. And I can remember
         my sister, she got up on the top of the roof on that sod shanty, and sit and
         barked at the wolves. And she was 97 years the day before yesterday; and
         she lives in Wenatchee. And then I remember when we come across^the mountains,
         there had been a train wreck, and there was kind of a lake there, and a car
         wreck, and spilled a bunch of cattle into the lake. They were laying out
         there floating in the water, I ,can remember that. And then I can remember
         when we got to Spokane, it was after the Spokane fire, and Spokane just had
         a rough lumber shack for a depot.
         
         SAM: What do you remember from when you first come down here?
         
         AB: Oh I can remember it was kind of a rough country. And then,our next
         neighbor up here that lived up on this place here, their name was Halseth.
         They had four boys. We went to the first school together. That was I and
         my sister, and the four Halseth boys, and Hawkin Peterson, and the three
         nigger kids, that was the first school kids. There was 10 of us. I can
         remember that.
         
         SAM: Did you work around the house a lot when you were a boy?
         
         AB:; Oh yeah. Yeah, I kind of learnt, well, built on the house here a little.
         And after I got part grown up, a carpenter worked here, and I worked with
         him and I kind of learnt to be a kind of a carpenter. So after I growed up
         I done a lot of carpenter work around through the country. Yes, there is
         houses out on the ridge and in Deary and Bovill and Helmer that I've built.
         
         SAM: You told me a story about a man that your father met who he had known a
         long time ago. Will you tell me that story?
         
         AB: Yeah. Well, dad went over from Norway to Sweden and went to work in the
         timber up there. And there was an English outfit that bought a bunch of
         timber in Sweden. Of course they'd have to log out to the small creeks.
         And the timber was shipped down to the ocean and loaded on the boat and shipped
         to England and sawed there. The biggest timber he took out up there and they
         sawed—and they made a lot of square timber—and the biggest square timber
         he took out was a 14 by 14, 76 feet long. That takes quite a stick of timber
         to make that kind of timber! Then, of course they couldn't log in the
         summer when it was dry; and then they worked around for the farmers there,
         and cleared land and one thing another, just to keep the horses busy. And
         he worked for a fella by the name Sahlin up there, and broke some land for
         him. He wasn't married and dad wasn't neither. And dad worked up there ten
         years, and he went back to Norway and he got married, and Sahlin is married
         a widow, and she had a boy, his name was Wallner. And they come to this
         country, and this Wallner started a dry goods store in Troy. Well, there
         was a lot of Swedes and Norweigans in Troy and around on this side, and of
         course they all went to Wallner's to trade. And dad was in there one day,
         and a Swede come in there, and he talks Swede to beat the dickens. And dad
         says to him, he says, "I hear you are from Jamtland,"
         The fella straightened up and he says, '.'Have you been in Oamtland?"
         Dad says, "Yes." He says he was out there 10 year. Well this fella
         wanted to know what he'd done out there. Well, dad says in the winters they
         worked for the Dixon Timber Company there, logging, and in the summer, when
         they couldn't log, they'd work for the farmers around there, clear land,
         break land, and one thing another. And this fella, he straightened up and
         he said, "It surely wasn't you that broke my plow?"
         Well, dad says, "I don't know whether I broke your plow or not," but he
         says, "I know I broke my own quite a few time." They got to talking, and by
         god dad has broke land for this Sahlin in Sweden, 40 years before,
         and they come and met here in Troy! Isn't that something?
         
         SAM: It sure is.
         
         AB: Well, Magnuson, he homesteaded down here, and then there was another fella
         by the name of Eric Larson that homesteaded down there. But then they couldn't
         get money, you know—like Eric Larson and Ben Lee—so they could file on
         that land at a certain time. And that's went back and been state land. But
         Magnuson bought that Eric Larson's land, so Ed Magnuson has got that. And
         he sold it to Carlson from down here by Troy, so they have got it now. And
         Eric Larson, he made a mistake. He come up here to hunt, and he slipped and
         fell on a log and shot himself accidently. He had them high cuffs with brass
         buttons in. Well it blowed off half of his arm and tore one of them buttons
         out of his cuff, and that hit him in the mustache and it stopped back and out
         of the eye. And that was a brass button, and that killed him.
         And then the Lawrences up here, at the old post office where Dansville
         was, they homesteaded up there about in the 90's. And Louie Halseth and
         M. S. Perry come in about '98. And Andrew Berg and the Erickson up there on
         the meadows, they come in about '89.
         
         SAM: Did the different homesteaders visit each other very much?
         
         AB: Oh yeah, they visited quite a lot together. By god they were more sociable
         then than they are now. By god you'd meet a neighbor on the road—there
         was all horse and wagon—they'd pull in under a shady spot somewheres and
         sit there and visit for an hour or so. And first I could remember—well hell,
         it was way up into the '30's you know—by god, pret'near every place pret'near
         every Saturday night, there would be a dance in some of the old cabins, and
         they'd all be there. And there was always somebody that could play. They'd
         play, and the women'd bring a lunch, and they'd have a big midnight lunch
         and maybe they'd dance 'til daylight and have a good time. But now, by god
         you don't see one another anymore.
         There was a fella down the other night—well it was the 13th he was
         down—that used to work for me on the thrashing machine. He worked for me
         about six years straight. And his sister was down. Well, this fella and
         his wife live down in Oregon around Salem somewheres, and his sister lives
         up here in this side of Deary. She fell here a year ago and broke her hip
         so she can't get around very good; she is pret'near my age. And they used
         to be along too on the parties. Well hell, there was parties all over. And
         even the niggers was along,
         
         SAM: You mean Doe Wells and his children?
         
         AB: Well, that is the younger part of them, that is Chuck and Mary and them.
         Roy didn't dance.
         
         SAM: How well did those kids fit in? Did they get teased a lot about being
         Negroes?
         
         AB: No, hell no, they got along good with the white. And they associated with
         the white right along. Goddamit, if it was a party with the whites, the
         niggers was right along. Hell I've danced with them niggers lots of times.
         And by god they were good dancers too.
         
         SAM: What was Joe Wells like? Do you remember?
         
         AB: Oh, he was a pretty good size nigger. But his wife was pretty light colored.
         I think she was kind of a mulatto. Oh year, I remember them. You know I can
         remember the first time I seen them niggers, I was just a kid. Boy I was
         scared to death of them. But it didn't take me long to get over that, when
         we started to go to school.
         
         SAM: Was there a lot of joking about them being Negroes instead of whites?
         
         AB: No, not much. Old Doe, you know, he used to say he was the only white man
         up around here, the rest of them was Swedes. Old Doe he used to say, "I
         like my whiskey, but Lou likes her tabacco." Well, the second house they
         had up there, it was an old lumber floor, and knotholes had fell out of the
         lumber. And by god, you know, she'd chew tobacco, and she'd sit there, and
         by god she could spit through them knotholes just as good as anybody. Well
         finally she died, and of course Doe kept a-drinkin', and whiskey went out of
         fashion, so that it was all moonshine; and he got too much of that moonshine,
         and that killed him. He come out with the Wells boys from Carolina. And
         about the first settlers in around down below Deary was Carolinians. Well,
         really the first bunch that settled up in here was seven Germans, but they
         left pretty quick, biggest part of them. One of them was Mike Tebor and
         one, his name was Albert Riggs. And down below here, they started in calling
         this the Seven Devil's Country, on account of them seven Germans.
         
         SAM: But they didn't stay.
         
         AB: They didn't stay. They just stayed a year or two and they left.
         
         SAM: Who were these South Carolinians?
         
         AB: Well there was Frank Wells and Crom Wells, and a fella by the name of Cole,
         and Mark Rogers and Bert Rogers...
         
         SAM: Well, you got most of 'em.
         
         AB: And Charlie Burlinghouse, and Frank and Mace McCoy, and Frank Ellis and
         Terry Ellis and old Hinchley...
         
         SAM: Did they all come out together from Carolina?
         
         AB: They come pretty well all together.
         
         SAM: So you think they knew each other back there?
         
         AB: Oh yeah, a lot of them did. Well, Cole and the Wells boys and Mark Rogers
         and them, they knew one another, they come right from the same place.
         
         SAM: Do you know anything about the Indians that were here in the old days? Did
         you used to see them?
         
         AB: Oh, we used to see them quite a lot. They used to pass by here quite
         often. There used to be quite a lot of huckleberries here. And there always
         used to be a bunch of Indians stop up there. A lot of times they'd stop
         right down in the yard here and get water here. There was one Indian that
         come along one time, and he's broke his wagon tongue, and he stopped, and he
         wanted to know...
         
         (End' of Side A)
         
         AB: ...And he wanted to know if I had any haywire, because he broke his wagon
         tongue. I took a look at it and I says, "Hell, you don't want any haywire
         for that." Because I've learnt so I was a pretty fair blacksmith. Well
         I went down in the shop, and I had a tongue just like it. So I took the
         irons off from that that I'd built, and put on it to brace it. And I took
         them up, and a couple, three, four bolts, and I drilled some holes; knocked
         the bolts out of the holes, and I put this iron on top, and put it on, and
         fixed his wagon tongue. It was a heavy hack he had. Well you know, I never
         been thanked so much in all of my life as I was from that Indian. Well
         there was years afterwards, every time he'd come by, he'd always stop, and
         he always wanted to know if I remember when I fixed the wagon tongue for him.
         There was a bunch of trees along the road out here, and they'd always stop
         there and have lunch.
         
         Oh yeah, they used to be quite a few Indians here. I remember, you
         know, they used to stop, well I was just a little bit of a kid, you know.
         And they were telling around that Indians stole kids, you know, God, when
         them Indians come along, you know, mother was scared to death that the
         Indians would steal me. Well I wasn't afraid of the Indians. The only
         ones I was afraid of was the nigger kids. I always wanted to get out with
         the Indians when they'd stop and have lunch outside!
         
         Well, when I growed up, I herded cattle for a fella down there by
         Moscow. He lived out on that catty-corner road that want across from Viola
         to Palouse. He was raised on the same place that dad was in Norway. And
         you know, there, they went by the name of the place; so he was the same
         name that dad was. His name was Ivor, and he had a brother by the name Henry;
         and there was one more of 'em, I can't think of his first name, and a horse
         kicked him to death. He had a few cattle, and he brought 'em up here, and
         I took caieof his cattle for a year or two. And then finally, him and Hooker
         was raised in the same place in Norway, they put their cattle together, so
         it made about 400 head. Well, I was about 16, 17. So they got me to herd
         them. And they had the Smith Meadow leased back of the Cherry Butte there.
         And those days, you know, you could keep the sheep off two miles from leased
         land, so they couldn't move in. We'd move the cattle up there in the spring.
         And then they had the Horse Ranch leased. And we'd keep 'em up there in
         the Smith Meadow for awhile; then we'd move up there on the Horse Ranch.
         Then they had the Shattuck's and Hughes' Meadow—at that big meadow on this
         side of Elk River where the road crosses the meadow there—they had that
         leased. So when we'd keep 'em on the Horse Ranch awhile, so the grass would
         get short, we'd move 'em over on the Shattuck's and Hughes Meadow, and keep
         'em there 'tils it was pret'near time to move out.
         
         I was with the cattle all the time. Had a tent I lived in. I had a
         little black dog, and by god he was a dandy. And those days, you know, you
         could buy .22 cartridges for 10 cents a box, that is, the .22 short or three
         boxes for 25 cents. And .22 longs, 15 cents a box, or two for a quarter.
         Well all I was doing, I had a .22, I'd shoot and practice every day. Hell,
         I wouldn't think of shooting at a bird's body. If I couldn't shoot his head
         off from the horse's back I wasn't hitting. I'd take a bunch of .22 cartridges
         and set 'em up on 50 feet, and if I couldn't knock them empty shells off in
         50 feet, nine out of ten, I wasn't shooting. Well Hooker's partner, he had
         a .22 Winchester, they were about a 25 caliber. So he kept at it up there
         at my camp; and every time he'd come up, every week or two, of course we'd
         have a shooting match, a penny a shot. But we never could get but a penny
         or two ahead, because he was a damn good shot too.
         Well that dog I had, I hardly took him with me in the woods. He'd
         stay right there at the camp, because there was quite a few bears around,
         and by god he'd keep the bear out of the camp. And that dog, he'd always
         lay right at the foot of my bed every night, and nothing could get in that
         camp. But he was a damn good cattle dog. And he was a good hunting dog
         too.
         
         Well, when we'd move the cattle, Andy'd come up. And I!d have them
         pretty well bunched, 50, 60, 70 head to the bunch, and I'd know pret'near
         where I had every cattle. And we'd gather 'em one day, and next day we'd
         move 'em. Well, we'd move 'em down to the Horse Ranch, and then next day
         we'd take 'em down here. Then we'd divide them here. Then maybe Hooker
         would be up, and Andy and Hooker'd take their cattle down that way. And
         Ivor Bjerke would come from down there, and he'd be up here, and we'd take
         his cattle to Moscow. I've drove a herd of cattle right down the main
         street in Moscow in the early day. They'd be surprised now if they'd see
         a herd of cattle coming down Main Street.
         
         SAM: Did you ever have trouble with rustlers?
         
         AB: No. I was up there on the Horse Ranch one time. I always had two horses.
         I used one, and I'd ride the other one. I'd get up just about four o'clock
         in the morning, and go around every bunch of cattle, and if some of 'em was
         a-gettin' too far back up, I'd turn 'em back, so they wouldn't get too far
         out. And one morning I saddled up a horse. And I haven't put up the rope;
         I just turned the horses loose with the long rope that they'd drag around
         in the field there, I generally had a chunk that they'd drag so they wouldn't
         go too far. This morning an Indian come along. He stopped. And he could
         talk pretty fair, and finally he says, "You want to trade horses?"
         "No, I don't want to trade horses."
         He set there quite a little while. He says, "Trade horses?"
         "No," I says, "I've got a pretty good horse." He had an awful nice
         looking horse. I had a kind of an old saddle on my horse, it was been used
         quite a lot.
         
         He set there a little and finally he says, "How you trade horses, saddle,
         the whole business?" Well he had a damn good saddle on the horse. I stood
         and I looked at him. I was just kind of a-wondering. I kind of thought
         maybe he stold that horse, but it was no brand on it. Finally I traded with
         him. He got off and and he get onto my horse. I get onto his horse. I
         rode out and the horse was all right. I made my trip and come in, and stopped
         awhile for lunch and went out again.
         
         That night I put a rope on him, and I tied him up to a stump out there
         on the meadow. Next morning I went out there, I thought I'd get him and
         saddle him. He acted pretty damn spooky. And I went to saddle him, and by
         god he throwed the saddle offa couple times before I got it cinched. Finally
         I got my saddle on. And those days I could ride pret'near anything that had
         hair on it. I got onto him and say boy, if you ever seen a horse that could
         buck, that sonofabitch did! Buck? But it didn't last long, when he seen
         he could throw me, he quit. But you know, I had to break him every morning.
         
         Well, there was a fella by the name Dosh Lamphear down there in the
         Hog Meadow. He was quite a horse trader. One day I rode the horse down
         there. I says to Dosh Lamphear. I says, "I've got a horse here I'd like
         to trade for a horse." I says, "He's kind of a mean horse to ride. I don't
         like one that's kind of mean to ride in the morning. Because a fella up
         there in the woods all alone, you never know what's liable to happen, you
         might get hurt, and nobody come along for a week or two."
         "Well," he says, "I got two, three horses here. I'll trade you for
         one of em." So finally I traded. I got a pretty fair looking horse from
         him. And the horse was nice and gentle. I put the saddle on the horse
         and went back up there. I got along fine with the horse.
         And it was only a week or two after that. This fella's nephew that
         lived over here, they kind of had an outlaw horse they couldn't drive worth
         a damn, he was balky. So he went up there and traded for a horse. He got
         this outlaw, and he wanted to know if they could break him all right. "Well,"
         Dosh says, "I don't know if you can ride him or not. Arthur drove him, rode
         him when he brought him in." And Ole went to get on the horse, and he
         got on the horse, and just as he landed on his back, he landed about 15 feet
         ahead of the horse in the road. (Laughs.) Well, he got up and they caught
         the horse again, and led the horse down. Hell, they couldn't no more drive
         that horse than they could fly! So finally they had take him up there, pay
         a little to boot and get another horse. And I don't know what Dosh ever done
         with him, because that Dosh was quite a horse trader.
         
         SAM: Can you remember any other run-ins that you had with Indians?
         
         AB: No, nothing else, just visited with »em. Visited with Mox Mox a few times.
         He was a pretty good Indian. Yeah, there was lot of horses down there—
         they'd go down and buy horses from him. Old Mox Mox was a good Indian.
         to He used to come up, and he didn't like see that they sold the timber to the
         company. "No," he says, "they spoil the country," which they did. Oh in the
         early days there used to be a lot of Indians come by here. But there ain't
         too many Indians left anymore.
         
         SAM: What was Mox Mox like?
         
         AB: Oh, he was a pretty tall Indian. He wasn't a bad looking Indian. And he
         could talk pretty good too. No, when they first started Bovill, you know,
         the town up there, old Mox Mox used to come up there quite a little. And he
         told Bovill that "They're spoiling the country now," he said. He wasn't
         coming back no more.
         
         Well when we settled out here, this flat over on this side used to be
         kind of a slough, and we drained it out; and when we went to break it out,
         we struck rocks once in awhile. There was quite a lot of flat rooks.
         They claim that the Indians has used them to grind camas for flour. Well
         one place down here, we struck a place, it was a bunch of rocks; they were
         built in a straight line and out that way and out that way about 30 inches
         wide, and about six and a half feet long, and you know, they were dug down
         in the ground that deep. We dug 'em out, and we kept a-lookin', and dad
         says, "I'll bet maybe we'll find some bones off froFm.an old Indian in here."
         But we never found none. But it's been something in way early days that the
         Indians has had there.
         
         And then it used to be places, round like that, that grass wouldn't
         grow. And right in the middle the grass would grow. And that spot'd be
         bare. I think it's been where there's been teepees and hides put down to
         sleep on, and it's killed the ground. I think that's what it's been. They
         all said it'd been war dances, but I don't think so. But you see lots of
         them places. Used to be a lot of 'em when we first come here, but now of
         course grass is growed over em.
         
         SAM: So that's all that's left of the Indians here.
         
         AB: Yeah. Oh, we used to find a few arrowheads once in awhile, and one thing
         another. We used to find quite a few of them but never took care of them.
         I'm kind of sorry of that. (Walks to a table:) Look at them. They claim
         the Indians used them as a mill grind camas with. I had quite a few of
         them out here, sitting out here, but they all disappeared, somebody'd pick
         them up.
         
         SAM: Would you say it's about a foot long, maybe a little less, sharp pointed,
         thick?
         
         AB: (Picking up another piece:) That's quite a rock.
         
         SAM: Crystal.
         
         AB: (And another:) That's a kind of a flint, I believe.
         
         (End of Side B)
         
         AB: I wish to Christ here five, six years ago that I would have took a summer
         off and went back to Denmark and Sweden and Norway. Because I could have
         spoke to all of them. Oh heck, I could read Swede just as good as I could
         Norweigan or American as far as that go. Our neighbor over here was a Swede.
         Well, dad was in Sweden for 10 years, you know. So he learned it, and he
         could talk just as good as any Swede, and he could read Swede. Well this
         fella over here, he had Swedish paper. When I was a kid I always went after
         the mail, so I'd bring his paper here. He had the Swedish-American Post.
         Well dad'd have to read that, and of course I'd read it, so I got so I could
         read it good. And Denmark and Norway, that used to be one country at one
         time, so they used the same language, but they pronounce different. But
         they used the same book, same Bible and everything. Well I could've went
         to Denmark, and then I could have went right across that little piece of the
         ocean that stick in there, and over to Malmo, Sweden. That used to belong
         to Denmark in the early day, but during the war Sweden took Skanor away from
         Demark, so it belongs to Sweden now.
         
         SAM: Did your family, did they speak Norweigan when you were a boy at home?
         Did you have to learn English in school?
         
         AB: Why yes, they spoke at home, but the girls has learnt it on the outside,
         and when they were home, so I learnt it from them pretty well.
         
         Did your parents learn to speak English good?
         
         No, not very good. Pretty broken.
         
         Did it ever give them a hard time that they couldn't speak English?
         Oh, not too bad. Well dad, it didn't bother him so much. But mother, it
         bothered her a little. Well after dad sold the timber here, he bought 40
         acres down there on the ridge. And of course we raised quite a little hay
         here. And we baled the hay here, and that 40 acres was all cleared up,
         and there was a lot a hay down there. So we'd bring the cattle down there
         and keep them down there in the winter, and then we'd bring 'em up here and
         keep 'em here in the summer. Well, next to where we lived, there was a
         bunch of Germans around there. There was an old German, his name was
         Heck, he'd pret'near always come up to the place, every other night anyway.
         And he spoke awful broken English, so I learnt so I could get along pretty
         well with the German. So you could say there was four languages I could
         understand pretty good.
         
         SAM: Can you tell me what your father was like? Tell me what kind of a guy
         he was?
         
         AB: Well that's his picture right there. When he was a kid, you know, there
         used to be a lot of them Russian wolves come over there, and I guess they
         were pretty vicious. That was in early days, you know, they used kind of
         them muzzle loaders and flintlocks. And they saved all the ashes out of
         stove and everything they could, and burnt potash out of it to make lye.
         Well, he was about 22, 21 or 2, and he was sitting up burning potash, and he
         heard the wolves. They had a hired man, and he got the hired man, and they
         went out to wolf hunt. They'd put a goat on the sled see, and them goddamn
         wolves would come right in on the sled. And dad put the swan screw in and
         pulled the charge out of the gun, because it's been laying out in the shop
         there where they were burning potash, so they figured it was maybe damp.
         And they poured in new powder, and put in a new flint, and they went out.
         And he's put in too much powder, and he blowed the gun to pieces, and the
         screw in the back end blowed out and went in under his eye and broke the
         cheekbone. I guess they operated on him six times. And those days they
         didn't use chloroform, you used to have to take it awake. They took out
         over 20 pieces of bone out of his face on that one side. That's why_ he's
         got the face turned so the picture is just from one side of the face.
         
         SAM: Did you say that your mother had a harder time because she couldn't speak
         English very well?
         
         AB: Well, it bothered her more, but of course there was always somebody around.
         And dad got blood poison and gangrene in his legs, so he died. And got the
         banker from Deary to come out, he wanted his will made. They wanted to
         deed the place to me. Dad say, "If you'll take care of mother as long as
         she live, we'll deed the place to you."
         "Well," I says, "that's all right, but we'll see what the girls has
         got to say about that." Well the girls, they both said that they didn't
         want nothing, so they deeded the place to me. Then mother got what little
         money they had, and she had that.
         And when dad died, I and my sister went into town, you know, there was
         no undertaker around here. But the fella that had the store in there, he
         carried caskets and one thing another. He had several caskets in there.
         And we was upstairs looking at the caskets, and here he come up. And we
         was looking at one casket, it was a pretty nice looking casket, about the
         same as the rest of them was a-usin', 40 dollars for a casket those day.
         Well, he had one there that was marked 80 dollars. That was a nice casket.
         He come up, he says, "You don't want that'n, you want this'n over here."
         That was a bigger casket.
         "Yeah," I says, "a pretty big nice casket, and quite a lot of price."
         And you know, 40 dollars was a lot of money those days.
         "Well," he says, "you take that'n," he says, "you'll have that'n for
         40 dollars." Well by god, you know, the neighbors around here, that've had
         people die and used that 40 dollars casket, so they went pret'near crazy
         over that, that I could buy that nice casket. I never told them that I paid
         only 40 for that.
         
         SAM: Why do you think he gave it to you for 40?
         
         AB: Well, I always traded with him. And he was kind of a funny fella. I
         don't know. Some people couldn't get along with him at all, and others again
         he got along with pretty good. There was another store in there that was
         kind of a-buckin' him too. But they couldn't do nothing with him because
         this fella that had the casket, by god he had the money! And he bought a
         lot of stuff by the carload lot, so he could sell cheaper than the rest of
         them, and make money. I know one time one fella brought in a bunch of hay
         wire, that is bailing wire, and he started in selling it cheaper than any
         wheres else. And by gosh old Dorgeson shipped in a carload, and by god he
         started in selling it for two and a half a spool, instead of three and a
         half at the other place. He was funny. But finally he sold out and he went
         down to Seattle.
         
         (He had two boys and two girls; and the oldest one of the girls died
         afterwards, but two of the boys I kind of think is alive, and one of the
         girls. They are down around Seattle. Well, the oldest boy come up here,
         oh it must be five, six years ago, and he come to Deary and visited 'em
         and by gosh nobody knew him. And one of the Andersons finally told them who
         he was. They come out to visit me. And I was a-workin' out here, and Victor
         says to me, he says "You know who this fella is?" I said, "Well just wait
         a minute, let me think." I looked at him and I said, "By god," I says, "he's
         got all the map of old U. C. Dorgeson all over his face." That was Dohnny
         Dorgeson. So we had quite a visit. Well, I ain't seen him for 40 years.)
         
         SAM: I wanted to ask you what you did after you took care of the cattle. What
         was the next job that you worked on after that?
         
         AB: Well, I think about the next job I worked on then was around the place,
         and then when they started in building the railroad, I worked on the railroad
         gang some, driving team,
         
         SAM: What do you remember about the building of that railroad?
         
         AB: Well, I remember when they put the cut through in Deary there. They had
         a big kind of a steam outfit, kind of a plow, and they plowed the hardpan.
         And then they had a rig that run right alongside of it that plowed the dirt
         up on a kind of a scraper. And that went up, and the dirt fell in dump
         wagons, then they'd haul it out and dump it. They claim, that fill through
         Deary, that there is a dago buried in that fill there. And they claim there
         is another one buried in that fill up there at Cornell. You know, there
         was mostly dagos and that stuff on the shovel gang. And one'd get in that
         the rest of 'em didn't like, they'd hit him in the head, and just bury him
         in the dirt. Then cover him up,
         
         SAM: Did you know about that back then, when they were building the railroad,
         that there were a couple of guys missing?
         
         AB: Well the bosses knew it all right, but what in hell did they care? Maybe
         these fellas had a couple, three hundred dollars coming in railroad work.
         Well, them fellas missing, they didn't have to pay 'em. See, that was
         money in the contractor's pocket.
         
         And when I drove team up there at Cornell, they blasted the whole damn
         cut there. It was wide, they were going to put in side tracks in there. And
         they had dump cars that run out with the dirt. And then they kind of had a
         bridge there we'd drive up on, and the dump cars run in under it, and a
         square hole; and we'd dump them slip scrapers so the dirt would go into the
         dump car. And when you'd get a dump car full, just start it, and then a fella
         would ride out on it, and brake it to a stop. Then they'd empty it, empty
         the car, and straighten up the car, and then a horse'd bring it back.
         One morning it was cold, and the fellas out there at the dump a kind
         of a-levelin', they were cold. They went down and set a fire to a big brushpile.
         Got it burning pretty good, and they got up onto the dump to dump a
         car that's come out. And by god some of the fellas that had been shooting
         left a box of powder in that brushpile. And by god that went off, and boy,
         there were sticks and logs and everything lying all over the country! Well
         there was a white man out there and a dago on the dump, boy they sure went
         a-runnin'. But nobody got hurt.
         
         Well I worked there 'til they got through with the team work. And I
         come home and stayed home awhile. There were a-buildin' a trestle, they
         called it High Grouse Trestle. So I went over there. They got up pretty
         high with it. And it didn't make any difference to me how high I went, I
         didn't get dizzy. The boss says, "Do you think you can stand it to walk on
         them timbers up there?" And that trestle was 97 feet high, you know. Well
         I got up there and I run back and forth on the timbers up there, and it didn't
         bother me. And so I got a job all right there, so I stayed there about a
         month during the winter. There was a fella from the old country that stayed
         here with the folks, and he done the chores here. Helped the folks do the
         chores, so I didn't have to stay at home.
         
         Well then, when we got through up there, the boss says, he says, "I
         wish to god," he says, "we had some more trestles to build." He says, "I'd
         like to have you went along, because you are about the fastest man on the
         trestle I've had." The rest of them were older man, and they were slower
         and more careful. Well, you know, them square timbers, they'd have to be
         bored and bolted together. And you take getting 97 feet high walking on
         2 by 12's. You take, the stringers was 2 by 12's bolted together, so they'd
         make 12 by 12's. And you are a long ways up in the air when you get up
         there 90 feet to run across on them.
         
         SAM: Do you remember what the dago's where like? Did you have much to do with
         them?
         
         AB: Well, they were Italians and Bohemians. Oh, some of them was damn nice
         fellas. There was one outfit staying up here that always got eggs an butter
         and meat from us. The boss's name was Pedro. He went back to Italy. And
         hell there's quite a few of them Italians that stayed here. You can't tell
         they're Italians now anymore. Hell they were just, some of 'em in one part
         of Italy, you know, some of them Italians was just as light as any of 'em.
         But the south part of Italy, they were pretty dark. And there was on
         Bohemian that used to live up there on the Hog Meadow, he turned out to be
         quite a logger. By god, you know, he was always making a little moaey;
         And by gosh, you know, when it got right hard times, quite a few fellas would
         go up there and work for him. And he always seemed to be able to have a
         little money. Well he had a nephew there that was kind of half foolish, and
         by god, you know, when he died...
         
         Transcribed and typed by Sherrie Fields
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13607</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Benson</previous>
      <next>Bjerke2</next>
      <disp_name>Bjerke1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
