<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">8/15/1953</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Joel Burkland, 1953-08-15, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:31:38</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Burkland, Joel</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Operated garage and service station; town marshall; secretary-treasurer of highway
         district (37 years)
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1892</birthyear>
      <residence>Deary, Bear Creek</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Swedish homesteaders (1880s). William Burkland's cousin</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fishing"&gt;fishing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#thieves"&gt;thieves&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumberjacks"&gt;lumberjacks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#service stations"&gt;service stations&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#blacksmiths"&gt;blacksmiths&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bear Creek"&gt;Bear Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Anderson"&gt;Anderson&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13612</file_name>
      <mp3>13613.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13613.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Why the family moved to Bear Creek; home being burned down by thieves</title>
            <synopsis>Father came to Idaho because there was timber and
               water, unlike Minnesota. He preferred moving up to
               Bear Creek than taking land around Genesee for those
               reasons. Thieves burned down the home place.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Building and inner workings of the flour mill; production of sawmill and prices of
               timber
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The water powered mill of his father and his partners
               (1904-1917). Initial ditch survey abandoned. Ole Bohman
               helped build it, being familiar with watermills in Sweden;
               they also looked at one in Canada. There was a 37 foot
               drop down the flume to the turbine, providing 35 horsepower.
               Five foot diameter grinding stones made Graham flour.
               The mill sawed about half a million board feet a year.
               Production of power. Since the timber was cut off the
               hills, the creeks have dried up. Timber bought for $1.50
               a thousand; good ship sold for $10 or $12 a thousand.
               Yellow pine and shop lumber were preferred. No upkeep
               required. There were ten men in the sawmill crew. Use
               of flour mill by people all the way to Bovill.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Life in the country; what the boys did for work in the area</title>
            <synopsis>Country was all timber with trails. The boys fought to see
               who could stay home from school. Work for boys on the
               place, cutting brush, clearing land, caring for the
               livestock, working in the mill.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Discussion of towns of Culver and Anderson; laying supplies in Moscow for the winter</title>
            <synopsis>Town of Anderson. Laying in supplies for the winter in
               Moscow in the fall. Snow was six or seven feet deep.
               Town of Culver.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1680</time>
            <title>The beginnings of Deary, its first homes, and why it was built; Fighting fires in
               Deary
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Beginnings of Deary. First homes. The town a natural point
               for commerce and log shipping in the early days. Now it
               is an agricultural center. Bucket brigades fought the Deary fires
               but there wasn't enough water; both burned most of main
               street.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>Knott girls drowning in Deary; Crime in Deary</title>
            <synopsis>Two Knott girls drowned in the big pond near Deary, though
               Mr. Burkland fished them out with a rake. No serious
               crime around Deary.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2220</time>
            <title>Native Americans picking huckleberries and digging camas</title>
            <synopsis>Indians used to come through the country to pick
               huckleberries and camas, especially around Bovill and
               other meadows. Now they have to go much farther back.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Hunting game and fish in the early days and the prices for fish</title>
            <synopsis>Game in the early days. Paying to ship elk into the
               country, who have since mixed with elk from other areas.
               Catching fish in Bear Creek. Dr. Gritman gave Mr.
               Burkland $2.50 for his string of fish from Bear Creek.
               Making a falls to catch fish for the whole family for
               school lunch. Catching two foot long salmon in Potlatch
               Creek, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Local men trying to create a way for fish to get through Bear Creek</title>
            <synopsis>Local men thought of blasting out the falls on Bear Creek
               so fish could get through, but gave up the idea because
               it was too big a job.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2880</time>
            <title>Impressions of the IWW on camp conditions and people blaming them for sabotage</title>
            <synopsis>The IWW did a great deal to improve conditions in the
               camps, and didn't do sabotage around here, although they
               were blamed for it.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Problems with lumberjacks throwing money around; lumberjacks getting drunk and casuing
               problems
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>When he was marshal, he found lumberjacks had more
               respect for law than local people. Lumberjacks made six
               or seven hundred and then went to town and blew it all in
               three or four days, buying drinks for everybody and throwing
               money around. He threatens one recalcitrant lumberjack
               with a billy club. After a night in jail, he buys them coffee
               and sends them on their way. Two jacks walk into a
               teacher's house to get warm on their way back to camp.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>Working as the Deary marshal; jobs as a city clerk; operating a Deary garage and service
               stage; services offered at service station
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>As Deary marshal he also changed the leathers on five
               well pumps every week, and was City Clerk, for $50 a month.
               He ran the Deary garage at the same time, converted from
               a blacksmith shop. He bought out the creamery and made
               it a service station. They hauled gas in a barrel from Rosalia
               once a week in 1920. Rebuilding batteries was a big
               business. Cars were put on blocks over winter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Work as the Secretary-treasurer for Highway District; years in public service</title>
            <synopsis>Secretary-treasurer for highway district, 37 years. He had
               over a hundred years of public service, when the state
               figured it up.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Money problems when the Depression hit; Mercantile Company losing money; surviving
               the Depression
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>When the Depression hit, he deposited $275 the night before
               the bank closed. He had about $50 in hand. Debts had to
               be given up, couldn't be collected. The Mercantile Company
               lost about $20,000. Getting through the Depression.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>People in Deary working in logging; town decline; ease of getting to Moscow; not knowing
               everybody in town
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Most Deary townspeople did and still do work at logging. The
               town has declined since the twenties, with far fewer businesses.
               Ease of getting to Moscow compared to old days. Lots of new
               people - in the old days he knew everybody.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Working for blacksmiths; working on early cars; and selling cars for cash</title>
            <synopsis>Work for blacksmiths. Work fixing connecting rods and
               brakes in early Fords. Selling cars for cash, no trades.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Early farming machines and practices</title>
            <synopsis>Early thrashing machines. Using a long belt to protect the
               wheat from fires.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5100</time>
            <title>Spending hours calming down a woman with a butcher
               knife; Life as town marshals.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Spending hours calming down a woman with a butcher
               knife, as town marshal.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Family's water powered mill. Early Deary, fires and decline. Boys' work
         and fishing. Marshall's work. Depression debts. 8-15-53 1.5 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13210_lcoh_13210.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13612</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Bubuly</previous>
      <next>Burkland_William2</next>
      <disp_name>Burkland_Joel</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
