<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">3/19/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>William Burkland, 1976-03-19, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:04:24</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Burkland, William</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer; logger</occupation>
      <birthyear>1887</birthyear>
      <residence>Deary, Bear Creek</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Swedish homesteaders (1888)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#blacksmiths"&gt;blacksmiths&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rural communities"&gt;rural communities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#festivals"&gt;festivals&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bear Creek"&gt;Bear Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13386</file_name>
      <mp3>13387.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13387.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Logging and homesteading for Potlatch company and the machinary they used; a man who
               couldn't sweat
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Logging on the homestead and for Potlatch. Using dollies
               and drays. A man who couldn't sweat.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>How harvesting and threshing were done in Genesee, time it took, and how hard it was</title>
            <synopsis>Threshing sixteen hours a day. Driving derrick team.
               Enjoyment of harvest - the engineer blew whistle at four a.m.
               The work didn't drive men; pitching bundles was hard. Harvest
               work and spring work at Genesee. Some Troy men took
               crews to Genesee for threshing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Working hard to survive on the homestead; hauling wood to Troy</title>
            <synopsis>People worked most of the time to make it. Activities on the
               homestead. Hauling wood to Troy in winter. Rough-locking
               wheels.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Runaway horses and the problems they caused</title>
            <synopsis>Getting tangled in a runaway which killed a horse. Once a
               runaway horse, always a runaway. Mr. Burkland's runaway.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>The differences between Troy and Deary; Police getting money for arresting people</title>
            <synopsis>Stopping in Troy during wood hauling trips. Troy was a lively
               farmtown, while Deary was a tough lumberjack town.
               Whiskey caused fights at dances. Marshall Hays almost
               arrested him for walking on the sidewalk with a bundle of hay.
               Dislike of Hays by people; he arrested a relative of Mr.
               Burkland who had a drink. Hays got money by arresting people.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>How hard homesteading was in Deary; How Potlatch company influenced town; Importance
               of Dahlberg; how hard clearing timber was
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Roundtree, who homesteaded at Deary, sold out for a team of
               horses. Pioneering was very rugged here - only foreigners
               could put up with it. Long delay before Potlatch came into
               the country. Importance of Dahlberg, the trader, for building
               up the country. Little money was paid for timber but any
               money was valuable. Clearing land, a slow process. Difficulty
               holding homesteads.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>How Potlatch helped the town of Deary grow and how it affected the town afterwards</title>
            <synopsis>Potlatch started the town of Deary. They would have started
               town at Avon because it was open, but were held up for more
               money. Deary townsite was almost entirely timbered. Water
               shortage at Deary. Deary grew fast - sale of lots.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Where early Deary merchants came from; Swan Erickson's reputation as a blacksmith</title>
            <synopsis>Many early Deary merchants came from Troy and Nora. Swan
               Erickson's various blacksmithing locations; his kindness,
               especially to kids; breaking of his horse.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Joe Wells and his family were an important part of the Deary local life</title>
            <synopsis>Joe Wells and his family were good people. Joe liked to
               drink. The head Potlatch crews stopped to eat and stay at
               their home. They were completely a part of local life.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>How poeple visited each other and had get togethers in Deary</title>
            <synopsis>Visiting was done in town rather than at a neighbor's once
               the town began. Neighborhood get-togethers.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>Discussion of purposely set forest fires and what they did for the land; Dahlberg
               and his father trading in the area
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Backfiring to stop fires. Frequent fires in the country set
               by many. Burning was good for the land. Dahlberg and his
               father had been peddlars in Sweden; more about his trading.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Coming into Deary from Bear Creek; Participating in acitives in town</title>
            <synopsis>Frequent trips to Deary from Bear Creek. Horses on the farm.
               Increase of social use of town: skating, baseball, confectionary,
               dances. This caused decline of rural get-togethers. Country
               dance pavilions (bougheries). Dahlberg's mill.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>Decline of Deary to lack of logging; Poltatch bringin in more money into the country</title>
            <synopsis>Decline of Deary when logging slacked off. Deary businesses.
               Potlatch brought money into the country. His parents got
               money from stone and timber claims, which they proved ud
               for $400.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6240</time>
            <title>Arson fires in Deary and the bucket brigade to stop them; different words for swearing</title>
            <synopsis>Deary fires maY have been arson to collect money. They didn't
               hurt the town. Bucket brigade. Harsh begged everyone to save
               his bank; "hen" was his substitute for swearing. Fred Heck's fun.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6600</time>
            <title>Deary fourth of July, town fair, strawberry festival</title>
            <synopsis>Deary fourth of July, town fair, strawberry festival</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6660</time>
            <title>Farming the family place. People farmed just to get by and
               keep out of debt.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Farming the family place. People farmed just to get by and
               keep out of debt.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6960</time>
            <title>Comparing farming in Idaho versus farming in Minnesota; Effects of Depression on people
               in the area
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He drove back to Minnesota to compare the farming potential, and
               found it no better than here. Depression didn't have much
               effect here because people weren't doing well anyway.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Neighboring supplanted by town life. Beginning of Deary. Homesteaders'
         struggle. Harvest work. Runaway teams. 3-19-76 2 hr 46p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: When you started to work in the woods-
         
         WILLIAM BURKLAND: Well, I started in the woods when I was a kid, but that was at
         home. I worked for Potlatch in '36- no, wait now- 1910. 1910 I worked
         for Potlatch; summer of 1910. But before that we worked- yeah, we wor
         ked at home, that is, logged to Dahlbergs. So I logged in the woods-
         I've worked in the woods all my life.
         
         SS:  Well when y°u were young and learning, what did your father have you
         do?
         
         WB:  Everything. Everything there was to do. Even skid. I drove horses
         when I was twelve years old. I started driving horses. From then on
         I took over the horses. When I waa around fifteen, sixteen I took over
         the horses entirely. My father didn't want to drive horses. So I
         got that job, and I liked it so I stayed with it. I drove horses for
         over forty years. Even owned horses of my own since Iwas around- well,
         in the '20's, I think. And I bought two colts, three year olds- no,
         they were younger than that- I bought one year old colts. I bought two
         of 'em in 19— When the Fair was in Seattle. The summer when the Fair
         was in Seattle. I raised them and started working them when they were
         three years old. And I worked them all the time. I logged with them
         when they were four years old; I logged with them for a feller down be
         low Deary, there. Fellow by the name of Asplund. In fact, he was Philip
         Asplund's halfbrother. And he had a contract to log, south of Deary.
         And I worked there in 1912 for him; worked all winter, that's the first
         winter I logged with that team. I worked in the woods ever since I
         remember. Sawed and swamped and skidded and drayed. Used dray logging.
         That was down to the mill., I told you we was at Pete Dahlberg's mill.
         We logged down there. And I done that as far back as I can remember,
         almost.
         
         SS:  When you say dray logging; what do you mean by that?
         
         WB:  One sled. We'd load a log on one sled, that was dray hauling. Drug
         one end of the log behind. They dray hauled. Potlatch - we done that
         even with the Potlatch for a long time. They dray hauled in the winter
         time and dolly hauled in the summertime. Dolly- they had a two wheel
         ed- made the wheels out of logs, and ironed 'em with two-
         
         SS:  bands-
         
         WB:  Bands around. That was dolly logging. And then they rolled the log
         on there and it pretty near balanced it, you see on the bunk. It didn't
         drag very hard. You could adjust that the way you wanted it. If it
         was steep downhill you could- roll the log so it was heavier behind and
         dragging harder and if you wanted it light on the behind, why, you put
         the log up ahead and almost balanced it. And they hauled awfully big
         loads that way. We'd use horses. They logged that way lots of times
         in the summertime. Potlatch did, before they started with the donkeys
         and then they started with the donkeys and then they pulled in the
         whole tree. That's what I was working on in 1910. I worked on the don
         key, and we pulled in whole trees. Of course, I didn't— well, I war
         ked out in the woods, too, . And then I worked on the skidway
         where they pulled 'em in. They pulled in the whole tree and then we
         had to measure it up and saw 'em off by hand. Me and my older brother
         and Bill Olson. Bill Olson - Did you know Alfred Olson in Troy?
         
         SS:  I knew who he was, yeah.
         
         WB:  You knew who he was?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         WB:  Well, it was his brother, his older brother. He worked with us on the
         skidway in 1910. And it was early in the spring and it was wet too;
         the logs were wet and the trees were wet; the ground was wet. And the
         sun got awfully hot and he went out for us. He was working there and
         it got too hot^ he was the kind of a guy that couldn't sweat, and he
         went out and we had to drag him out to the shade. But we went ahead
         and worked and he laid there about, oh, two, three hours.
         
         SS:  Was he a big man?
         
         WB: A big man? No, he wasn't a big man, just ordinary. But he couldn't
         sweat. He was one of them hidebound fellers, you know, that couldn't
         sweat. And my brother and Lwe sweat till was just running
         off of us. It was so hot in there and all that water and the sun was
         hot. It was suffocating. But then he got over it after he laid there
         a while, he got over it and come up and said he was going to help us
         so we put him on to measuring and we took the saw and sawed. And, oh,
         I 11 tell you, that wood work was awful hard work.
         
         SS:  Was it rough?
         
         WB:  Yes. It's hard work. You sawed by hand, you know. You stand there
         and worked all day; that was hard work.
         
         SS:  I'll bet there was a lot of it, too.
         
         WB:  Ya, you ain't a kiddin', there was a lot of it. There was about- well,
         when they logged there was about two gangs to the team, to keep a team
         going if they didn't have too awfully far to skid where it took two
         gangs to keep them agoing.
         
         SS:  How many men was in a gang?
         
         WB:  Well, you had two men to the gang.
         
         SS:  Two sawyers?
         
         WB: Ya. Two sawyers. One on each end of the saw. And then there was two
         of them. Two saws to keep a team going, unless it was so far skidding.
         But they didn't have- they didn't skid very far when they skidded out
         to the— see they're on trackside, spurs, railroad spurs, and they
         didn't figure on, oh, on, eighty rods, something like that.
         
         SS:  Were they using dollies then with—?
         
         WB:  No. Not when they skidded that way. The dollies, they were when they
         skidded further than that. They skidded a quarter of a mile or a
         half a mile, then they used dollies. But that was in the summertime
         when it was dry. But they did use drays even when it was wet, it didn't
         have to be snow, if the ground was wet they used drays and they put the
         log on a dray and balanced it and pull it in that way. That was the
         way they logged before they got the donkeys and the cats. Well, the
         cats, they didn't get them until way late.
         
         SS:  Were you working by the day? You got so much a day?
         
         WB:  Yeah. That wasn't too much, about two dollars. There wasn't much money
         in it then, them days, you know. We didn't have any money. I worked in
         the harvest field, not in the harvest field, on the threshing machine
         for thirty-five days, straight through driving derrick team for two
         dollars a day. That was sixteen hours a day, too. (Chuckles) We was
         up at four o'clock in the morning and harnessed up and lots of evenings
         we had to work in— well, we didn't work in lamplight, but the sewers
         did. They had to have a lantern for them to see to sew in the evening.
         
         SS:  Sack sewers?
         
         WB:  Sack sewers. It was all sacked grain then. And the sack sewers had to
         work in lamplight and of course, we didn't need that. The horses they
         knew the track they'd been going there all day long; forwards and
         backwards and forwards and backwards. We were pulling headed grain up
         on a derrick and then there was the feeder run back and there was two
         men on there raking that into the feeder, getting it into the machine.
         Them days the threshing machines had about, oh, let's see, two, four,
         six- twelve, fourteen men on the crew; on the machine crew.
         
         SS:  You were driving team?
         
         WB:  I was driving team. I was driving the derrick team.
         
         SS:  What did the derrick team do?
         
         WB:  They pulled in the headed grain from the stack. You know what a derrick
         fork is?
         
         SS:  Yeah, I've seen a picture of 'em.
         
         WB:  Well, they pulled them back on the stack and put them down in that
         headed grain, and then they motioned us to go ahead and we pulled up
         that load and and it took em up in the mast and it tripped it and it
         come down on the great big platform- oh, it was half as big as this room.
         That's where they dropped it down and there was a man on each side ra
         king that in- into the- what did I call it? elevator? And then it went
         into the machine.
         
         SS:  How did they decide whether they were going to thresh it all in a b ig
         pile like that or whether they'd put it in bundles?
         
         WB:  Well, they were out there with a header, the header bed, and then they
         had a header bed- that was made something like a bundle tack only much
         bigger. And then they hauled it into the stack, put it in there, just
         like a stack, you know. You open a stack and you thresh it all. If
         they wanted any divisions why they'd have to divide it before they come
         to the stack with it.
         
         SS:  Divisions?
         
         WB:  Yeah, if there was any division in the grain to be done, it had to be
         divided before they come to the stack with it. And after it was in the
         stack then it went in the machine. Same with all of it. Same way with
         bundles. You know, they stacked bundles, too. And after they started
         bundle threshing. But now in the Palouse country down around Colton
         and Uniontown and down in there it was all headed grain.
         
         SS:  Is that where you went to work?
         
         Yeah, that's where I went to work. That's where I worked. Out of Gene
         see. Yeah, I worked out to Uniontown, west of Genesee. Started on the
         Didrick Sonhaas place. You know where that is?
         
         No, but I know a little bit of the country. I don't know that parti
         cular place. Big place?
         
         Oh, ya, well, they were all The Didrick Sonhaas place that's
         right on the edge of Genesee. That's not a very big- that's a 160 acres.
         And then it was Charlie Sonaas and Fred Sonhaas and fluramers, they were
         all related. Fred and Charlie Sonhaas and Dick, they were brothers.
         And then there's a Flummer, he was married to Sonhaas's girl. And then
         it was, oh, I don't remember the names of all them through there.
         
         SS:  Did you enjoy harvest?
         
         Yes. I liked it. Slept out in the strawstack. Oh, yeah, I liked that!
         You get so you like some of them things, you know. Sleeping out in the
         straw pile and getting up at four. The engineer was up before thatwell,
         he got up before that so he had a whistle and he whistled and geeminy,
         you had to roll out. It hurt your ears! (Chuckles) Yes, I liked
         that, them days, I wouldn't like it now! In them days I liked it.
         Did the men work really hard on something like that?
         Hard as they wanted to. There was really no driving unless - if you
         was pitching bundles, that was harder than the rest of the work around
         there, pitching bundles. Then you had to pitch in order to beat every
         thing in order to get that into the machine and get out in the field
         again. And some of them bundles were both long and heavy. So that was
         really harder work. The header- or the derrick team work that was easy
         work, but I was just a kid then; I was about sixteen years old. So that
         wasn't hard work, but you had to be there all day right in the dust
         back of them teams. Backward and forward and backward and forward,
         and you went one time and the other feller went one time. And you
         come back and your forker. he took his fork and the other one he took
         his. Two teams and two forkers. You see- there was an opening in be
         tween the stacks, and one built up the stacks from that way and the
         other one built it up from this way back. Well, the stack was started
         from the dividing line, and then they built 'em up so they were out
         there about forty or fifty feet, each side, and that's where we had to
         pull 'em in there after that.
         
         SS:  That's big sized stacks.
         
         WB:  Oh, yeah, big stacks there, you bet. They had big stacks, they were
         about, oh, eight or ten feet high and they must have been about eight
         or ten feet wide. Oh, I tell you, that was lots of grain. T hey had
         lots of grain out there at Genesee and Uniontown they were pretty big
         farms, some of 'em were big farms. And even 160 acres, you know, the
         way wheat grows out there them years, I think they grew more wheat than
         they do now. More straw, anyway. And that made a lot of straw. Your
         header cut down- the straw was about that high- the header, you know,
         it cut up pretty high on the straw, but then they left about that much.
         To get all the heads they had to leave about a foot and a half, something
         like that, sixteen inches, and that all went into the stack.
         
         SS:  So that country around Genesee seemed pretty prosperous to you in those
         days?
         
         WB:  Yes, yes. That was always good country. That was the queen of the country,
         in Genesee. They claim there was some that was better than
         Genesee, but, I tell you, that was awfully hard to beat between Genesee
         and Uniontown. That was an awful fertile country.
         
         SS:  Did lots of guys come from over here to work over there
         
         Oh, yeah. Yes, pretty near all the old-timers worked over there.
         They worked over there in the harvest and a lot of 'em now like Arthur
         dad, he worked there, oh, there for several years before my time,
         He worked there from the time he came. He came out to Genesee and he
         worked around there for a long time, both in the harvest and the spring
         work. People were out there in the spring work, too. You know, they
         worked a lot of men^them days. It was all horse work and it was only
         about, oh, all the way from four to six horses for every teamster.
         And it wasn't very many teamsters that used six horses, they used three
         and four and they had to have a man with every team. There was a lot
         of man work them days. That's been done away and they're doing away
         with it right along. The man labor.
         
         Who was the outfit that you— would you go work for the same outfit
         when you'd go over there?
         
         I worked for several outfits over there. This time when I was driving
         derrick team, I worked for Nels Johnson. He lived right out south of
         town here.
         
         SS:  He took his whole operation from here over there?
         
         WB:  Ya, a lot of 'em anyway. You mean his outfit?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         WB:  He kePt his outfit- he bought itK Genesee, he bought it from Dick
         Sonhaas. And he always left it there when he worked it there. He was
         down there about three or four years, I think, and he kept his machinery
         down here. And then I worked for John Vedwick. He was from Troy. I
         worked for him after that. That was a bundlerrig, though. And I wor
         ked for Halvorson. Halvorson and Johnson down here. Worked for them,
         in the threshing. That was also a bundlerrig. Well, that was three
         years. There wasn't much more than that. I worked for- I was out there
         and hauled grain one fall; helped haul grain, helped August Johnson.
         He a Genesee man, he lived this side of Genesee.
         
         SS:  So one of these crews, one of these outfits with all the men on itwould
         quite a few of the men in the outfit be Troy area men, or the
         Deary area?
         
         WB:  It was with Vedwick, there was a lot of them. That whole crew was from
         Troy. And that was Oslund- that was John Oslund and Pete Swenson and
         Charlie Swanburg and a fellow by the name of Alfred Westlund and John
         Estlund. I don't know if I can remember any more.
         
         SS:  I'm surprised that you can remember so many that you do.
         
         WB:  Well, they were from Troy, they were all from Troy. And Andrew Heidahl;
         I drove Heidahl's team. I hauled bundles.
         
         SS:  Well, how much of the year, let's say around 1910, how much of the year
         could you work out in the woods or in the harvest? How much work was
         there?
         
         WB:  Oh, about thirty days.
         
         SS:  For harvest?
         
         WB:  Yes.
         
         SS:  What about woods work? How long could you work there?
         
         WB:  Oh, that's the year around, you know, the woodswork, that was the year
         around, if you wanted to be there all the time. The lumberjacks, that
         was the year around for them, sometimes. In some camps. Well, pretty
         near all the camps at that time when they used horses.. They didn't
         lay up for the winter, they wanted that snow. Snow and cold weather
         that's what the loggers wanted.
         
         SS:  So that means that those days, you could work pretty near as much as
         you wanted to.
         
         WB:  Yes. Work as much as you wanted to; pretty near had to to made it.
         
         SS:  Were you working the year around, yourself? Around 1910?
         
         WB:  Well, no. No, I was there in the summertime in 1910. I was there one
         year was all. One summer. ButA worked at home, that's where we wor
         ked in the wintertime. We stayed home and logged down here at the mill,
         Dahlberg's mill.
         
         SS:  What were you doing on the place then? You were logging? Mainly, or
         was that just winter?
         
         WB:  That was in the wintertime, we didn't log in the summertime.
         
         SS:  What else did you do on the place?
         
         WB:  Oh, we raised hay and grain and cleared land and made wood and I hauled
         wood to Troy along when I was about fourteen years old, I started hauling
         wood to Troy. We hauled about ten cords of wood to Troy every winter
         for so long, you know, I don't know how long. I hauled wood every win
         ter to Troy besides logging.
         
         SS:  What was that trip like? Hauling the wood from Bear Creek to Troy?
         
         WB:  What was it like?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         WB:  Like any other horse work.
         
         SS:  I mean hauling it in. What was the road like?
         WE: Oh, the road was good in the wintertime. Oh, ya. The road was real
         good in the wintertime. They didn't do the roads then like they do now.
         The horses was the ones that made the roads. They tramped up the trail
         and it wasn't icy like it is now. Now they scrape it, you know scrape
         the snow off and it freezes ice. They go down to where there's moisture
         and probably below that and then it freezes at night and you get just a
         glare of black ice in some places. It wasn't that way then. The road
         was tramped down by horses and it was usually a real nice road and your
         sled would run just as light as you please.
         
         SS:  How much could you haul in one load?
         
         WB:  Well, it all depended on how big a team you had. We had small horses.
         I hauled about three quarters of a cord up to a cord, around a cord if
         it was nice, dry wood, why, we hauled a cord to the load.TTw^'5 ^oh^'t a
         
         SS:  How much were you getting in Troy?
         
         WB:  I suppose it was around three dollars, I think. Three dollars a cord.
         
         SS:  Was that a day's work to get down there and back?
         
         WB:  Yes, that was a day's work. It was a long day's, too. Not too long
         about a ten hour day. Eight or nine hours anyway, it all depend^ on how
         good a team you had to walk. What the team could walk. I never run
         my horses. I walked 'em. And that way they stood it every day, I could
         go every day. If you'd run your horses, you'd play 'em out, but I never
         did that, I walked my horses. I had small horses and they didn't make
         as good a time as bigger horses o\oL5.
         
         SS:  When you say smaller, about what would they weigh?
         
         WB:  Eleven hundred and twelve; not over twelve.
         
         SS:  How many did you have on a team? Two?
         
         WB:  Oh, I had just two horses- two horse team in the wintertime. Person
         didn't like to drive four horses in the wintertime because it was up
         and down hill, too much. Some places you have to rough-lock, you know
         to go down with a load.
         
         SS:  How did you rough-lock 'em?
         
         WB:  Well, you had a rough-lock made and you had what they call a rough-lock
         lock on your chain. You had a chain you took under your runner and then
         you run it back here and you had a lock, you had a double piece of iron
         that you run your chain through the link, then you had a ring up here
         that you dropped down, bear down on that, when you got to the bottom
         you went over there and kicked that ring off and went on. Your roughlock,
         it was on the- either the rack or the sleigh bar, on your sledge.
         When you kicked that off it was free. You take the Troy hill, now, we
         had to rough-lock that all the way down. We come in on the north side
         at Troy, and come up on top for that road. And that was - at one time
         it was steeper than it is now by a long shot. They've been grading that
         for over eighty years! They've got it pretty good now. Them days, you
         know, you had pitches there to ride down. And, doggone it, I had a run
         away team^caught up with me down there.A It hit my rig. I was hauling
         lumber that time, and the one horse started up my tieboard, you know,
         when you haul lumber you had a tieboard, you put a twist on about the
         middle of your fcobs and then you lean that- let that tieboard hang
         back and it was getting slick by the time I got down to Troy and it
         was laying right down on the load and it bent down pretty near to the
         ground. This runaway team caught up with me and one of them horses
         run up that board and come up on the load and jumped off- (Laughter)
         I had to run my team off the road and out in the snow and they went on.
         But one of them horses got killed though, just the same. He was the
         one that run up the board, but the other horse pushed him into my load
         and he hit his shoulder against the load of lumber before he ever
         jumped up on the board and he skinned his whole shoulder, so they had
         to shoot him.
         
         SS:  But they didn't stop there, they went on.
         
         WB:  They went by. I got out of the way, so they went by and went clear
         down to the bottom of the hill and they stopped down there. One of 'em
         crowded the other feller off the road and he fell down. So they were
         laying one of em was laying down and the other was standing up.
         
         SS:  These runaways were not too unusual in those days?
         
         WB:  Oh, they'd have quite a few runaways, but they wasn't too many. Not
         bad ones, anyway. They'd probably get away a little ways and some teams
         wouldn't run. . probably go back and then they'd tangle up and stop.
         They wouldn't run. Some got awfully bad, you know. There's runaway
         horses. Now this one here that I'm telling about; one of them horses
         was a runaway horse, and a runaway horse never quits. He's a runaway
         the rest of his life. If he gets away a few times, why, he never quits.
         A horse'11 never forget what he learns. Whether it's good or bad, it
         don't make any difference, he'll never forget what he learns. It's with
         him all the time. And he was a runaway horse; one of 'em. That's the
         one that pushed the other one in on the load and he skinned his shoulder.
         The other horse wasn't hurt; the runaway horse never get hurt, but
         he'll hurt the other one every time.
         
         SS:  What would be the reason why horses would run away? I mean, how would
         they get started doing that? Bad handling?
         
         WB:  Well, he might get scared the first time. He might get scared and he
         might just get— you know a horse when he starts running he scares him
         self. Then the harder he run the harder he will run before he gets
         used to it, and after that, why, he don't get scared. Then he just
         runs away, just because it's a habit. He never forgets it. It be
         comes a habit, you know for a runaway horse to be a runaway. But in
         the first place he probably gets scared and gets started and after he
         gets started to run, why, anything he's got back of him will make an
         awful lot of noise and racket- they go pretty fast. Go about fifty,
         sixty miles an hour. And a runaway horse, he runs pretty hard when he
         first starts out and he's scares himself up and when you catch up with
         him he might be standing there shaking. And he never forget that. He
         just starts out anytime he have a chance after that he'll start out.
         You let a horse run away from you and he never forgets it.
         
         SS:  Do you think that there was a lot of difference in the way different
         people handled their horses?
         
         WB:  Oh, why sure! There's a lot of difference. I let one team get away
         from me and they run for about, oh, they run for about a big, long mile
         anyway, and then one of 'em fell down, just couldn't make the turn, and
         Nfell down and there was a feller that caught 'em and tied ' em up to a
         tree there and I found 'em. I walked up the road and I come to 'emwell,
         I think I met him too, and he asked me if that was my team. "Ya,
         it my team and it was my fault." (Chuckles) And I said, "Did they do
         any damage?" "Ya," he said, "they done plenty of damage. Your woodrack
         is laying all along the road! And your wagon is upside down."
         "Well," I said, "they didn't kill anybody?" "No, they didn't kill any
         body. I tied 'em to the tree down there. You'll find 'em there." I
         did, too, they were tied to a tree. I took em, I went homeland the
         next day my dad and I went back and we picked up all- everything that
         we could that was any good. And I just made up my mind that was going
         to be the last time - because it was my fault they got away.
         
         SS:  How did they get away? How did it happen?
         
         WB:  Just foolishly. I was going to water 'em and in place of knowing where
         I had the lines- they were highlife horses, too- they were young hor
         ses- in place of knowing where I had the lines, I just dropped the lines
         and went over and unchecked 'em. See, we had checks on 'em, a strap
         from the bit over the hame, well I unchecked them, otherwise they
         couldn't drop their heads down to drink. And after I unchecked 'em
         I went around and they drank and then they started up. I hollered,
         "whoa," but they didn't stop. (Chuckles) And I didn't know where the
         lines were, and they went right now. Gee whiz, they took right off.
         It was no use for me to run after 'em, cause they went to beat every
         thing! And I just made up my mind that was the last time a team's ever
         going to get away from me and I never had a runaway after that. And I
         was just a kid then. I was about fourteen, fifteen years old. I drove
         horses for forty years after that and never had a runaway. And I had
         good, young, lively horses too all the time; well fed and everything.
         So, if they'd a got away they'd a run to beat everything. Now, I tell
         you, a lot of that is all in the horsemanship. A lot of runaways, some
         times you have an accident and probably fall off where you can't help
         it or anything like that, and that's different, but anything as foolish
         as that runaway that was all foolishness,
         
         Well, I was going to ask you. When you got to Troy in the middle of
         the day with your horses with lumber; the cordwood, would you rest ^em
         there and spend some time in town?
         
         Ya. Golly, yes.
         
         What would you do?
         
         An hour, all the time.
         
         What would you do? How would you pass the time in Troy?
         
         Oh, I fed the horses. We fed them every noon in Troy. We had grain
         right with us and we had hay right with us on the load. And then Hd
         eat my dinner, whether I'd eat it at the restaurant or if I had it in
         a lunch with me; sometimes I had a lunch and sometimes I eat at the
         restaurant. And that's what we'd spend our time at. And we fed the
         horses, that was an hour every day.
         
         SS:  Would you have time to visit friends in Troy?
         
         WB:  0h» sure- Oh yes. Visit every day. Had a half hour, or more. Sometimes
         we stayed over an hour, if we had plenty of visiting, we stayed
         longer than an hour before we'd turn back.
         
         SS:  How did you know the people that were your friends in Troy? Were they
         people that had used to live out here, or people you'd met in town, or
         where did you know them from?
         
         WB:  People we met in town. We knew all the business men and practically
         all the Nora kids, so there was plenty of visiting .to do. Oh, yes.
         We knew Troy, it £ just like Deary, that's where we done our— We
         was here for twenty or twenty-five years before there was any Deary
         or anything. It was all in Troy, and Nora was all down there. All
         them young people at Nora was down at Troy all the time.
         
         SS:  Well was Troy a very lively town in those days?
         
         WB:  Yes. Oh, yes, it's lots better then than it is now. Oh, yes,'jwas a
         lively town. Yes, it was really better than Deary. Deary was more
         lumberjacks and toughies. Troy people, they were all farm kids. Farm
         people and newcomers and so on. Deary, that was a hard town to begin
         with. All " old lumberjacks'd drink and fight to beat everything!
         (Chuckles) It was a rough town, I'll tell you, that wa s roughie for
         a long time.
         
         SS:  Would you see the fights in town and stuff when you were in Deary?
         
         WB:  Oh, yeah, I've seen fights all over. They had some of them in townand
         they had some of them out at the dances, too. They were fighting.
         If they had some whiskey to drink it usually turned out in a fight.
         That was nothing. That was nothing.
         
         SS:  I heard the lumberjacks were kind of tough fighters when they fought.
         
         WB:  They were fight buggers, they were big buggers, too, you know. They
         were hard ones. There was a knuckle mark on a door casing up here for
         a long, long- several years, the feller ducked the blow and he hit the
         wall and they said there was knuckle marks in there- they showed me
         some marks, I guess that was knuckle marks, I don't know. The buildings
         them days was built out of green lumber and they wasn't as hard, they
         couldn't knock a mark in some of this hard boards, but them days, you
         know, that lumber was green and it was possible to mark- to knock a
         mark in the board if they had a good, big, hard knuckle. And some of
         them - those were the toughies- big longarmed fellers, you know, they
         took a dickens of a blow.
         
         I heard that if one lumberjack knocked another one down, that he mig ,ht
         stomp him with his cork boots.
         
         Ya, bet your life they went down flat on the ground, too. Knocked out.
         That happened often. It wasn't much of a fight if one of 'em didn't
         knock the other^down, and probably kicked the dickens out of him, too!
         Oh, yeah, they fought rough.
         
         Did you know about Marshal Hayes getting shot in Troy? When that hap
         pened.
         
         Yes, I think I was there the day he was shot. But I wasn't there just
         at that time, but I believe I was there that day. Yes, I knew Marshal
         Hayes. He come pretty near getting the old guy, he went after him good.
         I was just a kid, of course, didn't know anything. We fed bundle hay.
         And I don't know, I fed my horses down below that day, had 'em down below
         where I unloaded the wood. I unloaded the wood and I part of
         the hay, went down there and fed 'em while I was unloading. And then
         I had another bundle of hay that I was going to give 'em after that.
         I fed 'em part of one bundle and then I went back uptown- no, I went
         up- that's right- I'd left the sled or the wagon, whichever it was I
         had wood on, and then I went up the livery barn and bought a
         bundle of hay, because they'd already eaten up that first bundle. I
         went up there and bought another bundle of hay and I put it under my
         arm and startedKdown the sidewalk, and, of course, Hays, he was watching
         that and he was going to get me. Well I seen him- the livery barn was
         up there at Erickson's store and I seen him down there at the middle
         of town, I seen him coming, you know. He was walking to beat everything
         and he stopped and looked and I seen him and then I thought about it,
         he was going to get after me because I'm on the sidewalk with a bundle
         of hay, so I crossed over, went over to the other side, crossed there
         at the bank. (Chuckles) And then I went right down the street and
         he stood there and looked- he stopped and he stood there and looked,
         and I was walking the street and he didn't come, but he was after me
         that time.
         
         SS:  That was against the law to have a bundle of hay on the sidewalk?
         
         WB:  Yeah, you ain't supposed to walk on the sidewalk- it wasn't against the
         law, I don't suppose, but against their ordinance, you know, to walk
         on the - you ain't supposed to walk down the sidewalk with anything
         that'll put stuff onto the other feller if he gets too close to you
         and scatter hay on the sidewalk.
         
         SS: Well, from what I've heard, Hays was a pretty mean fellow.
         
         WB:  Oh, he was mean. He was trying to make his wages for Troy. He was
         working for Troy. He was trying to make his wages by prosecuting fel
         lows that done anything wrong. Yeah, he was mean! Watching every chance
         he had to get money for Troy.
         
         SS:  But I had the idea that people didn't like him. The people didn't like
         him because of all that arresting people.
         
         WB:  They didn't like him a bit, that's why he was shot! He was shot, you
         know. He was always after people more than he should have been. And
         then he got this- after, what was it- Jake Sleigh-
         
         SS:  I think it was Paine-
         
         WB:  Payne Sleigh, yeah. Yeah, I knew Hays. He caught my mother's cousin
         one time and he- there was nothing wrong with him, he had a drink and
         he was kind of out of line and a little lively and probably
         wobbled a little, I don't know, he was just as harmless as a toad, and
         he caught him and put him in jail. Cost him five dollars to get out!
         That was five dollars for the town of Troy.
         
         SS:  In Troy they tell about how Joe Wells used to go drinking in Troy and
         then Hays would chase him and he'd get away!
         
         WB:  Oh, yeah, he was after everybody that drank a little bit, why, he was
         after 'em. He had pretty near everybody in jail down there and fined
         'em. Then that was, I figured that was some of the judges, too. Axel
         Olson he wanted to help Troy to pay for the policeman! (Chuckles)
         Axel Olson was the judge. That wasn't these Axel Olsons that's living
         now. That's the older set.
         
         SS:  Yeah. Well now I heard that he got shot by Sleigh because he went up
         the hill and Sleigh was having a quarrel with his wife and told him
         not to come in-
         
         WB:  Now, I think he was called up there though. Or took it upon himself
         to go up there, I don't know which. But then, I think Sleigh was drunk,
         too, you know.
         
         SS:  Well, they were mad at Sleigh after that. I mean that I heard they
         had to get Sleigh out of town, into Moscow pretty quick, because some
         people were really- some of Hays' friends who were in the Odd Fellows
         were-
         
         WB:  Well, I don't know. I didn't know Payne Sleigh, I knew Jake Sleigh, he
         was a nice feller. I used to deal with Jake Sleigh. We used to trade
         horses and I kind of liked him. I didn't know Payne Sleigh.
         
         SS:  You know, we were talking about Deary before; you mentioned to me- was
         it Roundtree who sold out at Deary before the town started? What was
         that story?
         
         WB:  Yeah, he sold his place. See, he homesteaded right in the middle of
         town of Deary. But then he wasn't the only one. There were lots of
         'em doing that. He traded his place for a team to get out of here.
         That was Roundtree.
         
         SS:  Just to have a team, he traded 160?
         
         WB:  Yeah. Well, that 160 wasn't worth about $100. If you'd a had the
         money in the early days, you could buy 160 for $100. Some of, you
         know, they got anxious to go, they'd been here and couldn't see no
         future here. You had to be a working man- you had to be a foreigner
         to see any future in this country them days! It's just like getting
         down here in the woods and set there and no markets, no nothing, you
         had that 160 acres and nothing done on it. If you cut down the trees
         why you had all stumps to get rid of. I tell you, she was a hard thing
         to buck. That took a bunch of Swedes and Germans and foreigners to see
         through that.
         
         SS:  Why foreigners and not Americans? Why would the foreigners be more
         willing to do it? Than the Americans?
         
         WB:  They were used to it. Now my folks and all the other Swedes, they came
         from Sweden; Sweden was really nothing but rock and timber, that is all
         it was, especially where my dad come from. It was nothing but rock and
         timber. And all was then there, where my dad came from, was just to
         chop logs. They didn't even use saws to saw 'em with; they chopped
         'em off. Chop one end square and the other one beveled. They usually
         stood on the log and one— now, my dad could hit almost straight as a
         board, almost. say they can't hit the same mark twice, but he
         could do that. And he chopped one end was square cut and the other
         one was beveled on both sides. And that's the way he chopped logs.
         Sometimes they stood on the— if they have the smaller timber, they'd
         stand up on the log on the water. Everything was drove there, you see,
         drove by water. That's the way they moved their timber.
         
         SS:  Well, I was thinking when Potlatch came into the country; didn't that
         open up a good market for people to make money with their timber?
         
         WB:  Yes. But then, we'd been here for twenty-five years before they came,
         or more. We came here and like those fellers up here, they homesteaded
         here in the early '80's or middle '80's, anyway. And Potlatch didn't
         get here til 1905 and then it was nothing doing then for two or three
         years or four years. So you can figure the '80's- '85, '95, 1905 is
         when the railroad come and then it was about five years after thatit
         was twenty-five years. The people were here and there was absolutely
         nothing. They had to make their way and and it was a chance a^d 4V\e6«.+h«rtw
         What made it better down there where we lived was Pete Dahlberg.
         
         SS:  you were telling me about him.
         
         WB:  He was really the making of the country down there. He'd trade for
         anything. Anything. Didn't make any difference, you could trade him
         anything you wanted for anything he had. So they could trade with him.
         And those that could get in touch with him they had some chance to trade
         stuff and also get stuff. He had that sawmill and he had the lumber
         and that was needed badly, because they didn't have any lumber before
         that. So, he traded lumber for anything they had, it didn't make any
         difference. If you wanted to trade, why, you could trade with him.
         
         SS:  When Potlatch came in, how good was the money that they gave for the
         timber? Did they get it cheap, or did they get it dear?
         
         WB:  Oh, ya, they get it cheap; two dollars a thousand. Two dollars a thou
         sand is all they paid.
         
         SS:  So people didn't get rich selling their timber to Potlatch?
         Oh, no, they didn't get rich, but they got something to work with just
         the same. You know, you could buy a lot for a dollar, too. Fifty cents
         for a pair of overalls. Now they're eight dollars a pair. Well, you
         bought them, all you wanted, for fifty cents a pair! dollars for a
         pair of shoes, now they're twenty-five. That was a big difference, too.
         It didn't make any difference how little money you had. If you had any
         money, why, you could buy anything J' That's the reason^they could trade
         a team for 160 acres. That 160 acres wasn't worth more than about $100.
         Because all that was on it usually, was a log cabin, and they didn't
         figure their time to put that up. Some had doors and windows in 'em
         and some didn't. So there you are. But then I think Roundtree hadhe
         had a door and window in his. It was that way for years.
         
         SS:  So really, it sounds like nobody could really get ahead.
         
         WB:  No, they didn't get ahead and it took time to get ahead. They could
         get ahead, it wasn't that, but they had to get rid of that timber to
         get any ground, and then after they got rid of the timber, they had to
         the stumps that came from that timber and then after that, about
         ten years or so probably they could get rid of the stump , unless they
         were used to dynamiting and then they could blow out the stump . But
         they didn't do that. These fellers that came here, they sawed down the
         timber and burnt that up. They felled trees like them there and they
         bored in through the heart and then they bored down to the heart and
         they met and then they dropped fire down in there and them trees were
         pitchy, you know, and it started burning and they'd all win
         ter and burn. Well, they'd burn off til there was nothing but a shell
         and then they'd saw or chop that shell off and got rid of it that way.
         I'll tell you that was a slow process. And hard work, too. But they
         didn't care for that, they were used to that.
         
         SS:  How many acres could you clear in a year. The amount of land you would
         clear up in a year of work on a place?
         
         WB:  That's a hard question. It's hard to say.
         That all depend on how good a worker he was and how much time you put
         in at it. I'll tell you, it took about, oh, say, about fifty years be
         fore they had about forty or fifty acres. That would be about -
         average about an acre a year. In about that time they had about- most
         of 'em, unless they went at it- devoted most of their time at doing that
         it was about- they'd have about forty or fifty acres cleared in about
         forty or fifty years. That's about the way that worked cut. But that
         wasn't the hardest part of it; they first twenty years, they had to
         set here and homestead it, they couldn't leave the place. Leave it
         and then they'd jump 'em. 'Course if they had a wife and family, they
         could leave them on the place and then they'd have to walk to Genesee
         on a Sunday evening and walk back on - walk on Sunday evading and walk
         back on Saturday night. They had to come home, too, and change clothes
         and be with their family. And that's the way the man worked for maybe
         a dollar a day, dollar and a half, or something like that. A dollar a
         day and they worked for less than that to begin with, the first years.
         But then, that dollar would buy more than ten dollars would buy now.
         So it's as broad as it's long, you know.
         
         It was Potlatch that started Deary. Oh, yes, absolutely. They were
         the ones that started- they wasn't the ones, but - but they bought
         everything around there that they could buy. They bought near every
         thing. And then they sold the townsite to a townsite company, and
         then the townsite company they started a town. That was agreed on be
         fore they ever sold it to them. And, if they couldn't buy the ground
         reasonable, why, they didn't stop either. Now they wanted to build a
         town at Avon, course that was open country there, you see, the meadows
         and everything. But they tried to hold 'em up there on the townsite.
         They tried to buy there, but them fellers they tried to hold 'em up
         a little too high. So then they came up here and started a town here.
         They had already bought this. So that's the reason the town is in
         Deary, otherwise it would been down here at Avon. That's where they
         figured on building, too. But them fellers there they had the meadows
         and they had cultivated ground and everything was ready there and they
         tried to hold 'em up on the price a little higher. That didn't work.
         
         SS:  Was the site of Deary timbered before the Potlatch came in? Before
         the town started? Was it timber on the site?
         
         WB:  Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  It hadn't been developed or farmed or anything?
         
         WB:  No. No, no, it was all timber. That was logged. A feller by the name
         of Snyder logged Deary. He had a contract to log. He logged the
         whole thing around here. So that was done after Deary started. Thefe.
         was a little clearing there, fellow by the name of Blaylock had a home
         stead there and he had about, oh, I don't know, five or six acres cleared
         around. So that's really where they started, you know, was on that
         clearing .
         
         SS:  That's all that was cleared? About five, six acres?
         
         WB:  That's all that was cleared. That was all that was cleared, enough to
         prove up on. You had to have so much kinda cleared to prove up the
         place. I think it was five acres.
         
         SS:  I think that's right. Were there many springs right there?
         
         WB:  Yeah. It was water coming up there; it wasn't springs, it was just a
         seepage. But it was water in the ground. That was something that
         flowed from the hill on down. You know, if you had a slope where there
         was timber back of you, why there was always water draining down there.
         They didn't find any water in Deary— in less than 150 feet. And there
         wasn't much. They never found more than so much water in Deary. That's
         the reason they don't have any- they couldn't get water in Deary. So
         much and that was 150 feet. They had to go down to that and it wasn't
         enough for a town. So they had to go back east of town, the next draw,
         Brush Creek, they call it. Arthur lives on Brush Creek. And
         that's where they found the water. That's where they got the water.
         There was a geologist here and found that for 'em. But Deary had so
         much water, and they went down and they thought they'd go down deeper
         and find more, but they went down 1000 feet, I think; five, six hundred
         and a 1000 feet; they didn't find any more water. There wasn't any
         more to be had. And the geologist told 'em there was no use- "You
         won't find any more than so much." And they found that in any place
         where they dug, they found it at 150 feet. So much water, but it was
         n't enough. It was enough for a family or something like that, not for
         a town.
         
         SS:  Did the town go up there fast when it started building? Did itjkind
         of spring up over night?
         
         WB:  Oh, no, but it went up pretty fast; the first part of.town. It went
         up pretty fast. It was, oh, I don't know; in about five years, why it
         was bigger than it is now. There was more building. 'Course it wasn't
         very substantial. Anything, you know, just lumber buildings.* It went
         up that fast.
         
         SS:  I've heard Jorgeson was the first one to start a business in town there.
         
         WB:  Yeah. Well, he was one of the first ones. Well, Jorgeson was the first
         one to have a store in here, but then there was that Peterson, Ben Pet
         erson, he moved the hardware store in there from Troy- no, he lived in
         Troy, he started the hardware, he moved up here and started a hardware
         store. That was, I don't know, was the same year, it was pretty near
         all started the same year; the following year; anyway, it was in the.
         fall when the railroad come in. Let's see, when in the world did they
         sell them lots?
         
         SS:  They were selling lots in 1908, I know that.
         
         WB:  I think they were selling lots in 1907. Of course, they sold before
         that. But they had an auction sale on lots in - in the fall of 1907.
         But Jorgeson started before that. I think he started building in 1907.
         But then, you see, he bought from the townsite company. He picked his
         Of
         lot before they ever started selling, and then after they got kind of
         squared off and got all the surveying done,Nthey had an auction sale
         on lots. That's when Dad bought forty acres there. That was in the
         Homan Orchard tracts, though.
         
         SS:  Did many of these store people come from Troy and Nora?
         
         WB:  Ya, they did. Now Jorgeson was here, he didn't come from Troy, he
         came from Nora. He had a store in Nora,, moved that up here. That is
         half way between here and Troy. And so, he came from there and then
         Ben Peterson he came from Troy. He started a hardware store. And Eric
         Anderson, he started a jewelry store. He also came from Troy. And
         John Saline, he started a saloon. He also came from Troy. And then
         Nella Call, he started- he got the post office. But I think he started
         a confectionary before. He was a farmer down here at Avon.
         
         SS:  And Swan Erickson was from Troy, too.
         
         WB:  Yeah, Swan Erickson was from Troy. Yeah, he came from Troy. Course,
         Swan Erickson, he had blacksmiths all around here before that. He was
         here with the early settlers, and he started blacksmithing. He first
         started blacksmithing down here at the Anderson post office. That's
         where Ted Cliff lives now. And he blacksmithed there and then he moved
         up- him and Shoberg, they moved up this way about a half a mile from
         the— that's right south of Rueben Johnson, on the hill there. You
         know where Reuben Johnson live?
         
         SS:  Uh-huh.
         
         WB:  Well, on the hill there, there was a feller name of Shoberg had forty
         acres . So they moved that blacksmith shop up there and had it
         there a while. And then Swan Erickson moved back down to Nora and put
         up a blacksmith shop there, and after that he moved to Troy. And then
         when Deary- after Deary^ got to going, then he moved up here. Had a
         good blacksmith shop there, real good one. Well, he had quite a good
         one in Troy, too. But the Troy Lumber Company wanted to buy him out
         and then he sold to them. He had his blacksmith shop right there at
         what was the Troy Lumber Company's office. You know where that was?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         WB:  Well, that's where Swan Erickson had his shop in Troy.
         
         SS:  What kind of a guy was Swan Erickson?
         
         WB:  He was a good guy. Very good guy. Really too good for his own use!
         (Chuckles) He wasn't too awfully easy, but then he was an awful good
         Very nice fellow. 
         
         When you say too good for his own use, you're thinking of maybe too
         kind to people?
         
         Yeah. Yeah, he'd give up and give 'em a lot of things that they pro
         bably wasn't entitled to. He was very good. He'd argue too. He'd
         give in, and well, help 'em along. That is, if they'd insist on it,
         he'd help 'em. ^He was an awful good guy; Swan Erickson.
         
         SS:  I've heard he really liked the kids.
         
         WB:  Oh, yah, he liked kids. Well, he'd give them anything that they wanted
         Anything that they wanted, why, he'd give it to 'em. Yeah, they wanted
         something- if they wanted something they'd come and ask him, "Yah, yah,
         he'd say, "You go get it, I'll pay for it." He was just a good feller,
         that was all. Then he had a horse- he bought a horse and it was about
         half broke when he got it, and he was no horseman at all. And t he kids
         broke that horse for him, I think. They rode him. At first they couldn't
         ride him, he'd buck 'em off. Then there was a circuit rider came up
         here; a preacher, and he used to be a circuit rider. And I don't know
         why that horse bucked. It might have been that she was kind of ticklish
         on the cinch; you know, cinchbound they called it. 'Cause when they'd
         the saddle on her, why she'd start bucking. And this preacher he
         was a circuit rider, he wasn t afraid of , so he wanted to borrow
         that horse from Swan and ride out some place out here in the country.
         Yah, he could have the horse, but he says, "I don't know if you can
         ride it." "Oh." he said, "I'll try," (Chuckles) "It might buck you
         off." "Well," says, "that's alright if she does." He was a pretty
         young man at that time. And he put the saddle on 'im and got in the
         saddle and started 'im out and gee, the horse went right up in the air
         and bucked to beat everything, and bucked himself down; bucked til he
         fell down! And the preacher he just jumped out of the saddle; when he
         started falling, he just jumped out of the saddle and stood by the horse
         and then the horse got down and pretty soon he laid there and wanted to
         get up, and he got up and the preacher he was right in the saddle again!
         He was in the saddle before the horse got up. "Well," he says, "you
         think you had enough? Let's go for a ride!" And he started kicking 'im
         along and started 'im out and the horse never bucked after that. Never
         bucked after that. Bucked so hard, you know, he went down. Got his
         hind feet^doubled up and he went down. The preacher he jumped out of
         the saddle and when the horse started going up, he was in the saddle!
         He was a pretty clever man, that feller. But he'd rode all his life,
         he knew what he was doing. He wasn't afraid of the horse. And then
         after that, why, everybody rode him. The Olson girls. Emmy Olson
         had- what was it? four or five girls. And they'd all ride him at the
         same time*, they rode him from here to the tail. They'd all ride him.
         There were three or four of them girls around the horse and ride him.
         
         SS:  What about Joe Wells? Did you know Joe?
         
         WB:  Joe Wells?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         WB:  Oh, yes, I knew Joe Wells. I knew Joe Wells all the time. He was here-
         I think he was here probably before we was; not very long before, but
         probably a year or so before we were. And I knew him all the time. I
         stayed there- I used his barn one winter. He was around there all the
         time. He was a nice feller. I liked Joe Wells. And we logged up
         there on the Anderson place and we used his barn, and he was around
         there, too. I think he was loggin' some place that winter, too. And
         I knew him and his wife, too. And £dn| , he was a real nice Negro.
         And Chuck was alright, too, but Chuck would drink quite a little bit.
         He'd get kind of mean sometimes. He drank. He got in trouble every
         once in a while. A little bit, not much. Joe Wells would drink, too,
         but he wouldn't get in trouble much. He'd get a little loud and they'd
         tell him to shut up. "Well," he says, "I know my room is little." So
         he'd shut up. They said the whiskey would work on him! (Chuckles)
         But Chuck he was worse. He'd get mad and want to fight.
         
         SS:  Did a lot of people visit over at their place?
         
         WB:  Oh, yes, yes.
         
         SS:  Wellses?
         
         WB:  Yah. The Potlatch people- that is, those that came, you know, the first
         ones. That was really the head crew; the engineers and surveyors. They'd
         eat there. They'd always stop for dinner at Joe Wells. Especially
         if they orders in ahead, so they knew they were coming, they'd eat at
         Joe Wells place. Yeah, they run quite a little lodging there when they
         built the railroad. They made a little money there then.
         
         Would you say that their family was just as accepted as any other fa
         mily in the early days here?
         
         Yes. Yes. Absolutely. They were in on everything around here when they
         were younger. Both the boys *'the girl and they were around
         every dance and everything. And even the old people were, they were
         just as welcome as anybody else. I don't know of any place that they
         wasn't welcome.
         
         Do you think that changed a little as time went on the country
         Changed and the town got in here? Do you think that they were more
         together with the people in the early days, the homesteaders?
         
         WB:  Oh, yes, they were always together.
         
         But what I'm asking you, is, do you think that changed as time went on?
         
         Well, no, I don't think it changed very much, but the only change is
         they visit differently than what they did when - in the early days.
         It change in that way that they don't group together like they did in
         the early days. They grouped together, they'd always go to a place,
         neighbor and have their fun at the neighbor and visit at the neighbors.
         Now, you know, you go to town. You visit in town in place of out in
         the country. We didn't do that then. We visited right out in the coun
         try; neighborhood. So it would change that way. 'Course, I don't
         think the people change much. They are about the same as they always
         was. But the visiting part of it is a little different than it was.
         You know, we'd go to a neighbor on Saturday evenings. Some places we'd
         dance. Some places we'd play cards. Some places we'd do this and that.
         It all depended on where you went, and how they wanted
         it. But now, if you want to do anything like that you've got to go to
         town. So it differ^ that way, but otherwise I don't see any differ
         ence.
         
         SS:  When you visited the neighbors would it just be the two families?
         
         WB:  Oh, no.
         
         SS:  Or would there be more than two families?
         
         WB:  Oh, yes, there'd be several of them; three, four families together,
         and maybe more. Some place, you know, they'd have a dance. And there'd
         be a whole lot of people, both young and old people come in. That is,
         if they had room. Some of these people put up a big building and you
         had quite a little room. And then there'd be three, four, five, six
         families together.
         
         SS:  And dinner? Food? Eats?
         
         Yeah. Yeah, they'd always had - they'd always bring and have a lunch
         together.
         I was going to ask you: Did you know the Hansen brothers that made
         the coffins?
         
         WB:  Yes. Yes, I knew them. Sure.
         I've heard they were really good to work with wood. They were very
         inventive people.
         Yes. They were. They had a sawmill up here, too. Up there east of
         Helmer. They had a sawmill there, and they were pretty handy with
         wood- with wood work. Yes, I knew them. I forget their names: was it
         Carl and Herman?
         
         SS:  I've just heard 'em called the Hansen brothers. That's what I've heard.
         
         WB:  Yeah, yeah, they called 'em the Hansen brothers.
         
         SS:  Did you know Maimer Anderson?
         
         WB:  Malker? Yes. There was one Malker and one Malcus, but they wasn't bro
         thers, of course.
         
         SS:  Axel's brother. I'm thinking of Axel Anderson's brother. Malker.
         
         WB:  No, I didn't know him very well. I knew of him. I didn't know him
         very well. I knew Axel Anderson better than I did his brother.
         
         SS:  Did you work for him?
         
         WB:  No. No, I didn't work for Axel Anderson
         
         SS:  They backfired from the houses in the homestead days? They used to
         set fires?
         
         WB:  Yeah, they backfired.
         
         SS:  What was the idea there?
         
         WB:  Firebreaks. If you backfire from your house, the fire that came in
         won't come any further than up to that burn. That stopped 'em. You
         backfired. They started a fire around their own place where they could
         hold it, you know, and backfired against the other fire and when it
         came up to where the other one had burned there was nothing to burn. It
         stopped there. That was what they called backfiring.
         
         SS:  Did homesteaders do that every year?
         
         WB:  Well, if the fire come, otherwise they wouldn't. If there was a fire
         come; there was nobody put out a fire. They'd start a fire way back
         maybe- well, everything started a fire. That was started by prospect
         ors, miners, campers, Indians and the homesteaders. Anybody started a
         fire, and nobody put it out, it burnt there til it went out. And if
         it came in on the other feller, he'd backfire from his own place and
         let it burn. It was nothing but the old grass, if there was any left,
         and in the fall of the year, and of course, after the grass got matured
         it burned, too. Green grass don't burn. And after it burnt it wasn't
         over, say a week, til the green grass started to come up again. That
         burning don't hurt grass any, where it burns all the time.
         
         SS:  So, you're saying that the homesteaders didn't care very much if there
         was a fire?
         
         WB:  That didn't make no difference. It didn't bother them any.
         
         SS:  It didn't burn the timber?
         
         WB:  No. No, no, no, there's no timber to burn, just big trees. What burns
         the timber is; your big treesj they shed bark, and you leave that bark
         for about- you leave a tree there without a fire around it for ten
         years and you got that much dry bark, and that's what kills your tree,
         because that gets awfully hot. That's almost like coal. But where
         fire goes every year, they wanted the fire to go.
         
         SS:  You mean, there used to be fires that often? Maybe every year there'd
         be a fire come through?
         
         WB:  Every year, every year. In the early days, that is, before we came,
         when the country was wild, lightning would set fire. And there'd be
         something that'd set fire; prospectors, you know there have been pros
         pectors here all the time, and campers, everything. Indians. Indians
         come here- went through here and went back in the mountains, back here
         on White Rock and picked huckleberries. Well, they'd all start a fire
         and nobody ever put a fire out, you just left the fire burn. It burnt
         out. Either burnt out by itself or otherwise, well, it'd have to burn
         out by itself because they never put it out.
         
         SS:  Or maybe rain would come.
         
         WB:  Yeah, rain. That'd put it out. Yeah, otherwise it didn't burn
         when it came to where it had been burnt before; there was nothing to
         burn; it went out. And green grass didn't burn, it's nothin' but old
         grass that burned.
         
         SS:  — when you were young, doing exchange work from one place to the other.
         
         WB: Oh, sure, sure. We exchanged work. Everybody did that. You got that
         in with Ed Swenson's.
         
         SS:  He Talked about that, yes.
         
         WB:  Yeah, that's all true. I've read that book, it's all true, everything
         he said. That's the way we got along. Exchange work, there was nobody
         hiring. Nobody had any money. There was nothing to get money for, it
         was all exchange. That's why Dahlberg was such a help for this country
         because he d exchangeAanything. He was really in the business. He
         was in that business before he ever come to this country. He was a tra
         der; pedlar. He was a- what do they call 'em? Well, he was a pedlar,
         went around the country with a peddling bag on their shoulders; peddling.
         
         SS:  Back where? In Minnesota?
         
         No, back in Sweden. And his father was before him; he was a pedlar.
         They'd carry the packsack and went around the country and peddled. That's
         where Dahlberg got his-- That's where that come from. That he was such
         a trader. Now, I'll tell you Dahlberg was the biggest help for this
         country that ever could a got here. Anything that he had; he didn't
         have groceries or anything like that, or foodstuff. Well, he had food
         stuff in the way of tame animals. Yeah, trade for anything. Pigs,
         chickens, horses, cows, it didn't make any difference, he'd trade lum
         ber for it. And they all wanted lumber after he started the sawmill.
         That was the only place they could get lumber^Come all the way from
         Uniontown up here and trade 'em colts, horses. There was one feller
         came with four colts and Pete got three of 'em. Come up here with six
         horses and four colts, and before he left, I think of course he stayed
         over night, and when he left Pete Dahlberg had three of them colts.
         Sold 'em to the neighbors around here. Traded them to them for maybe-
         I don't know how he sold 'em, but if there was any money, he'd get it
         of course. He'd sell cheap enough so that they could buy it- . they
         had a few dollars, why, cheap enough so they could buy 
         up the money, too! 
         
         SS:  Well, after Deary started; after the town came in here, about how often
         would you go to town from Bear Creek then?
         
         WB:  Oh, we'd get up there pretty near every day, up to Deary. Yeah, we'd
         go anytime we wanted. That was just a little ways then. And we'd drive
         the team and hack- we drove the team and hack for four, five- well from
         1905, Deary started til 1916. We got the first c ar in 1916. Be
         fore that we had- I had a one-horse buggy and drove all over the country^
         with that. We could drive as far- we couldn't get around like we
         can now. We couldn't take off and go a long ways, we have to limit
         ourself to what a horse could do. But, we always had four or five hor
         ses, and I had a- one or two very good single horses. See, our horses
         wasn't very big them days. They run around 1,100 up to 1,200- I don't
         know whether we ever had a 1,200 pound horse til I got them colts that
         I bought broke. And then little horses, it didn't hurt them to travel.
         Well, once the town started— you were saying that it kind of changed
         that the people did more in town and less in the neighborhood. Did
         that take a long time to change like that, or did it change right away?
         No, it didn't take very long til they got the buildings. Oh, I don't
         know, maybe two, three years. See, when Ben Peterson came up here, he
         built the hardware store, then he put in upstairs there- he put in a
         skating rink. Well, then of course, the people went up there. The
         young people went up there skating. And then they started baseball
         games. Well, that took the people up here to town. And that started
         pretty near as soon as Deary- a year or two after Deary started, why
         that went in. Then the Holbrooks come in here and started confectionaries. And then
         they wanted the people to come up here.
         
         SS:  What about dances? Was there dances in town, too, then?
         
         WB:  Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  Where did they have the dances?
         
         Well, they had it in the skating rink. They had skating rink and dance
         hall; that was in the hardware store, Ben Peterson building.
         So then there was less get-togathers out in the country here? There
         was less neighborhood get-to-gathers- like you said you used to dance
         at people's homes, and I guess then they stopped doing that.
         That kind of divided that up, you know, after the town started. So
         then, if you had a dance out in the country you wouldn't have probably
         more than just a few neighbors got together and had a danca. And they
         didn't have any public dance. There was no public then. The dances.
         they had amount to anything. Of course, in the wintertime there'd
         be just a few neighbors together probably and have a party of their own.
         But before that, the dances, they had pavilions. They called 'em pa
         vilions. They'd build the pavilions outside. There were several of
         them. There was one down here on the Taylor place. They had a pavilion
         and my brother was in on that. They built pavilion. That was on a
         Potlatch place. They had a baseball diamond and they built a paviliondancing
         pavilion.
         
         SS:  Was that temporary? Just for the summer?
         
         WB:  Yes, it was for the summer.
         
         SS:  I think I've heard that called the boughery, too.
         
         WB:  Well, some of 'em calledKthe boughery, yeah.
         
         SS:  Was it the same thing?
         
         Yeah, it's the same thing. They called it a dance pavilion or a boughery,
         
         Yeah, that's the same thing.
         
         SS:  What would they build it out of?
         
         WB:  Oh, they built it out of lumber, then. That is, that was after Dahl
         berg, you know, he started that mill in the early '90's. So that's
         where they got their lumber. And he sawed lumber and he had a planer,
         too, so he planed- he sized the lumber any everything. So that's what
         happened.
         
         So it was just temporary, these pavilions? Just for th e summer and
         then they'd take 'em down.
         
         Yeah, take 'em down- well, I don't know, they'd leave them over winter,
         too.
         
         — About Deary and when it started to go downhill. Because you said it
         used to be a lot bigger and better town than it is nowdays.
         Oh, I donft know. Well, you see, there used to be a harness shop and—
         was it three taverns? But I don't know when it started to go down. And
         a hotel. Two hotels.
         
         Doctors and dentists.
         
         I think it started to go down when the logging was done around here.
         That's what started the most of that go down. See, that was, oh,
         I don't think that was- when did they log here last? Remember? What
         year?
         
         They logged here in 1916 on this place.
         
         SS:  1916
         
         Oh, yes, in '16- '18, '20. I think they were down on Bear Creek in
         the '20's. Oh, it was about 1930, I'd say, it started to slowly go
         down. It didn't go down to where it is now, but then it went downtwo
         blacksmith's shops- There was at one time, two blacksmith shops
         and two or three garages, repair shops, of course, and a hotel and a
         harness shop and a shoe shop, and I don't know- there was two or three
         or four, whichever it was- they called 'em near-beer joints. That was
         taverns, you know. And there was two poolhalls- and what in the world
         was it more?
         
         SS:  That's quite a bit.
         
         WB:  And a telephone- what you call that- the telephone?
         
         SS:  Exchange?
         
         WB:  What you call that- that telephone they had here?
         
         WB:  Yeah. ?Aws' Just a telephone exchange.
         
         WB:  Yeah but then- ? had it. What we call them? Well, anyway it
         was a telephone office. We called 'em telephone offices. You see,
         they had a kind of a central here; telephone central. They'd call up
         Troy and exchange-
         
         SS:  Well, let me ask you Bill, how much do you think that Deary, the town
         changed this country around? Do you think it had a huge affect, or
         some effect? Did it change the country around agreat deal? The way
         people lived?
         
         WB:  it changed in one way, it brought in more money. Course, that would
         have come anyway, I suppose. It brought in more money. The Potlatch
         Lumber Company brought in more money here. They made more cash. That's
         where the change was, mostly. It brought in more cash. I don't know,
         if it had been like it was when we first came here, it'd a been pretty
         slow. You know they had mills here, but they didn't make enough money.
         Potlatch come in here with money and their mill- they started that Pot
         latch mill- that brought in a lot of money, too. We noticed that around
         here, too. The Potlatch business down there, that Potlatch mill. I
         have an idea that's what made the change.
         
         SS:  I get the idea though that Potlatch kind of got the timber here almost
         
         WB: for nothing. They kind of just walked off with it.
         Yah, I know, but that, don't make any difference. You know, there was
         a lot of timber here. Boy, there was a lot of timber here. So we got
         part of the bulk anyway. We got a part of the bulk that was taken out
         of here. There wasn't much value in the timber, but every little helps.
         They had timber claims, the best of timber claims, but they sold for
         only about $1,200 and $1,500, that's what the^timber claim is, but they
         had $1,500. They got $1,500 and they didn't have fifteen cents before,
         so there you are. It all goes together. Now my mother had an awful
         good claim, it sold for- well, that sold for a little more, but Dad got
         $1,500 for his. He had a claim.
         
         SS:  Where were their claims located?
         
         WB: Oh, my mother's claim was located just east of Bovill over on- let's see,
         it between Potlatch and Elk River. That's where my mother's claim
         was located. And my dad's, I don't know where in the world that was.
         That was further back. But he didn't get that much money, either. He
         got about, I think around $1,000 for his.
         
         SS:  Did she go out there and live there on it?
         
         No, they didn't. They proved that up with money; $400. They didn't live
         on them, not on the stone and timber claims. It was the homesteads they
         had to live on. That was supposed to be a home, but not on the stone and
         timber. They took up what they called the stone and timber and they
         proved that up with $400.
         
         I was thinking, did you think that the fires in Deary had much to do
         with the town going down? Do you think the fires hurt the town very
         much?
         
         No, I don't think so. The buildings that they wanted to, went up quick,
         that they wanted to go up. And then they built better buildings. You
         mean when the town burnt?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         WB:  I don't think that hurt neither the people nor the town very much. I
         don't know, them fires, you know, you can't never tell about them. They
         start and oh, it is accidental and all that, and sometimes they want
         'em to burn. That fire wasn't until in the '20's.
         
         WB:  The fire was not in the '20's?
         
         SS:  Was in the T20's, she said. I've heard of that in other towns for the
         insurance money. Guys would burn down their buildings for the insur
         ance money.
         
         WB:  Why, sure, they want 'em to burn, some of 'em. If the business slacks
         out, and they have got a cheap building, what's the use of holding back
         if they're got—?
         
         I don't think that was the reason.
         A person don t know that. That's something that held secret and you
         never find anything about that or what started the fire.
         Well, in Troy they caught- there was a Knutson-Hennings saloon burned
         down and they caught 'em. They had a deal about burning the place
         down.
         
         Ya, well, they didn't catch these- of course, I don't know— the fire
         started in the night, and what started it, that's another one.
         Did you ever get out and fight on that fire? Were you in on that?
         In Deary? Oh, I was out there, sure. I was out there, but then it
         was going to beat everything. There was no fire department either.
         It was just bucket chains. Two men at the pump pumping and then we
         carried water.
         
         SS:  Was it a line? A bucket brigade?
         
         WB:  Oh, I don't know, there wasn't a line at all. There wasn't that much
         buckets around there by the time I got there, course I got there pret
         ttyy ee;arly. I was living right in Deary. In one and the other
         I was living down on the farm- the first part I was living down
         here on the farm, and that was three miles to come, that would burnt
         up before I ever got there. I got in on the tail end of that.
         Well, this fire when you were in Deary; how much burnt down that time?
         What happened?
         
         Oh, I don't know, it was quite- I think Main Street, practically every
         thing on the west side but the brick building burnt down. Because I
         know- Harsh, head of the bank, and he was out there, he was a peg leg
         ged feller, he was out there and he says, "We've got to save the bank.
         We've got to save the bank, otherwise we'll be up against it. We've
         got to save that." 'Course they went in and saved- the fire was coming
         K everything, but they carried water and held it back, so they saved
         the bank; that was a brick building. And there was a feller, Fred Heck
         he was always full of the dickens anyway, and he said- Harsh was out
         there, and he says, "We've got to save the bank! We've got to save the
         bank!" And when it was over with then he says, "Hen, I saved my bank
         anyway!" (Chuckles) And it was really the others that saved his bank.
         Oh hen, he always say hen.
         Hen?
         Yeah, he used that for a byword. He says, "Oh, hen," he says.
         Fred Heck did that?
         No.
         Harsh did that?
         That was Harsh, he'd always say "hen". Whenever anything went wrong
         he'd use that for a byword."Oh, Hen," he says, "I saved my bank, any
         way." After he'd been begging everybody to help save the bank It
         wouldn't a burnt anyway because it was a brick building.
         
         SS:  So Fred Heck was just making fun of him?
         Yeah, he was making fun of him. Fred Heck, he'd always listen to things
         like that, you know.^ He was making fun of him. Fred Heck he was al
         ways full of fun. If you had any fun, why, he was right there. No,
         that time the town burnt all the way from Jorgeson's store clear up to
         the bank, all the buildings. And that was the last fire.
         Did you go to celebrations in Deary?
         Yeah.
         What did they celebrate there?
         Fourth of July. Yeah, they had celebrations every year. The Fourth
         of July - the first celebration was the Fourth of July, then they had
         a big celebration, and the second one was the fair, I think. They had
         a fair, that was the second celebration.
         A Fair, like a town Fair, like a County Fair would be? Course, it
         didn't amount to that much but that is what it amounted to anyway. They
         had a Fair; they brought in stuff that they raised on the farm.
         What about that Strawberry Festival? Did they ever have that in the
         earlier days?
         Oh, yes! They had that for several years. They had a lot of them Strawbery
         Festivals. But then, you know, that kind of petered out, too.
         
         SS:  What would that be? The Strawberry Festival?
         
         WB:  Well, just a get-to-gather, something like a fair. And then they'd
         have strawberries to sell, and that's about all it amounted to. And
         then there was kind of a celebration.
         
         SS:  So» when you were " up, let's say in the teens and the twenties
         and even in the«^irties, mostly what you did was worked on the home
         place; on the farm?
         
         WB:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And you farmed it?
         
         Yeah, I farmed it. I took that over in about, oh, see, in about '17.
         1917. And I farmed it til, well, I farmed it - we rented it out to a
         fellow named MLtzenberg in '32. In '32y[we rented it out. And then
         the fellow that rented it, he gave it up. He never farmed it. So I
         had to set up again and start farming, then I farmed it for another
         ten years. Now, let's see, I took it over in '17, and then I quit it
         in about '40. Then I quit farming.
         How many acres were you farming then?
         
         Oh, I farmed about 150 acres. I farmed our home place, that was about
         100 acres and then I rented a place, oh, let's see- yeah, I had another
         place of my own. Yeah, that was about 150 acres, anyway. 'Course, fif
         ty acres of that was hay. I took care of some hay down here on the
         ^creek. That was my mother's cousin owned that and I took care of that
         the last years. He got sick and couldn't do any work; he wanted me to
         take care of his hay, so I monkeyed around with that. But that Crflihd
         farm up there on the home place-
         
         SS:  Wasn't that on the creek, too?
         Yeah, that was on the creek. It was on the creek in one way; it was
         off of the creek, it was on the hills, but we had forty acres run down
         to the creek. You know that's the way they took up their land. So it
         run down to the creek and that's where the buildings were, down on the
         creek.
         How was it then as far as what you were getting in the amount of money
         you were getting for the crops in those years? Were yo u finding it
         like you were just getting by, or were you getting quite a bit of money
         for those crops?
         
         No, we were just getting by, all. I paid a third, yeah, let's
         see, I furnished all the teams and everything. I furnished the outfit
         so I got half, and then the folks got the other half of what grain was
         raised. And then I had some cattle there, but they were mine. I made
         a little; there wasn't much money in it. There was no money in it to
         speak of. Just getting by, that's all we had to figure on is getting
         by. Not getting too much in debt. That's what anybody ever figured on
         is to keep out of debt and then make aliving. There wasn^tnybody ma
         king any money in this country only the ones that had something to sell.
         Like after the Potlatch got here, they sold logs off of the places.
         Then they got a little money. Sold the logs, but even then they didn't
         get much. It all depends on how much logs they had left, of course.
         home
         But we kept the logging off of the place, so there wasn't much
         money left- or many logs there.
         You stuck it out, I mean, did you ever very seriously consider ever
         moving to someplace else and trying to make more money?
         Nope. I didn't. We heard a lot about how wealthy some countries were
         and how big money it is. There was a girl, a cousin of mine come here
         from Minnesota and she told us how they made money there and they farm
         ed and made a lot of money. Well, I think they did make a little money
         on some things. But we went back there three of us, was going to make
         a trip, so one fall we started out and we drove clear around through
         Montana to Missoula and clear up to North Dakota. I had a cousin there.
         And we stayed there overnight. And then there was Alfred Nelson, I
         don't know, he lives in Troy. Do you know him?
         
         SS:  I don't think I do.
         He used to have the repair garage there, repair shop. He has sold that.
         Him and his cousin started that, that repair shop, so he used to be
         there. And then him and his wife had a restaurant up there on the
         other side of the post office. How long you been around Troy?
         
         SS:  About five years.
         Well, he must have been there, his wife anyway. They had-^a coffee shop
         there on the other side.
         He went back too, to Minnesota- Dakota with you?
         Yeah. He went back to North Dakota and to Minnesota. They came from
         Minnesota.
         
         SS:  So what did you find there?
         
         You found it just like we had here, only I thought it was a worse set
         up than they had here. There was nothing but a cow-milking chance there
         either. was a cow-milking chance for living, there, just like
         it was here. I couldn't see any difference. So I couldn't see anything
         else. They could raise corn and probably that was worth a little more.
         I don't know. They didn't sell that, they fed it to the pigs and the
         cattle. And it was just a cattle exchange, We had that same
         thing here. So I couldn't see any difference. I couldn't see where
         they were any better off at all. That didn't improve it any. We went
         all through Minnesota from the north end to the south, and then we came
         back by the way of Wyoming and South Idaho and up to Lewiston and then
         back here. We made that round trip. We made over two thousand miles.
         And I couldn't see anything that they had over— we had the same thing
         here. They probably had a little better chance because they had open
         ground and we had to clear this here, of course. But, it don't make
         any difference, you got a better chance some way and it's worse in
         others. Makes it more work anyway. So I didn't see any difference.
         It was all the same. And we was back there to my cousin in North Dakota
         and of course, he was there in North Dakota on that North Dakota prairie
         and he was old when we was there and he didn't work any more, but
         there was others working there and I couldn't see it.
         
         '38?
         Yeah. '38.
         Did the Depression hit you very hard here?
         Depression?
         
         Yeah, did.it hard?
         
         Well, it didn't hit us very hard, didn't seem like. We wasn't used to
         as much as some of 'em had. That didn't make any difference. We were
         making a living. We made that during Depression, too. So, it didn't
         gat back very much in this country. Might have in some countries, I
         don't know. You know, that the difference, if they've got very good
         times before, why then the Depression hits harder, but if you ain't ma"
         king any more than just a living, why, the depression don't hurt you
         so much. That's the way that works.
         
         END OF SECOND INTERVIEW
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13386</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Burkland_Joel</previous>
      <next>Butterfield1</next>
      <disp_name>Burkland_William2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
