<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/12/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Gustav Carlson, 1976-07-12, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>4:03:28</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Carlson, Gustav</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Teacher; census bureau officer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1899</birthyear>
      <residence>Burnt Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Swedish immigrants who settled in 1891; he left the area as an adult.
         Willa
         Carlson's brother-in-law
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#University of Idaho"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#construction"&gt;construction&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rural schools"&gt;rural schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#quilting"&gt;quilting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#midwives"&gt;midwives&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crops"&gt;crops&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#planting"&gt;planting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mail carriers"&gt;mail carriers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#unions"&gt;unions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#socialism"&gt;socialism&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#prostitutes"&gt;prostitutes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#students"&gt;students&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rural communities"&gt;rural communities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fraternities"&gt;fraternities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#picnics"&gt;picnics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#friendship"&gt;friendship&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Swedish Americans"&gt;Swedish Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Burnt Ridge"&gt;Burnt Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Lewiston"&gt;Lewiston&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Spokane"&gt;Spokane&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13395</file_name>
      <mp3>13396.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13396.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Fathers immigrating from Sweeden to Moscow and build some of first buildings at the
               University of Idaho
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Most of the children in father's family came to America from
               Sweden. How parents came to Spokane from Minnesota; to
               Moscow to work on the first university building. Buying Jack
               Driscoll's place on Burnt Ridge (1899). Smith place on Burnt
               Ridge. Sons bore brunt of clearing Carlson place while father
               built houses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Rural schools on the Ridge in 1899</title>
            <synopsis>Rural school. Shorter length of term. Boys became retarded
               by "laying out" of school to help on the farms. No teachers in
               the fall of 1899 on Burnt Ridge. Some teachers were not even
               high school graduates, but had passed the examination for a
               third grade certificate. Teachers were good enough to get the
               children going. Mostly men teachers on Burnt Ridge. A
               teacher who played favorites forced a boy to chew a mouthful
               of paper.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Few boys on the Ridge continued onto high school, which was in Lewiston</title>
            <synopsis>"Laying out" of school discouraged boys from going to high
               school, which was regarded as requiring brilliance. His
               brother Joe was the first on the ridge to go away to school,
               to the preparatory department of Lewiston Normal. Mother
               reluctant to leave Moscow because of educational facilities there.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Extensiveness of work on the farm</title>
            <synopsis>Extensiveness of work on the farm.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Description of mother as a hard worker</title>
            <synopsis>Mother a very hard worker. When old she worked on quilts.
               Help from an Indian woman to deliver her baby in Spokane.
               Her midwiving on the ridge. Sisters helped with farm work
               when mother was gone.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2220</time>
            <title>Description of sister Ellen who worked in Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Sister Ellen worked in Troy store when young, and worked
               in local prune and cherry orchards with other girls.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Homes in canyon off the south end of Burnt Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Homes in the canyon off the south end of Burnt Ridge. They were
               places to live, but not to make a living. Some of this land was
               purchased by Sanders.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Man confused by land and road boundaries</title>
            <synopsis>A man who couldn't survey his land boundaries right. Burying
               survey stones at the section corners. A man who used a road
               so much he thought it was his.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Homesteaders didn't stay too long in the area; many Swedish immigrants went to church
               in Troy
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Good neighbors were fair about helping each other. Most of the
               original homesteaders didn't stay too long. One man was hot
               headed. The Swedish people attended Lutheran church in Troy.
               Sanders bought land on Nez Perce prairie and sold his land to Lanphere; he died trying
               to homestead in Canada.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Origin of Burnt Ridge's name</title>
            <synopsis>Burnt Ridge's name probably came from being burned.
               Indian burning.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Parents believed they should control children's income</title>
            <synopsis>Parents believed they should control children's income.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Various work on the farm was delegated to boys of all ages</title>
            <synopsis>Older boys worked out in harvests, while younger did work at
               home. Beans required cultivating all summer; hiring boys
               became too expensive, leading to switch to peas. Bean growing
               replaced fallowing (c. 1910). A small bean crop prior to that
               time. Cycle of wheat, oats or barley and fallow. Some
               neighbors raised corn and potatoes, but markets were poor.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4380</time>
            <title>Farmers and wheat varieties</title>
            <synopsis>Wheat varieties; farmers tried the new kinds.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Problems of harvesting wheat and beans on Burnt Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Seeding fall wheat before the snows. Spring wheats. Good
               winters had good snow covering and no hard freezes after chinook
               winds. Increased concentration of beans didn't pay; problems of
               harvesting beans. Stacking grain was necessary before
               threshing machines became common. First steam rig to
               appear on Burnt Ridge; subsequent threshing machines. A
               community-owned thresher on the ridge.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5460</time>
            <title>Preparing ground for wheat planting</title>
            <synopsis>Preparing ground for planting. Beans weren't planted before
               mid-May. Rolling a log or clod masher to even the ground.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>Wheat, beans, and peas growing in Latah County</title>
            <synopsis>Planting beans in straight rows. Dew and rain determined when
               you could start in the field. Long threshing days. Wheat yields.
               Peas took hold in eastern Latah County first, because summers
               were cooler. Experimenting with varieties of peas and beans.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6600</time>
            <title>Failed attempt at Farmer's Union</title>
            <synopsis>Efforts to have farmer's union didn't come to much. Duthie and
               Green had warehouses in Troy. Warehousemen made money on
               resale of sacks. Dockage.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Modernization and improvement in lifestyle for farmers in the 1920s</title>
            <synopsis>Farmers improved their position year by year, so they could
               buy places that came up for sale. Many owned their land clear
               but mortgaged as they expanded. Cars came around World War I;
               first car around Troy was the mail carrier's. The twenties was
               hard on farmers. Some ridge families. A farmer who planted
               to grass and quit farming.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7500</time>
            <title>Hunting on Burnt Ridge a mystery</title>
            <synopsis>Hunting on Burnt Ridge remains a mystery. Wild Davy
               (David Coventry) and author William Drannon were thought
               to be the same person by many because of the picture in the book.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7920</time>
            <title>Political parties in Lewiston and Troy area; father supported Socialist Party; teachers
               discussed current events in schools
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father supported Socialist Party. His convictions were formed
               from broad reading. Populist party; Ignatius Donnelly's novel
               about the future. Father was only socialist on Burnt Ridge, but
               there were a few around Troy. Inland Echo, a Lewiston socialist
               newspaper. Socialists ran Fourth of July celebration at Troy
               one year. Socialist philosophy: public control of things
               publicly used. Sympathy for workingman. Farmers'
               independence - they felt they were getting ahead by themselves.
               A good teacher who discussed current affairs with the school
               kids predicted that many socialist ideas would be widely accepted.
               Father sometimes debated politics with neighbors.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8580</time>
            <title>Harvest fires and hostility of the IWW's</title>
            <synopsis>Hostility to IWW's. Harvest fires probably arose from smut and
               carelessness; never confirmed that they were set by IWW's.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8820</time>
            <title>School life at the U of I; classes, Army Corps, drinking at fraternities, fight between
               U of I and WSC
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His schooling. At the U of I he was in Students' Army Training
               Corps, which was disbanded before he was called. Small size
               of University. His career work. Drinking at fraternities was
               kept quiet. The university presidents' (including Lindley) discouraged fighting
               between the U of I and WSC.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9180</time>
            <title>Double standard of men and women in University</title>
            <synopsis>Double standard - a dean of women but no dean of men. Sex
               outside of marriage was kept very quiet at the university because
               it was so frowned upon. University boys at ROTC in Spokane
               went wild at night. Soliciting in Spokane and Moscow. Some
               prostitutes started as impulsive girls. Boys were too young
               to fight in the First World War; they came back demoralized and
               this was reflected in changing morals on campus.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9780</time>
            <title>Interruption of education for need to work and fulfill family duties</title>
            <synopsis>Students often interrupted education to work. Men looked at
               women as intellectual equals. Women were expected to become
               homemakers after marriage, although many worked later. He
               decided to teach because it seemed to offer good opportunities.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10380</time>
            <title>Tension between town and country youth in Moscow and Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Why more town youth went to high school than country youth.
               Social tensions between town and country were much greater in
               Moscow than Troy, where there was little difference.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10680</time>
            <title>Students seek alternate cheaper housing and hire own cook</title>
            <synopsis>A large number of students rented a house together and hired
               their own cook. Many didn't join a fraternity because of the
               extra expense. Importance of fraternities was overrated.
               Fraternity and non-fraternity students mixed freely.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10980</time>
            <title>Non-Greeks financially more independet than parents; classes; political parties; social
               activities in school
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Non-frat boys were more independent financially from their
               parents. An oddball who was a wizard with figures. Advantage
               of teaching mathematics over history. Young people
               thought they were far removed from pioneering. Difficulties
               with early cars and mads. Winter isolation wasn't great.
               Social activities at the university - dances, picnics, church groups.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11820</time>
            <title>Churches in the area; father opposed churches and family was known as heathen</title>
            <synopsis>Father's opposition to church formalism and emphasis on
               appearances. He did support Nora Lutheran Church, which
               had active missionaries. Father's independence of thought. He
               bought many books to learn the language. He wasn't a highly
               practical man. The family seldom went to church and was
               perhaps regarded as "heathen." They went to church on
               Christmas morning and Easter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12540</time>
            <title>Closeness of families that lived on the Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Closeness on the ridge came from deep ties between families,
               based on kinship and old friendships. Cnusin relationships on the
               ridge. Influence of family connections in settlement.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12840</time>
            <title>Swedish immigrants formed close communities in the area </title>
            <synopsis>Tendency to trust kin. Many on the ridge were Swedes from the
               same province in Sweden. Non-Swedes may have felt somewhat
               as outsiders. Porter got a reputation as a bully. Use of
               school as community center, for speakers and regular Friday
               night parties. Play parties at homes. Kellberg was an
               interesting character: his story about hangings in Wyoming.
               Despite opposition to dancing, young people danced in town and
               at a few special places on the ridge.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>13920</time>
            <title>Sons drank less and were less religious than fathers</title>
            <synopsis>In many cases sons drank less than their fathers; drinking sons.
               The young turned away from religion.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>14160</time>
            <title>Crime and murder in Moscow of Hays and Sly</title>
            <synopsis>Many thought that Marshall Hays was trying to get Payne Sly
               to resist to justify killing him. Hatred of Hays for arresting
               people so he could rob them. Hays had said he was going to get
               Sly. Story that Sly walked towards Moscow after the killing
               and turned himself into the sheriff. Death of Clemm, a heavy
               drinker, went unsolved; a fatal knifing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Family interrelationships on Burnt Ridge. Rural school and farm work. Changed
         attitudes of second generation. Father's socialism and religion. Non-fraternity education
         at the university. Troy killings. 7-12-76 4 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         GUSTAV CARLSON: — farm out there. And of course, they knew - realized these
         farms couldn't support that many people, they had to go elsewhere
         to work. Some few of— he was a family of eleven children- he came
         of a family of eleven children, he was the eleventh. Eight of those
         eventually migrated to America; four before he did, four of the older
         ones, and one brother came with him; they came together. And then
         two sisters followed at later intervals. So, there were eight that
         spent most of their lives here. Well, the last one did not come right
         away, most of her children had migrated first, and she took the two
         youngest and came over to join them. he.
         
         SS: But his parents didn't?
         
         GC: No, no. Well, his mother was dead almostj So he could bar.
         
         SS: How bad was it in Sweden at that time?
         
         GC: Well, it was hard work and not easy living. I guess nobody ever
         starved, that is, ? was never complete in Sweden back
         even in those days and has improved gradually since, it is quite a
         different country now and has been for a long time. I visited there
         in 1928 the first time and again in '61. Of course, I could see a
         tremendous difference in thirty-three years. But then they were
         pretty well- a lot of things done, they had good roads in and
         they had lots of cars in '28.
         
         SS: How did your father and mother wind up coming to Moscow?
         
         GC: Well, he had worked there in Minnesota. He went into carpentry,
         and he worked that and he came first to Spokane. He had a job
         waiting for him in Spokane, he had been hired by a lumber company
         that was centered in Minneapolis. They were building out there and
         they were going to build a mill and he went out there to build that
         mill, to house the machinery and put it in when it arrived, building
         the sawmill. And he had a partner in that and took a contract to
         put up the buildings and put in the machinery when it came. And he
         continued working there for some time; that was in 1887, I think he
         came out there- 1887. he went out there before father and
         managed to find a piece of land which he could buy, and he was work
         ing on that on his own time building a house on it. She came in
         the summer and my brother, Paul, was born in the fall of that year,
         he was third in the family, they already had two children, born in
         Minnesota. Around 1891, they had some depre
         SS:ion years there, panics,
         they used to call 'em, and that wasn't so good, and . work was
         getting scarcer and he came down to Moscow and that was the Steel
         Company, and the construction company that was building the first
         University building in Moscow, a wooden structure. So, he came down
         to work on that. He was building foreman on that- on the erection
         I think
         of the first university there. Quite a few years later burned down,
         somehow or other, I don't know just what year that was.
         
         SS: That's the administration building.
         
         GC: Well, they just put up a single building, in 1891. No it
         was wooden, wooden building they put up first. And the next building
         that went up was brick. I know that the first buildings I ever saw
         were brick and cement, when I was old enough to see what they were.
         
         GC: He worked the carpentry on that first building
         University building.
         And then, how did he wind up deciding to become a farmer?
         Well, he had gathered together a little money, and he came off of a
         farm and he had the land idea. taking up land and buying land.
         And the homesteaders were quite a few and some of the homesteaders
         were selling out. And that was the land that had been homesteaded
         out there by a fellow who wanted to sell out and go over to where
         his relatives, brothers, he had a lot of brothers. You've probably
         run into some Discolls- well, this was Jack Driscoll. He was a, oh,
         
         SS:- young Jack Driscoll died a few years ago. Did you know him?
         
         SS: I knew of him.
         
         GC: Well, his widow's still living, I think and his son is Dennis Dris
         coll.
         
         SS: Right.
         
         GC: Well, he was an uncle of this Jack Driscoll. Old Jack, he remained
         unmarried, but I think he gave his land to his brother Joe's sons.
         
         SS: But then, he wanted to move over to Driscoll Ridge?
         
         GC: Yes, he bought in over there at Driscoll Ridge and his relatives
         were there. The Driscolls and the Dunns and the Cunninghams were
         all his relatives. They came originally from eastern " and
         settled in there.
         
         SS: So, your father-
         
         GC: -bought that land out there. Well, he worked carpentry around
         Moscow, particularly building houses in the city and in the country
         around for about- until 1899. He was working at that. And then he
         bought that land out there. Oh, he continued to work. He worked
         for a time after he got that to get ready cash, because there were
         new houses going up, some of the old cabins were being taken down
         and new cabins (built). He built the house where Clarence Johnson
         lives. There was a fellow named Liverson lived there at that time,
         and he wanted that new house built. .One of 'em, and that house where
         Rudolph Smith lives; you know Slim Smith?
         
         SS: Yeah.
         
         GC: I vaguely remember their going up there. They came, what they did
         is came in 1902. The kids came in the house but I think Pearson
         had been up there before; I don't know which year that was erected.
         I think it was the summer before they started building on it,
         I think he wasn't satisfied with the little house. He had a big
         family, about nine children- well, they didn't have nine when they
         came, I gue
         
         SS: they had eight. And there was a little, old house on
         that place that could hardly house those so he had to- I believe
         he completed that house before he moved his family up. He was
         living down in Genesee, and he continued to own a farm down there
         after he moved up here.
         
         SS: So, your father could make some money building houses when he was
         starting farming?
         
         GC: Yes. You see, I don't think there were more than thirty acres broke
         on that place when we got out there. And the amount of land on top
         of the hill before it tipped into the canyon,was 160 acres a mile
         long and a quarter wide. It was about ninety acres. We broke up
         some rather flat land down in the canyon where it was leveled off.
         About ten acres more later on. We were busy breaking out that and
         clearing it of trees and the brush and cutting wood. We sold wood,
         we did it piecemeal there. I think it was about 1905. From 1899
         to 1905 got it all cleared out on top of the original farm.
         
         SS: How much did the kids help?
         
         GC: Oh, I would say, quite a bit. My two oldest brothers were mostly
         in command of the farming. He was out building a good deal* those
         years. He built several houses around Burnt Ridge. Some elsewhere
         in this county. I never did think particularly But I re
         member, years later, drive by in a car, "Ibuilt this house." He
         would say. (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Well, You know talking about kids helping the family-
         
         GC: My two oldest brothers, Walter and Paul, Walter at fifteen, well,
         came sixteen the next spring and he took the brunt of the work around
         there. And Paul was about three years younger- Paul was alx^ays
         strong and husky as a kid. Well, years later, he had his
         troubles, but they did an awful lot of the work; the kids did. And
         you see, there wasn't too much- they didn't go to school too much.
         They went to school, but school terms were not like they are now.
         They didn't go to school nine months of the year. They went about
         five months, in country schools. A couple of months, maybe in the
         colder weather in the fall then they generally laid off during
         the worst of the winter season andAwent about two or three months
         in the spring. They extended that to about- I don't think they ever
         got^seven months in the years in which they went to school. Actually
         the first school year I spent was supposed to be a seven months
         school, but it wasn't. The teacher left about five to
         six months, I think. That would have been in 1905.
         
         SS: That was the end of the school year?
         
         GC: the school year and they never went beyond seven months,
         though they had a good seven months the last two or three years,
         oh, about five years, I gue
         
         SS: that I school,- One year
         they had a divided term. Well, I remember my sister, Edith, was in
         school then, it was supposed to four months of the fall and
         three months in the spring, but I can't understand how they did that,
         because they were out too early to have them lay off with that much
         in between. I think it was ' that.
         
         SS: What did you think of school when you first went there?
         
         GC: Well, I kind of enjoyed it from the first.
         
         SS: What do you remember it being like?
         Well they had pretty fair teachers there, I suppose.
         And they rassled with a whole horde of kids there, up to forty,
         in a single schoolhouse, sometimes, the average was probably less
         than that. Oh, I could remember, some of the teachers didn't have
         high qualifications for education, that I know. I don't know what
         the first two teachers I had had, or three. Well, the third tea
         cher, he was mainly education in this area and he became a univer
         sity graduate by going back to school from time to time and was *~
         superintendent of a school here in this county, I think it was up
         at Potlatch before he finally retired, and he just kept on for a
         long,long time. But he took education piecemeal, while he taught
         in the meantime, he was already/married.
         
         What was school like for you, you know, as a youngster going there?
         Could you learn as much as you were ready for, or was it ?
         
         Well, I don't know whether it was or not. They all tried to allow
         a certain amount of time for all the kids and get 'em started and
         I don't know that they had any kid out there who was retarded enough
         that he couldn't learn to read within a fairly short time. They
         were at least all that bright. They didn't have any real dummies
         to contend with, you might say. There was nothing particularly bril
         liant, I suppose, about most of us. But nobody was really on
         the weak side. There was some that behaved slightly retarded, but
         the thing is the boys, so often laid out of school in the fall and
         the spring to help their parents with the work, and so they spent
         such a too small a time to get the consecutive education in. There
         were gaps. They'd come back and enter classes with other children.
         They couldn't make special classes for 'em, they'd just get in and
         they'd sometimes be in the same grade twice or if they looked ready
         
         GC: for it to the teacher,why move0up to something else. That held true
         almost up to the end of my school experience out there, except that
         last year, the state had more stringent school laws. Both qualifi
         cations of teachers and for attending and compelled them to come back
         unless they were fit first- eighteen years old before they could stop.
         That was later lowered to sixteen, because they thought there'd be
         not much use if they were sixteen to compel them to come back. A
         whole bunch of 'em came back that winter fairly early, and went to
         school.
         
         SS: Would you say that most of the boys-
         
         GC: Most of those big boys laid out- started laying out when they were
         twelve years old, a lot of 'em.
         
         SS: That, in your family?
         
         GC: Well, it more or less happened with Paul and Walter, Now
         Paul completed the sixth grade and Walter was to be in the eighth.
         Ellen told roe that she and Walter had been recommended by the teacher
         in the school they were to take the entrance examinations for the
         University Preparatory School. They had a University Preparatory
         High School, for that fall when they came out, but they never en
         tered because we moved out here. We were out here- that was one
         thing, too, they hadn't been able to get a teacher that first year.
         That's when the school stood vacant until spring.
         
         SS: On Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC: On Burnt Ridge. And then they got a girl to teach from- for a few
         months in the spring.
         
         SS: So then, you kids didn't go to school?
         
         GC: That particular year; the fall of 1899, didn't go to school.
         The wages were tremendously low for teachers in the country schools.
         Thirty dollars a month or something like that. But they got this
         girl from Little Bear Ridge. I think she'd been down to Lewiston;
         had a school then, or maybe she'd been just through high
         school or maybe not even that, because they had what they called
         first, second, third grade certificates and they could teach on
         a third grade certificate if they passed an examination in school
         subjects. And that's why some of them wasn't even high school graduates
         that taught up here. They were^young, but they passed a test
         in it. Now. Joe said, my brother Joe- later,he went into educa
         tion arid spent his life at it, that he saw the importance of finding
         out about those examinations and he saw some old lists of 'em, and
         he said they gave some hard examinations. Very hard examinations
         on school subjects so that a person passed those tests it showed
         he knew something about it, probably a whole lot more than he'd
         learned in school. So in that respect, you generally got people
         who were probably quite intelligent.
         Do you think that most of the teachers in the school, like the
         Burnt Ridge School and the other ridge schools were capable teachers?
         I think they did fairly good. Nearly all of them could get the child
         ren started, the primary kids started, they knew how to do that
         whether they'd been trained in it or not. And they taught things
         there. There were one or two that were kind of weak, I think. My
         brother, Carl, who was there when he was oh, thirteen or fourteen,
         he said that that teacher they had that year was stuck on hard pro
         blems in arithmetic. He was always good in math, he became a math
         teacher later on. And he could see that he was stuck on things
         and gave the wrong solutions. He could work 'em out himself. But
         aside from that-
         
         SS: Were they strict? The teachers.
         
         GC: Most of 'em were fairly strict, oh, not-, oh, I can remember Mr.
         Peterson that was the same man that I said taught early there, I had
         him for four months one year. He was quite strict. Had a reputation
         for that. And he's the one that stayed went on and got an
         education and got himself a good education before he quit -to go
         back to school. But the only woman teacher I ever had out there,
         strict.
         
         SS: Were most of the teachers you had, were they men?
         
         GC: All except- That was the only woman teacher I had and that was for
         only about two months.
         
         SS: I kind of had the idea that most of these schools, it was mostly
         women teaching.
         
         GC: Well, I think there were lots of women teachers, but somehow on
         like, well, on BurflTt Ridge they got men teachers. There were quite
         a few men like, well, Steelsmith here. Frank Steelsmith taught
         school two years on Burnt Ridge and he did it on a third grade
         certificate, which means He just
         had to pass an examination.
         
         SS: I heard that he was a bit of a teacher.
         
         GC: Well, he was, I think in a way. He wasn't particularly strict, but
         he was hard on some kids, easy on others. I really believe that, I
         don't think- maybe he thought that he didn't like some kids or some-
         thing. Ted Sundell I don't know if you know Ted.
         
         SS: Oh, yeah.
         
         GC: Oh, he hated him like sin! But he did something to Ted there that
         made him mad. Ted was always fooling around, chewing up paper as if
         it was gum, and to
         SS:ing out on his desk, he came over there and
         he just started picking up paper and he said, "Chew it. chew it. Chew
         it"! a sheet off of his tablet, crumpled it up and said, "Chew
         it." So, he had his mouth so full that he couldn't hardly move.
         Ted was about ready to rebel, but he didn't. Ted was a big kid then.
         He would have been difficult for Steelsmith to handle if he decided
         to rebel, but he was so mad, that I think he hated Steelsmith from
         that day. Well, it was a funny kind of punishment.
         
         SS: Yeah, it really was.
         
         
         GC: add kind of Punlshment for him to be attracting the attention of the
         other kids and doing it for that purpose, but it was an odd sort of
         thing to do, make him have so much paper in his mouth that he was
         near to choking.
         
         SS: Yeah, I can see why he wouldn't like him after that.
         Well, you know we talked about the kids, the boys laying out of
         school and helping on the places and it makes me wonder. Do you
         think that held- do you think that would wind up holding some of the
         boys back?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, it held them back. If it had been as they are now, those
         kids would have all gone on to high school probably. Every 
         But in those days, the people didn't think of such thing as high
         school, they thought that was higher education that was beyond the
         grasp of a simple farmer and farmers' kids. They had a certain res
         pect for it, but they thought it took a huge talent. It was the
         thing for the very brilliant. (Chuckles)
         
         SS: I suppose then that few of 'em would think about college if they
         didn't go to hi h school.
         
         GC: The first kid to go away to go to school was my brother Joe. Peter
         son came down and told my dad that Joe wouldn't profit by anymore
         years-ft he said he's a good scholar. And that year they had a Lewiston
         Normal School, as it was called. They had a preparatory and a
         couple of years extra rolled into one, and he went down the to go
         to school. And later Carl went. Those were the first two that left
         the Ridge. After we got started, why, we kept on going to school.
         
         SS: Your father didn't mind losing their work?
         
         Oh, no. No, he believed in education. He was sorry that he hadn't
         had . No, our parents were strong for education and were sorry
         that they weren't in the position to send everybody in the begin
         ning. And Mother actually was rather reluctant to leave Moscow,
         because she thought that they had good schools there. She was
         really put out when they came out on the farm there that year and
         found that they hadn't even gotten a school teacher for that fall.
         Then, too, I could imagine^a lot of women, I don't know how your
         mother felt about it, but there were some women- to live out on
         a farm on the Ridge would be, you know, a lot rougher than in town.
         Oh, yes, it is, it is- it was. Farm women worked hard out there.
         Most of them had children too, in those days and they didn't have
         the conveniences. No electricity; no cars, and none of that. It
         was- as far as going to town was concerned- we seldom went to
         townAmore often than we'd need to lay in groceries. And they often
         raised a few cattle and .smoked meat for the off-season. And then
         bought some fresh. They had cattle and hogs, nearly everybody,
         chickens. And they raised vegetable gardens, aid all that took
         time and work. All the chores around the farm. It x*as long days
         that farmers put in, naturally. No eight hour days, they were
         nearer fourteen, they got up in the morning, more
         than that when you count mealtimes in,before they were ready to go
         to bed.
         
         SS: You mean, the way it sounds- you were saysing, there wasn't any
         leisure time at all.
         
         GC: There wasn't any leisure during the day, really. You got up in
         the morning and started taking care of the animals and harnessing
         horses and getting ready for the fields, a large part of the time,
         spring and fall. Even in the summer there was haying and culti
         vating and things of that sort and then breakfast after you had
         taken care of your animals,Amto the fields. At noon you'd have
         a little leisure time, you had to rest your horses enough to- so
         they could stand the work, too, you know. And suppertime and
         then chores after supper. Oh, I don't know, there were times when
         it wasn't so Bushing, you know. Wintertime there was much less times, al ways went
         out and cut wood, usually then. Laid up a
         year's supply of firewood. It was all wooden stoves, of course,
         and they really burned wood. It was the cheapest thing that they
         had and most of 'em had a little on their places. Some were sort
         of lacking in that. And then they spent their leisure time breaking
         out
         
         GC: - used to walk through woods about the last quarter mile on our
         place, and we used to cut acro
         SS: to what they called the Aller road.
         That was on the Aller place, you could cut off a little on the way
         to school that way, a shorter way through. And he has a lot of
         woods down there, that you'd walk through first before we came up
         to where his fields began. There's not a tree on that place now,
         except maybe some on a piece of scab ground. (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Do you think that your found the work hard?
         
         GC: Oh, yes. Mother was always the worker. She couldn't stop working,
         even when she was old, she was always dabbling in something, if it
         was nothing else, she'd make quilts and crochet things; bedspreads
         and things like that. And she was still working on something that
         winter that she got her bad cold, which went into influenza and died,
         She was eighty-six then.
         
         SS: She was well known as a nurse and midwife, too, wasn't she?
         
         GC: Well, a midwife, yes, I don't know when Mother learned that really.
         But she knew, she'd had children herself, but she had midwifed
         children I think in Spokane and in Moscow when we lived there. Spo
         kane was just largely a village of tents when they came there in
         1887 and with quite a bunch of the Spokane Indians camped nearby.
         Actually when she was- when Joe was born there she had Indian woman
         help her for a while in the house there. She never bothered too
         much about Indians, but she thought it was rather too much when the
         women's husbands came to collect their wages. He didn't wait
         until she was home, he didn't even let the wife take the wages home.
         
         SS: What kind of midwifing-what do you remember it being like? Or doing
         the midwifing?
         
         GC: I'v known. They would call on her before they got- well,
         let's see. It was about 1908 or '09 when they got telephones. I
         was about eight-nine years old- the telephones out there and that
         helped some. But I imagine, let's see- I think it was earlier than
         that, about 1907 they managed to get phones in there, and that made
         it easier but they'd come and notify somebody and sometimes- when
         she was going acro
         SS: to Americn Ridge, and the only way that she'd
         go was eigher walk or on horseback, and usually one of the boys
         would go with her across the canyons there on the
         trails. She went over there a couple of times to deliver babies
         at the Moody house. I don't know ifNthe Moddy family's still around
         here or not. There was a Ted and an Ole.
         
         SS: Would she deliver the baby? Would she actually deliver the baby her
         self, and then would she stay and nurse the mother?
         
         GC: Well, she'd stay for some little time til she saw it was alright, or
         she could get some help in the house, if she needed it,yes. And,
         oh, she delivered some there on the Ridge. I don't know just how
         many she delivered there.
         
         SS: Was she doing all her own chores as well as that?
         
         GC: Well, when she was away on a midwifing, why, we took care of
         the house. I had an older sister who came fourteen in the fall
         that we came to the farm and she was very capable housewife
         at that age, I'd say, I think she was. I couldn't recall anything
         her about for several years, I was a baby then. And she always seemed
         to be grown up- she was between thirteen and fourteen years older
         than I was. And there was Edith, she was about three and a half
         years older than I was, too, later on. But Ellen went out to work
         early, too. There was so many things that could be done,
         you don't see prune orchards on Burnt Ridge now, but there was se
         veral large prune orchards there, and they had these driers, that
         they constructed, frame building driers with racks and things and
         knew how to dry their prunes. I wish they'd lasted until I
         had a look at 'em see how they were operated, but they
         began taking them down about that time because they found that they
         didn't make much on the prunes and they did better on the wheat.
         
         SS: Your sister worked out?
         
         GC: She worked out a good many times. She went, I think that same fallno,
         not the same fall- that same year that wetcame out there, she
         was working that fall and winter came and there was no school out
         there, she came into town and worked in one of the grocery stores
         that winter. They didn't think anything)particularly about age of
         kids going to work, as long as they did the work. And I remember
         she was going off cherry picking and prune picking and apple picking.
         There were orchards, all kinds. And disappeared
         
         SS: She would stay at the farmers?
         
         GC: Yes, they'd stay at the farmers. They came in a big groups sometimes
         in these large cherry orchards. Oh, they'd bring their own blankets
         and they'd find a place for 'em to sleep in some outbuilding, and
         sometimes just in some area they'd lay out these old blankets under
         the stars. And there was a lot of that going on. She worked on
         Little Bear Ridge and American Ridge and some of 'em moved downstarted
         in the early picking down Lewiston country, went that far.
         
         SS: She would go by herself?
         
         GC: Well, she. be other girls; they generally went in groups. And
         they did some right on Burnt Ridge for a while. I know the Kellberg
         place out there, well, they called it the Kellberg place, Ernie
         Anderson there now, he married one of the Kellberg daughters.
         There was a big prune orchard on that one and a drier. And Sanders
         lived just opposite us. We had 160 and he had 160 parallel, a mile
         and a quarter mile and he bought up some old canyon land, farms,
         that people were ready to abandon and sell for any sum because it
         didn't amount to anything but pasture land and they were silly to
         try to cultivate it. Most of 'em weren't really that, one fellow
         I know lived down there in the farm- what was our home place, small
         house and he had a sizeable family, I don't know how they got 'em
         in it.
         
         SS: Lived up in the canyon?
         
         GC: Yes, in the canyon down there on a little flat, where they could make
         a garden around it. And sometime- somebody had occupied it before
         him and had a pear orchard. That's on what is now the Trout place
         out-Vhere.
         
         SS: How could he make a living?
         
         GC: Well, he didn't make a living on that. He worked for the railroad
         and kept his family out there and they raised garden and he was a
         section hand. He didn't make much either. With quite a family,
         they had a spot to live on and raise a garden. That was about all
         he wanted and a little hay for a horse, something like that.
         
         SS: Were there a number of people living in the canyon at that time
         
         GC: Well, there are at least- one, two, three, let's see there was
         about four hou ?es, old hou ses, I remember around the southern
         part of Burnt Ridge, the point down there.
         
         SS: They were in the woods.
         
         GC: Well, it was not very heavy woods on those canyon sides. Well,
         the other had pretty good timber around it, yes, and a little flat
         and actually we cultivated that afterwards, some. haytiown
         there and fed it to the cattle, usually in the canyon. Cut and
         stacked it down there. And then around the other side was what
         was called the Cusick place, and that was a bigger cabin, but I
         never did see it whenjanybody occupied it; they'd gone. And that
         land was bought by Sanders, he just used it for pasture. I don't
         know, he must have got it at  price- cheap figure; they
         wanted anything they could get out of it. And up the canyon, just
         about opposite the Rudeen place; you know where Jhat is; well,
         Arthur Anderson owned- Arthur Anderson's son- George Anderson, you
         know him, he owns it down there which is an old brick house. Rudeen,
         Paul Rudeen's father- do you know Paul?
         
         SS: No, I didn't.
         
         GC: He didd about four years ago. His widow's still living, Mike Rudeen's
         out here. You've probably met Mike.
         
         SS: Yeah, I know who he is.
         
         GC: Well, his grandfather settled in there and he bought that land. And
         a family named Monahans lived there. Monahan was a son-in-law of
         Cusick. And that was a still better house, quite a bit better. And
         then there was another one; oh, it wasn't but a little ways.in the
         canyon, why he didn't- I don't know how it is, it must have had some
         topland so close to it and why he didn't build his house up on top,
         I don't know, but he didn't. Wheeler, was his name. And that was
         abandoned, too; all of those were abandoned, except this one that
         was on the which Sanders bought, our neighbor first.
         He it^for pasture land. And I remember that family just rented
         that place that was living in there. It was homesteaded by a fellow
         named Coberland. This fellow lived there Hagen. And I don't know
         how many children there were, but I went down there when I was a
         little kid about five years old, seemed to be an unending stream of
         little girls around there. (Chuckles) Most probably fewer than I
         thought.
         
         SS: You know, in some places I have heard that they would have-some of
         the neighbors would have disputes over there land,the boundaries
         and that kind of thing.
         
         GC: Oh, that's happened a few times, I think. Actually, that has hap
         pened. There was a little fellow on American Ridge. He picked
         up eighty acres of land; only about ten acres- I don't think there
         ten acres- six or seven on top of the hill. Dad built his house
         for him, and the rest of it was down there and he had an exaggerated
         idea of how much pasture you could get out of th«f . The steep hill
         side on the American Ridge and timber, not much grass reached up a
         little ways on Burnt Ridge, across hat, bordering our place and
         he started surveying it himself. And he couldn't survey,Agot his
         lines all crooked. I think on the other side of the- on our side
         we saw it was coming altogether wrong and talked to him about it.
         And his son, Fritz, came over there, he saw it was wrong, too, he
         helped straighten his father out, so he got that fence he already
         started fencing it and setting up posts. We told him to ask the sur
         veyor to come out and do it, we wanted to make sure that he understood
         that he was wrong and they laid itAdown to the corner, but it was way
         off- about sixty, seventy yards off of his lines. His lines weren't
         even straight. I don't know, I don't remember too much about the
         boundary, that probably came before- in the early days when
         ti was all wooded and they didn't know to find the stones. They
         put heavy stones, put markings on them that they ujtalerstood and
         sometimes when they did that, we found that they'd put a
         stone- sank it right in the roadway before it entered our place, and
         there was supposed to be a stone there so they started digging down.
         He took a few measurements, he looked up the road and says it should
         be the county road which took so much at side, fifty feet
         wide, said this is in the middle of the road here and it should be
         here and he found it, a great big stone had been buried there as a
         corner stone. I don't know, I think that survey had gone
         through but who knew where to find those stones, and they'd have to
         have a surveyor out and most of 'em couldn't afford to- afford that
         much.
         
         SS: So the surveyor had laid stones, right along.
         
         GC: Yes. He had.
         
         SS: I wonder if there were trees that they would probably prefer to put
         a mark on trees.
         
         GC: Well, if there was a tree nearby, the description said so many feet
         from a tree, that's what it said by this, and they said- and there
         was something hung in the tree. I don't know what they said they
         up it hung in the tree. Anyway, one of the surveyors climbed - measurec
         where it should be and - here this must be the tree and he
         out climbed up the tree ajeld says, "Here it is." And the marking was
         just about gone, he said, "but this is it, alright, here."
         Something had been wired to it. I think it was a little stone, cir
         cled wire around it and put the wire in this tree and he wired the
         tree. The tree had been growing in the meantime and it had em
         bedded the wire in there- into it. Of course, what they needed was
         a surveyor's description before they could start looking for those
         stones. And sometimes those trees got cut down in the process of
         clearing the land. I don't remember on Burnt Ridge itself of any
         disputes; Did you hear of any?
         
         SS: Not boundaries, no. I was thinking in more general disputes. I
         was thinking about whether you knew of any disagreements among the
         old neighbors around.
         
         GC: Well, no, - there was disagreements with neighbors, those things
         took place, of course, like every once in a while they- somebody
         thought the other one was acting like a bad neighbor and not keeping
         up his share of the fences and things like that. Oh, there was
         things like that happened, I guess I know one neighbor in the old
         days, the he'd sort of made to his house ran right through a
         neighbor's place through woods there, came out to the main road.
         And he'd used it so many years he sort of regarded it as his own,
         but actually, it wasn't. He was entitled to egress along the line
         fence and then corner and then follow another line fence where
         they laid the public roads. He didn't like it at all, but nothing
         came of it. I think he was somewhat ignorant of the law. He thought
         if he used the road long enough it became his.
         
         SS: What do you think made a good neighbor, or on the other hand, a
         bad neighbor?
         
         GC: Oh, someone that wasn't- if there was things to be done together
         and they wanted certain work done then he helped you and you'd help
         him and you would try not to be unreasonable in your charges and
         willing to pay for his. You'd be willing to pay for work he does
         and sometimes you just exchanged work, but not to be (unjreasonable
         about it, to be reasonable about how much work should be done for
         the other. And generally keeping up your own shares of the fences
         that needed- because horses and cattle loose
         in the fields at certain times of the year, like in the fall before
         they sowed. And they often had fields fenced off, too, so that they-
         
         SS: Do you think that—?
         
         GC: Sometimes, of course, they were just personalities that clash-
         That was a fairly normal neighborhood most places.
         That group that was there- I don't know, a lot of them were people
         that had homesteaded. Quite a few were original- of the original
         homesteaders there were very few that actually remained too long.
         The Ruberg family was one. Mrs. Walner owns that part now, down
         on Burnt Ridge. I don't know if she lives there or not yet.
         
         SS: I haven't met her?
         
         GC: No. And Jack Driscoll, that we bought from was one, and Sanders
         one. He was a Canadian.
         
         SS: You would think that most of that land had changed hands by the time
         your family came out?
         
         GC: A large part of it already had changed hands. I don't know who orid
         She ginally was the- Any Allert livea but he came a few years
         after us. He bought from Gerard, but Gerard was more of a land
         speculator than a farmer. He bought some places out there.
         
         SS: You talk about personality conflicts; what would something like that
         not interested in names or anything.
         
         GC: Over? Oh, yes, they just generally forgot about it eventually.
         
         SS: Well, but I mean what would cause it in the first place?
         
         GC: Oh, I don't know, it's just- oh, the same thing as somebody- some
         body was a little bit of a bully and tried to run things and some
         body'd call him on it.
         
         SS: I was thinking, you know, that to be living in the same place for
         years and years with the same neighbors that you could have some
         thing that would build up with time-
         
         GC: Oh, yes, it's true, they were and I believe they were seldom lasting.
         And very peacefulest of the time. You did have one hotheaded neigh
         bor there, he eventually moved, too, but he lived there a long time.
         His father wasithe youngi^Tan, it was the son that was hotheaded. He
         was just But he calmed down as he got older, too. Got
         married, had a family, he was very quiet then. (Chuckles) Strictly,
         I wouldn't recall what started any of it, little things. I know,
         I heard of this- these other two a fued started up
         between a couple of fellows over a disagreement.
         
         SS: Did most of the people there go to the same church?
         
         GC: They did. But by the time we got there the large part of them were,
         and they got moreso. That community became rather Swedish in ori
         gin. Sanders was not, he was a Canadian, he and his wife and-fhevhad
         relatives out here, a whole bunch of them. Mrs. Sanders had
         three brothers and a sister, they all came by way of Minnesota and
         I think those old folks moved out their parents first in covered
         wagon days. They were real old-timers. One of the first settlers
         probably in the area around Troy.
         
         SS: What was the church? Was it just at the end of Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC: No. We never had one on Burnt Ridge.
         
         SS: Oh, I didn't know that.
         
         GC: We came to Troy.
         
         SS: Oh, they came to Troy?
         
         GC: The Lutheran Church at Troy and it's still in existence, it's the
         one that's had a continuous existence there. I think it's probably
         subscribers for the only one that's had a really continuous existence
         it since that time. And there were a lot of them Swedes and Nor
         wegians settled north of Troy and east of Troy toward Deary onto that
         area there andA northern parts of Little Bear and Big Bear Ridgeswell,
         they were a mixture of course, and then there was pure brutespurely
         one thing or the other. When I started school- well,.Sanders ~^Mtfy
         was living there, but Sanders moved over to Melrose. He got that
         idea when he- he went out harvesting, as they called it, they had
         these long harvests with steam engines and he was a good steam en
         gineer anqhis son usually went with him as the water hauler with
         the four-horse team. And he worked for somebody over;on the Nez
         Perce Prairie, that wanted him back every year, he could handle
         an engine and he didn't want to lose him, so he got interested in
         land over there so he sold this place to a fellow who was also trying
         to speculate in land. that lives in Troy. An
         oldish man then, but he was interested in buying and selling land.
         And he sold this here and moved over there. But then he got the bug
         to go to Canada, and some of his brothers were already in- had reaced
         western Canada from eastern Canada and he spent about three years
         there and then he went up and homesteaded in Alberta, near Calgary.
         I talked with his daughter here about five or six years ago,
         Kyoungest daughter, who was a little older than I was, and he died
         about two years after he got there; heart attack. She said the
         family never knew that he had a heart condition, he never told them.
         Said, besides her dad was too old to pioneer fit his age. He was a
         pretty old man to have as young a family, must have married late in
         life.
         
         SS: One thing I was thinking of- do you happen to know where Burnt Ridge
         got its name?
         
         GC: Well, I'm not so sure, but they said there'd been a fire across that
         and it burnt out . I believe that there'd been a pretty good
         flame at one time, because there were still charred trees in our
         canyon, charred- stems, so there'd been
         some fire up that distance, how much of Burnt Ridge it had covered,
         I don't know.
         
         SS: I heard that the Indians did quite a bit of burning.
         liked
         
         GC: Well, you know, they did burning, or they the underbrush to
         disappear, so they would set fire at damp time of the year and
         let the underbrush get started and usually didn't harm the big
         trees. And then it was kind of clear. Cleared enough so that the
         big fires wouldn't so ctten start during the summer, during the hot
         months, because it's the small brush at the bottom that gets
         the big ones started, they have to get up enough heat before they
         start streaking up into the sky and burning the big timber. They
         used to do that they said because they wanted to be able to see
         through the trees for the deer hunting in the fall. Get them cleared
         out. And they'd do it year after year and it didn't do much damage
         to the big timber and it helped them in hunting. It wasn't so easy
         for the deer to hide. Well, there was logic in their way of looking
         at it.
         
         SS: You know, when you were talking about your sister working out and
         about the boys helping at home clearing land, and what that makes
         me really wonder about is, what the mea was about - the parents
         held then about whether the work that the kids did was for the kids
         or whether it was for the parents. How did they look at it?
         
         GC: Well,, I suppose the main thing was they really believed that they
         should control the kids incomes, that varied with parents, some
         were more liberal than others in their way of looking at things
         and the kids usually have some say in how their earnings went and
         others didn't.
         
         SS: What was your father's attitude?
         
         GC: Oh, he wanted to make sure that we didn't —
         
         END OF SIDE B
         
         GC: — there shouldn-t be anything wasted on- on what he would think
         of as foolishness. Ellen used to bring home things a lot for us smaller children,
         I remember that, some nice article of clothing or something like
         that to please us, even a few toys, when you were small. The boys
         used to go out harvesting too, Walter went out a good deal and the
         younger ones could take care of the work during the summertime, the
         chores and hayA and things like that, before the bean raising began
         and this country was all beans before it was peas, like they have
         now. There wasn't such a heavy summer schedule until the grain ri
         pened, it was just hay. And beans came on they had to be culti
         vated for weeds, they planted 'em in rows and that was always a
         summer long job for when they come out of the ground that occupied
         people. They had to hire- and they hired largely kids from town in
         the summertime to come out and hoe beans. And that got to be too
         expensive a method when wages kept going high, too, and they found
         peas did better. The first peas didn't seem to do as good, I think
         they improved the quality of those- of field peas, or somethingmaybe
         they didn't know how to fertilize like they do now. Of course,
         they planted without fertilization for many years and they found that
         beans helped. It's a nitrogen ple*nt, you know, it's a nitrogen
         absorbing plant and that's why it was so popular, too, they could
         raise better wheat if it had beans on it the year before. And they
         idle had to fallow before that. They just had to let it lie and grow up
         to weeds and then grind it in with the disc, kill 'em off every so
         often. But the development of* beans as an alternate crop they gen
         erally had something sowed on an acre every year now. That didn't
         begin until the end of beans, about 1908 and '09 in large quantities,
         Oh, I remember a little bean field x*e had about ten acres once be
         fore, but that was harvested ourselves by hand- by pulling the beans
         and threshing them off on a canvas. It was a slow, painful process but we put away
         several sacks of beans for ourselves for the year
         and sold a little excess That comes more under the head of gar
         dening than it does of a money crop.
         
         SS: So, you practiced fallowing prior to that? You'd grow wheat and
         then leave it fallow the next year?
         
         GC: Well, not two years,Aevery other year, every three years or four
         years, fallow the ground, and then change from wheat to oats, to
         oats or barley.
         
         SS: What do you mean? After the fallow?
         
         GC: Well, generally right after the fallow wheat, then follow it with
         oats, maybe one year or two years, oats or barley, and more oats
         than barley. This recent development of barley is a little bit-
         The recent development of barley is sort of a renewal. There was
         a time when they almost quit barley and they got as good prices for
         the oats and they could raise more of it, usually. Much more oats
         and less barley raised at one time. Now, those were the only ones.
         Cook, some people raised some corn crops and some potato crops,
         but nobody ever made anything great on 'em, and they were discon-
         tinued. neighbor that came out from Oklahoma, he lived
         just north of us, that place is owned by Ed Ramsdale now, but he
         had tried several things and some of that land was young and he
         raised some big corn crops.
         
         SS: Raised corn there?
         
         GC: Corn. Got some big crops on it and he got some potato crops.
         But he didn't have much luck with sale on those things, either. Po
         tatoes 'd be low and potatoes had an uncertain value. And sometimesoh,
         we had a neighbor, before he bought that place, which once be
         longed to Sanders, it was rented out for a period of three years
         to a couple of different farmers, one stayed one year and one stayed
         two and the last year, they paid such high prices for potatoes
         the year before that he thought he'd make it on potatoes. My goodness the bottom dropped
         out of them the next year, so much so, that
         he didn't even haul all his potato crops to town. Couldn't make
         wages on it.
         
         SS: What about corn? I wondered about corn. It seemed to be if you
         could grow it some places-
         
         GC: Oh, it grows alright, but we just can't compete with the Midwest
         on corn, for a corn country. It just doesn't seem to be as good Acorn
         in the country here. They took in some of this special highgrade
         corn they developed in Iowa and Nebraska and those places
         and tried to get it- but they sometimes often put in more or less
         as a garden crop; sweet corn, and use it during the summer so they'd
         have the corn on the cob to eat. All along I think- I don't know
         if there's|any gardeners left that didn't do that. Heck, Bruce did
         it out there when he was living east of Deary, they had a little
         sweet corn. Sweet corn and sunflowers.
         
         SS: What species of wheat were people growing on Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC: Well, it's changed with the
         
         SS: I mean back around the turn of the century.
         
         GC: Oh, there was what they called Little Club, belonged to the club wheats
         and it was succeeded largely by the Jenkins Club which had a red
         
         SS: The Jenkins Club?
         
         GC: Jenkins Club, and Little Club and Big Club as they called them, named
         after the- more about the size of the kernels- the size of the heads
         than the kernels. The Little Club usually yielded heavier. Smaller
         heads, but more of them. Stoo^ out more. And then they began getting-
         and Red was a type. That was brought in from the Ukraine.
         And Turkey Red. That was a Turkish wheat,^it was a bearded wheat.
         And they were reddish kernels, both of them. Red Russian
         soft what, but Turkey Red was a hard wheat and commanded a little
         premium. Main trouble was it didn't yield as well as the
         other kind, the soft wheat and most people will quit it because
         too many less bushels to the acre than could be covered by the
         premium from the hardness Blue Stem was an old favorite. It was
         both spring wheat and the fall wheat. Turkey Red and Red Russian were fall wheats.
         Little Club and Big Club were spring wheat. Jen
         kins Club could be planted either way. And then I remember several
         of the other- we begun getting hybrids. Hybrid No. 128 and Hybrid
         No. 143, we raised both of those kind.
         
         SS: Did you do a lot of experimenting and people in general in those
         days?
         
         GC: Yes, they would try new wheats came out and new varieties of
         oats. I remember what they called side oats, instead of just a
         spray of heads they were in clusters of four or five, six to a side,
         to the side b oats. Looked kind of unbalanced, small
         I don't know, it seemed to be about as good as any other.
         
         SS: Did you ever hear about Adams Alaska wheat? That fellow from Julia
         etta that was putting out-
         
         GC: Well, there was a- what they called the Alaska wheat at one time, I
         remember. I don't remember it too well, but it was introduced down
         here. Maybe it was the same or not,as Adams.
         
         SS: This fellow in Juliaetta was pushing his won wheat that he called
         Alaska wheat.
         
         GC: Lately?
         
         SS: No.
         
         GC: Long time ago.
         
         SS: Yeah, around 1910.
         
         GC: Maybe that was it, I don't recall much about that, except there was
         a so-called Alaska wheat. I sort, imagined that was one of those hardy
         wheats that they could grow around Fairbanks on the short season
         basis in the summer.
         
         SS: Well, let me ask you- could you describe to me pretty much what the
         season was like? When you first- what you would do for the planting
         and taking care of them and the harvesting the crop and when you star
         ted it and when you finished it?
         
         GC: Well, starting the you tried to get as much fall wheat as
         you could. And that entailed- before they started raising beans,
         entailed the summer fallow to s eed it along in September- or I mean,
         October or November, usually, they wanted to get good rains it
         and sprout it up. And there was some difference there. I remember wheat it was much
         raised and lasted longer and
         probably still used, forty fold wheat, because the proper time to
         put it in, most people thought was the last thing before the snow
         fell, just have enough moisture to sprout it underground and it lay
         there until spring and come out in the spring. So it was tricky
         trying to determine just how late they should risk it. And they
         tried- a normal way when they started raising beans was to use the
         bean ground and get that in as soon as they could after the be^xis
         were harvested off. The bean harvest was usually later than the
         wheat harvest; get the wheat harvest done mostly in August and the
         bean harvest might last into September. And then vou'd sow that and
         then you'd go to plowingAthings and try to get all the plowing done
         that was possible in the fall. The idea was to get it all done but
         the type of season you had sometimes interfered and depending on
         the land, rains, you couldn't determine how rainy or how dry a fall
         you'd have. We had falls where there was mild enough even if you
         had a little rain to plow to the end of November, others where they'd
         by stop the first of November.
         
         SS: Were there falls where you couldn't get the wheat in at all?
         
         GC: Well, I don't remember any on our own farm, at that time, when I
         was a kid. But, they always managed to get the farming in sometime.
         But;I think there have been one or two falls like that, I've heard
         of here where it started raining in September and didn't quit long
         enough to get the fields dry enough.
         
         SS: Wheat was the only crop that you put in in the fall?
         
         GC: Yes. There was a fall barley, but I don't believe too many of 'em
         used fall barley, too afraid it might freeze out. Wouldn't stand
         the winter, and so they put it in in the spring. Oats was strictly
         a fall crop and much more popular during the years that I grew up
         out there than it is later on.
         Oats was planted in the spring?
         h'the spring, yes. And barley, they planted barley.
         But people didn't want to plant their wheat in the spring?
         Well,they couldn't get it in in the fall, like that, then they
         would plant it in the spring. And some split it, put in spring wheat
         too. Sometimes the fall and^winters were too severe and the fall
         wheat was slow coming on in the spring, the cold springs, and it
         wasn't any better than if they would have planted in the spring.
         There were what they called spring wheats and fall wheats, like Blue
         Stem and Big Club in the old days were the principal spring wheats.
         Later on Jenkins Club was used in the spring, too. Then thev had the
         fall wheats.
         
         SS: What kind of winter did the farmer hope for for the wheat?
         
         GC: Well, what you hoped for was not too cold a winter, and since they
         knew they was going to be freezing and more sometime or other, they
         liked a good snow cover, because the snow on top of the snow would
         absorb the freezing and it isn't like Alaska where it freezes the
         soil a long ways down and it would be kind of frost free on the surface
         if had a good covering of two feet of snow. That would be
         a nice amount to have over the fall wheat until it melted in the
         spring and then they could afford a hard freeze after the snow was
         gone. They were sort of set for that. That was one of the risks
         of course, of fall wheat, that the snow would disappear under
         Chinook or under rain and it would have a hard freeze on that stuff
         you got
         beforeAa snow cover. That was called winter-kill, was the term
         generally used, and is still used, Ithink, where fall wheat (is)planted,
         I guess practically all this planted around here now is fall wheat,
         isn't it?
         
         SS: Yes, the wheat.
         
         GC: Uh-huh. I don't think too many people plant spring wheat except if
         they got stuck.
         
         SS: Were Chinook winds pretty common then?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, they always thought they would get one or two during the
         winters.
         
         GC: Yes, a little flurry of snow before a freeze would come.
         
         SS: Sometimes you would lose part of that anyway.
         
         GC: Oh, yes, it would be damaged. I don't remember that we ever had
         down our farm one so damaged that we replanted, it looked fair
         enough to bring a good crop and I think our fall wheat was the best
         ever had there, really. It was a steady diet. It really made
         a big difference then to get it in in the fall rather than the spring?
         
         GC: Um-huh. Beans were very good for a while and the price was so comparable
         enough that you didn't need to have- later on, they raised beans with
         a lot more pounds to the acre but then the expenses grew on and
         the price didn't rise in proportion, taking all the harvesting that
         beans take. take cutting, don't handle them with combined har
         vester or it'll shatter 'em out, had to be cut together and put through
         a threshing rig. Stacked and let dry a little and then hauled 'em
         in or stack them, one of the two. And they often stacked 'em be
         cause it was felt that the weather would be too undefendable at that
         time a year in September or late August to risk the rain them
         because they'd have to- if they would start laying there and drying
         out the seeds would start popping- the pods would start popping open.
         They would stack them and then dry them out?
         No, they let 'em dry. Then they'd stack 'em.
         
         GC: Stack and top them, generally with a canvas or^straw and wait for a
         threshing machine to get around. That was one of the ways. Of course
         the first threshing machines that I know, all threshed out of stacks.
         They stacked their grain. There weren't so many threshing machines
         that they could get to- you didn't know how many weeks you'd have to
         wait before you could get it threshed. We had to wait an awful
         long time one year before we got a deal. They had an old horsepower
         through rig. And by the way, I saw- we were going my sister-in-law's
         pictures here, and there was a picture of her father, Mr. Cummings,
         it was marked with an arrow and that was he, and they didn't see
         where they got the power, somebody asked me, oh, it Darcell's husband-
         Mavis' son-in-law, well, here it was, a group of about six teams
         going 'round and 'round on a power machine, and that was whatthrough
         a cable, not a cable, it was a rod.that turned over and over
         and turned the threshing machine. That's the first kind I remember.
         They had that kind on Burnt Ridge,the first time I saw them. And
         that year that thing couldn't work went out of commission and left
         the Pearson family, who lived^where Slim Smith now lives and our
         family and Porter- but Porter, he had a threshing machine. We lived
         down there below Slim Smith's and I don't know if there was a house
         at the edge of the canyon, I don't know if there was a house left
         there or not, but that was mostly a canyon one, very small, but he
         owned a threshing machine and he was a threshing machine man.
         
         SS: Left these families without any threshing?
         
         GC: Well, he had very little- yes. He had his family living there but
         he did very little farming, he was a horseman. He did horse work.
         
         SS: I mean is, is this when this went out of commission
         
         GC: No, this othere one here, it was just gone, didn't know how to fix
         it or too expensive, it was owned by a few people - owned stock in
         it, bought it together. He, he came down at the end of the season,
         he'd been out threshing, oh, quite a ways away from Troy with his
         threshing machine and he pulled in he threshed Pearson's first,
         which is nearest his place and he came down and threshed ours. The
         first stem rigs was on that- Burnt Ridge, threshed those two places
         at the end of the season. We had our grain stacked, of course, like
         did, of course, in those days and we'd had rain in between, it
         was dried off at that time. They hauled up that threshing machine
         over that grade coming up the road there, the road to our p ce in
         there and threshed. Sanders wasn't raising any grain in those days,
         hardly. I think maybe he had moved away that year, it is possible that he had.
         
         SS: Is that why they stacked it instead of leaving in the field?
         
         GC: Because they wanted it protected against the rain?
         Protect it against rain, because they didn't know how long it would
         be before they could get (it) threshed.
         
         SS: And then they went over towards leaving it in the fields when they
         felt more confident that threshing machines would make it?
         
         GC: Yes.
         
         SS: Because I know in later years they did a lot more of that bundling
         than they did.
         
         GC: oh Yes they started that. When you had a season of twenty-five daysthreshing
         season could be done in about twenty-five to thirty days,
         they went to leaving it in the bundles. K Sometimes they had to wait
         two months before a threshing machine.
         
         SS: What changed that?
         
         GC: They got more machines in, more people could buy machines.
         There were an awful lot of people that didn't have much cash to
         buy^thing . And there were very few threshing machines, old-fashioned
         types too, and they got better threshing machines ' worked. Not many
         years after that time there, oh, I think, let me see, I know we
         had threshing machines came in on Burnt Ridge from outside for a
         couple of years. Paine- there's still Paine families around Troywould
         be grandfather or great grandfather to most of 'em, he brought
         one in*once. And Hokenson, Hokenson and Gunderson- there's still
         Hokensons I know, too, around here, from Bear Ridge. They brought
         a threshing machine in and then the farmers went together and pur
         chased one. They got the price of a new machine and everybody that
         wanted to put in as many dollars as he thought he could, so they
         got enough to buy it, threshing and engine.
         
         SS: So, it was joint-owned.
         
         GC: Joint-owned, with each man having so much stock in it according to
         how much he put in. We were in on that and nearly all the farmers
         were. I believe a few of the very small farmers didn't go into it
         and some that were renters didn't go into it. (^plUSeJ
         Now, if you had good weather in the fall and you were planting
         on bean ground on which weed cultivators had been run during the
         summer and it was still pretty loose and weed free, the thing to doprobably
         the best thing to put on it was a springtooth harrow, you
         know, those goes over in springs and pulls in behind, and that usu
         ally was very good at level ing little spots in there and usually
         loosened it up enough you could seed right in it. Sometimes if there
         was a little too much weed handled in there it probably be
         better to use a spiketooth harrow on top of the springtooth, or
         afterwards, to smooth the ground after seeding. Sometimes they just
         put it in and you were through. That's when you Wbve springtooth
         into a drill, that's when you have bean ground. And, of course, on
         summer fallow, you usually used a disc harrow. Rolling disc, you've
         seen them too clean^that up and you uaually had to use a spiketooth
         on that to level it, to get out those ridges that the disc
         formed and then put the drill in. Usually you didn't need a harrow
         afterwards, sometimes people did to make it smoother, as smooth as
         possible for witner and figured onee the snow was on it would pack
         evenly and they wouldn't much . Usually they had
         on these drills a little chain back of these shoes at which the
         seed went into the ground that was very good level,If you had
         drags one with a good- with those good little on 'em, they were made
         different, some were lots better than others, it acted much like
         a leveler. Now for beans, it was best to start with the
         Nand let lie open during the summer to absorb as much moisture as
         posssible before the- under the ground moisture and generally leveled
         real it. Sometimes had to level it if it was bumpy and^washed by heavyby
         several thaws and several that- and a spike tooth harrow was the
         best thing to level it with. And then usually it is better to just sometimes
         you put a disc on, not so bad, sometimes you put- if it
         was bad you might put the spiketooth first and then you disc, other
         times you'd reverse that according to the condition of the ground
         to get it level. And then it'd be- that was done as early as pos
         sible, but it didn't need to be done too early. There was no use
         preparing it too early because- we always considered it dangerous
         to plant much before midMay, because of late freezes and get the
         crop in and have the ground cold and freeze and the ground cold and
         the beans wouldn't sprout so good. But sometimes earlier, the tenth
         of May or so on, like that and plant on into midJune,put in a garden
         as late as that and sometimes the weather forced postponement, so
         that was one reason why they wanted to start as early as they could
         if they felt the ground had warmed up sufficiently to sprout beans
         well. That, you nearly always had that harrowed and often they used
         to run a roller^ it. Some people had these log rollers, homemade,
         a big log and they bored a hole right through the center and put a
         rod through there and this log was used to roll ground and make it
         even. Break down all the clods and have it real smooth. Some used
         what they caled a clod masher, those were usually homemade, too.
         Made of heavy planks and sort of built one slanting this way and one
         slanting under it always, so that they'd fit down and if you had
         a little rough field and it was dried out enough that there was some
         weight;it pretty big clods in it yet, why, you could if you wanted to
         and oh, just use stones or anything to weight it to make it suf
         ficiently heavy to smash those things down. They were generally a
         two-horse rig, in the horse days, and the roller was a two-horse rig
         
         GC: See the markings of the bean planters, see, they went up and down
         two of them at a time, two, and keep them the same far apart they
         usually use a little stake to set at each end. I know when we used
         to run the stake with string attached to one side of the field to
         the other as a guideline, run to keep the rows as straight as pos
         sible for cultivating, so that the cultivator could be handled on it
         without tearing up beans. If they were out of line it would )te that.
         But lately they got a bean planter with a trip on them. These very
         first ones they required a wire trip, a wire coiled across the field
         right between the horses and it had little knots in it all the way
         and it was tripped on those things, those were the first? That was
         a slow process you had to reset those every time you came to the
         end of a row and put them back. But those were succeeded by a
         trip that they had right on it an automatic trip on the- to let
         the beans down. They planted, say flat beans, two feet apart, but
         some of em took off that trip afterA and planted a single row
         just letting the beans fall in a small space so you one bean
         at a time as you walked along, one or two beans and filled the row
         complete. They wanted to have them so they could cultivate both ways,
         The first one is squares, north and south, say on a field and then
         east and west. That was given up after a fex* years and it made it
         much easier. You generally just watched where the succeeding line
         was, where the wheels just run up and you either just guess the
         distance, estimate so that you were the right distance all the way
         up or you could attach a little marker like a kind of a, oh, it was
         usually a slat and another^to it, at a certain distance, nailed to
         it so that slat would be following the previous mark, the wheel
         you mark of the previous one and then you always knew how far'away from
         Of the other track so as you could make- the team would step^easy on
         the bit and they would guide nice and straight up and down, you
         could get rows that to be^a perfect pattern. I know we had
         a dandy team for that in later years there, high- black mare
         and a horse that could walk right along with her and they just
         stepped off those bits and you had to hold them to a certain spot
         and they went right up the line and down the other.
         
         Black bear?
         
         Mare.
         
         I thought Bear was the name of- of that horse, you know.
         
         No, a mare that's a kind of a leader in the field team, she could
         lead out and set the pace, if you had a six-horse team working, some
         thing like that.
         
         When you were planning like that, would you do it from early morning
         until nightfall?
         
         Well, actually- sometimes you could put in a long day, but then, now
         it depends on what you were doing. You wouldn't want to start plantingNif
         there was a heavy dew on the ground the night before, you
         wanted it to dry out so that the shoes that were planting the
         ground where the seed fell through would run along that without clogging with mud
         and the same way with the drill. If you'd had
         a little too much rain, a little rain probably wouldn't hold you
         up more than an hour or a heavy dew. You waited for that to come off
         in seeding, or in plowing- oh, even in harrowing it could get a lit
         tle too moist sometimes early morning to start out, but plowing
         you'd usually start right out on that, it didn't bother much, un
         less it had a rained and really got muddy. But there was warm days
         particularly the harvest days were long days. They threshed as much
         as- oh, some of 'em made eleven hours, some made thirteen
         hours in the field threshing because everybody was anxious to get
         this done. They didn't object to long hours in order to get that
         done. And the wages, of course, were naturally higher for harvest
         work than any other time, when the wheat harvest was on and the
         bean harvest was on. And they'd thresh long hours. They shortened
         'em up as the years went by, didn't go quite as long. I know when
         my brother, , sewed sacks, that was one of the hard jobs on
         a threshing machine for Edmundson and Paine- went out to that Ridge
         and they'd put in a fourteen hour day in work, their meals outside
         of that, which was something. And they had one of what was known
         as a very big rig at that time, they'd 1,600, 1,700 sacks in
         a day. And a grain sack weighed about 140 pounds, they hold of wheat,
         sack sewers and they usually use two to handle that. A man could be plenty
         tired I think, handling 600, 700, 800 sacks in a day's time,-for
         fourteen hours. That was, of course, always determined whether they
         were in good heavy grain or not. The heavier the grain the faster
         they turned out the sacks. If they had a fellow that had a remar
         kably good crop of wheat, forty bushes, or forty-five bushels, that
         was good for those days. They didn't have these fertilizers to take
         care of it. Then the grain really rolled through.
         
         SS: What would the average be?
         
         GC: Oh, I suppose, year in and year out, thirty bushel or thirty-five
         for fall wheat. Highly variable according to seasons, of course.
         There was lots of forty bushel wheat one year and
         sink to twenty bushel wheat in a bad year. But it was the day be
         fore fertilizers. It was a little more consistent I think, after
         they started raising beans, peas and beans, some raised peas. The
         peas took on in the eastern Latah County, up through Deary and to
         ward those hills up there before it- they began raising it down on
         the ridges. Awas tne cooler summers they had up there and higher
         ground and the peas nearly always got cooler weather when they needed
         it in the blossom so that they wouldn't shrivel off. Hot weather
         at the wrong time, you can lose a lot of blooms. And they were getting
         successful up there with peas on what we down here regarded
         as poor land because it was all in the heavy timber, most of it at
         least, and years of both pine trees and fir trees extracting nitro
         gen out of the soil it took a long time for it to grow back in.
         They could do it with clover crops and.legume crops.
         
         SS: What made peas preferable to beans?
         
         GC: Well, later they seemed to get so they could raise them anywhere, I
         think possibly they experimented with different kinds of peas. There
         was a whole series of different varieties of peas,
         could tell you more about that, she did what they call pea picking
         down here when she was attending school sometimes. They sorted out
         the odd peas, so they had nothing but nothing but peas, so she could
         recognize six or seven different kinds of peas by looking at them.
         I was never that good, they all looked more or less the same to me.
         And I think they just did that and found out there were peas that
         could stand more warmth than others and peas that required cooler
         weather. It was a question of learning. They changed varieties
         of beans, too, several times. And they got these red beans, some
         them in of afterwards, Mexican beans. There were only two kinds of beans
         planted, I think white beans that were the real crop when I first
         remember beans, they called 'em the La Uf Washington and the little
         Navy. The little navy was^a smaller bean, but actually it didn't
         always yield- sometimes yielded better than the others.
         
         SS: What was the other one called?
         
         The Lady Washington. But they passed out of use, but I think they
         was pretty good beans. And then they raised brown beans, too. The
         brown bean, the red bean, I guess you'd call it, they was more brown
         than red. I don't know why more of it wasn't fielded, at the time
         we planted a few acres of it we got just as good yield and the price
         was just as high, so I don't know it never became popular, but
         they did get in a reddish-brown bean later.
         
         You know, it makes me think about marketing some: Was there any
         cooperative marketing going on when you were growing up?
         
         Any efforts to have—I remember when the Farmers' Union- you started talking Farmers'
         Union. I was still a kid but how many people joined it, I don't know
         I don't think it figured very largely here around Troy. It was somewhat
         later^. But I know I wasn't more than eleven years old, I don't
         think when I heard them talking Farmers' Union.
         I wonder why it was rough to get that kind of thing. I would think
         the farmers- they could get together to thresh together, I would
         think they could get together in marketing.
         Yes, it seems they could. The Grange succeeded later much better
         and it was called the Grange. But there is a Farmers' Union, too.
         
         They put up some warehouses in this country. I don't know just—
         Well, a lot of 'em belonged to the associations in Moscow, headed
         in Moscow now, that owns the warehouses and they were kind of a com
         pany.
         
         SS: In those days you took it to Troy, right?
         
         GC: Well, Troy was our nearest place.
         
         SS: Who would you take it to?
         
         GC: Troy? Well, they didn't have one in Troy as I remember it, Duthie
         had a warehouse there for a good long while, but he eventually sold
         out there and moved to Lewiston, but then that was after I was- I
         think I was in college about that time. But Green was there a long,
         long time, not the Greens in the brick house.
         
         SS: No, Green, Brocke's father-in-law.
         
         GC: His father-in-law, yes. He was there a long time'and we dealt with
         him and Duthie both at different times, sometimes at the same time.
         And those were the two men. I think somebody else had some in
         there at one time or another. Jolley, was the name of a warehouse
         men that preceeded them before Duthie got started and I think before
         Green did. But he moved on, I don't know why- found a better loca
         tion.
         
         SS: I've heard, occasionally, farmers complaining about the- you knowjust
         how good a deal they would get from the warehouses; do you re
         member that at all?
         
         GC: Well, yes. They generally took it on a basis, however, I think
         Green and Duthie both did, of the cost of exporting from, here to
         certain places. Probably most of it, - I don't think much of it
         went to Spokane, but to Portland. Lewiston milled quite a bit for
         quite a while, and I don't know if they still mill down there or not,
         I think they do. (interference) milling, it's better
         to ship the whole wheat, more economical and less loss than to ship
         flour. So the milling that was in Moscow and Lewiston was for local
         use for bread right here. That was more what it was for. Well, I
         don't know, my father thought that Green and Duthie were much the
         same. One of the things that were pointed out to me a long time
         later by hotel people here in Troy; says, "I wondered how these peo
         ple could carry on all that, there was so little dockage and
         within a few cents of that." "I found a reason," he said, "it's
         the sacks." They sacked grain in those days. They didn't have
         facilities for hauling it in like they do in trucks, they didn't
         have those kind of bins, or they didn't have those kind of elevators
         they had buildings in which they had to store it in sacks; pile up
         the sacks. And, he says, "All those sacks-" Oh, I don't know, they
         kept rising in price over the years, a little bit, ten cents a
         sack- he says, - all those sacks hey can sell them for second
         hands at about two cents less. Most of them are good for another
         if season after using once, and they can sell all those things
         back. The seconds a little cheaper than- at a smaller price than
         the new ones, and get all of it back that way." That's the way I
         figured-
         
         SS: So, they kept their sacks then?
         
         GC: They kept the sack, yes, they didn't turn the sacks back. They sold
         When them back the next day. A They paid so much a bushel, so much- it
         included the sack.
         
         SS: That doesn't sound like they were operating on a big margin then.
         
         GC: Well, it made quite a margin.
         
         SS: The sacks.
         
         GC: The sacks and the dockage. They never would turn out these threshing
         machines, every thing clear. A little piece of hard dirt the size
         of a grain of wheat came in with it it might turn it out without
         breaking it up. It would be like a little hard kernel in there
         and they'd generally sample a few sacks and gauged a load on that.
         Or widJL oats would slip through, a certain amount- maybe some weed
         seed, but that was usually- it got blew out.
         
         SS: Then how did they figure dockage?
         
         GC: Oh, half a percent or one percent or something like that. I think
         they probably were- oh, I am sure that they gave themselves a liberal
         margin on it; their dockage rates.
         
         SS: Then they'd actually make profit on the dockage.
         
         GC: I think they made profit on the dockage. Of course, if they were
         correct on the dockage they couldn't make too much then, because at
         the other end, they wouldn't pay for wild oats in the wheat here,
         they would fan that out and have only wheat left, so they couldn't
         do it so much on the dockage. But this fellow he insisted that the
         sacks was a tremendous thing. And, of course, that was one dockage, sold
         they docked a pound on sack they got and then it right back.
         
         SS: Well, let's go back to the farming for a minute. What kind of shape
         was the average farmer in? Was he getting ahead every year by
         selling year-by-year selling his crops?
         
         GC: Most of them in our area were and I think the same was true of
         most of those farmers down on the ridges, if they were
         they were very careless farmers. I think most of those fellows on
         little Bear Ridge and American Ridge and Burnt Ridge piled up a
         little. Now I'm sure they did because certain of the smaller ones
         decided to quit and go somewhere else. There was often a farmer
         right nearby who would bid on his land and get it in and increase
         his acreage a little. They went down- the number went down
         in here. Now the land that we owned included the Sanders land,
         which increased the acreage by about, oh, sixty-five percent, cul
         tivated acreage, and Kellberg bought part of that, too, including
         those canyon farms which were only pasture and they had to move out
         and he got quite a bit more, and Goard-
         
         The Goard family?
         
         Well, the last of the Goards that lived here at that time, died
         this last year, I think they told me. He wasn't farming, he was re
         tired and renting his land. But they owned land on Burnt Ridge
         there.
         
         SS: So people were concentrating their farms?
         
         GC: he had a small farm there, eighty acres and he bought land,
         he had, I think more money than most of those when he came to the
         country, because he bought land on American Ridge and as he had a
         chance to buy more over there, he sold off that one to Kellberg,
         where Ernest Anderson now lives. So that included a considerable
         number of acres at least what were three or four 160's- well, not
         160's but owned by different persons, Goard and Sanders and Cusick,
         he got in on that. The last you may as well forget about as far
         as farming land was concerned, it wasn't. (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Well, were most of the farmers, did they own their land free and
         clear, or were they still tied up with mortgages?
         I'll tell you, the mortgaging came later in many cases. When it grew
         more expensive and taxes grew higher and they sometimes had low
         prices on wheat. Variable prices on wheat and beans- fell after the
         World War I. And some of them probably bought- were mortgage free
         to begin with- bought land and then found that they had to maybe get
         a small mortgage and it was tough on 'em and they had to mortgage
         more. But, I think most of those at one time owned all their's free.
         I don't know how Kellberg was situated, I think he had money when
         he came about 1906 to buy the first place he had. But
         he took mortgages, I think, to buy the rest that he expanded with. I had heard that
         the period after World War I, in the '20's was a
         kind of difficult one for a lot of farmers there.
         
         GC: Yes, it was a difficult time. They had a wave of prosperity in -
         during the war, as far as prices were concerned. And that's the
         time that most of the automobiles were bought by farmers. There were
         only a few farmers that owned automobiles before that time. I think
         it was that time that the first automobiles were bought on
         Burnt Ridge. During or just after World War I, about 1919-'20.
         There were some around town but they didn't hit this country at all
         1910 or '09, that is, Troy country, there'd be some in Moscow.
         I can remember the first car I saw, it was at a Fourth of July celebration,.
         in Troy. (Chuckles) Oh, I was ten years old, I guess. But I know Sawyer, who was a
         mail carrier got one because
         he figured he could use it in the summer season to advantage. And
         Duthie bought one about 1911 or '12, Leland Duthie.
         
         SS: The mail carrier used it for mail delivery?
         
         GC: For mail delivery, yes. They used to have to keep their own horses,
         they didn't use a mail wagon provided by the post office.
         
         SS: So, the farmers got to buying cars in World War I and weren't they
         kind of inclind to expand their acreage too, due to prices?
         
         GC: Yes, they were, they were trying to expand their acreage and some
         were selling out to them. It was some years, but a lot of them re
         mained there for quite a while. The Rubergs didn't give up- well,
         before World War I, there were two farms of eighty acres- originally
         160- one 160- they were brothers and one of 'em sold half of his
         to the other. Both of those fellows had left before, that was two
         families that vacated. One went down to Yakima where he raised his
         family and the other, they went to town and they had a difficult
         time because of a husband and wife disagreement. But that was two
         farmers that- who had their children in school I remember. But af
         ter World War I the Pearson family who had- the father died there,
         and two of the boys- the oldest boy died and then five years later
         another boy died and they sort of left.. And one of the boys, he
         went to a dental school and he turned dentist and he spent his life
         as a dentist. The other boy, he went into the bank. And he was
         recently retired- (interference) And the girls were married and
         left and so on, so they sold out eventually. That's the place where
         Slim Smith bought, Slim Smith's father bought that at that time, he
         was an expander. He bought several farms- there were two or three
         farms that lay west from where the old schoolhouse stands on
         Burnt Ridge, that area, family that was on the Pearson place before he bought it,
         when
         I was a little kid, I think they went down to homestead somewhere
         in the state of Washington. Another family there that had lived
         where Joe Porter, who owned the- who I said a while back, bought place.
         the first steam rig into there^ Porter was really
         not a farmer, he did team work, he had a bunch of good horsespu-
         f his family on a place to stay, when he was working .
         out.
         
         SS: So, you're saying that it was kind of rough in the '20's there
         with the farmers because the prices weren't-
         
         GC: Prices went real down, badly.
         
         SS: And that encourages more farmers to get out?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, it did. Some felt they had better get out before they-
         prices and higher prices for things they
         bought.
         
         SS: Other than they they had to go in debt for young men, like yourself who might
         want to go into farming
         at that time.
         
         GC: Darn little. They were leery of it. Some who had been prosperous
         before simply quit.  Planted the whole thing down in grass and maybe buy
         a few cattle themselves to pasture on it or rent pasture on the grass or else cut
         some hay, as the opportunity Of. Didn't raise
         any wheat, let it lay during those years.   they'd better not
         spend anything on it beyond the grass seed and they put good sweet
         clover or clover and alfalfa on it and let it go at that, quit
         the farming for a while. But not all could afford to do that.
         
         SS: That's what I would think. I want to come back to farming ,a little
         bit, but there's a couple of things about Burnt Ridge I want to
         ask you about, a couple of incidents I thought you maybe would know
         something about. Did you ever hear about the hanging on Burnt
         Ridge kid
         
         GC: Oh, yes, yes. I heard about that when I was a small
         
         SS: And people still wondered?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, I was a small kid, it was not too many years before thatbefore
         we moved there, but Lawrence Johnson lived there, Clarence's
         dad, and he was one of the men that took 'em up. But nobody knew 
         and that's the funniest thing I ever heard, too, seemed to me, if
         that description I heard of it was right; I would have thought
         they'd have taken him to Troy and put him aside somewhere and see
         if somebody could recoitaiAze him, but they didn't seem to- nobody
         that looked at him knew him, and the people that found him, I think
         it was a kid that found him, and that hanging- 
         hanged fo as far as they knew.
         
         SS: So they had no idea what had happened or anything?
         
         GC: No, no real clue that they had, of course, I don't know what investigation-
         I don't know if an officer came down to investigate or not.
         They just wanted to know, they toldAwhat happened and then nobody
         seemed to know who he was so they buried him. A rather free and
         easy way of performing, I 
         
         SS: Where did they bury the guy?
         
         GC: Oh, I don't know that either. Maybe they buried him in 
         
         SS: That's what I was wondering.
         
         GC: I think Clarence Johnson could tell you that.
         
         SS: Yes, I must ask him.
         
         GC: I think his dad was one of folks went down and carried
         the man up
         
         GC: Where did they find him?
         
         GC: Oh, in-
         
         SS: Camp's Canyon?
         
         GC: Oh, well, yes, down that way. I don't exactly know where it was
         either, I think it was between- yes, the Camp Canyon lies between
         Burnt Ridge and Bear Ridge.
         
         SS: Right.
         
         GC: And I think it was down along that canyon side there, just how
         far down I don't know.
         
         SS: Was there'any speculation about that?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, there was speculation, everybody speculated, but nobody
         could think of who might hang this- well,Athey didn't know who he
         was, what did anybody want to hang him without knowing who he was,
         so they wouldn't have a clue as to who his enemies might be.
         
         SS: The only thing I could think of, it might be Vigilantes or some
         thing like that.
         
         GC: Yes, well, as far as anybody knew, there wasn't any such thing.
         There was nothing like that.
         
         SS: Do you ever hear of the rumor that I read about that there was a
         what was called a wild man on Burnt Ridge? That there was a wild
         man living in the canyon or something like that?
         
         GC: Wild man? Well, I wouldn't think- no, I never heard that. The only
         one that I heard spoken of is when this fellow they called Wild
         Dave.
         
         SS: Oh, did you know of him?
         
         GC: Yeah. He lived over up toward Moscow Mountain and used to come in
         to Moscow more than Troy. I gue
         SS: he appeared there, too.
         
         SS: What was he supposed to have been like?
         
         GC: Oh, he was dressed roughly and had a big shaggy beard and wore a
         guns and that's about all. He'd come in and get drunk and talk big.
         As far as I know, he never hurt anybody. (Chuckles) But he looked
         as if he hadn't been cleaned up in five years, I guess or something
         like that. People pinned that tag on him. I think the name's Coventry,
         ADave Coventry.
         
         SS: Right.
         
         GC: fou know a book came out and it was signed William F. Drannon and
         told of his life in the West, and you look*at the picture in that 'CM.
         and many swore that picture was of Wild Dave. A neighbor who lived
         out there one year, renting^Sander's place, his name was Sturtevant,
         and they had that book.
         
         SS: They had a book, and-
         
         GC: They had a book and the picture looked so much like Wild Dave to
         some people they swore that he must be the guy that had that
         book put out. He called himself William Drannon in that picture.
         
         SS: Drannon? Do you think that he was the same person?
         
         GC: I don't know, I never saw Wild Dave myself.
         
         SS: I've heard of that, even down to today, people think they were the
         same person. I, myself, don't.
         
         GC: The picture in that book?
         
         SS: Yeah, they think that this Wild Dave wrote that book, but I don't
         see why he would have changed his name for that.
         
         GC: No a He impreSSed everybody as anything but a literary person.
         That was written- I read the book; his life's adventures and rela
         tions with Kit Carson and Indian wars and he had one thing on everypicture
         of a fellow, supposedly- no, I guess maybe drawn by an artist
         of a fellowA he called the American Cannibal, that he killed
         and ate his squaw one winter in the mountains.A Hard winter and he
         couldn't get out. I don't know, it was a little sensational-
         Most people that read the book thought it was a bunch of lies about
         himself, whoever wrote the book.
         
         SS: Yeah, I think since then it's been documented that he never did
         most of that stuff, it was a bunch of lies and a good story, he
         never did know Kit Carson.
         
         GC: I've never seen another copy of that book. Have you seen it?
         
         SS: I haven't seen that book- (noise interference)
         
         GC: that book, and we all read it .there.
         
         SS: Well, you know, your brothers were all active in the Democratic
         party; I was wondering when your family-
         
         GC: Into politics?
         
         SS: Yeah, and into being Democrats.
         
         GC: Oh, I tell you, Paul was really the first one, most of us were not
         active politics at all. My brother, Carl, and Joe and Walter,
         they Kusually vot the Republican ticket. I always voted the Demo
         cratic ticket mostly.
         
         SS: I've heard that your father had pretty strong-
         
         GC: Socialistic ideas, yes he did, very strong Socialistic ideas in
         the old Socialist Party that was in this country and in which men
         such as Benson and Hilatfit and those were active. There was a good
         deal of votes pulled by the Socialist Party and different ones back
         about 1908. They pulled about a half a million votes and there were
         several times after that they polled up to a million votes or
         so, but then it kind of died out in the '20's; disappeared. And I
         think 1920, itself, was the first- the last year it polled a sizeable
         number of votes.
         
         SS: Was that when Debs-
         
         That was with Debs. And BensonArun after that.
         Do you think your father got his convictions from—?
         Oh, reading on various things. He read a great deal on politics
         and economic theories. He was a reader all his life, I guess
         I know. He'd collected quite a library of various books
         largely on religion and history.
         
         Do you think his views on Socialism came from Sweden, or do you
         think he got them here?
         
         No, I think that was after he came over here. Well, he- there were
         some- you know the Populist Party wasn't exactly socialistic. It
         had its good years there in the late 1800's, but it was very much
         more socialistic than the Democratic Party has ever been.^ And such
         fellows as Ignatius Donnelly, who ran for- was the candidate one
         year for theApresidency, but I think died before- during the cam
         paign they had to change and he'd been Lt. Governor of Minnesota.
         He was active in labor organizations in the Populist Party. We had
         a book by him at home, but that wasn't- that was a prediction novel
         set in the future, something like Edward Bellamy's, Looking Backwards.
         Only he was not encouraging like Bellamy, who thought that hings were
         going to be better. He thought that things were going to be worse.
         He was a 
         
         SS: Seems like maybe he was right.
         
         GC: Maybe he had something, too; he was not completely right.
         
         SS: Your father, he was probably one of
         the few people around here that was- I mean around this area that
         was- had strong convictions.
         
         GC: Well, he was one of the few. Of the Burnt Ridge people there was
         nobody else, I don't think. But down around Troy there was a fel
         low, oh, I forget his name now- Jennett, who was active in that party.
         
         SS: Socialist Party?
         
         GC: Socialist Party. And there were one or two others-, when they estab
         lished that Socialist newspaper in Lewiston thaif- ran for several
         years before it folded.
         
         SS: Do you remember the name of that one?
         Inland Echo. Later, they called it the Inland Empire; changed the
         name. I don't know whether it passed from one hand to another, be
         cause they were hard , then it folded up.
         Was your father- did your father get to know some of the other peo
         ple that were involved in it?
         Yes, there was Underwood, was the name of one, and I can't think of
         any one fellow. The Socialists had a picnic in Troy one time, took
         over the Fourth of July celebration and organized it, and they had
         speakers up here, that talked . And they had some
         speakers- I know I was eleven or so but I heard a little of it but
         I was not^interested in hearing him talk. I was with a bunch of kids
         
         SS: Was your father ?
         
         GC: No don't think he was. I think, the fact is, I think that was
         the same year that he went to Sweden, about 1912. He took a trip
         back there to Sweden to see his people back there about that time.
         
         SS: Where was Underwood from?
         
         GC: Well, Underwood, I don't know where he was from originally.
         
         SS: Was he in Moscow?
         
         GC: Well, he was in Lewiston at this time, but he was from somewhere
         else. And he was a literary man of some kind. He had published
         a book of poetry, I think, and things like that. Oh, I never heard
         a thing about him afterwards.
         
         SS: As far as your father's convictions go being a Socialist; what do
         you think that that meant? You know, the kind of ways he would like
         to see society grow.
         
         GC: He thought that- what they might call more pure socialism. The publie
         control of things publicly used, like racehorses and food
         crops,Aall those things that had to be used by the public and limit
         private property to individual needs for himself. A house, because
         that was something that would be private property, that's for his
         own use. Land needed to produce food, that's a public utility,
         that's for public use. That was just about the creed of the socialists
         of that period. They changed both before and after, I am sure, but
         that was the kernel of their belief, is the public control of the
         things used by the public, the and mines and waterpower
         and land, all that.
         
         SS: Do y°u think he had any vision that people would have more or less the same amount
         of money to live on?
         
         GC: Well, I don't think; no, he knew that that was very true, that
         some people needed more wages because there was more demand for them.
         The technician needed to have- or ought to be employed at a higher
         salary than no technician at all and that it took more education
         for his work.
         
         SS: But he was pretty sympathetic towards the workingman?
         Oh, yes, he was very sympathetic, he thought they got the worst of
         the deal. That the workingman got the worst part of the deal in
         our setup. I heard that much andA he was right on that score.
         They still are getting it, in many ways, the worst of it.
         you know, what's interesting about it to me in part is that generally the farmers,
         I don't think have been too sympathetic towards la
         bor and the unions.
         Well, no. The farmer had a kind of an independence. He could make
         it on this land he had, and he found that he was doing it year after
         year and maybe laying a little aside, and  oi more things for the homes and all that
         sort of thing. They could improve it. They
         built new barns and new houses and all that. I don't think any of
         the houses on Burnt Ridge was the ones originally put up.
         So, your father was kind of different in that way. He was looking,
         it sort of seems to me, a little more farsighted in- (noise) every
         body in the same boat.
         We had a school teacher out there that to talk a great deal
         of things. He was a pretty good teacher. 'We often wandered from
         the subject if he was talking on things and he encouraged kids to
         now read the newspapers and know what was going on* and he'd
         talk about it to 'em every once in a while and he was the one that
         if he found was teaching some subject Md oon^hm came up related
         went on to talk about that, he'd elect a class time for
         one particular class or anything like that and he held the interest
         of the students and just keep right on talking about it. (Noisy)
         It was probably as good a way of teaching as any. I think learned
         as much in the long run.
         
         SS: He talked about current affairs?
         
         He'd talk about current affairs. And he said about these thingshe
         said, "Those things don't always happen at once," he says, "now
         in the Socialist Party has a lot of things in it.fhese other parties
         are going to take over. A lot of the things that they advocate," he
         says, "will probably be in use some day, but they won't be called
         Socialists when they do." Well, that's happened, I know. They were
         the first party to back women's suffrage, the Socialists were. They
         were the first ones that advocated the graduated income tax, and quite
         a few other things that have come to pass at one time or another.
         We never think of socialism as just things that they advocated
         in their platform for that particular time. They had, besides their
         kernel, they took sides on issues up before the country at that time.
         they didn't The party did, they always did that, A incorporated those things
         exactly in their idealology, but things that were done.
         
         Did your father ever get a chance to be active at all?
         
         Well, actually, he sympathized a little bit with that Inland Echo
         that they was going to put out a socialist paper there. And he may
         have put a few dollars in it, I don't know.
         
         Did he try to talk to his neighbors? Did he try to persuade them?
         
         Oh, if political discussions came up and they opened^up with him,
         he would, othersttde he didn't. He'd give his side of these things
         he could talk fluently on that, he was never at a loss for words. If the argument
         came up he'd just pursue it right on,
         and he  rather heated, too. But, oh, then our neighbors around
         there, why, they knew his beliefs and he knew their's and they tal
         ked about something else. Talked about the farm crops or how this other family was
         or something else.
         
         SS: What about the IWWs? What did he think about them?
         
         Well, I don't remember him saying anything about it, but, well, that
         came along about-
         
         SS: '17.
         
         GC: '17, and^He didn't have much use for those things. He thought those
         kind of organizations didn't help anything, as far as I remember. I
         don't know, the IWWs attempted organizing industrial workers of all
         kinds together, but some of thel,organization men were gave it a bad
         name. Probably half of those people that they thought were IWWs
         weren't. I know some people saw sort of tramps coming through the
         country looking for work they might be IWWs. It was
         rather silly, people were too scared of IWWs, if you had to see
         one under every bush like some of the people saw communists about
         the time^the First World War was over, there was some investigations
         here and there. i know that there was - some people were saying that the fires in
         the fields, in the harvest fields were being set by IWWs.
         Oh, there was some fires sometimes, now, I don't know whether they
         were set or not, I don't think they ever came to the truth of it.
         Now, smut in the wheat, that's kind of a disease, they sometimes
         get that in the wheat and that stuff could explode, if you were run
         ning the machine hard. And smokers of all kinds were around these worked.
         threshing machines, too, and they used to follow- had a perman
         ent crew and they'd just bed down in the haystack- in the straw stack
         at the end of the day with their blankets and it was just as likely
         a lot of those things were made from careless sources as anybody else.
         
         Did you go through the eighth grade on Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC: Yes.
         
         SS: Then what did you do after that?
         
         GC: Well, I was out one year^ I finished high school in Troy.
         
         SS: Then you went to high school in Troy?
         
         GC: Then I went to the university up here, later to California. I
         laid out a year in between there. One year I wasn't in school.
         That's all I missed until I went through college. Of 
         
         SS: Did you go in the service at all?
         
         GC: Yes, I was in for one that didn'^interrupt my college education.
         They put what they called Students' Army Training Corp on the cam
         pus^ during the First World War. That wasn't the ROTqfthat they had
         in these, but regularly enlisted students, and they started calling
         them up as they came to them. I know they were calling the older
         ones first, and they'd gotten down to about- I was about nineteen
         years old then- they were delving into the 20s and they were coming
         down so if the war hadn't closed in November of that year, why, I'd
         probably been called out. As it was they didn't know what to do
         with them for about a week or two then orders came that they were
         to disband them all by Christmas. Release them. So, that wasn't
         much. I was in for a time in this last war, too, but I don't know,
         I was a little too old then, and they decided after a physical exam
         ination to release me. 1941 and 1942 and *43- I should say.
         
         SS: What was the University like when you went there?
         
         GC: Much smaller college. I think it was- I think, the number of students
         in regular courses could not have exceeded 800. Washington State,
         which probably twice that much. Oh, with the correspondence
         courses and short courses that they used to give injagriculture- I
         don't know if they still give them or not- the extension courses
         and those things, they totalled a couple of hundred more. So
         at one time of the year, in the winter, what they claled the short
         courses- they called them the short ags- short agricultural coursesthat
         was the term for them- at least they're all short. There were
         a whole bunch of those in there, made for about a three month's
         course, special course.
         
         SS: But you were taking—
         
         GC: I took the regular AB course. And I taught school for about four
         teen years after that then I left it and went to Washington and
         worked for the Bureau- the Division, as they called it thfc^ office,
         later, of Vital Statistics. It was part of the Census Bureau when
         I ended there, but reorganization took place in the government there
         and they transferred it to the Public Health Service.
         
         SS: This was DC.
         
         GC: This was Washington, DC, yes.
         
         SS: You taught school?
         
         GC: Before that.
         
         SS: Did you teach around here?
         
         Oh, I taught in California more than anywhere else. I did teach
         one year here in Idaho. I taught out in the Philippines for a while.
         I was two years down at Klamath Falls, Oregon. I went back to school
         at the University of California for a year after that, then I was
         out in the Philippines quite a while. Then traveled a bit before I
         came back.
         
         Let me ask you a little bit about what it was like being a student
         in the university in those days. Was there much social life?
         Plenty of social life, yes. Plenty of social life, but a lot more
         sedate sort than they have now. Well, maybe some of the fraterni
         ties had a little drinking there in private, but it was usually
         very private. They didn't let it get out, just sort of kept quiet.
         Nobody talked about it if they went there. And otherwise, it was
         pretty quiet. Sometimes they had fights with other students from
         Washington State when they had the game, and that was sort of a
         silly thing, but they did,
         
         SS: Oh, the big rivalry was with Washington State? Was it a big rivalry
         in those days?
         
         GC: Well, it was quite a rivalry, yes, and sometimes with clashes between
         the rooters. Not very common though. The presidents of the univer
         sity at that time, that one over there and Washington State and
         Idaho, oh, they clamped down on 'em both, they understood each
         other. And they even got kind of tough with students who tried
         starting any of that stuff.
         
         SS: Do you remember President Lindley?
         
         GC: Lindley? Yes. He was president that year I graduated, but he left
         I think about that time, too. Lindley was- he was one of those that
         just believed there should be no rough rioting and fighting and any
         thing that had no business around the university, or vandalism
         or anything like that.
         
         SS: Did you think a lot of him? Do you remember?
         
         GC: Oh, I think they all respected him. His son graduated the same year
         I did. He became a newspaper man. Lindley. He wrote-
         
         SS: Dating?
         
         GC: oh that was allowed, of course. I'll tell you though, they had the
         dormitory there, just one dormitory for girls'and about four or five
         fraternities- sororities, you know. Those girls were under pretty
         strict surviellance by the house mothers and the Dean of Women, who
         lived at Ridenbaugh Hal1-^ was the only girls1-
         
         SS: Was that Dean French at that time?
         
         GC: Dean French. What was her name? Perineal- Permeal Jane French.
         
         SS: She had a reputation for strictness didn't she?
         
         GC: Oh, yes, she really- the girls didn't like to be called up before
         her. Yes, I guess she was- Of course, there were always girls that
         lived out through the town in places, too, lived in the halls and
         that, but she was Dean of all the women and they didn't have a Dean
         of Men. That's one thing that most colleges even then had, but there
         was no Dean of Men. You answerA to anybody except- for missing cla
         SSes or anything else. Of course, they might ruin their standing
         with the professors if they were too lax in attending classes but
         then it was up to them. Strictly double standard.
         
         SS: Well, talking about the double standard; like what, the relations be
         tween the sexes and that kind of thing?
         
         GC: Well, that was hard to say.
         
         SS: I was thinking-
         
         GC: Among university students I know one thing about it - you'll probably
         never know. Careful people there, because that sort of thing they
         were all against and the university wouldn't be tolerant to any person
         who's reputation was, as they say, tarnished. But whatever hap-
         pened was kept between themselves. I know the ROTC had an encamp
         ment one year while I was there and they had it up at Fort George
         Wright and they mostly had liberty at night and a lot of the boys
         went really wild up there at that time. They had a chance to get out
         of Moscow and on their own for a while away from the university campus.
         No repercussions whatever, no report^ they were out on
         their own. No inquiries were made or anything like that. That's
         the way our commandant felt about those things, I'm sure. the bawdy houses in Spokane.
         
         SS: But that was probably mostly like
         the bawdy houses in Spokane. )That's what they went to.
         
         GC: Oh, yes That's what they found or the ones that were on their own. Free
         lances up there. They were kind of freelancing in town,
         to the whorehouses too much. They were big enough to support that kind of thing, being
         a city.
         Yes. There wasn't really such a thing as a bawdy house in Moscow.
         They were there alright in places, they were rooming somewhere.
         ARooming in the hotel , and when they appeared on the streets
         they were like anybody else but they could do their soliciting very
         expertly^ even the hotels unaware of it or maybe they winked
         at it as long as they behaved themselves, maybe they didn't even
         know. I've often wondered about the women that got involved in that sort
         of thing, what their backgrounds were, you know, where they came
         from. If they would have tended to have grown up in poverty.
         
         GC: Well, I don't know.
         
         SS: Just drift into it?
         
         Drifted into it, I think, probably. I know, some of them started
         VI think^not as whores to begin with, as rather impulsive young girls
         is another, and then drifted into it from th«r .
         I kind of have the idea that in those days from some things that
         I've read about stuff in just that period of time, that some of the
         old Victorian standards were kind of starting to slip and colleges-
         I know in the '20's colleges got a little wild with the flappers and
         all that. Yes, I'll tell you- a fellow here- well, I went to school with him
         once in college and he went right on and got PhD degrees in physics
         and became a physics teacher. He taught at the University of Idaho;
         came back there and taught first and^he drifted on to Wisconsin
         uring the World War he was summoned to Washington for their
         group of scientists to work on things- on weapons. He told me when
         he was a professor here at Idaho that things were changed completely
         after that war since the boys were coming back, he says,some of them
         one and two and three and four years from the time they'd first
         started college*. Some that never got to college in the first place
         starting at age twenty or twenty-one or twenty-two and that time
         was the lowest ebb here in control of the kind of life that the stu
         dents had. A lot of those boys- nothing wrong with them- but his
         idea was- he safdi that they're too young for the experiences they
         had in the war. He said that this idea of sending the young men to
         war is tough on the young men it has a deteriorating effect on 'em.
         They're too young to stand it, he says, and that was about the time
         of the Second World War he's talking about. And he didn't like the
         idea of sending eighteen, nineteen year olds into war; says that
         it's going to be rough on them. It's going to have a bad influence
         they re too young to carry that. And he sort of blamed that* althou^n
         they never got around to drafting those under twenty-one. They re
         gistered them all and a lot of them enlisted that were eighteen and
         nineteen in that war^and twenty. Went in by enlistment in the wave
         of patriotism, I suppose you'd call it.
         
         SS: You're talking about the First World War?
         
         GC: First World War and when he came back, that was the early '20's
         when they started coming back.
         
         SS: Of course, they were probably quite a bit older than the girls, too.
         
         GC: They we^e older than the girls at that time. The girls- of course,
         there were less girls during that war years than there were, too, a
         lot of those dropped out and took positions in war work and earned
         considerable money; they went up. But there's one thing about it
         most of them didn't have much money up here. A large part of 'em
         were one and two and three years retarded on age, you might say,
         but it was because they stayed out and worked.
         
         SS: You talking about women?
         
         Women and men both up here. Women were great to try to get a year
         or two in in college, in which they can draw a temporary teaching
         certificate that was only renewable - it wasn't renewable after so
         many year unless they took more college work, and they'd make their
         way that way,a lot of them would. If they got in a year they could
         make a temporary certificate in a year and one a little bit longer,
         I think for five years, if they took two years. So they went out
         and they got teaching positions and a lot of those were overage girls
         that were coming back; experienced teachers coming back to finish
         up. They didn't have very many choices in the terms of the kind of cour
         ses of study for a career at that time.
         No, they didn't. There was secretarial work, business  and that was
         handled largely by business schools, although they had accounting
         up there at the university and some were taking that and teaching
         and well, nursing, they always went to the hospitals from high school.
         Oh, there were some that took specializing in home economics and diet
         ician and that. My nephew, Keith, Bruce's brother, his wife was a
         hospital dietician before- when she came out of college, worked at
         that for a time.
         
         Do you think that men- and this is a question because things have
         changed a lot- are changing. Do you think that in those days that
         the men tended to look on the women- you know, the boys on the girls
         at the college as being inferior.to them, or being less than equal?
         
         GC: Well, I don't think that was so true. Maybe they thought some things
         were for girls and some for men, but most of 'em recognized the girls I think as being
         intellectually equal, among college men. Oh, pro
         bably that might have been true about the ordinary man, say of forty
         jfosf had tetti raised fifty- the generation before they were, did have that idea,
         but
         a lot of those were pretty liberal on that point, too. Some people
         ing were not so keen on educat girls, they thought they were going to
         marry and said that was lost time. It was lost if it was not econ
         omically beneficial.
         
         Do you think most men would have expected maybe the women too, would
         have expected that when they got married that she would give up her
         work and become a homemaker?
         
         Oh, yes, that was common. That was common, but a lot of them some
         times found they were glad that their wife had an occupation in the
         if that she could work at he wasn't prepared for and
         because he was losing his job;Awhere he worked was closing down, something
         like that, a plant closing dovm. No, there were married women tea
         ching thenQw^th husbands. I know the wife of one of the professors
         up there Aa job in Moscow High School, professor at the university. All children were
         grown, they just had a couple. I tal
         ked with her once, she said- when I was taking a teaching certifi
         cate we did our observations in Moscow High School in the different
         things and I talked with her, I told her why I was there, I talked
         with her a good deal, I knew her husband.
         
         SS: She the wife of the president?
         
         GC: Not the president, he was a history professor. And, oh, she told
         me that just to sit at home bored her, and she could get plenty of
         social life in the evening without putting in full time to it. So
         she took the job teaching. In my remembrance of . it was one
         of the easiest ways of teaching she had that I had seen. She seemed
         to hold that class in the hollow of her hand, all interested.
         
         SS: What made you decide to become a teacher?
         
         GC: Oh, I don't know, I was a little lost as to what I wanted to do. I
         seemed wanted to go out and get a job immediately and law or medicine
         a long ways away. Well, I never seriously thought of medicine. I
         never liked that kind of thing. But I did consider law, but then
         sometimes it was a long time for the young lawyer to get started
         even then. The demand for lawyers wasn't so much, there weren't so
         many suits. That's something that has multiplied extremely sincealways
         suing for this and that and civil suits, fill 
         
         SS: Was it that way in the early days, too?
         
         GC: There wasn't near as much of that when I was a kid, you'd hear
         about suing for this or that, but then there wasn't much compared to
         what it is now. I think recourse to the law on civil damages of any
         kind has increased tremendously from that time. They didn't do
         if somebody happened to fall down and hurt themselves on some
         body else's property- I don't think anybody thought of that. You
         probably thought they were too darn clumsy and it was their fault.
         It wasn't too difficult to put yourself in a position to be a tea
         cher then?
         
         No, you know teachers are fairly well in demand and they were not so
         awfully highpaid and a lot of teachers found they could enter
         something else. A chemistry teacher would enter a chemical company,
         something like that, so there was a constant change and they
         opened up places for other people. And sort of things like that
         happened all the time. And there was an increasing population, both
         by immigration and excessive births which ran pretty high then, increasing
         much better than one percent yearly, natural growth, one and a half
         percent, no doubt. And a steady stream of immigration reaching a
         million ayear sometimes, net increase of amillion ayear from
         Europe. It's no wonder the schools kept increasing, the college
         enrollments, the high school enrollments and the others. It was a
         period of growth for secondary schools about that time, they went
         to a fair minority of the population. You know, at the time I star
         ted high school in 1912, '13, they didn't have all the/rteighth grade
         graduates coming in, didn't have half of them. A lot of people
         thought that was for the bright ones.
         
         SS: Were there fewer country kids proportionately than town kids?
         
         GC: Yes, fewer proportion. Town kids were into town and decided
         they just as well try.
         
         SS: Do you think that was the reason was easier acce
         
         GC: Easier access and also, they wouldn't have regular employment at
         the age of entering high school that the country kids would have
         weren't on the farms. Some of the parents anxious for 'em to go, they
         thought their kids were average and ' high school was for
         intellectuals.
         
         SS: How much time-
         
         GC: Actually we learned different when I went to high school. I was
         
         SS: How much relation did the country people like the Burnt Ridgers have
         to the town? Did they have a lot to do with town?
         
         GC: Well, quite a bit. Well, now the thing is, a large part of 'em went
         to church there and they met the town population that belonged to
         the samachurch; the churches there. And they went in and they got
         acquainted with all the people they dealt with, and often they made
         friends with some of 'em around there. And a certain number of peo
         ple from the town after they went out and got jobs during the harvest
         and so-on, when they needed extra hands, went out and worked in the
         country. So there was no strict division there between the town
         people. For a town as small as Troy it didn't matter too much.
         
         SS: As compared to a place like Moscow.
         
         GC: Moscow, would probably be a group probably that were largely cliques
         that were entirely town but I don't think that would hold true of
         the country they mingled.
         In Moscow I get the ideat that there were a lot of people in town
         that really felt they were better than country people; called them
         hayseeds or ?
         
         Oh, yes, they used those terms. I probably felt that, but that was
         a way of calling each other- of razzing each other. And some of the
         talk was not too goodnatured, either, they used that kind of term.
         I remember the term hayseed for a farmer and oh, these other
         terms, too. The loggers and the farmers kind of took jibes at each
         other. (Chuckles)
         
         Would you figure that there'd be a little of that, say between people
         in Troy and the people on the ridges as compared to a place like
         Moscow?
         
         Oh, I don't think it would be all that different, if there
         was. It would remain that probably there was a larger group of
         fairly wealthy people in Moscow that tended to cling together social
         ly, that's about all. The rest had to deal with farmers a lot on
         business and theyi trade with farmers. Which would keep that sort of thing down.
         Yes, yes. A large part of their trade- Moscow has always had a lot
         of farmers around it, there's quite a little area there and they did
         a lot of the buying. That's what I was thinking of, you know, like in Troy, the kids
         even
         would identify better with country kids.
         
         GC: Oh, yes, they would. There was no distinction, really, the kids
         knew each other. We had some kids come out there- there were some
         kids that seemed to- I don't know maybe some of them had
         relatives in town, there'd be that, too.
         
         SS: Did you feel like a country kid when you went into the university?
         
         GC: Well, I don't know, I didn't feel particularly one way or the other
         I wanted to go very badly, I went up there and I guess maybe some
         body kind of regarded me as pretty much of a country kid. Maybe
         I was blissfully unaware of those.
         
         SS: There must have been a lot of country kids going to the university
         from around the state.
         
         GC: Oh, yes, were from off the farm, there were probably more
         kids came off the farms than the towns.
         
         SS: Did you get involved in a fraternity, or did you stay in a—?
         
         GC: No, I never entered a fraternity. I stayed at a house with a group
         of boys once, they just organized among themselves for economy sake
         and rented a big house that was for rent that would hold about twenty-
         five people and hired a cook and, all took care of our own rooms
         and cleaned and that was it.
         
         SS: What was your thinking about the fraternities? Did you feel that
         you were better not to be in one, or did you just not want to?
         
         GC: I'll tell you, the economic cost, I lived on a fairly slim pittance,
         I realized was a bit higher in the fraternities than where I was
         staying outside, and that was the deciding issue on that for me.
         Besides- I really didn't care all that much about the- oh, any social
         of it advantages,and I think they were overrated, too. By the time I
         got through I it was over- and by the time I reached my junior
         year I thought fraternity life was overrated as to what it gave the
         And there was a lot of the young men outside that that were just as
         influential at politics as those in there. We almost elected a
         member of our group down there, one year, failed by a small
         margin, a non-Greek letterman. Mostly Greek lettermen that ran thethere
         were just-joo many of 'em. There were quite a few fraternities
         for the population of it at that time. Oh, I don't know the ratio
         what it is now or then either, so I guess I couldn't say, but I
         suppose if there were 400 men in regular attendance there, that half
         of them were fraternity.
         
         SS: Do you think that those kids that were not in a fraternity would
         identify with each other better than—
         
         GC: Maybe a little better, yes. Maybe a little better with each other
         than - there was a lot of difference there. Some of my^friends were
         fraternity men that were my acquaintances there. I knew the fellows at
         the house that were nonfraternity men better, but I got acand
         saw about and quainted with some that I have had classes withA drilled with on
         the drillgrounds and all that. Oh, there wasn't any ill feelings
         that is, I think the same thing was true with a lot of the frater
         nity men, a lot of 'em were- had their good friends in the non-Greek
         fraternity men.
         
         SS: Do you think, that when you say the economics; was there a significant
         cost difference to live in a fraternity?
         
         GC: Yes, there was quite a bit. It was significant in terms of what re
         sources they had then. Five dollars more then meant in living costs
         a whole lot more than it does now, a dollar was worth something then
         you got a full scale meal in a hotel restaurant for -five
         cents. So you see, in terms of actual dollars it probably wasn't so
         large but in terms of what the dollar could buy it's quite a bit.
         
         SS: This would be about five dollars a month difference, or would you
         say more?
         
         GC: Oh, probably more than that, I'd say the cost was ten dollars more
         a month, maybe more than that. I know a lot of 'em spent a good deal
         more than that. The dues and the social life they're expected to
         attend and all that. Oh, I would say- well, one of the fellows
         there, I roomed with him for a while, a fraternity sort of solicited
         him and he decided to join after a while, and I don't know, he
         told me what it had cost; ten to fifteen dollars more per month for
         him to live there after he'd paid his initiation fees and for the
         entrance and that sort of thing. I think that's the term he used.
         Anyway, it sounded large- pretty high to the fellows down there.
         Oh, another fellow I knew there, well, two or three of them had
         stayed out one and two years working before they started school and
         they thought they were fixed to go on through college and they weren't
         about to use it all up in one year by joining a fraternity or bring
         it down, they were budgeting their costs to go through. Lots of
         them got help from their parents of course, but not so many of them
         were entirely dependent on their parents. They worked summers and
         some of them worked at jobs right there, if they could get hold of
         a part-time job 5.
         
         SS: dependent on their parents.
         
         GC: Oh, they're financially less dependent-
         
         SS: Those that were in the fraternities.
         
         GC: oh» yes. I'd say that's definitely true. Those that were outside
         were less dependent. Sometimes I wondered about that, but I don't
         know, in some cases, individuals, 1^ wondered about at the time that
         I- but I had no way of knowing what their situation was.
         
         SS: I imagine that-
         
         GC: One or two - oh, there were one or two of the types, oh, they wasn't
         invited into a fraternity. There were some that were kind of oddball.
         I remember one who was quite brilliant in some things, but he - oh,
         he was sloppy in dress and all that and didn't seem to fit well in
         to any social group. He antagonized people. They thought he was
         odd. He studied accounting, I think eventually. And he was sort of
         a speed demon on reading fast - you've seen those things advertised
         those speedreading ? Well, I think he was a speed reader before
         that thing was invented. And, also a speedster in mathematics for
         quickness They tested him against an adding machine with an ex
         perienced person at the controls an adding machine, and he could
         beat it on figures. Adding a column of figures faster than she
         could put them in and he'd come up with the right answer before she
         would. (Chuckles)
         
         GC: Well, no, he was odd in many ways. He tried teaching school after
         ward, He wasn't much of a success at that, he couldn't hold a
         job. He monkeyed around with various things. He was promoting land
         deals and mining deals and things like that, he never settled, I
         don't think at a regular job all his life. I saw him a few times
         after he was in college and he was odd. I didn't dislike him at
         all, I talked to him a good deal and the fact is, he came-CtfoM.Latah
         County here on one of these backwoods farms beyond Deary x think^he
         has relatives still living in, I don't know.
         Vvrkind's?
         
         SS: I've heard of him, because I heard that he was a wizard at figures.
         
         GC: Yes, Shorty land, we called him. Oscar, Oscar I think was his
         
         SS: Did the young people from the- this area kind of keep track of each
         other at college? fou generally u ovld.
         
         GC: Oh, yes, if you saw somebody from here, why,- but sometimes or
         A other there was a lot of piling what course they take. Law students
         were law students, engineers with engineers and so on regardless whether they wereAfraternity
         or non-fraternity that's the way a
         lot of them found their friends there.
         
         SS: Was there something you were specializing in?
         
         GC: I took my major in history and minors in English and mathematics.
         
         SS: Why history?
         
         GC: Oh, I liked it. I don't know whether it was good or not, after I
         got into high school teaching, I was teaching mostly mathematics.
         In fact, I think I liked it better than teaching history. It was
         such a more definite. You could tell how a student was doing a whole
         lot easier and where he was having trouble in teaching mathematics
         thanAhistory or something like that.
         
         SS: Did you feel when you were studying history that there was much
         in between the pioneering that went on out here, you know, the whole
         idea of 
         
         GC: Well, no, we never considered ourselves pioneers when I was a kid.
         We considered the pioneers that had arrived about thirty-forty years
         before. We considered we'd passed that stage. (Chuckles)
         
         Thought we was right up-to-date. Looking back on it and knowing
         how we lived without any electricity, without automobiles and all
         that, they probably thought we were, but people didn't have those
         in the cities, either, or anywhere else, and they were just some
         thing that came along. No, it wasn't until just about World War I
         was on or a little before that automobiles began to become com
         moner and commoner, about 1910 and '11 and then the tempo increased.
         One of the things was the poor quality of the engines that they had
         at that time, you'd see people stalled along the road, something'd
         gone wrong with them,Ahad to have it hauled off or send for a me
         chanic. Hire a farmer with a team of horses to haul it into town.
         When cars became dependable enough so you could go someplace and
         come back again with a fair chance of not having to have a break
         down, then they began selling them. That was one of the qualities
         of that and they made tires so poor that they'd blow up easily
         if they got a little hot; tires and all that. And, of course, the
         roads had a lot to do with the bad tires, they had very little pavement^
         and they tossed gravel on so many roads, rough
         gravel, that was the way of putting the solid base in and hold down
         the mud and made it rough, a lot of 'em were stony, the roads. And
         the grades hadn't been laid out, there was an awful lot of this
         straight up hill and straight down hill stuff. So, it was rough on
         the cars to stand it. Any kind of a car would be rough with them
         kind of roads they had and the poorer cars, why, people thought
         those things they'd better keep to^cities where you could travel
         on a smooth road.
         
         SS: How difficult did travel get in the winter?
         
         Well, where we lived, we were six miles out of town, about. We al
         ways made it alright. Sometimes we would get too much snowfall to
         go on in, we d break out the roads with horses. Sometimes
         after we had the cars- used the cars- why, the car was sometimes
         harder to get through than the horses. Shucks, I was up here once,
         I'd been teaching in California, I came up here on Christmas and
         there was so darn much snow that it piled up about six feet and peo
         ple were coming in - the further places tha^f* had to abandon their
         car travel and they were putting horses through and that was around
         1935. There were still lots of horses, horses being used at that
         time, but they were on their way out. There was more and more mech
         anized farms and fewer and fewer horses each year until they disaappeared.
         You know, we were talking about social life at the university; I
         was wondering- what were the kind of things you did for social life?
         It was mostly campus dances. Oh, yes, and they were generally
         held in the gymnasium^there and they had them regularly. Otherwise
         students would often organize picnics for the bunches, some
         up to Moscow Mountain, a few of 'em. We were horse-drawn, that
         way, we hayracks, so a whole bunch of us could get on and
         on up. And then, I don't know, there was always the group of churchgoers
         that socialized in the churches^ town and
         college.
         
         SS: Did you generally live in an apartment?
         
         GC: I lived in a roominghouse most of the time there. Generally- rooms
         meals in the same house where there was a bunch of boys all going
         to the University. I think there were one or tx*o sometimes that
         weren't. I know one high school boy was living away from home stayed
         there one year.
         
         SS: Your father wasn't very strong on the churches was he?
         
         GC: No, he wasn't. Now, he believed firmly in the Lutherans interpre
         tations. He felt that the churches were too commercialized, they
         were departing too far from what was recommended. He was pretty
         much of a fundamentalist, you might say. He thought that they
         made churches too much of a question of building and money and all
         that, it occupied their time, too much, he was not too strong for
         churches. Though he supported that church in Nora pretty regularly;
         the old Nora Church up on -, it was what they calledwell,
         the term was Mission Friends, translated - the Swedish Free
         Church,- nonluth- it was Lutheran in doctrine, practically all, but
         had departed from it. And that church lasted up there for quite a
         while, up there at Nora. And they put out an awful lot of mission
         aries in the field. Oh, most of the ministers that I remember up
         there had served in Alaska among the Eskimos, at one time or another.
         Had served there or went up there
         
         SS: What do you think would be the difference behind the departure from
         doctrine that your father would see?
         
         GC: Well, he didn't like the formalism of church. He was better
         satisfied with a church where a. congregation iust got together
         and listened to a fairly learned man talk on the Bible in relation
         to ordinary living. He didn't- Now I always thought that he be
         longed in the Disciples of Christ- that church, commonly known
         as the Christian Church, he was more like that I think in his outlook
         than any othere.
         
         SS: Would that be more of a revival kind of church?
         
         No, it's a creedless church, they don't care what you believe, be
         lieve what you like. All they are concerned with is how a person
         lives his life and what he can do to live it like they say a Christian should.
         So, your father was moce interested in the idea of religion as an
         ethical force in a person's life?
         
         GC: Yes, absolutely. It seems more to me like a freethinker, I mean, an independent
         thin
         ker. Well, he was. He had ideas on most subjects that he come in contact
         with and more often disagreed than he agreed (Chuckles)
         
         SS: Do you think that that encouraged- that his philosophy encouraged
         his children to think for themselves?
         
         GC: Oh, I think so. Oh, I suppose it did, I never thought particularly
         about it, but undoubtedly it did. He said people ought to read and
         read and think for themselves. He was a great reader all his life.
         He spent lots of time- he subscribed to various newspapers, sometimes
         several of them, just to read what they had to say in editorials
         and all that. And^he read various books from time to time. Some of
         those books I just wondered why he got 'em, but he said when he was
         learning English when he came over here he could speak it
         in a little while, he got books and read them and learned how to usehow
         the language was used that way. And he wasn't particular what
         kind of book he got hold of. He got hold of some that he knew were
         good and what the subject matter was. It was largely history and
         religion and a few famous cla
         SS:ics. I know one of the books I read
         early because it was in our library was,A Quo Vadis. And I
         read it before I could fully understand it. And. and such
         things like that. And then there was a book of English poets as I
         can remember; a great, big book of English poets. He bought those
         things in different times.
         
         SS: Would he involve your mother in those discu
         
         GC: Well, not much. She wasn't too much interested in that, she was
         much more interested in the home and the well-being of her child
         ren and things like that; what to do next.
         
         SS: Do you feel that he was le
         SS: practical than some guys because of
         
         GC: Probably he was, I don't think he was- he the best of farmers,
         don't think. I think my brother, Walter, learned to farm faster
         than he did under the conditions on which we farmed here. He'd been
         raised on a farm in Sweden but evidently they were really small
         farms and a large part of the time was spent in- a comparatively
         short period of time was spent farming and a large part of the
         time as woodsmen in the forests nearby there. And I saw farms in
         Sweden that he might have, small farms, which are- when I first went
         back there. of course, they had a whole lot better machinery than
         he ever saw, machinery was invented after he came here, but it
         wouldn't have been the same thing. They farm a ten acre plot or a
         fifteen acre plot and raise some wheat and some rye on it and haul
         it to the mill ' it ground into meal and bring the flour
         home, they used to do that and that's a lot different than raising
         to sell to support economics. They got their ready money from the
         working in the woods there, these woodsmen. Different kind of a
         life entirely.
         
         SS: One thing about that that reminds me of- is that the feudal system
         was still pretty strong there when your father left- I mean, there
         were some big land owners.
         
         CC: Well, there were some big land owners, but I think comparatively
         speaking, there weren't so many, that is, it seemed to me that what
         they called a big land owner would never have been called a big land
         owner, it is all a matter of comparison.
         
         I'm talking about these early days when your father left.
         Yes, I mean that. They spoke of a person had a big tract of land,
         oh, heck, he probably didn't have 100 acres in cultivation on it,
         and the rest were so much smaller that it was comparative, that was
         all comparative. Of course, there were large tracts undoubtedly
         held by- held some places in Sweden from ancient times and that
         had managed to hang onto their land.
         
         SS: Did that mean that you kids go?
         
         GC: We didn't go regular to church, no. I think the church goers regarded
         us pretty much as heathens.(Chuckles) I think. But that never
         bothered us 
         
         SS: Would you go like on the—
         
         GC: I remember when the Kellberg family came from Missouri. They were
         Swedish, but they had lived in a non-Swedish community and probably
         were Lutheran. Mrs. Anderson, Anderson, was one of that, she
         was about two years old then, just a baby, but after they got here
         I think Mrs. Kellberg- when she realized there was a Luteran Church
         in Troy, she immediately wanted to go and so they joined that church
         and went there. But I believe one of the boys told me they never had
         any church in that community in Missouri that they attended before
         that. Of course, the oldest boy was only about ten when they came.
         That's the way they were/just influenced by the fact that they landed
         in a Swedish community and the old folks were Swedish and they -just
         reverted back. They'd gotten along very well without a church appa
         rently for the itAerval without missing
         
         SS: Would you be inclined to go on Christmas or occasions?
         
         GC: oh» Yes» yes, yes. Yes, we would. In fact, we went, we always
         went up to that- an old Swedish custom of oh, a morning service
         on Christmas, starting about six o'clock, and we used to go. Christ
         mas was one that Dad insisted on going to, because I think it was
         reminiscent the old days of Sweden, he sort of felt that that
         was something that should belong. I don't know. And on Easter, the
         same thing. I wonder if this Lutheran Church practices early mor-
         ning service any more. I don t know whether it does or not.
         
         SS: Well, the one other thing I wanted to ask you about was, how close
         do you feel the community was on Burnt Ridge in the early days?
         
         GC: Oh, I don't know, really. I think they felt friendly toward each
         other, most of the people. They were neighbors I don t know
         as there was any great closeness except special families felt close
         to each other and others didn't. Oh, Kellberg and his brother-inlaw,
         lived on the adjoining place just north of us, those kids con
         torted together a great deal. Now, the Ruberg family were cousins
         with about three families on the Ridge, related, you know. Then
         you got to the northern part of the Ridge, you got to Lawrence John
         son's, oh, he was the mother(?) to the Deleen children. There's still
         Deleens around here. Lawrence was Clarence's father, he was the
         brother of Mrs. Deleen and cousin to the grandfather of the Larsen
         children that went in here. And I guess they were cousins or se
         cond cousins to the Andersons that lived up there. They were quite
         a group there of peoples that were related. One came, he told about
         it- the advantage and got them to move in and he'd find a
         piece of land for them. Now f^deen who lived up there, was a rather
         distant relative of my father, but he'd grown up with him in Sweden
         practically, they'd gone to the same schools and were the same age
         and they kept track of each other in this country and Dad was more
         or less interested- responsible for him being here. And he bought
         that place out there and he saw that land, what they were doing
         with it, he wrote what he'd done and told him that the land, what
         looked like good land to him seemed to be going awfully cheap out
         here and Rudeen got immediately interested and when the chance to
         buy came up here he sent a check of money to him and put down his
         option to hold it. 'he got out here and he bought it. They
         were our closest friends, the Rudeens, simply because Dad and Rudeen
         were old friends rather than what they were- they were second cou
         sins or third cousins, something like that.
         
         SS: Sounds like kinship played an important part in it?
         
         GC: Kinship played an important part there. Now, the Swansons came la
         ter. They came- Frank Swansffn came just about- with his family, the
         same time- he's Alvin's Swansen's father, and I think two of his
         children were born after they came to Burnt Ridge. But then two of
         his brothers came down there, they were unmarried young men and one
         of 'em married a Beleen girl and the other married and Andersen
         girl. They married in one generation of people already
         settled there. Ed continued to live out there, he's got- his descendents
         are Austin Swenstn and Richie and Eddie are his grandsons.
         George, he lives somewhere else. He went up around Spokane or
         Coeur d'Alene and settled up there.
         
         SS: Sounds like kinship was the most important part of this?
         
         GC: Well, it probably was. And I think the kinship of reached to
         gether on a lot of that.
         
         SS: People got related that were living next to each other.
         
         GC: Yes, they did. A lot of these people are related out here in dif
         ferent degrees of cousinship from those early marriages. I imagine
         quite a few o# those people on Burnt Ridge, are about second cousins,
         third cousins and fourth cousins relationships living right here in
         Latah County. And I know it had some effect because Kellberg came
         mostly because the Alders had settled , and Mrs. Alder was
         Kellberg's sister and she was very close to her family. She was
         glad to have Kellberg come out. And later, she had two brothers-r
         Mrs. Kellberg had two brothers; one of them came out here as a young
         man, I probably at invitation and married somebody
         here and settled and thenAinduced another one to come from Oklahoma,
         and he came. Both the Kellbergs and the Alders had in Oklahoma
         before that. I don't know, Alder was what they called an '89er, he
         was in the rush down tnere.
         
         SS: I heard a nubmer of people were in Ashtabula at some point.
         
         GC: Ashtabula, Ohio, yes. A lot of them went in there^nd established
         themselves. Some came out here and some came later, but I think
         now - Clarence Johnson's father or maybe it was his mother, that they
         were established there for a while, then came on out. Lawrence John
         son arrived before he was married.
         
         SS: These kinship ties, I take it, meant kind of that you were often
         times, like your father and Mr. Rudeen, that they were together in
         the old country and backhand they were kin-back there?
         
         GC: Uh-huh. They did. There was a kind of tie there in kinship. I
         didn't think about it, but I learned that the same thing was true
         over on American Ridge. Those Chaney families moved in and I
         think some of their wives are related to some of the other people
         there. I know the Harlan family and -
         
         SS: The Driscols and Dunns and Cunninghams?
         
         GC: They were related- the Dunns and Cunninghams were sisters.- the
         Driscoll men. There was the old patriarch his sons were
         older than my father, but he came out here, too,with them. He was
         an old man, he died long before my time.
         
         SS: Do you think there was kind of a natural tendency to put more trust
         or rely more on people you were related to than to people that you
         just were friends with?
         
         GC: Oh, I think so. I think possibly there was. I think they clung to
         their own quite a bit and trusted 'em much more. I think that's
         true. A lot of those people first that came on Burnt Ridge, - well
         the related ones were all from one province there, a single province
         there, where all these Andersens and Deleens came from.
         
         SS: Which province?
         
         GC: The province was called Vasternorrland , But a lot of those others
         were, I know Westbergs were from there and I guess both- and I guess the Kellbergs
         from there and the Swans, but Alder, he himself washe
         was from some other section . It -just seems that an awful
         lot of the people that landed there was from that province.
         
         SS: Well, you think that the people who were not Swedish who lived on
         Burnt Ridge when you were growing up- there were some of those-
         
         GC: Oh, yes.
         
         SS: Do you think that they just weren't as much of a part of the community?
         
         GC: I think possibly they were- they did feel that way. I don't think
         they deliberately made them feel that way, but of course they didn't
         belong to that church. I know the Sanders family, wEre friendly
         to us in spite of the fact that Old Man Sanders had certain peculia
         rities- his main peculiaries came from jaga which he would go on
         in town.
         
         SS: Drinking.
         
         GC: Drinking. Every so often he had a hard drinking bout.
         
         SS: And that made some of the more sober people not-
         
         GC: Yes. Of course, they were not all teetotlers, by any means. Most
         of 'em, a large part of 'em were accustomed to a little drinking.
         Though some weren't. As far as I know, I could probably name the
         ones but that wouldn't mean anything in particular. But I know some
         of those- we had different ones there, but so many of those didn't
         stay long enough to get acquainted, Sanders family, they
         friends with the people on Burnt Ridge, but now, of course,
         Joe Porter he settled down, he was the man I said owned the threshing
         machine, but he was a fellow that liked to act tough, carried his
         revolver by his side and was always apparently trying to bully some
         body and things happened to him once in a while- he would get pushed
         and that sort of set people apart from him because he wasn't
         acting particularly friendly and liked to be friends. But his kids
         were nice kids, by golly; two girls and a boy. They got along al
         right with the kids in school, they wasn't too bad, but, I don't
         know they may have felt a little like outsiders because they weren't
         part of the community like the others were. I don't think very
         many people invited Porter into their homes, he and his wife. Well,
         of course, there was a little thing- his wife was part Indian, about
         half or quarter, but those children didn't show much Indian and I
         think they all married white. They probably disappeared into the
         white race.
         
         SS: Was that Burnt Ridge schoolhouse used for community get-to-gathers?
         
         GC: Yes. It was really a community get-to-gather, and if there was
         some speaker in the church, missionary or such, he went bv there to
         speak to 'em. If they wanted a politician, if it was election time
         why, he'd in there in the evenings. Farm Union organizer
         I heard speak there once, he was in there. And they went there. And
         they used to have, oh, parties at-nights. About Friday nights in
         the wintertime they practically always had some kind of a party
         there, social, box social or just get together with a little program
         or singing.
         
         SS: Did they play party games there?
         
         GC: Yes. Well, I'll tell you in the schoolroom they couldn't really
         play that, they didn't have room enough, they filled the seats.
         They played those outdoors in the summer- the they played
         those a lot.
         
         SS: I was thinking when the adults got together.
         
         GC: Oh, yes, I mean the adults there, to play it inside that schoolhouse,
         there wasn't space enough because it wasn't that big a schoolhouse,
         probably all filled with seats, mostly. But I remember those
         parties- party games used to be played a lot some indoors and some
         outdoors in houses around the town. I remember years ago when I
         was a small kid, they held one of those at: our house. I thought
         there was a terrific lot of people there there weren't more than
         fifteen altogether there. (Chuckles) That was before I was of
         school age.
         
         SS: Did they have dancing on Burnt Ridge? Or was that frowned on?
         
         GC: Well, I'll tell you, a lot of those church members frowned on their
         children dancing, but neverthe less, they into town, to the
         they were community dances in town^pretty regularly, too. And I guess they
         got used to it because eventually some of the places they could
         dance there. There was quite a few places, homes, that opened it
         up to dancing.
         
         SS: Even on Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC: Yes, on Burnt Ridge.
         
         SS: This was later?
         
         GC: Oh, I don't know, a little later, maybe I was seventeen, eighteen
         years old. Kellberg let 'em have a barn dance. He built this big
         barn before they put in the hay. He didn't care one way or the other.
         Kellberg, I don't think was a religious man, he thought it was
         probably good for his kids to go to church and it was a comfort to
         his wife. in his, own.
         
         SS: What was he like?
         
         GC: Oh, he was a joker- he'd get pretty sarcastic and pretty sore about
         things, too, but he was very vocal, but nobody scared him. Oh, he
         wasn't a powerful man, but he just wasn't afraid of anybody regard
         less of how big he was, he was ready to speak up and speak his piece.
         I liked Mp. Kellberg.
         
         SS: Were he and your father very good friends?
         
         GC: Oh, they were good friends, yes. My father got disgusted with him
         once in a while because he was a teller of tell stories and you
         never knew when he was just laying it,on or whether he was actually
         recounting an incident that happened. He was a good deal older than
         his wife, oh, he was about the age of my father/fhat would make
         it about thirty-five years or so that he was older than his oldest
         child, probably. So, he was ower quite a while in this country.
         He was in Wyoming for a while. He rode as a cowboy on ranches out
         there for a nubmer of years, things like that. He said his intro
         duction- I remember that, he told his introduction to Cheyenne
         is when he came from the railroad- he worked on the railroad there
         into Cheyenne, the Union Pacific. As he came, town he found thishe
         saw a man hanging on a telegraph pole and he counted seven of
         'em. Men had been hanged to telephone poles, there had been a lynch
         ing party. That was his introduction to Cheyenne when he came in.
         
         SS: Now, is that supposed to be true or not?
         
         GC: Now, I don't know, I just wonder if he wasn't laying it on.
         
         SS: You never could tell?
         
         GC: you couldn't prove it. He swears that it was true, but no one
         investigate whether that happened or not. They probably didn t care,
         
         SS: One more thing about these dances or these get-to-gathers. Usually
         if you're going to get together in some of these homes, would it be
         for dancing or for parties?
         
         GC: For play party, yes, if you went into a home.
         
         SS: You'd play party games and that kind of thing
         
         GC: Yes. I know they had- what was it now? Actually there was only one
         or two places that did any dancing to amount to anything. One
         was big square house up there, it seems to have been taken down long
         since. People there didn't object to dancing, they had a good sized
         parlor, people could dance around there to a little music, they
         couldn't entertain a whole lot of people, but they didn't mind.
         
         SS: Were they Swedish? This family?
         
         GC: I don't know what they were. Several families lived there at one
         time or another. I can't even recall their name now, but I know
         they went there. They said they could dance there. They danced
         when somebody was invited there for dinner, it wasn't it wouldn't
         be given especially for young people that wanted to dance, they
         came there and if people wanted to dance, I think they would dance.
         But, I seem to remember, oh, I do remember one place; there was a
         house that was vacant a good deal. It had went through several
         hands- who purchased that- purchased by someone who lived elsewhere.
         And he let them into that house to use it. 'jHey had a good sized-
         What had been undoubtedly the livingroom and dining room of the
         house. If they didn't mind crowding a little they could get a
         dozen couples, maybe, on the floor at once. Probably less
         actually there. And they danced there some. I know it was one
         of the boys that I went to school with, he was a little older than
         Six I, I thinks year; or so, was running the farm at that time forhis
         mother still owned it, she was a widow and he liked to dance.
         He'd been away attending college for a little while and he liked
         dancing, so he let 'em in and they had it there and he lived at
         the homeplace there. He and his sister- his sister was much younger
         than he but she kept house for him.when he was farming and there
         we danced, it wasn't the old folks, in case, it was the youn
         ger generation that was growing up.
         
         SS: So, would it be fair to say that the older generation didn't approve
         of it?
         
         GC: Didn't approve of it- much. They didn't really try to stop the kids
         after they were grown or near grown. I think they realized it was
         futile.
         
         SS: What about the younger generation drinking? About the boys having
         a drink or two?
         
         GC: Well, I tell you, I think the boys were less inclined for a little
         sip now and then than some of their fathers were; some weren't.
         I know there were a couple of men there, that, oh, they'd like a
         drink once in a while. They weren't fellows that stood around the
         bar downtown, they would take a bottle home and have it there, give
         a neighbor a drink if he came in, that was about all. And some were
         dead against it. It was odd about one family I know out there. All
         the boys eventually became more or less drinkers, none of them real
         topers, but occasionally- social drinkers, but the father was dead
         against it, he wouldn't touch it. One of the reasons was that he
         had a hard drinking father, and he thought it made things pretty
         tough on the kids, so he stayed away from it entirely- But his sons
         sort of- they thought their father didn't get any fun out of life,
         guess, I don't know. They were never, as I understood nuisances
         on account of alcohol anywhere at anytime. I don't know, I think
         oh, a few of the boys drank a little. My brother, Paul's generation
         liked a little drink now and then. Oh, one or two of 'em could
         get tooted up alittle from time to time could
         drink, would always like a little drink and sometimes he drank too
         much, they said, I never saw him that way,, I didn't think it was.
         But then I was still a kid when he grew up, he would be about fif
         teen, sixteen years older than I was.
         
         SS: Do you think the younger generation was less religious than the older?
         Yes, a lot of em just stopped going to church. When they grew up?
         Yes.(slight interruption)
         
         Things just grow with the kind of life they had in this country.
         I think there was less there was more doubt dn religious matters,
         growing up through that period. They used to accept it, and then
         there was less and less of that. And, I think, there was maybe revolt against the
         strictures they put on 'em.
         
         SS: What was that?
         
         GC: Oh, going to church and all that when they didn't feel like going
         to church. (Laughter)
         
         SS: And maybe being against all that dancing so much and all that?
         
         GC: Uh-huh, a lot of 'em. A lot of 'em became independent in their
         thoughts.and it didn't include church. I'll tell you, Dean Swanson
         was one of the earliest freethinkers I knew to express himself on
         that. I think immortality is just- we go down to the grave
         and then it makes more earth and more life comes from that, that's
         all. Most of them never expressed themselves very much on religion.
         A lot of them so that their children went back to church.
         Though they hadn't been very good church members in the meantime.
         (Laughter) 
         
         they found was murdered, nobody knows whether he
         committed suicide or who he was.
         
         SS: Which murder?
         
         GC: Oh, the first one I remember of, I was just a small kid then and
         it made quite an impression on me because, well, I had heard of mur
         ders and knew what they were- I thought they happened to wild, mean
         people living a long ways from the kind of people I knew.(Chuckles)
         But this mat?shall was shot down in Troy by a fellow he went down
         to arrest. Most people thought there was more or less a case of
         self defense, they thought he went down there to try to force him
         to resist and have an excuse for killing him. That was what a lot
         of people thought and it was told different ways. There's a little
         account of that in that book on American Ridge that Ann Driscoll
         wrote.
         
         SS: Was Hays pretty unpopular?
         
         GC: Yes he was unpopular, yes, except with his cronies and he didn't
         have too many of them. Well, I don't know, my father despised
         He said he was crooked. He and his boys, Henry and Harry worked
         a game on people^. Harry would pick a fight in a saloon and the old
         man would come in an arrest the other fellow for assault and battery
         and bring him to jail and probably club him over the head and then
         he'd- when it came up to court he'd bring other things that he had,
         a knife maybe or watch that he had taken off of him and a pocketbook
         with maybe a dollar left in it. That was all he had and the fellow
         would swear that he had moreK ,and it happened so regularly
         that he thought that was a game, that they were making money that
         way by arresting people and lifting their wallets. (Chuckles) It
         could have been. He didn't last too long in this community after
         that. The two Hays boys pulled out fairly soon after that. I think
         there was another- I heard that she had another item in ' that I
         had always heard differently, and that is it said that Payne Sly had
         said that he was going to get the marshall, but I heard it the other
         way 'round; that the Marshall said that he was going to get Payne.
         So that's two stories there, I don't know which is right.
         
         SS: I heard- two people said to me that after the killing that there
         were a number of people that wanted to lynch Payne Sly.
         Yes, yes, the marshall's two sons, Henry and Harry, they were twins,
         I don't know if Bill was here, he was an older son, or not at that
         time, but that leads up to the other contradiction from the way I
         heard the story. He said that there that he was surrendered and
         brought to Moscow. Well, it didn't say how he really surrendered,
         but I heard he just-look his rifle and walked across the railroad
         tracks and up into the American Ridge side there where there was
         plenty of woods at that time and then he crossed over over to the
         Moscow road and sat down beside the road and waited.- he figures
         the marshall would be telephoned for, or ti^raphed for, I think
         they didn't have much in the way of telephones at that time, and
         he'd come down for him and when the sheriff came down from there
         he walked out and surrendered himself. And the sheriff just turned
         at Troy his team around and drove back to Moscow and notified them that Payne
         Sly was in custody. He wasn't taking a chance on those people,-
         
         That's what you heard?
         
         That's the way I heard it.
         
         Now, there was another murder?
         
         Well, Clemm, a fellow that was, oh, I don't know- well, his wife
         ran a boardinghouse and I don't know, he was a hard drinker, he
         was found in an alley down there back of a little restaurant,
         or near the, - not the- but the alleyway ran past the restaurant,
         and he was found in the morning I think or late at night or some
         thing, dead there, and it looked as if he had had his head banged
         in. No one was arrested for that. They didn't know who had done
         it. It might have been even in a fight. Somebody had knocked
         him down or hit his head or something like that. But he was pro
         bably very drunk because he had a daily habit of it.
         
         SS: I heard something about there was a suspic ion that this black guy
         that ran a restaurant in Troy that had done that.
         
         CC: That he'd done that- oh, he'd done that- somebody started that, but
         as I understood it, there wasn't an iota of evidence-
         SS: That this guy had done it.
         
         GC: Had done it; the last they knew of him he was tending to his affairs
         he in the restaurant until closed up and went home.
         
         SS: So nothing ever happened to him?
         
         GC: No, nothing ever happened to him. There was nothing to arrest him
         on. There was a third one down here and that seemed to be a sense
         less murder. I never understood exactly why it came to pass. They
         said there was a witness to that and the story that those two men
         seemed to be quarreling but not very hard and somebody said he'd
         given him something and he took and rammed a knife into him. Just
         exactly- I never did hear what the cause of the quarrel was sup
         posed to be or why he was suddenly enraged, but anyway he was ar
         rested and brought to trial. I never did know just exactly what
         kind of a sentence he got. Payne Sly got life sentence, but he didn't
         spend more than six, seven, eight years there.
         
         GC: He was abrother of old Jake Sly ..
         
         END OF INTERVIEW Transcribed by Frances Rawlins 10-17-78
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13395</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Cameron</previous>
      <next>Carlson_Gustav2</next>
      <disp_name>Carlson_Gustav1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
