<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">5/14/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Willa Carlson, 1974-05-14, Interview #4 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:18:13</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Carlson, Willa</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #4</intnum>
      <occupation>Teacher and farm wife; author of manuscript on Latah County history</occupation>
      <birthyear>1896</birthyear>
      <residence>American Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Missouri (early 1890's)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#racial discrimination"&gt;racial discrimination&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lynching"&gt;lynching&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farmers"&gt;farmers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#vigilantes"&gt;vigilantes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#discrimination"&gt;discrimination&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#American Ridge"&gt;American Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13398</file_name>
      <mp3>13399.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13399.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Future of society</title>
            <synopsis>A questioning look at the future of our society.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>Roots of racism</title>
            <synopsis>Roots of racism in the American colonies.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Prejudice against African Americans on American Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Prejudice against African Americans in attitudes on the ridge.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>African American familes (Joe Wells)</title>
            <synopsis>Elmer Wells, the Gub Mix family, and Joe Wells.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Joe Wells; lodging not open to African-Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Joe Wells was welcome to eat at the Moscow Hotel.
               Blacks couldn't stay overnight there, but found lodging
               in local homes.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1080</time>
            <title>Northern Methodists verses Southern Methodists on American Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Division on American Ridge between northerners and
               southerners: the North and South Methodist churches.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Lynching</title>
            <synopsis>Fight between Bob Clemm and a Black person in Troy, ending in
               Clemm's death and the threatened lynching of the Black person.
               (Mrs. Carlson is unsure of the details).
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Old Man Carlson sympatized with Black Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Old man Carlson sympathized with Black Americans, hated
               slavery, and had strong opinions.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>North verses South (Civil War) not as prominent on American Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Political differences on ridge between North and South
               became less important than they had been back East,
               Gold taken from North Idaho went to the Civil War.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>Local politics; women's politics</title>
            <synopsis>Local politics. Influence of university on the ridge,
               George Davidson, the first local graduate, "Talking
               politics," Women's politics" was gardens, chickens and
               babies, Charles Cummings planted by the moon, and
               his gardening was followed by many.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2580</time>
            <title>Politics; successful farmers</title>
            <synopsis>Politics. Morrill Act brought university here. Farmers
               wondered about prospects for irrigation in south Idaho,
               and sympathized with early settlers' problems. They
               speculated what would happen to the country. They talked
               about successful farmers like Martin Thomas, lawyers,
               and local politicians like Burton French. People looked
               at personalities more than politics. Al Roberts thought
               Republicans were Lincoln's party, but Republicans also
               favored high tariffs. Some people worshipped Lincoln,
               but he, like Washington, was a man with weaknesses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>Vigilantes on American Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Vigilantes on the ridge go after a horse thief in the
               early days, (cont.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Vigilante activities; Hanging Tree</title>
            <synopsis>(cont.) Two boys sitting in a tree heard the men
               underneath planning to hang the thief there. The
               boys never knew for sure that the suspected the act had
               been carried out, and called it the Hanging Tree.
               People were tight-lipped about vigilante activities.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Squatting on land</title>
            <synopsis>People tried to protect the unclaimed land, occasionally
               by squatting. New arrivals usually had some connection
               with those already there or nearby.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4140</time>
            <title>Charles Cummings purchased land from Al Roberts</title>
            <synopsis>Charles Cummings bought 40 acres from Al Roberts, who
               had gone in debt by co-signing for others in the hard
               years of the 1890s.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Socialism; Democrats;</title>
            <synopsis>Peter Carlson (her father-in-law) was practically a
               socialist in his beliefs, but was a Democrat, Manfred
               Harland had keen evaluations of issues, such as
               responsibilities of county commissioners.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>Women not attending political speeches at schoolhouse</title>
            <synopsis>few women went to political speeches at the schoolhouse.
               As a child Mrs. Carlson sees through the false flattery
               of politician Merriweather Lewis.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4920</time>
            <title>Political parties not important; </title>
            <synopsis>Political party made no difference in the men's concerns
               on the ridge. Charles Cummings put his money in the
               best stock for his farm. The old Roberts house. Political
               differences were kept quiet because the people were
               neighbors.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5220</time>
            <title>Supporting IWWs, need for industrial organization</title>
            <synopsis>Her husband Paul and his father supported the IWW's
               because they understood the need for industrial
               organization. Ridge farmers who did well were usually
               against them.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5340</time>
            <title>Swedish neighbors on American Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Carlson was wholly accepted by the Swedish people
               on Burnt Ridge.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Problems on family farm</title>
            <synopsis>Problems on the family farm.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>Fire that burned down Carlson home</title>
            <synopsis>The fire which burned down the Carlson home. The tasks
               that had been done that day. When the fire breaks out,
               her first concern is for the children. Saving things from
               the house. Fire caused by cinders on the roof.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Social and political views of American Ridgers; racial prejudice and regional
         divisions. Family adversity: typhoid, house fire, trouble with hired hand. Suspected
         vigilante
         hanging. Electioneering. Kendrick fire of 1904. 5-14-74 2.5 hr 48p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         WILLA CUMMINGS CARLSON: (She is discussing the State of American Society).
         This is, as I sayfan interesting time. It's an interesting time. It also
         is I think pretty well inlaid with tragedy.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: When you say that you think we can go—what did you say—we
         can go down to the finale or—
         
         WC: Well I said which will we go? There's going to be-if it's a climax, and
         Ithink it's a climax, and it's been building and building-all right now,
         when the climax breaks, it goes over. We don't stop, things go, the wheels
         turn. Well all right—in anything, comparing it to any of life's crises,
         after the climax there's afinale. Now are we going down towards that finale,
         or will we start buildinq toward anew finale? That's going to take engineering.
         
         SAM: Well when you say if we have the edifice, what do you mean by that?
         
         WC: What I mean is this. I don't know where I get the idea, but I think of
         anything that we build in the way of askeleton government of any kind, that
         it's been built, hasn't it, by human hands? And after it's done—you know
         many of the edifices with which we deal are not seen by the eye. Don't you
         think that, that there's an edifice been built? Well is it built on solid
         ground, is it built on rock, or is it built on sand? And just as those that
         we have, all the signs, all the similes that we've given in literature and
         everywhere else-well don't think we're not building them all the time ourselves.
         And what are we doing? Iused to try to teach my children that. You're building
         all the time. Now where are you building? Are you building solidly?
         Oh well some of the kids, some of my own, you know some of them, you probably
         see which ones mostly. Oh, what do you know about it and how can you tell?
         Well you can do what you want to, and you can tear down and build up again.
         You have to build with repairs, and of course that's true in many cases. And
         they always think they're engineers of their own building, but they're not
         always. If they can interpret and see what's coming, go with it or against
         it, solidly, Ithink they're better off. Have you read The Late Planet
         
         SAW: No.
         
         WC: Well, now you're of a-you've had, you say, a Jewish background, which
         interests me, because the Jewish background, with the few Dews I've been
         privileged to talk with about the their background-Ordinarily, those that
         Iknow, they've had it and that's it, and they don't want to enter in any-
         (Break.)
         
         WC: Ithink so. And history bears this out. All countries have come to those
         crossroads.
         
         SAM: What do you think that his crossroads is? Is it acrossroads of moral
         fiber, ethical—what is it?
         
         WC: Largely. Largely. That's caused the downfall. There is atremendous effort
         to get them back on aroad of strict morality. But apart of it is looseness.
         Ideplore the tearing down of-nou Ibelieve in constitutions, don't get me
         wrong. I'm liberal in alot of in law and order (chuckles), much as I deplore the kind
         of laws we make and
         the decisions that we come to sometimes. But nevertheless I believe in order,
         and at heart I am aconservative, in away. Idon't believe in reckless
         waste of human energy nor human power in any way. And as far as all this
         business of racial contention and one thing another, it's been terrible and
         still we had it. Ule should have knn.„ni And you look back at history, of
         course our hindsight, the hindsight of all of us is so much better than our
         foresight naturally. We've had that told to us many times, and Ifor one have
         accepted it because Ican see the truth of it all around me. But now we
         should know as we look back over history that-and Ithink it is significant
         in our history, and Icbn't hear very many making anything of it, and Iknow
         I've mentioned it several times, and even historians say, "Well that's one of
         the accidents, just an accident." Naturally when things are going on they'll
         come at the same time, but look what happened: now back in 1619 happens to be
         the year in which the House of Burgesses, which was astab at getting selfgovernment,
         real democratic government of the people in Virginia, the new
         colony in the new world. Ispeak of 1619 and I'm talking about the new world
         of the United States, not because Ibelong to the United States all together,
         of course that's why Iam looking at it naturally, because Ihappened by
         accident to have been born here. Accident? No. Idon't believe things
         happen by accident. And that was that year anyway it started, and all the
         world had turned their eyes on the colonies. And here was this colony over
         here going to try an experiment in self-government. And at that time there
         were several patriots that had come in, and they had made their speeches and
         made their stabs for this particular sort of thing. And then that same year
         was the year when the Dutch ship landed with a cargo of Negroes, slaves that
         they had brought from Africa, in Virginia. And there were these colonists,
         many of them those that had gone up here to establish self-government, out
         there elbowing each other out to get the best slaves. Buying the slaves and
         introducing them into Virginia, the very same year in the very same colony!
         They were introduced, and it was aDutch trading vessel, that brought in. I've
         always pointed that out too to the English, who were so proud of their record,
         that it was aDutch trading vessel that brought the Negroes, the first Negroes
         into the colony of Virginia. There was also asmall attempt made to quash
         some of the drinking that was going on there, because there was a lot of
         that.^We forget that sometimes in talking about the colonies. There were
         bring/up alot of-you can be sure that licentiousness prevailed in some of
         those places.
         
         SAM: I'd like to ask you now to look at the Ridge in the old days. This is
         very interesting to me. What were the attitudes that you remember towards
         race on the Ridge?
         
         W C: Towards race?
         
         SAM: I mean the Negro problem.
         
         WC: You mean the Negro problem. Well (chuckles). I'll tell you. I was a child
         and of course I didn't know the big things. Ididn't know the big overall
         things. I hadn't philosophized. I hadn't taken into consideration the
         religious aspect that Ilearned to have later. I had to learn that,I didn't
         come born with it. My people were not even religious people, and of course
         they wondered where Igot my ideas when I'd come home with them, and many
         times Iwas shut up because they didn't want me talking about such things.
         So Ididn't know too much when Iwas little. But Idid know about the Negro
         problem. I was afraid of Negroes. Now I must have gotten that fear from
         people around me, because no other place. My mother was from Missouri and
         she knew alot of Negroes. And the Negroes that she knew, she was perfectly
         at home with and talked about them. But, she had the idea of all the white
         people—now for instance, she trained me to always say Mister and Missus,
         and to this day. that was good training. After I grew up even, Irealised
         it was good training, because alot of people thought, they said to me, "Well
         you must have had pretty good training, because you always say Mr. and Mrs.
         to the older people, and you're quite polite." And Iwas complimented for
         my politeness by some very rough talking people, people that never thought of
         saying anything but your first name. And Istill have that notion that if the
         people are strange to me, I'm one of the last ones to start calling them by
         their first name. That seems to me to be alittle more familiar than you
         ought to be with strangers. But my mother's reason now, coming back to what
         the training would be, was that you called the Negroes, the servants, by
         their first names, because after all, they didn't have any other names. No,
         they weren't permitted, as Ilearned when Igrew alot older, that they weren't
         permitted-They had their own marriage rights, „lot of them did, and they
         xn marriage. They weren't allowed to go to achurch to be married, no sir.
         They weren't permitted anything. They weren't given any legal rights. And
         .hen it came right down to it, look at the Dred Scott decision, that aNegro
         slave was c^ooertv. and should be treated as property. He had no more right
         than a horse or a cow.
         you think the attitudes on the Ridge were in the abstract? How did they about that
         too. But !knew aman, we know
         aman, and you probably have run into him too-old Elmer Wells, he still
         The .ells family lived back in North Carolina along with these mixes that
         are here-the old Nixes, the ones that came before them. Ididn't know any
         of 'em, but Ijust know of the family, the Hix family. And Elmer wells
         practically worshiped at the feet of old Cub nix and his wife, that they
         hu^and knew him and worked with him before he died-of course he was alot
         older than my husband. But he came here as ayoung man, and was interested
         politically and one thing another, he came from North Carolina, well Elmer
         wells had known them bacckk ttnheerree, hbuutt tthhe«y„'rdd ubeen poor compared to
         the Mixes.
         their slaves. They were very lovable people, some of those, but still they
         recognized as people. Even in the Constitution, It took three-fifths
         fifths people, aperson, as aslave clear back in the Constitution. Alot
         Constitution. I'm not very conversant with it now because I (chuckles) haven't
         read it in so long, but when I was in school I was very much interested in
         government and I surely read the Constitution, and I learned that we didn't
         have alot of rights that we thoughtwe had. But then we treated the Negro
         shamefully and always did! And couldn't somebody see that that was a terrible
         way to treat those people?! Isn't it something terrible to think that our
         ancestors didn't know how to do and that they could look upon human beings as
         being three-fifths of people? Isn't that awful? It's ridiculous. And I've
         been talking about that ever since I learned it down in grade school.
         
         SAM: What was their attitude towards Joe Wells, though?
         
         U C: Well, Joe Wells was like so well by Elmer Wells. They came out here some
         way, that family of slaves followed the Wells out here. And Idon't know,
         I never did know that story because I didn't know them, I didn't live in that
         neighborhood. And not until long afterward did Iknow that he'd got his name
         from Elmer Wells' family. But Elmer worked for my husband for awhile. He
         was old but he could still grub brush, and my husband was afiend for grubbing
         brush by hand, even though the tract of land that he cleared wouldn't ever
         produce enough to pay for the wages of clearing it. But that's the way my
         husband was, that's the kind of an economist he was. And he did not know
         how to manage money. An awful good fellow in many many ways, but—I'm sure
         Elmer Wells would have thought that, because he was agood Democrat though
         for Elmer Wells. And Elmer Wells was a very good Democrat and he went around
         making an awful bad noise with some ugly words about the Republicans. That
         was his style of being aDemocrat. But he liked Joe Wells. But still, Joe
         Wells was a Negro. He was not up-to-date with them. Now I understood that
         when the Wells came down here—I don't know this for a fact, and I'm not
         telling it as a fact nor even suggesting it's a fact
         
         SAM: Hearsay.
         
         W C: Yes, it was pure invited to eat
         with Mixes, but he didn't eat at the same table, they always set another table
         for them. Idon't know about that. But afellow by the name of Thompson ran
         the Moscow Hotel, and he said,can sure eat here." But
         at that time they had arule in the Moscow Hotel that no Negroes could stay
         overnight in the hotel. So agroup of singers came in here, guite along time
         ago. And Iwas young and out on American Ridge, and Ihad no influence and
         had no way of doing things. And my father wouldn't have thought of mixing
         in anything like that. He wouldn't have thought of it. He didn't think it
         was right, Icbn't mean to say that Poppa thought it was right. He said,
         "They've no right to do that to those people, lock 'em out of ahotel or Refuse
         to feed them or give them housing." But there'd be people here around town,
         here and there, that would take them in for anight's lodging, and feed them,
         and that's the way they did eat. well they went over to Pullman and Pullman
         wouldn't take 'em in either for awhile. But Pullman and their main hotel over
         there, Washington Hotel, admitted the Negro to the hotel before they did over
         hare at the Moscow Hotel. Now at that time there was only the Moscow Hotel
         in question, because it was the big hotel here, the only building that called
         itself ahotel. Anything else would be boarding houses or lodging houses,
         but there were no other hhoott-eoliso aa+t- fpi^r.sft. IT can remember the time when
         that
         was the only hotel. And alot of people thought that was right: "Why the
         idea of a Negro thinking he could go there'" And there were just lots and
         lots of people wouldn't think of letting a Negro sleep in their house.
         
         Sm: But evidently there were some people who did because they got places to stay.
         
         WC: Oh yes, there were some who did. They were divided. Now the people on
         they would have wanted to see a Negro get justice-I think. But we had the
         South Methodist Church and the North Methodist. And when Iwas alittle girl,
         I said, "Why is it the M. E. Church South is up here on the north end of the
         Ridge?'.' And Icould ask that, oh nobody—"What do you care! "—nobody paid
         attention to me among the younger people of course, and the older people
         didn't want to talk about it, I'm sure that was thereason they turned me off.
         But I did ask that because it was a question to me. But my question wasn't
         on Negro subjects, it was on why was the South Methodist Church on the north
         end of the Ridge, and why was the North Methodist Church down on the south end
         of the Ridge? Two Methodist Churches, and the people that went to 'em. Now
         here and there was afamily that'd always go to the other end of the Ridge to
         go to church because it was the right kind of achurch. Well finally, I
         suppose it was Mrs. Roberts that told me—I wouldn't say so, but I think so—
         that, well, the people on the south end of the Ridge were all Northerners, so
         they had aNorth Methodist Church. And on the upper end of the Ridge, there
         were quite afew people that had come from the South or Southern sympathizers,
         or from Kansas where they had Southern sympathizers, so they were Southern
         sympathizers, and they named it the South Methodist Church. But they brought
         it along with them from the East where they'd come from because they were all
         from the East. Now this was not completely true, because the lines weren't
         that clearly defined. There were people that went to the church because it
         happened to be the church where they were set up. And they realized that they
         didn't have any Negroes out here so they had no Negro problem. But was the
         reason that it was separated in the first place, it was the North and South
         Methodist Church. And so I found out.
         
         SAM: To what extend do you think that the differences between northern and
         southern parts of the country did play apart in the lives of the people on
         the Ridge?
         
         WC: Oh, it played apart, not abig part. They talked, well it was understood
         that this fellow, they say that he fought in the Confederate Army, they'd say.
         Well he was an old Confederate soldier. Well, they nodded their head and
         looked around; they didn't shun him but didn't trust him completely either.
         There was that feeling, that feeling of distrust about the Confederates.
         
         SAM: On the part of the Northerners...
         
         WC On the part of the Northerners, of course, and vice-versa, idon't know
         about that, Ididn't happen to be around enough Southern people to hear them
         say. And there was aNegro came to town once. Idon't mention this and don't
         tell it, and Iwouldn't write down anything about it, because Ido not kfD w
         at this late date Idon't know what the real facts were. And !am just indebted
         to the people who were around me for-and they had only hearsay. Those were
         People that weren't in town. This happened in Troy, and of course we lived
         out in the country, and Iheard scraps of conversation, and Iheard 
         because Ilistened. And this man, aNegro, came to town. Idon't know what
         there for. But just acommon, poor workingman. And Iwas very, very young.
         Oh Iwas down in the lower grades, eight or nine at the most was what Iwas,
         oountry, but Idon't remember when she came, so she'd come before Iever went
         to school or anything. Mrs. Clemm-she kept house for her brother in the
         'em, they were drinkers and so on-Bob and .alter, well Ilearned to know
         real well, and he reformed his drinking, and he has afamily of
         seven children !think, and they are strung out over American Ridge, and of
         course they wouldn't know anything about their father's dealings, and all
         these things happened before Walter ever had the family. But Ilearned to
         know Walter Clemm real wweelnl,, aanndd lliikbe hmi»m, khe was alikeable fellow. And
         he
         had this brother Bob, who was not so likeable, I'm told and I never knew him.
         I knew him when I saw him. And he had a wife-Walter waiter wasn't married at that
         time, he was much, much younger-he had awife and adaughter. And the daughter
         was just practically ababy when this happened. But there was acafe in town,
         and it was run by they said a Southerner. And of course he was a Southerner
         that knew Negroes and had been around them and wasn't one that hated the Negro,
         not by any means. And he let him eat at his cafe. So he ate at this man's
         cafe, and Idon't know what about his lodging. There was aquestion about
         that. Well he and this Bob Clemm got into afight one night, drunken fight,
         brawl, in the cafe, and the Negro was killed. Now wait a minute!
         
         SAM: I've heard that a Negro was killed in Troy.
         
         WC: Now wait aminute. Was the Negro killed or Bob Clemm was killed, Ithink.
         Maybe they were both killed. Ithink Bob Clemm died that way. So then they
         were going to hang the Negro, that was the talk. "Lynch him. Lynch him!"
         And there was that talk was all around. And Iremember I've heard since that
         there were cool heads that stopped alynching party. But maybe they both
         died. But Iremember them saying, well it was good riddance to bad rubbish
         if the Negro got killed, everybody was in favor of getting him killed. And
         he hadn't done athing, Iheard that, hadn't done athing wrong. Only go
         down there-I suppose he was carousing, same as Clemm was. You see Idon't
         know the particulars of that, and so Ican't tell them at all. But Ido
         know that there was this terrible fight between Bob Clemm and the Negro. Now
         whether they were both killed or one was killed and the other wasn't-But
         Ithink Bob Clemm was killed, because oh everybody sympathized so with his
         widow. And I'm not so sure she was so deserving of sympathy, but there was
         a lot of sympathy expended on her.
         
         SAM: And you don't have any idea what eventually happened to that Negro, whether
         he was himself died or tried? He wasn't lynched, though.
         
         WC: No, he wasn't lynched, and I'm sure he wasn't tried. I'm pretty sure he
         either was killed or died from the effects of it. I'm pretty sure of that.
         99
         You know Ihaven't thought of that for many years, along time. I'll tell you,
         my husband's father could have told you all about it, because oh m^ he was
         incensed by it, and by the treatment of the Negro, but he'd come from Sweden
         and HATED SLAVERY! And my father-in-law was certainly no moderate about
         anything.
         
         SAM: Why did he hate slavery so much?
         
         WC: Because he didn't believe in it! It was part of his religious upbringing
         too.
         
         SAM: In Sweden?
         
         WC: Yes. He had that upbringing, Iknow that, and so of course it was partly
         that. Oh no, he hated that, and (chuckles). Iremember him saying one
         time-I shouldn't be telling this-but he considered himself an authority on
         religion and politics, and he brooked no interference from his family. And
         of course Ididn't know any better than to take astand against him a time
         or two, but Ilearned to keep still and just let him go and let him believe
         what he wanted to believe. But Ido remember him saying, well the Negroes
         farther because the Bible prophecy was that. And Isaid,
         "I didn't know that you had the Mormon idea. That's the Mormon idea too."
         That was only hearsay with me; Ididn't know that the Mormons had it. I
         hadn't studied Mormonism or anything at that time. But they do have apretty
         black image of the Negro in there as far as that's concerned. But then Iread
         the Bible and get something entirely different to my father-in-law. And I
         believe in the Bible, Ihave great faith in it, but then there are large
         parts of it that Iadmit Idon't understand, so that Iwouldn't think of arguing
         with. Iread them and take it into consideration and Iask'em questions,
         "Is that what you believe?", but as far as me starting to argue and say,
         "No, no, no," and all that, Idon't do that, on these people who have inter
         preted it. But of course you know it does say in there that the sons of Ham
         shall be the hewers of wood and the drawers of water in the camps of Shem,
         of course-Shem's and 3apeth, too, as far as that is concerned. And Shem
         of course they say will always make aslave of the Negro. Well of course if
         that were absolutely true, then Shem is no more to blame than anybody elseif
         it's acurse on Shem, he's got to put up with this hewer of wood and drawer
         of water, you know? Now that's aplace to which these people who are arguing
         that donH want to go. The Bible certainly doesn't put Shem to blame for it.
         It was leveled at them, according to the Bible. Now that's quite amystery
         to me. And it's been amystery, alot of other things are mysteries to me.
         Ibelieve that there is that element of absolute truth in them, but that we
         have it, Idon't know about. And Icertainly didn't know if my father-in-law
         had it either. Paul's father lived, of course went on Burnt Ridge, he didn't
         on American Ridge, and most people were beneath his favor of even talking
         with 'em, because he didn't think they knew much, you know. And there were
         alot of ignorant people (chuckles) among the early settler, as far as that
         was concerned, but I'm not so sure they were as ignorant as he thought they
         were. But the Swedes out on Burnt Ridge were very religious, they were all
         brought up religiously. Not Paul's father's way-as Itold ya, he was of a
         reformed-oh my, he would've bounced up and shaken his fist at me if he heard
         me say reformed, but Iconsider that the Friend's Service in Sweden was a
         great reformation, even on top of Luther's. And Luther, by the way, was a
         
         SAM: What kind of effect that had, whether you were from the North and South, on
         the political beliefs of the people?
         
         WC: well it had some. Idon't think that after they got out to American Ridge
         and they had to dig hard for aliving-I think it began to mean less and less
         to them than what it meant when they were back close to the war. You see they
         didn't come out here until well after the Civil War. And yet some of the
         gold from the Pierce mining district-I can't say this for afact, now, but
         somewhere in my notes had alittle in about some of that gold was taken out
         and shipped to the war. And some of it went to the Confederacy. But whether
         it was minted, Ididn't trace that. Idon't remember what that was. Iknow
         Ididn't do the tracing of how much it was or whether it was minted or not.
         Idon't know, because by that time the country was getting so torn up that
         their regular system of minting the money wasn't very well known. But Ido
         know that that was said, that here was this note that actually, even though
         the country wasn't settled up out here, there was some gold going in. Of
         course the California gold was taken, alot of that was taken into the Civil
         War. But 1861 to '63 there-Pierce discovered gold at Orofino in '63. Orofino
         is named by him. Of course "Gold Ifind," or "Ore, gold ore Ifind." Idon't
         know whether Igot that into Blake's (Mavis Lee UtlnV. „nnl nead or not uhen
         he was studying, but Ithink so though, about Orofino. He's so fond of
         Orofino.
         
         SAM: Well listen, did it tend to shape-would you be more likely be Democrat
         if you were from the South and Republican if you were from the North?
         
         WCt Yes, that was said on American Ridge. I've heard the oldtimers say that.
         Well it was mainly the Oemocrats. But that wasn't true on American Ridgethe
         Democrats didn't all gather on the southern end of the Ridge and the
         Northerners, the Republicans, all gather on the-I was going to say the top
         of American Ridge-on the northern end of the Ridge. But actually they were
         nearly all Republican up around Bethel, that was the Northern Methodist-or
         Southern Methodist on the northern end of the Ridge. Iget my norths and
         souths all mixed up here, you'll have to kind of remember that.
         
         SAM: Are you saying that they were really all Republicans in the Northern
         Methodist Church—or the Southern Methodist Church?
         
         W C: No, that's the Southern Methodist.
         
         SAM: Well that seems unusual since you were saying that was the Southern Church.
         
         WC: Yes, yes, Iknow it does. But somebody told me and Ithink it must have
         been Mrs. Roberts. She was mainly the one that was catching alot of those
         things. They were Republicans of course, and they came from the North. They
         were Republicans, but then they didn't belong to the Church either. That is
         Al Roberts didn't, but his brother was aregular, oh my yes, he was ariproaring
         Methodist.
         
         SAM: What do you remember about politics from the Ridge country and around Troy
         when you were young?
         
         WC: Idon't remember very much. It was local politics. Iremember quite a
         little bit about local politics, they were very much interested in local
         politics. And at that time, Moscow, although it was the logical center-you
         see we didn't have an organization whereby we had a central area like Moscow
         in those days, and the politics of the county were spread all over the county.
         And consequently it was not until oh Iwas coming up to high school age
         practically when they began to get more. And it was after the University
         came to Moscow that it became acenter...Now Ihave that timing put out in one
         of my notebooks. Did you get it?
         
         SAM: Idon't remember saying it was the coming of the University that made Moscow.
         
         WC: Oh Iprobably didn't say it, but it's implied. Of course Iby reading my
         notes know that the implication was there. That's what I've said about a
         lot of the things in my—I'd almost have to explain a lot of them.
         
         SAM: Well, that's what we're doing.
         
         WC: Uh-huh. That's it. Iwould understand the implication.
         
         SAM: OK, what is the implication then?
         
         WC: Well naturally when the University came there were more and more of the
         young men and women were coming up to the University and getting ideas, taking
         political science and learning about it, and thinking that they should have
         people that knew alittle bit more. And aboy from our ridge down there,
         American Ridge, George Davidson, he was the first one that Iknew of to
         graduate who lived on American Ridge, southern end. Well his father was a
         Republican, Joe was aRepublican. But he'd come into the country. Idon't
         think Joe Davidson was either Northern or Southern in views, because oh he was
         of Scottish extraction Ibelieve and had come by way of Nova Scotia to this
         country, and had lived in Nova Scotia, and he came here Idon't know about
         his politcal affiliations. Ididn't know the older Davidsons very well;
         knew them, but Inever talked with them about it. But he was avery, good
         friend of Mr. Roberts and I'm quite sure they were Republicans. Well George
         went to school, and Ithink he was the first boy to graduate from college.
         And well my goodness, the farmers all around, including my father, said,
         "Well, it was possible to send your kid off to school and he'd get so much
         education he'd be an educated fool." And that's what George was, he was an
         educated fool. He'd come out there and telling them how to farm, and telling
         them how to do this and how to do that. And oh yes, he knew all about politics
         and everything else. Well Inever heard George talk politics. Inever was
         around. Inever knew George until Iguess after he graduated the University
         and he got to going with somebody that Iliked awful well, and then Isaw
         him afew times, but they weren't talking politics. Iremember that Imet
         them when they were on their way to be married. Fern Carlton, and she was my
         ideal. When Igrew up Iwas going to be like Fern, Iwas going to teach
         school like Fern. And Imet them coming in this rubber-tired buggy, and oh
         George did sit up and he did think he was somebody. Anyway Iremember that
         Iagreed with everybody around the country because he-But Ithought he was too,
         Isort of agreed with George, he was somebody. It sort of made me believe
         that, you know, the way he looked. Most other people didn't. However, I
         liked George afterward.
         
         SAM: Was it going to college that gave him these airs?
         
         WC: Iwouldn't know, but Isuppose so. Inever knew him before. So Isuppose
         so. His brothers didn't go to college, but they went farther than the eighth
         grade. They went to Kendrick and took all that Kendrick had at that time in
         the way of ahigh school. It wasn't afull high school, Idon't think. And
         they were afamily who knew quite alittle mere than just an ordinary rural
         family. They believed in knowing something. But they didn't enter politics
         at any time.
         
         SAM: Talking about local politics, you're saying you remember local politics.
         What kinds of local issues were there?
         
         VC: Oh they didn't have issues and talk issues! Ididn't learn that until I
         got in high school along time afterward, about issues. Ididn't call them
         issues. Ididn't know what they were. But they talked about it-they called
         it "talking politics". They talked about what man did this and what man did
         that, and whether to change the road from the southern end of the county to
         someplace where it* connect alot of places, that seemed to be the idea.
         And well, they would have to contend with some rich farmer who would try to
         get the road over his way, and that wouldn't benefit these smaller settlers.
         But they all sort of tended toward leaning toward the rich one, because he
         could do more for 'em and give 'em more time to the road to make the road, and
         things of that sort. Now those were the things that they were discussing.
         And then of course in the matter of politics, what the men talked about and
         what the women talked about-the women would always say, "Oh the men, let
         go out in the other room, or go out on the porch. They just want to talk
         politics." And they called alot of things politics that had no politics in
         it, as Ican look back and know. But Iliked the men's talk alot better than
         Idid the women. The women talked about the chickens, and what kind of chickens
         they thought were the best, and how many eggs they got from their chickens,
         and how much money they got for their eggs during the winter, and how to
         make butter and all that stuff, and then how to take care of the babies. And
         some of 'em were wise enough to get amagazine that had some late lessons in
         it and they'd discuss them. Well that was their politic—the babies and chickens
         and early gardens and all that.
         
         And when the men met with any of the women, came in, they did stop to
         start talking to them. To my father-he was agardener, and Itell you a
         professional gardener, the best gardener on American Ridge, I'll swear to that.
         He was, and they'd ask him, and he was an authority on it, and still it
         wasn't from book learning. But he was anatural observer. Iwish Ihad his
         eye for observing everything. And of course in the process as he had grown
         up in Michigan, his father before him and his mother, they'd been great
         believers in the stars and the moon and so on. So he planted his potatoes
         in the moon. So they'd come by. "Whatcha doing, Charlie? Mighty cold day
         for you to be planting those potatoes. They won't come up. Planting them in
         the moon, Isuppose?" "Yeah, I'm planting them in the moon," Poppa'd say.
         He had acertain moon to plant 'em in. "Well, they won't come up-I'll
         Plant my potatoes about amonth later and I'll have better potatoes than you."
         "Okay," Grandpa would say, "we'll find out." And my boys will swear to it
         that Grandpa's potatoes were the biggest and the best (laughs), and they were.
         Grandpa always had the garden, and the women would all say that. "Charlie
         will have the best garden, you all know that. So you go home and get the
         garden ready." And they did! They didn't plant in the moon, they planted
         after Charlie. All the good gardeners that wanted to have good gardens tried
         to plant 'em when Poppa did. So when the men got together, they would talk
         to the women, because the women had an awful lot more to do with gardening
         than the men did in most cases. Not in our case-Grandpa did it, and then we
         children had to garden. Oh Ihated it when Iwas a kid, but I did learn it
         and learned it right, and right now and I'd rather garden than do housework.
         So the men talked about that, and they did talk about the kinds of chickens
         that they thought laid the best. And Poppa was always out for hints on
         building chicken houses and things like that. Well now that was their politics,
         and that's what they talked.
         
         SAM: But when the men were by themselves they talked politics.
         
         WC: When the men were by themselves they talked what the women called politics.
         But as Isay their politics included alot of things. Now it did include the
         kind of wheat-were they going to change to this new kind of wheat? Well
         now they understood that up at the University they were trying to create
         another kind of wheat. Well that was their job, some man would explain to
         the farmers that didn't know-because alot of the farmers didn't know, some
         of the more learned ones would say that that was their research and that was
         right, that they were searching it out. But that that was how we got the
         University~as Brigham, who was one of the main ones, acounty commissioner
         from Genesee, and Mitchum, from Kendrick, that got the University, and largely
         getting it through the Morrill Act, which created the agricultural school at
         the University. That is also the reason why Boise has not been able to cart
         the University away from Moscow to Boise as they've tried to do many times
         and thought they'd do. They thought they'd steal the Law Department. Ttey
         finally did get Boise College and then kept on adding more colleges until
         practically they had a university down there. But they couldn't kill the
         University of Idaho because they had the Morrill Act up here, and so many
         things had been created through the Morrill Act at the University. So that
         in 1909, when Teddy Roosevelt came here to speak in front of the University,
         he spoke on apile of sacks of wheat that were around in front of Morrill Hall.
         
         SAM: What did the Morrill Act specify?
         
         W C: Well, Morrill was an ag man and he left it to an ag college for the purposes
         of research and developing the country around where it was built. And here
         was a fertile field up here in the Palouse country, which is of course one of
         the fertile spots of Idaho,but it isn't so big. It isn't anywhere near as
         big as South Idaho, but of course at that time South Idaho was a waste of
         desert land. And the first crop of people that were to come in and get it
         started and dig the ditches—after awhile, after everybody had gone broke and
         gotten out of there because their windmills wouldn't work, they didn't have
         enough wind to run 'em to get water into their ditches, and they didn't know
         enough about irrigation. And these people up here were speculating if those
         fellows ever get irrigation down there—Well, there were two schools of thought
         as I remember: some people would say, "Ehhhh, they'll never be able to get
         the water turned on to the land down there in that desert to make anything
         grow." And then the others: "Oh, you'll just be surprised. That'll make
         that a fertile garden and someday it will be." "Well, why don't you go down
         there and take a claim then? You can get it almost for nothing." Well they
         didn't want to be among those first ones. They felt awful sorry for those
         people that were in there building it up. And of course they did leave and
         there were well-improved farms, people that had spent a lot of money down
         there when they left. Well you see, that's what they did. Oh, I haven't read
         about the Morrill Act for a long time. I used to know a lot more than I do
         now.
         
         SAM: Oh that's OK. That makes me wonder, do you think that the farmers that
         did come to this country, came and stayed partly because it was more like the
         old kind of farming that they knew how to do? Compared to this irrigated new
         fangled kind of farming?
         
         W C: Oh yes, that's what settled this country, sure. They didn't want to come
         there. It took a lot of legislation, there were men that worked on that.
         Finally the Carey Act went through, and they began settling southern Idaho
         and Wyoming and sections of Montana. And they got in under the Carey Act.
         Now I'm not conversant enough with the Carey Act to start talking to you
         about it, but at any rate it assisted with getting irrigation into the country,
         and getting the streams ready and prepared for it. Of course they had to get
         down below the source of supply naturally to get the water directed in that
         direction, and then big irrigation ditches made. And they certainly did dig
         'em in those days, and there was work for engineers, plenty of work for that.
         Some of these long-sighted men were saying, "With this University here, the
         boys can get trained, we'll get engineers, we have to have surveyors, and
         this land going to have to be surveyed, and the irrigation ditches will have
         to be taken care of. The plants will have to be run," and all th.t/of'thing.
         And these men were talking about that-what's going to happen to the country?
         
         SAM: The local people?
         
         W C: Local people. I listened to that.
         
         SAM: What's going to happen to the country around here?
         
         WC: Sure, and how's it going to work. Oh yes, and that's what they're going
         to do down there.
         
         SAM: They weren't thinking about irrigation for up here, were they?
         W C: Oh, no, no. No, no, no. Although—
         
         SAM: what did they think would happen to the country around here?
         
         WC: They didn't know, but they speculated. Some thought this was going to be
         awonderful country, it just had to have more development-and it did. And
         then of course marketing was aproblem. Lee Carlton was aman, he had afruit
         dryer down on the lower end of American Ridge, southern end of American Ridge,
         at least they were south of us-we had avantage point right in the middle of
         the Ridge between Troy and Kendrick. Now for instance, my father had worked
         for Martin Thomas who lived on the very end of American Ridge, southern end,
         and had a fertile spot down there. He'd gotten ahomestead and bought out
         two or three other pre-emptions, had come in with alittle money. And a man
         that came with a little of money could make a lot of money. He didn't have
         the source of supply that J. P. Vollmer did in the early days. Later on he
         did-he became the president of the bank down at Kendrick, and he said whether
         the local people were going to be able to borrow money or not. And of course
         Iguess he borrowed on his own, Idon't know about that, Inever heard enough
         to know. But they finally had to get a bank so they'd have the control of
         some money that kept building and building bigger and bigger farms and getting
         more and more money. So he was a very wealthy man. And they talked about
         him and how he was building, the men did, and Iheard all this. Men were the
         ones that were doing the things. They were the ones deciding whether they
         were going to have big farms or little farms. And what in the world were a
         few settings of eggs? What difference did that.make, you know? And Iwas
         never interested in that. And the men didn't talk about things Iwas interested
         in all the time, but sometimes they did. Iliked them to get into Constitutional
         arguments and all that sort of thing.
         
         SAM: Did they?
         
         WC: No, no, nobody did. Oh once in awhile somebody would bring up Constitutional
         law. And they talked about which lawyer was the best. Iremember Supager (sp?)
         was alawyer in Moscow. Farmers ought to have alawyer-a lawyer ought to
         be here so that if farmers had to go to law about anything, he'd be sympathetic.
         Well what man do you think would be the most sympathetic? Well that fella
         didn't know anything. Some fella would have had arun-in with this lawyer or
         that, and they got some erroneous ideas about who that lawyer should be.
         And Iremember that they were very strong for Burton L. French. They hadn't
         looked into Burton L. French's background. I know that, but Iknow it from
         my years of learning afterward. But as Irecall it then, well it was good to
         get Burton in as aCongressman because he'd told them he'd work for them
         and so on. He never worked for anybody but himself, he only worked for
         Burton L. French. He was too narrow minded and too empty minded to know
         very much about what to do. He just went out, he'd graduated the University
         of Idaho, and he had worked his way through school, he was to be admired for
         that. Ihad his younger brother, Carlton French, for ateacher one year,
         and he was an excellent teacher. And Ibelieve he knew more in one minute
         that Burton did in a week.
         
         SAM: Would people realize that Burton French wasn't really doing anything for
         them after he got in and didn't do much?
         
         WC: Oh Ithink alot of people did, and all the Democrats did of course. I
         had my eyes open, and Iwas aDemocrat long before Iever dared say it.
         
         SAM: Did people believe that-what was their idea of what politics was all about?
         
         WC: They didn't know politics! How could they talk real politics? They didn't
         know real politics. But they did talk about personalities alot, who represented
         politics. And once in awhile aman knew more. Now Mr. Roberts, Iloved him-
         and Mrs. Roberts, Iloved them, they were wonderful people-and I'm not
         saying one thing against 'em, and Iwouldn't write down athing against
         Al Roberts for anything in this world. But, like him talking about Frank
         May who had spent all his life collecting mortgages, well he tried to collect
         hunting trophies, and had spent days and days tracking across the wilderness.
         He was in the Selway forest long before any other white men had gone up
         through there. He met and made friends with the Indians. He was one of
         the best ambassadors of good will among people. Al Roberts didn't have any,
         any inhibitions about race. If aNegro had come to his house, he'd have
         taken him in and kept him overnight. He hadn't known many. They didn't
         travel up into Pennsylvania and Ohio, so he hadn't known many Negroes.
         And Inever heard his philosophy about Negroes, except that Iknow his
         style. And I do know that old Joe Wells, he would meet him on the street
         in Troy when he came down there once in a while, and I'll bet he never had
         a heartier handshake than he had from Al Roberts. And he stayed at Joe
         Wells' house up at Deary when he was around with the assessing, and told
         about that—that he'd stayed overnight there, and old Joe Wells and his
         family, how great they were. And they got out their musical intruments—
         I don't know what they played. I don't know that 'cause I didn't know those
         Negroes. Goodness sakes, I was kept in home, I stayed home. And my mother
         was very particular about me and when I went to town I had to stay under
         their supervision very close. And when I got to going with the neighbors,
         well there weren't any Negroes around town there.
         
         SAM: But they played musical instruments and had a good time—
         W C: Had a good time, and sang—
         
         SAM: But you were about to say about Al Roberts' politics, politically.
         
         W C: Yeeaah, he was a Republican, and that's what he knew, and that was Abraham
         Lincoln politics. It was Abraham Lincoln who freed the slaves. Actually,
         actually, they were freed by a lot of Southerners too, many Southerners
         that helped, as far as that was concerned. But then Abraham Lincoln had
         said as a young man that if he ever got a chance to strike a blow at slavery,
         he would. And he did, and he had that, and he actually believed he was
         doing this for the freeing of slaves, and he did go through that. But when
         you know history you know that right along with it you know the Republican
         tariff men were running up the high tariffs to protect their industries
         here at home that didn't amount to very much. And they were doing a lot
         of things. Of course the Southerners didn't now, because they were raising
         cotton and they wanted a good price for their cotton, and they didn't want
         a high tariff on it. And they didn't want to have to have it so that they
         had to pay the Northerners a big price to get their cotton manufactured and
         manufactured here at home. So the Southerners weren't in favor of a high tariff.
         But believe me, the northern Republicans were! And they more or less fooled
         Abraham Lincoln, but you know he hadn't had a chance to have an education and
         he couldn't possibly have known everything. When I first learned that he had
         some weak spots, I thought that was too bad because I'd been taught too Abraham
         Lincoln was ahero. Why I'd heard people say, well, if they were gonna worship
         a man— They believed that every man had to have somebody to worship. I
         heard people talking about that. Oh I listened to all these things and took
         'em in. Idid not believe, Iam not born to be a believer of everything I
         hear. But that was ray good fortune, that is, I consider my good fortune.
         Maybe not, maybe you should believe more.
         
         SAM: But they said if you were going to belive in somebody—
         
         W C: —Somebody to worship, you could just as well worship a man. They were
         more or less athiestic, athiestic till they came to die, or near death.
         
         SAM: And they were talking about Abraham Lincoln as being the man?
         
         WC: Well, Iheard it said—I don't know for sure who said it—that if they
         were going to worship a man in the United States, they were going to worship
         Abraham Lincoln, because he came nearest to being a£od, a man who stood head
         and shoulders above other men. He did make a great president and certainly
         did wonderfully well for his background. And I'm willing to honor him, yes!
         I pay great honor to a man like Abraham Lincoln, who could come out of a
         background like that and do as well as he did and have the lofty ideals that
         he had. But at the same time he was a mere man and he had the faults of a
         man! He had human failings, and they were bad ones, very bad ones, big ones.
         And George Washington was far from being a man to worship. After the
         Revolutionary War, I know that I've heard different ones say, historians
         talking about it, well it appears as though people were in the mood to worship
         a man like Washington afterward. A leader, a great leader at a time like
         that gets a lot more acclaim that what he deserves and probably a great deal
         more than what he wanted. I'm sure Abraham Lincoln didn't ask for it.
         
         SAM: Well do you think Lincoln was the most popular politician on the Ridge?
         Of course he was dead by then.
         
         W C: Oh no, by then he was a dead hero.
         
         SAM: Who were some of the other personalities—you say that they talked personal
         ities—who were some of the others that they talked about?
         
         U C: Well, they talked personalities. When I said they talked personalities I
         was talking about personalities of the time being, among their people. Well,
         was Lafayette Keane agood enough county commissioner to be elected county
         commissioner again? Was Manfred Harland a good county commissioner, good
         enough to be elected again? Or should they get somebody else in? What
         would he favor? And there had been cattlemen's associations, and then some
         people were strong for the law, and other people were wondering about those
         vigilante committees. We weren't very far at that time from the vigilante
         committee days, when people used to get out, and they had a sort of a
         secret committee of vigilantes that, if there was any trouble in the
         neighborhood, the vigilantes got together. And they said they had hangings.
         Iknew a man a little older than I(chuckles). Raymond Harland, and he told
         me that he never did get into it, never did find out, but that his fatherthat
         was Manfred Harland, he was the neighbor on the other side of us—
         belonged to, he said he learned after he got to going to school and one thing
         another, it was a vigilante committee. And he asked his father and his
         father never told him, he just laughed and joked at him, gave him jokes. But
         Raymond says, "He belonged to that," he said, "because Iwent and listened
         one night, they met in our granary." And he said, "And they talked about
         there were some horse thieves in the neighborhood and what should they do
         with them? And they'd caught 'em and they all knew where they were."
         Raymond said he never found out, and he said he and another kid—he told who
         the kid was and I've forgotten who it was. But Ididn't dare put that in my
         notes either.
         
         where they met,
         and they were so afraid they'd make anoise so that their fathers would hear
         'em. But they got by and they listened to this meeting they had under that
         tree, big old tree.
         
         SAM: What did they hear them—
         
         WC: Oh they heard 'em discussing, and they decided they were going to hang that
         man. He didn't know whether they did or not, he didn't know that, but he
         thought that they did, and he thought they hung him there under that tree.
         And he said after that, they, the children-oh they were getting to be pretty
         big kids-called that'the hanging tree." As far as they were concerned that
         was the hanging tree. They'd listened to this meeting. But his father went
         away that night, that next night, but he saw to it that the mother had those
         kids locked in so Raymond didn't get out. So he didn't get to go there, but
         they would have gone and seen whether they had ahanging or not. But he
         was pretty sure. He said everybody was pretty solemn about that. That was
         horse thieves. They caught 'em with the horses. But now I*n't know those
         particulars.
         
         SAM: You say the cattlemen's association. This wasn't cattle country, was it?
         WC, No, Isaid cattlemen's association because Iam very well acquainted with
         Idaho history, .Idaho history, and there were cattlemen's associations-
         
         SAM: They were vigilante committees.
         
         WC: -And vigilante committees were all over the state. And you read an
         Idaho history and you'll find that out.
         
         SAM: I know about it, I mean I've heard of them.
         
         W C: Well I'm sure you would have, in the work that you're doing. If you don't
         believe it, now I was going to say to you that the reason—you know a lot
         of people have said to me, "Why in the world," and they thought I was lazy—
         and I got lazy after I got sick—but why didn't I get all this material put
         into a book? And I did sort of regret it at one time, and then when I see
         some of these people coming out with things that are much less—But I dbn't
         know. As I say I was interested in the human interest part of it, and I
         wasn't so interested in the history part. But if you thing there's not
         Idaho history written, all you need to do is look at one of my bibliographies.
         Why I did research, my goodness sakes, and read on all this history. I've
         got all this—I don't know whether you noticed that or not, on Borah?
         
         SAM: I didn't see that particular—
         
         W C: Oh well, here's all this material on Borah.
         
         SAM: Did you hear anything else about vigilante stuff around—
         W C: Not around the effects of it in this county, no I didn't. But people
         knew that it was, but they were pretty close mouthed about anybody that
         might have belonged. Now Raymond, in talking to me about his father, he
         didn't expect me to go blab that or put it in any book, you know, that even.
         And that was carefully guarded, that secret was carefully guarded, and so as
         Raymond said, "You know they never told anything that you could get ahold of."
         But I know that that man's wife didn't know anything about it. She didn't
         bother about any of his meetings.
         
         SAM: Do you think that it had anything to do with what you mentioned—one of
         the quotes in the newspaper articles that was in your manuscript—that the
         people in the country were holding the land for their friends? I know that
         a lot of the vigilante stuff in some areas had to do with land possession.
         Who would be allowed to take the land? If you were holding the land you
         wanted somebody to have it, not just anybody that came along. Do you think
         that that was at all afactor, it was involved at all? V» jU8t curious.
         Idon't know if that would have anything to do with vigilantes or not.
         
         WC: No, it didn't have anything to do with vigilantes, but in some cases I
         expect it was. For example, you found alot of good land, as Isaid in
         my notes: why were they coming out here? Well they'd heard from these
         Brillharts who'd come ahead. They wrote back to Kansas and told their
         neighbors, "Get up" so-and-so and so-and-so-well Al Roberts happened to be
         one of them-"and come on out, the land is fertile here, and it's here for
         the taking. But you have to get here before the others do, because there's
         going to be alot of people come in." And they knew first come first served.
         Now of course there were squatters, so they might go over abuild ashack
         or something, and let one of their older kids live in it or something of
         that sort to fool people, to indicate that they had that land too for a
         little while, to stall off people coming in and taking it. X've heard of
         them doing that, but Idon't know of anybody who did it really.
         
         SAM: It doesn't really matter to me, the names or anything. I'm just curious
         about the kind of tactics that people would use. Do you think that they would
         try to actively discourage people who came out looking and say, "Oh, all
         the land is taken "?
         WC Ohh yes, if they didn't want them there they did, you bet they did. They
         discouraged them, and they looked on with disfavor people that came in.
         Yes, I'm sure they would do that. I'm very sure that they did that.
         
         SAM: Would you say though that many of the people that came in were unknown
         to everybody when they came in, and yet came in and established themselves
         and were wholly accepted? Or do you think that most of the people that came
         out were in some way related to people that were already there?
         
         WC: Yes, they had some kind of an inkling here was aplace for 'em to go.
         And it was only later when oh real estate companies began to send out men,
         locators, they called 'em. Yes, and advertised that they'd locate you on a
         claim if you came there; then people came out, and strays would go in and
         try to get located. And if they didn't suit the neighborhood they didn't
         have anice time. That's true of all pioneer communities, Ithink. But
         Idon't know of anybody being run out and there were all kinds of people
         that come in. Now for instance Frank May came in from Oregon, and Idon't
         think he had any people here, but he did know some people that lived out
         close to Moscow. Well, they said, "There's land unclaimed down there." Yes
         they'd get some of these agents, oh you know how those land sharks are: they
         were anxious to make money without doing anything, and they would go out
         and locate you on some land that's left, and they'd keep maps of the country.
         
         SAM: Would you say though that most of the people that came out were related to
         somebody who was already there, or a friend?
         WC« Most of them were, on American Ridge were, yes. But they came out with a
         whole bunch of them, came together. Now they might have paid some locator,
         they might have paid some real estate man to give them an idea or maybe a
         n»P of aregion, but they didn't have them go and locate them. And then they
         went out and if it was surveyed land they'd get maps from the land office,
         and it was surveyed up in here at that time. Now that was the reason given
         for the Russians who camped here at that time. They didn't stay here because
         they didn't want-they were told, they didn't drive them out, but that they
         would be squatters on the property because it was not surveyed. And so
         when they went to the land office to try to find out, they couldn't get clear
         title. They knew that because it was not surveyed. But you could squat
         on it and then take your chances on being able to get it when it came time,
         when it was surveyed.
         
         SAM: Do you know at what point roughly the American Ridno y 'xy ufie amencan Ridge
         country was closed
         because it was all homesteaded, and aftpr fhaf ,• + ' and atter that xt was only sold—if
         a person
         wanted to buy, he'd be buying from a homesteader? Do you know how quickly
         all the homestead land was actually taken there?
         
         U C: Oh I don't know how fast it was taken. I was born in 1896 and I couldn't
         be expected to know very much by 1900, could I? (Laughs.) Not about the
         land. I didn't give a hoot about that.
         
         SAM: Well Isuppose that by the time you get to people were buying land, then
         the land that was available was probably all taken up.
         
         W C: Well there was no more land available for homesteads. And my fatherthere
         was no land available for a homestead for him. And he bought that
         place, and oh, let's see, he bought the 40 acres from Mr. Roberts. (Oh
         Igot so interested in this stuff the other night that Istayed up reading
         it till four o'clock. I got reanimated. I told Mavis. I said, "I'm
         terriblY interested in this stuff," and regardless of my eyes. Of course
         Ihad to stop two or three times to bathe my eyes, it wasn't steady reading.
         And Ilooked at the clock and it was four o'clock. Why I haven't done that
         since I was in high school studying, absolutely.) And I found that about
         Poppa in there, about him buying that 40 acres off of Al Roberts' homestead.
         And then Isaid-of course Ididn't make myself particularly popular in my
         family by saying it's poetic justice. Because Mr. Roberts had out of the
         kindness of his heart sold off 40 acres of that land to pay the debts for
         men who had gone bankrupt and for whom he had co-signed their notes at the
         banks. And then of course they couldn't pay, and Al Roberts had to pay be
         cause he was the co-signer. And the only way he could raise money was to
         sell some of his homestead, and he sold 40 acres.
         
         SAM: When was this about?
         
         WC: Oh well it's in here, what year it is, but Iknow what time it was aboutit
         was right close to the beginning of the century. It's a way back there.
         But I don't carry all those dates in my mind.
         
         SAM: No. Do you know how your husband became aDemocrat?
         
         WC. Oh his parents were Democrats, very liberal. His father in fact was con
         sidered asocialist, was asocialist, but down here where they didn't have
         asocialist party, why they acted as Democrats. Ithink my husband waswell,
         he had leanings toward that line. They were pretty strong that way.
         They were known in the old country as liberals. Yes, he was always a
         Democrat, he never was anything else. He didn't come up in aneighborhood
         where they were Republican or where they learned-Like my friends were
         Republicans, but however on the other side of us lived Manfred Harland, and
         Manfred Harland was aDemocrat. And Ididn't have to get very old to know
         that Manfred Harland™ for heaven sake, don't ever let this get into my
         book, in to any notes-there're descendents of those people living-but
         it didn't take me forever to learn that Manfred Harland was the smarter of
         the two men. He was more of aleader, and that what he said about the
         qualities of the men that they were putting in as county commissioners,
         especially, who had to do with the doings in the county. They decided a
         lot of things. Idon't know what all they did do, but they had to go and
         write out different trails for roads, they saw to it. And they helped
         set the taxes, what the taxes were going to be. They found where the schools
         were going to be, and if the school was big enough or too big, they had to
         have them close enough together that the children didn't have to walk too
         far to get to school. And they had to take care of the poor in the county,
         they had to look out for them. Oh they were lots of things that had to be
         done, and they needed men to do them. So some of the talk that went on
         around the porch when Iwas curled around the post of the Robert's place
         (chucklesJ-i'd be curled around that post, and Mr. Roberts used to wind
         up by striking out with aglove or ahandkerchief or anewspaper at me and
         saying, "What do you think about it, Willa?" And Ialways had an answer.
         I learned that that was asmart thing to do. And Ialso learned how to tone
         my answers, Iwasn't to be aflip, I'd have gotten spanked if Ihad been
         flippant, well it never occured to me to be that way.
         
         SAM: Do you remember what kind of answers you might give?
         
         WC, No, Idon't remember the answers. But Iknow they said Ialways answered..
         And Ilived to learn that by being careful and by knowing what Iwas talking
         about that Igained the respect of people around me.
         
         SAM: Well did he have pretty strong ideas then, Mr. Harland, about the difference
         between the good politicans and the bad ones?
         
         W C: Did Mr. Harland?
         
         SAM: Yeah. Did he have strong ideas?
         
         WC: You bet he had strong ideas. He didn't always air them completely.
         He kept the neighborhood in pretty good spirit. And Itold about the
         political speeches, didn't I?
         
         SAM: In your book. Do you remember any of those specific tmo*n / u.iub specific, I
         mean a guy coming
         out and speaking?
         
         WC: Oh goodness yes, Ishould say. Iwent to 'em. The women were invited
         out of course, but no women went except Ada Harland, who was ten years older
         than I, and she didn't want to be the only gin there so she'd get me to
         90, and Iwas delighted to 30. And of course if Ada hadn't been going I
         wouldn't have gotten to've gone alone. And Poppa thought it was kind of
         funny because Iwould tell at home, 1remembered much better than Poppa
         what was said, and he'd ask me if Iremembered what so-and-so said. I
         remember Merriweather Lewis, M. H. Lewis. Of course the Republicans were
         more favored by Poppa and Mr. Roberts, and it was easier for me to get to
         go. But Iwent to the Democrats too when they came. Iwasn't old enough,
         when Iwent to any of those Iwas not old enough to discern the differences
         or to be critical of the differences. But Ido remember that Merriweather
         Lewis. He was running for state representative, and they atayed all night
         at Mr. Roberts', Mrs. Roberts wasn't home. And of course he took in all
         Republicans, they all stayed with him, they made beds for 'em at Mr. Roberts'.
         And they went down there, but he came up and asked my mother to be sure—
         they were just across the road—that she'd give them breakfast, supper and
         breakfast, and accordingly they did, they were there for that. And of
         course they complimented her on everything, including my baby sister. Oh
         I don't know, she wasn't walking, and she was a great big heavy baby. And
         she became a very good looking young woman, far better looking than I; but
         nevertheless, she was a homely little dickens at that time. And so he
         braqqed on her» and Isaw Momma smiling and taking it all in, and Igot
         close to her and pulled her dress, you know, I just kept pulling her dress.
         Now I wasn't very tall then, because I kept pulling at her dress, and then
         I got around, and then I looked up at her and frowned, and she told me oh
         to go on and do something, she didn't want me there. She ignored what I
         was trying to do for her. And I remember this was after they'd eaten break
         fast that he was standing there dishing out this flattery. I remember that
         she got into the syrup pitcher and put syrup on. I suppose that we'd had
         hotcakes for breakfast, Idon't remember what we had for breakfast, but
         it sounds about to me as if we'd had hotcakes. And she had syrup all over
         her and she was dirty, and she just looked awful. Momma said, "Oh my goodness,
         what in the world have you been into?" And then she said to me, "Can't
         you clean the baby's face off?" Well of course I'm almost nine years older
         than she was. So I was between nine and ten, I wasn't so little. I knew
         enough to try and hide from him that Iwas trying to attract my mother's
         attention. And Idid, Itook her and got away from there. Iwas glad to
         get her away, wash her face and she bawled like a fright. I remember that
         now when I think of it, I remember her crying so hard. Of course I don't
         suppose Iwas very clever about doing it either. But anyway she got down
         and Idon't believe she walked, Ithink she crawled back to my mother. Oh
         Mr. Lewis was telling her that they would have so many things, they were gonna
         work for the farmers, and envisioned better homes and all this sort of thing.
         And Ialready knew that Ford Robbins could build telephones; he came from
         Chicago and Iwas all in favor of waiting on Ford and his cohorts.
         
         SAM: —To do it for you.
         W C: Yes.
         
         SAM: So in other words this guy, he was flattering—
         
         WC: Yes, and he was false, and Iknew it. Isaid, "I wouldn't vote for that
         man. Iwouldn't vote for that man, he's no good." Poppa said, "Why not?
         What makes you say that?" That was after Poppa got in. And Itold him what
         she did. And he looked at, and Isaid, "Momma took it all in." And Isaid,
         "She promised him she'd vote for him." "Oh," she said, "I didn't either."
         My mother was kind of ashamed of it afterward too, because Poppa sided with
         me, he knew Iwas right. He said, "I don't believe in these guys that go
         around in politics, Idon't believe -em at all." But Ido remember that
         this fella that was with him-can't remember his name now but Idid know him,
         and Poppa knew him. And he said, oh he couldn't expect anything out of him.
         He said, "He's just abag of wind like his old dad was." But Ican't remember
         his name. But anyway Iremember from their spesch-I don't remember much from
         their speeches.
         
         SAM: Do you think that in office that some of them did indeed try very hard to
         do a good job and—
         
         WC: Some did. Some did. But I'll swear to ya that this Merriweather Lewis
         who was some relation to Lewis and Clark, that Lewis, who was also Merriweather,
         he was some relation to him-and I'm sure from my own childish observations
         that that Merriweather Lewis didn't amount to anything. Why anybody that'd
         come around, stand around trying to get awoman's vote, bidding for it, why
         Idon't think anything more of him than Ido of Nixon that's handing out
         the dollars for a vote. Flattery, the same thing.
         
         SAM: OK, there's one more thing about pontic's that I'm wondering about, and
         that is how do you remember the differences between Republicans and Democrats
         as far as views?
         
         WC: There was no difference! There was no difference as far as that ridge was
         concerned. They were all concerned about the kind of wheat they were harvest
         ing, whether it was going to rain at the right time, whether they'd have a
         3une rain or not, and what breed of chickens was the best, and how were the
         horses. And Poppa was an authority on that, because he didn't have abig
         operation, he had only a small farm, never did get a big one. He had 40
         acres to begin with. Well it wasn't very long until they had 80, and he
         never did get more than-he finally Ithink worked it up to 160 by including
         some canyon land that he had for pasture for cows. And he got the best kind
         of cow that'd hang on the pasture land. They were Ayrshire, and when he
         got started in them he got full-bloods. And they did hang on the canyon side,
         and they were very good, they were dual purpose cattle. They were good for
         beef and good for milking, but they would have been abetter beef cow, I
         guess. So he got them, and he didn't have bull-blood horses or thoroughbred
         horses, but as near as he could. He had agood mare, Idon't know, Ibelieve
         he said she was seven-eighths Percheron, and then he went to aPercheron
         stallion and took her, and he bred them up. And he then got another mare
         some way, he bought one that was also agood one. And never had many horses,
         but about every other year he sold ateam. He got the colts, wonderful
         colts and mated them in ateam and broke them to drive, and he had ateam
         to sell. Full-blood cows, he got nothing but Ayrshires. He had full-blood
         hogs. Everything he had was good, good stock. He had to pay out for it in
         the first place, and we had to do without alot of things. My goodness, I
         sure did without in the way of decent clothing and one thing another-as long
         as we were covered and not too much patched and clean and had shoes to wear
         on our feet. I don't think he thought so much about anything except that
         things must be kept up right, the farm must be right and now that. But
         now not near all the people were like that. And Mr. Roberts, as he said,
         "Frank May's never had any fun in his life, and Ihave nothing but fun."
         Well he didn't care much, they still lived in that old house, and Mrs. Roberts
         lived all her life expecting anew house. And then when the girls—they
         married very poor, and they didn't have maney to help them get ahouse, it
         was bad enough to get a house for themselves. But they finally decided that
         they had to tear down the old house and build asmall cottage for poppa and
         momma, and they'd all go together, and they were all going to build. Put
         the crops in this year—of course it didn't cost as much then to build a
         house as it does now-and they were going to build ahouse. And you know
         uie all started in harping "Don't," because this little old brown house stands
         for so much. Why Ithought it would be alandmark we just couldn't destroy.
         Iadded my voice to the others. It's gone now, but she lived in that as long
         as she lived, and then they used it afterwards too.
         
         SAM: Let me ask that alittle differently then. When Mr. Harland and Al Roberts
         got talking politics and your father got talking politics, did they disagree
         with each other very much because they were one Democrat and one Republican?
         
         WC: Not agreat deal. They shut up when it came to that, you know. Not a
         great deal, because they were neighbors and they remained good neighbors until
         the end. And they didn't fight each other very much. At home there were
         things said. "Oh Al, you know Al. You know Al," he's advocating this guy
         or that guy, somebody in Congress that they'd heard about. Iwouldn't know
         what those issues were all about now, because Ican't remember them.
         
         SAM: At the Harland's house?
         
         WC: At the Harland's, yes. Iwas given free entrance to all these homes. As
         I've told you many time, Iam aproduct of American Ridge. They all contributed
         to my education and to me. They might get mad at the other kids, and I've
         heard -em say that so-and-so would never be welcome in their house again.
         Of course that usually wasn't, that'd pass after alittle while. But Iwas
         never barred from anyone's house, never.
         
         SAM: What do you remember being said about the IWW on the ridge?
         
         WC: Oh, there wasn't much sympathy for the IWW's. They called them "I won't
         work." They did not understand industrial organization. They did not under
         stand unionization. And Ididn't learn about unions and unionization until
         Iwas married. Then my husband knew that thoroughly, and of course he and
         his father and his father's family, they understood that. But then Paul's
         father had been acarpenter and belonged to acarpenter's union, and they
         knew unions from the first time, and he'd come from Minneapolis knowing.
         He was right in at the outset when unions were organized in this country, and
         knew they had to be organized. So Iheard plenty of it then.
         
         SAM: What was his attitude?
         
         WC: Oh my goodness, he was in favor of them of course.
         
         SAM: So he believedin what the IWW's were trying to do?
         
         WC: The IWW's were trying to put across something which had been forced upon
         them by the conditions that they had met. Working conditions and things of
         that sort were terrible, wages were kept down, and they wanted what the unions'd
         call scab labor. They'd take scab labor because they would work cheaper than
         these people, and could work cheaper because their homes were there and one
         thing another. And the workmen couldn't make aliving at the wages they'd
         give them. So they were in favor of unions, my goodness yes, Ishould say.
         
         SAM: Would you say this was generally aSwedish attitude? 
         W C: No, I wouldn't say that.
         
         SAM: —Just occasionally, certain people?
         
         W C: It was a workmen's attitude. A lot of the Burnt Ridgers had the same attitude
         had
         that the American Ridgers/about the IWW's. They were in comfortable homes
         down there, and they could make aliving, and they didn't believe in paying
         high wages to laborers. And itinerant laborers, they said, "They'll come
         through and pretty soon they'll run us out of the home." Well I'll tell ya,
         it got to be about like that in some respects. If the farmer wasn't very
         good and he hired a man that was frugal, and he had to pay the wages of the
         time. That man saved his wages, pretty soon he could buy the farm from the
         farmer. That happened in some cases. Not on Burnt Ridge, not among those
         thrifty people, not among the Swedes. Swedes aren't like that, they work.
         That was a£ood neighborhood. The Swedes on Burnt Ridge, that was a fine
         neighborhood. I have nothing but the greatest respect for all those old
         Swedes. I liked 'em. And I fitted into their community when I married and
         went to Burnt Ridge to live, I became a Swede like all the rest of the Swedes.
         And they accepted me just as fully as Iaccepted them. Do yet! They tell
         me that, the younger ones. Usually when one of the young ones married some
         body, they would prefer a Swede coming into the neighborhood. But that didn't
         make abit of difference with me. Iwas accepted I've been accepted all my
         life. I've never done anything much, nor anything like that. I don't boast
         of anything. But Iam very happy to say that Iwas always accepted. I've
         never been, you know, had cause to worry because Iwasn't being accepted—
         
         ...Bad luck followed us around. Talk about bad luck-I didn't think it was
         bad luck. Ithought it was the natural result of lots of things. Ihated
         it and was sorry for it, but I've never berated anybody for our fires. But
         at Kooskia Idid think it was because of trouble that my husband had had
         with two or three men, and Ithought that it was his fault that he had
         encouraged one man to be-He was aregular, well he was abad actor. He had
         him and even took him back to work after he knew that he'd cheated and every
         thing else. And he didn't like him and thought he was acheat, he said that
         don't know what it was he did-well, I'm not going to go into it, Ido remember
         what it was-but Idon't know whose fault it was either. But he was mean and
         he'd just do anything in the world, and he told about some of the meanest
         things he'd done to other people. Oh Ihated to have him around, and there
         wasn't any love lost between him and me. And we all got typhoid fever and
         couldn't imagine why. And there was atainted spring on the place and an
         old tainted cistern, but the cistern was locked so that the children never
         helow the barn. And of course that could have been typhoid, we knew. But
         Paul Dr. got it first, and Ithought he'd gotten it someplace where he was
         swimming. As Isaid this was adry summer, we were expecting typhoid, even
         the doctor was expecting some typhoid someplace, but we never thought about
         it being us. And gone over home to help my
         father get ready to/on a triph Eastb,, aannad sseeee ttoo iitt fthh*aft khe got off
         on a trip
         to his folks back in the East, and Iwent on aTuesday, and then Iwent back
         Friday. yes, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, yes, that what it was, Istayed
         that long and got back to find Paul Jr. sick And nf a ^r. sick. And of course he hadn't
         had
         the care that he ought to sick to think that he
         hadn't. Well, Paul said, he was alot better- had Better, had him get up and go to
         th
         neighbor's to take a message over there to one of them. I said, "How did
         he go?" "Well he went horseback." Well I said, "He's been sick, and his
         stomach bothering him. Don't you know better than that? I'll never go and
         leave him with you again!" And that was the way I felt that minute. And
         he came home and he said, "Oh my," he said, "I almost fell off of the horse,"
         and he was as white as a sheet. That was the beginning of the real sickness.
         If he'd had care in the first place and had gotten to adoctor, maybe it
         wouldn't have happened...
         
         Well the upshot of it was we all got it, and the doctor sent for this
         vaccine and didn't get it in time. Well the baby came down with it right
         away, but he'd played with Paul Jr. We didn't know it was that. And so
         he would run, Bruce, he'd run and play, oh he was a fast one to learn. He
         was only eight months old but he could walk around by chair anywhere. And
         he'd go to where Paul Jr. was lying on the daybed that we had, Ihad made a
         bed for him out in the living room, and pulled the shades down and made it
         cool in there for him. Of course we had no idea it was typhoid fever. I
         thought that he had had this stomach trouble and got it made worse by galloping
         on that horse, because Iknew he couldn't be trusted not to make the horse go
         pretty fast. But the baby got sick. By that time the doctor said, "I'm
         going to take a test. I've got to take the test." He said, "I think he's
         got typhoid, para-typhoid." Well that was terrible. He said, "I've sent
         for this vaccine—"
         
         The kids and Iall came down with it, we all had it, the rest of us.
         And Paul Jr. got over it first, got up. And that was the winter we moved into
         Kooskia, so I'd have them in town so they'd go to school down there. And the
         doctor saidl wouldn't be able to walk for ayear, wouldn't be able to do my
         own work, and Isaid, "Oh, just wait till Iget out of bed. It'll go fast with
         the kids to take care of." But he did have abottle, that was just coming
         into use at that time, and he heard about it, and he thought, "I'll get a
         bottle of that, because every year Ihave acase or two of typhoid, and this
         dry year I'll have some this year." And he got that in, and if he kept it
         on ice or in the freezer he could keep it for along time, he knew that.
         But six months was the limit, and then you'd be out the |35-it cost $35 an
         ounce. Equire something, made from horses anyway, this equire, what in the
         world was it called-well anyway, the vaccine.
         
         Well Igot bad. So when they were watching for the crisis, the woman
         that was there with me, she said, "You have to call the doctor," because I
         was dropping so low. And Iknew this but Iwas too weak to talk, and I
         didn't want to waste anything talking. Iwas going to tell them, "Quit
         worrying about me," Iwas coming through all right. I'd been having adream
         and I'd come out of the dream and Ikna wthat I'd gotten help from my dream.
         Iknew perfectly well Iwas getting help and Iknew the source of the help.
         Don't tell me there isn't help from above. Ihave had that demonstrated several
         times in my life. But Icouldn't tell them. But Iwent to sleep. The crisis
         had happened and Iknew Iwas through it. But Iwent to sleep, sound asleep,
         and when Iwoke up there sat Dr. Woodward, agood old doctor. He sat on
         the side of my bed ^1^, .puffing, cigar smoke just as hard as he could puff
         it. Well Iknew he wouldn't be doing that in my bedroom if it'd been-That's
         the way he escaped infection of course of all these things. And Iknew he
         was excited, I could  I could
         talk, and Isaid, "Hello doctor." "Hello yourself, thank God!" he said.
         "You've come through, haven't you?" He was sitting there expecting me to
         die the next minute.
         Well that was our It was so worried. I was
         so worried about my kids. The living room was along living room in that
         old log house. And they stretched out beds there. And there was Mavis, and
         Keith, and Paul Or. was out there too-he wasn't well enough to be considered
         ed every morning. And theyy ssaaixdo Ii ddiiddnn't-t, *thha^t It was out. I might
         have been
         out amorning or two but Idon't think so. There was never amorning that
         Ididn't-that was what Idid, that was my occupation, waiting to hear the
         knew that if something had happened to one of those children, they'd never
         tell me. No it was a horrible time.
         
         And, what gave us the typhoid fever? Well we thought this and thought
         that and thought this and thought that, and they said, "Well you'll have to
         take your water off and have it treated." So Paul got, the neighbors came in
         and helped him do that, helped him clean out our spring, our wonderful,
         wonderful spring, wonderful water. Did seem like wonderful water, and a
         log cabin over it for cover, but of course there were big cracks between the
         logs—it was never a chinked cabin. 
         it. Everybody said that Paul should have known that, and Iguess we should
         and it was just open, the spring was open on the inside of that log cabin.
         And that's our drinking water. "Well," Paul said, "we keep dipping it out,
         and then we dip close to where it comes in." There's abig run-in, it was
         ahig spring. And we did, we'd take drinking water from there, but of course
         we had cooking water and everything else, and then we'd have water from there
         -xra. It had been painted black, and so far as we knew we didn't have any
         twisted around something. And two big long pieces of this had been hooked on
         to something,
         that when they lifted it out of the water and put it out to examine it and
         see what it was-before they got around to examine it, it had fallen to pieces
         like ashes. And they did save the ashes, then took that up to the University.
         And it was determined to be the falling apart of meat, some kind of meat. So
         that this fellow that worked for us, he frequently came up on the
         ridge yelling and drunk and hollering. He always hollered something insulting
         when he got past the place, insulting towards Paul. Iheard him hollering
         but Inever did listen to see what he said. But Paul had heard him several
         times and said he was cussing. But he used to stop and go into the spring
         whenever he came up to get water for his car, that was an old car that could
         hardly hold together, to get water, because he'd come up that hill. And he'd
         go to the spring. Of course he knew all about where the spring was. And
         he'd come across the woods where he got into the spring and get water. But
         who thought about him doing anything to the spring? Nobody did. But we did
         afterward, and we figured he did, but we never knew it. And Ithink Mavis
         mixed those things up.
         
         SAM: As Iremember now, Iremember Mavis saying he threatened her father, threatened
         to kill him. I remember her saying that.
         
         WC: Well now that was another fellow, but then that fella, he didn't poison the
         spring. That was awhite man really, but he'd been reared by the Indians.
         That's astory that belongs to Idaho County. And it is astory, and Howard
         Wilson is acharacter. And he liked Paul in the first place and followed him
         around like adog. And he came up to the house and Paul always asked him in.
         And Iknew he was afunny one and seme people were afraid of him. Well I'm
         not afraid of anybody, I'm not afraid of anybody unless it's afreak, you
         know. Of course for you to boast that you're not afraid of anybody and then
         meet up with some absolute freak or inhuman person or somebody who is insane,
         you know, that's different. He wasn't any of those things exactly. Of course
         he was freakish, (chuckles) I'll have to admit. Oh he was terribly funny
         he just did do alot of funny things. And then all of asudden he turned
         the other people up there on the hill. But he finally got to thinking that
         Paul was cheating him Iguess or something-I don't know what he thought.
         he turned against him anyway, and he didn't want to have anything to do
         w.th Paul Carlson. And he'd say things to the other neighbors. But he'd
         come by there,but it'd usually be when Paul was away. And Ididn't dare
         not treat him right, because Ifigured that we'd better treat him .
         I wasn't going to go out of 
         would you like a he always wanted acup of coffee, so
         him acup of coffee, and if Ihad anything else to give with it, I'd
         him whatever we had. Iusually had bread, "That's good bread," he'd say,
         "that's good bread. You make good bread my  Miz Carlson, you make good bread."
         liked to hear what he came every once in awhile. And then he
         went up to the neighbors  and he would drink a potful of
         coffee there, because knew exactly, how to handle him, but
         she'd known him all her there all her life, and she'd
         known him all  she knew just how to handle him. And he always
         called her "Millie". Well he guessed he'd have to go up and see Millie
         And Millie didn't appreciate him, but she treated him all right.
         And he always did that. Oh it was over cattle on the hillside that Paul had. He let
         his cattle
         run and the others, they had open range, and all the settlers drove their
         cattle over to that spring range, the hills above the Clearwater River. It
         was over that some way. And he claimed it more or less belonged to him and
         guessed that he ought to collect money for it or something. Inever did
         know exactly why he turned against him, because he seemed to like him so
         awful well in the first place. But Isaid to Paul, "That's your style! You
         do that to 'em. You don't see through people in the first place. And you
         let all your reserves down, and treat them so wonderfully well in the beginning,
         and then when you find they're partly made of clay, like all people are,
         then you tighten toward them and change and they don't like it." But then
         what do you do? You don't change the habits of grown-up people. But that
         was Paul's way.
         
         SAM: So, did he ever—?
         
         WC« Oh Paul was afraid of him but he never did anything. And he knew he had
         Paul scared and that was another bad thing. When people said, "Are you
         afraid, you and the kids?" "No, I'm not afraid of him!" Isaid. "I've
         never seen anybody that was Iwas afraid of," Isaid, "here or any other place.
         I'm not afraid of 'em unless they're absolutely lunatics or something like
         that."
         
         SAM: So eventually he—
         
         WC: Eventually he just let us alone. And he was concerned about the typhoid
         fever. Idon't know, he never asked Paul, but oh he asked the Fitting familythe
         ones that lived above us-how we were. And he would stop and ask whoever
         he saw or the nurse that was there: "How are they? Oh Ihope they get all
         right," he said. "Is Mrs. Carlson gonna get well?" Of course the doctor had
         practically given me up,
         
         SAM: You weren't frightened of his saying that he was going to go gunning? You
         didn't believe it?
         
         WC: Ithought he might for Paul, but Inever was scared for us as afamily.
         There were other things that went on in the community that made me alittle
         I, was afraid of Howard Wilson. No, !wasn't afraid of him.
         wasn't. 
         
         SAM: Are there fires that you remember about in the early days in Troy. I
         they had all the brick buildings.
         
         WC: Yes, there were that several buildings burned, talked about it, but  out i don't
         remember any
         Tire in Troy. Ido remember the one in Kendrick, when Kendrick burned out.
         and then of course some kind of a flap Ihelieve there was one flap you could lift,
         but lf he had gomebody
         he wouldn't let ya lift that flap. My goodness. So they took me when Iwas
         a woman, and Mr. Roberts wasn't but he was an ordinary size
         man. But they put me between seat in this hack, and
         three people always rorip , when somebody was with 'em they'd have three
         Troy hill, and Mrs. Roberts said, "You shouldn't have gone home so early
         Vou want to stay in town all day?" There was always this little bantl
         
         "Do they do that all the time? Don't they get along?" Well no two people ever
         got along better really than Mr. and Mrs. Roberts. But they did have that
         bantering way. Iremember that he did that day. "Do you want to stay in
         town?" "Well," she said, "you know it's hard on the horses when you take
         out of town this early. It's gonna be hard on them to climb the hill."
         And of course the hill was nothing like it is now. You went up all the hill
         and made two or three little crooks and turns in it, and with ateam and
         horses it took along time climb it. So we got up on top of the hill just
         to where it got smoothed out, and "Looky there, Fanny!" Mr. Roberts (chuckles)
         said. Ican just remember it! Iwasn't very old, but Iremember that just
         as well as yesterday, it seems to me anyway. "Looky there Fanny!" he said.
         Look at that. There's afire up there!" And it looked like it was up in
         the sky to me, as far as Iwas concerned it was up in the sky. And she said,
         "Al, that's amirage!" "Oh yes, Iremember we used to have meerages back in
         Canada, didn't we?" He never would call it anything but "meerage" (chuckles).
         "Al, that's amirage!" Well, he said, "Where is it?" He said, "There's
         Hill's store, but it's upside down." And Ilooked and Isaid, "Why everything's
         upside down, isn't it, isn't it, Mr. Roberts? It's all upside down, isn't
         it?" Well, "Yes," Mrs. Roberts said, "That's the way amirage is. It's
         heat and it's Ore." "why," Mr. Roberts says, "Hill's store is burning up!"
         And then he named two or three other places. He said, "That's Kendrick,
         Kendrick is afire!" Oh whup! He took the whip out of the stall for the whip,
         you know, and whipped those horses, and said, "We've got to get home, find
         out about that. My goodness that's awful, I've got to get to Kendrick."
         Idon't know how he went to Kendrick; Iguess he got another horse or rode
         one of his cayuses. But anyway, it was, it was Kendrick burning. And there
         were eight or nine buildings that burned that day. But it was so hot, and
         there it was, you know. And that rock wall that they had in Kendrick-of
         or they talked about it and analysed the thing, that the heat beating against
         that rock wall, you know and reflected it back, and it
         made aspot to reflect that heat and deflect it upward enough that
         
         SAM: you mean you could actually see the buildings upside down,
         
         WC Upside down! They were upside down, and oh !wouldn't have known one
         huilding from another. But Mr. Roberts says, "That's"-not Hill, Hull-"Hull's
         store, burning," he said.
         
         SAM: It was right in the sky?
         over in Montana all the time. Oh yes, I did fnn n yes, I did too, see a mirage once.
         Where
         was that? someplace I saw a mirage, but it was just water, it looked like
         to it. Because it was a lake along way off and got reflected up the sky.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13398</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Carlson_Willa3</previous>
      <next>Carlson_Willa5</next>
      <disp_name>Carlson_Willa4</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
