<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">8/19/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Sister Mary Christina, 1976-08-19, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>0:30:11</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Christina, Sister Mary</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Nun. She helped care for Mary McConnell Borah at the Maryville home.</occupation>
      <birthyear>1899</birthyear>
      <residence>Beaverton (Oregon)</residence>
      <origin>n/a</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mansions"&gt;mansions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#legislators"&gt;legislators&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mentally handicapped"&gt;mentally handicapped&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Oregon"&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Washington"&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#D.C."&gt;D.C.&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Lee Magnuson</interviewer>
      <file_name>13397</file_name>
      <mp3>13398.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13398.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>180</time>
            <title>Moved to Idaho mansion in 1886; privy; kidnapping</title>
            <synopsis>McConnell family moves from marriage to Idaho. They
               moved into Mansion on December 24, 1886. A woman upset
               the "privy in the house." Kidnapping of Mary McConnell
               as a baby in Portland; the kidnapper had lost her own
               baby and thought she was hers.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Dinner with Theodore Roosevelt; Senator Borah</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Borah's first dinner with Theodore Roosevelt at
               the White House. The dress she bought for the occasion.
               She called Senator Borah "Billy". Her personalized
               car. "Little Borah."
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Senator Borah's death; Mrs. Borah's life in Washington D.C. and Idaho</title>
            <synopsis>Senator Borah's death - he slipped getting out of
               the bathtub. Mrs. Borah's survival from parrot
               fever: Senator's prayer for her; her desire for mashed
               potatoes when she recovered. After his death she
               returned to Idaho briefly, and then back to Washington,
               where she visited Idaho servicemen and wrote to their
               families. Her injury in a revolving door, which could
               well have been fatal.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Mrs. Borah in Oregon; Richard Nixon; 100th birthday</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Borah came to Portland to live with her sister,
               and came to Maryville in 1966. In 1968 Richard Nixon
               called her a loudspeaker hookup. Mrs. Borah's hundredth
               birthday. Her wonderful character.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Mrs. Borah worked with mentally ill men</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Borah's ability to handle institutionalized,
               mentally ill men. The Idaho legislature supported her
               in her last years, keeping it secret. Her special
               dishes when sick.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Mrs. Borah's precious possessions</title>
            <synopsis>Some of her precious possessions.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Stories Mary Borah told about her life in Idaho and Washington, D.C. Mary Borah's
         last year. 8-19-76 .5 hr
         Lee Magnuson
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>
Sister Mary Christina, 1976-08-19, Interview - MP3 Recording

Lee Magnuson, Interviewer

Latah County Oral History Collection, University of Idaho Library

Transcription by: Courtney Berge

[Small talk while someone speaks on the telephone]

[Interview starts at 2:05]

SMC: Well, Mr. and Mrs. McConnell came from the east and they met over here
in Oregon. That's Mrs. Borah's parents. They were married in Salem,
Oregon, then they moved to California and Mrs. Borah was born in
Arcata?, but in articles many of them say she was born in Eureka, but
Arcata? is just a suburb of Eureka. Then they came back, she lived in
Salem as a child. Then moved to Yamhill in Oregon and Mr. McConnell came
here to Idaho and built this mansion. And they moved in the day before
Christmas in 1886, and they had an open house after they moved in. And
although Mrs. Borah was at such an advanced age, she remembered the name
of a lady by the name of Mrs. Johnson who went through the house and she
saw the lavatory, and said, "The idea, a privy in the house, I'll never
come in here again!"

And then later on, before they went to Idaho and lived here in Oregon,
little Mary became ill. The doctor didn't know what was wrong and
Grandma said, Grandma lived with them, "I'd like to take her to
Portland. I know a doctor there that could help her." So Grandma took
Mary McConnell on the train to Portland. And on the way there was a lady
across the aisle staring at the baby. When they got to Portland, Grandma
went to Portland Hotel, its torn down now it was a beautiful old fashion
hotel where all the dignitaries who came to town went. So Grandma went
to find a room, and she put the baby on the bed, and they didn't have
bathrooms by each room in those days, so she put the baby in the bed and
left to go to the bathroom. Came back, the baby was gone. So she rushed
down stairs and said, "Did you see anybody carrying a baby?" She
described the type of blanket or whatever was around the child. "Yes, we
saw a lady carry that baby out." So they called the police right away
and went out searching and they found a lady holding the baby about a
few blocks away and they could tell by the look of the lady that she
wasn't normal. They found out later that she had lost a child and she
saw this child and she thought that was hers. So, if they hadn't found
her she would have had an entirely different life than what she had.

So, then in one picture I have here, maybe some of you have seen the
picture, she has a necklace of hand carved elephants. They're all ivory.
And she said an old Indian here in Idaho carved them and gave them to
her when she was a child.

And then she, I think you know that part of it, that she met Mr. Borah
when her father became governor of Idaho and they were married. Then
they went to Washington D.C. in 1907. And they were there, not very
long, when Mr. Borah became very prominent in the senate. He had a very,
very wonderful way of speaking. He was already becoming prominent in
Washington D.C.. He came home one evening and Mary said, "We got an
invitation to go to the White House, we're not going are we?" "We
certainly are," he said, "to get an invitation from the White House is
practically a command." "But I have nothing to wear." You know how most
women will say, right? I have nothing to wear. "Well," he said, "get
something to wear." So she went over to town to get a dress, and found
one. She loved pink, so she had a hard time getting a dress to fit
because she was very small. I don't think she weighed more than 100
pounds. Along in the conversation they found out she was Senator Borah's
wife, and then one of the clerks ran to the propriety and said, "Just
think Senator Borah's wife is here buying an outfit to go to the White
House." So the proprietor came along and saw the pink dress and brings a
pair of pink shoes. And, "Oh, I can't afford that." "It's on the house."
So he gave her the shoes and gave her some accessories to go with this
pink dress.

So it was her first trip to the White House and Theodore Roosevelt was
President. And she was placed right beside him. Theodore Roosevelt was a
very hard person to entertain. It seems there was a man by the name of
Mr. White that Roosevelt mentioned. He knew something about a Mr. White.
He had read some book that he wrote. And then Mrs. Borah said, "You know
that Mr. White was a very dear friend of Billy's and he spent a vacation
at our house and he was writing that book and I named it." He had
proposed some names, I wish I could remember the name of the book.
Anyway, they talked about this book and after the meal was over they all
wondered what on earth she talked about to get that conversation with
the President. Because everyone said he was a very hard person to
converse with.

Now she knew all the Presidents' wives from Theodore Roosevelt on down
to Johnson. But she also knew the Nixons because the children, when they
were little girls, they lived in an apartment not far from the Borahs.
And when they first, maybe some of you remember the old electric cars,
they were electric cars that were invented were used around about 1912
along in those years. Some man gave her an electric car, it had her name
on the side of it. And she wanted to surprise, she always called her
husband Billy, so she had it behind the house, or behind the apartment,
and Mr. came home and she said, "I have a surprise for you." So she took
him outside to see the car and he didn't like it at first. She said,
"Well, he gave it to me and I couldn't say no and he already had my name
on it." So she often took Billy to the Congress, when he went as a
Senator to his work.

And she, of course, knew all the different ambassadors. And one day she
was out some place and there was a little child, son of a little
ambassador, and he was trying to think of her name. He said, "Oh, Little
Borah." So that's the way the term arrived, you've heard that "Little
Borah." That little boy called her "Little Borah" and that stuck. So she
was called "Little Borah" the rest of her life.

Now have you heard how Mr. Borah died? I haven't seen any article any
place, but she told me that Billy used to go out every morning. He loved
horses, so he took a horse with him to Washington D.C. and every morning
he'd go riding on his horse. So they always had breakfast at 6 o'clock
in the morning. This particular morning, she was already in her place.
She had a servant by the name of Daisy, a Negro lady she loved very
much. So she said, "Daisy, go see what's the matter with Billy." So she
went and he was in the bathroom and she called him, he didn't answer.
She said, "He's in the bathroom, he doesn't answer." So she says "Run
down the hall and get the doctor." They lived in a big apartment, so the
doctor came and he couldn't get the door open, so he got some other men
to help him open the door. And Billy had stepped out of the bathtub,
slipped, and knocked his head against the doorknob and he's lying there
unconscious. They picked him up and took him to the hospital and he died
three days later, he never came to. He was very active yet, 75 years
old, he was getting kind of old. At that time, that was in 1940, she was
70 and he was 75.

I imagine you are all acquainted with that terrible disease she had here
in Idaho, the parrot fever. But there's one, the story she tells about
is different than the article, but there's one part that she tells I
think was very very beautiful. She said the nurse told her, that one day
while she was lying there unconscious, when she got the parrot fever it
was in July, and it was very hot, when she came to there was snow on the
ground, so she was sick that long. So when the nurse told her, after she
was better, one day the nurse went in the room and Billy was kneeling by
her bed and he was crying and he said, "Oh God, please, please let Mary
live. Don't let her die, I need her." And all the doctors said that she
would not live. Hardly anybody ever lived after they had parrot fever,
but finally one day she came to and the nurse said, "Are you speaking?"
and she said, "I'm hungry." And she ran out and called the doctors and
nurses, and she came back and Mrs. Borah said again, "I'm hungry." "Then
what would you like to eat?" "Mashed potatoes."

Then after Mr. Borah died, she came back to Idaho, but she stayed a very
short time because all her friends were gone. She didn't know any of the
people anymore around here, so she went back to Washington to live. She
lived there 'til about 1960, and she became very well interested. She
was lovely person, always wanted to do things for other people, never
thought of herself. So she went to the hospitals and visited soldiers
from Idaho and used to write to their mothers about their sons. She did
a beautiful job with these soldiers.

Then one day she was invited to a birthday party. Some lady lived in a
hotel, and this hotel had these revolving doors, they go around and you
get in a section and somebody gets in the next section, you've seen
those doors. Well she was in this section of the door and a young girl,
about 18, very heavy set, big girl, came in and gave that door a shove
and knocked Mrs. Borah against the wall. Now she was a little frail
person, and knocked her down, but she got up and they said, "Are you all
right?" And of course she was the kind that didn't want to give in, and
she said "Yes" and they helped her to the elevator. She went up to the
birthday party and they played games, and she managed to sit there at
the chair. Then they get up and they're going to the next room to look
at the birthday cake and she couldn't move. "Mrs. Borah are you ill?"
And then she told them what happened, they were gonna get an ambulance,
she says, "No, you call" she had a Negro chauffer, and she said, "You
call...Whatever his name was." So he came and picked her up and carried
her off to the car. He said, "Shall I take you to the hospital." "No,
take me home." So he took her home. And they called the doctor and the
doctor came and he was horrified when he saw her, but he said, "Now I'm
gonna get a nurse to sit with you because as soon as you think of
something you want, you'll get up and get it." So the nurse sat with her
until she went to sleep and the next morning when she awoke, she felt
something big on her side and she pulled up her gown. There was a big
blood clot under the skin and her leg was black all the way down. So she
called Daisy, "Look Daisy, what's this." And Daisy took one look and she
ran to the phone and called the doctor and the doctor came and they
brought an ambulance and they took her to the hospital. And she heard
the doctor say, "She survived parrot fever, but she'll never get over
this." But she did, she must have had a good heart. Anyway, she got over
it, and then that was shortly before, or around 1960.

So she was there, and she had two nieces in Portland, her sister Ollie
lived in Portland. And that's a question often asked, "How did Mrs.
Borah get to Portland and to Beaverton, why wasn't she in Idaho?" Well
Mrs. Lueddemann, was her sister's name, lived in Portland, and by the
way Mr. Lueddemann was a personal friend of Helen Keller. And Helen
Keller used to come to Portland to visit the Lueddemanns. And when Mr.
Lueddemann was ill, when these two girls, Mrs. Lueddemann had two
daughters, Mary and Joan, they lived part-time in Washington D.C. with
Mrs. Borah and went to school there. And when Mary, one of Mrs.
Lueddemann's daughters, came to visit Mrs. Borah she said, "Aunt Mamie,
your sick. I'm gonna take you to Portland with me." So Aunt Mamie was
happy to have somebody take care of her, I guess. So they sold, it's
sad, she had a collection of between two and three thousand elephants,
and she loved that collection very much, but she managed to bring a few
of them with her to Portland. But her things were sold, and she was
brought to Portland and lived with her sister for a while. And then her
sister became blind, so the two nieces put their mother and their aunt
in a nursing home. They were in a nursing home just a few years before
they came, they heard about Maryville, so they brought them to Maryville
in August 1966. And so she was there until she died January 1976. Ollie
died, I don't know just what year, but Ollie was 96 when she died.

Now in 1968 when Nixon was campaigning, he came to Portland. We have
primaries in May in Portland. He came to Portland to campaign, so I knew
what hotel they were staying in. So I called and asked for the person
who was taking care of, sort of secretary for Nixon. And so someone
answered, and they got Mrs. Nixon, so I talked to Mrs. Nixon for about
15 minutes on the telephone, explained that I was a personal friend of
Mrs. Borah's. I said, "Now I know Mr. Nixon cannot campaign on election
day. Wouldn't it be nice if you would come out to Maryville and visit
Mrs. Borah because she knows you." And Mrs. Nixon said, "I'm very sorry,
but we're planned to go to Seattle tomorrow, election day, so we can't
come out." But she said, "Couldn't I talk to her on the phone." I said,
"No, that's not possible because she does not have a phone in her room
because her hearing is very bad. We'd have to take her quite a distance
to a phone and then she wouldn't understand you and it upsets her very
much to try to talk on the phone." I said, "but you could write to her."
So she wrote a letter. I had a chance to read the letter and she
mentioned me in that letter. And I was gonna ask her if I could have it,
but somebody stoled it, I never got it. I was sorry. I would have liked
to have had that letter in my book.

Then in November, her birthday's in October. That same year when Nixon
was campaigning for president, he knew when her birthday was, so he had
the telephone company, it must have been an expensive deal they did. The
telephone company came and established a special telephone in the living
room of Maryville, and Nixon knew the exact time they were gonna have
this party, it was broadcast on the TV and they had a loudspeaker on so
she could hear it. And he talked on the telephone direct to her and
wished her happy birthday while they could see him on the TV. Now they
planned that whole thing for her birthday, that was a big ad for him, I
guess, when he was campaigning.

Then when her 100th birthday came along. They made all kinds of
wonderful plans. First of all, there was a girl, a very beautiful girl,
Maureen Bassett, who graduated from our school. Her whole family just
loved Mrs. Borah, they went often to see her. Maureen was working for a
radio company, radio place in Hillsboro, so I told her, "Wouldn't it be
nice to have Mrs. Borah make a tape and have it on the radio." "Oh, that
would be wonderful!" So she had me go with her and we went over to Mrs.
Borah's room and she asked her questions. And she told the story of
getting that dress for her visit to the White House. She talked for 45
minutes on the radio, it turned out beautifully. Do you have that tape?

UNKNOWN 1: No

SMC: I must ask this niece, has the tape. And I'm gonna ask her if she
can't have another one made and give it to the museum because it was
just beautiful the way she spoke that whole 45 minutes. She was very
rational until she was about 102 and that was lovely. Well, then on her
actual birthday the Republican ladies from Portland planned a grand
affair. They had a bouquet, it was about that big around, one hundred
red roses. Oh, it was a gorgeous bouquet. And they had a big reception
for her, many people came. Nearly every one of her birthdays TV stations
would come and take pictures. Now for her 100^th^ birthday it was
broadcast around the world because there was another family that was
very much, many families just loved her, and these people were related
to one of our sisters and a boy, a young man, had been there to visit
and now he was in Vietnam and this came over the TV in Vietnam, and that
boy got so excited, "Oh, I know that lady, I know that lady, I saw her!"
He was so excited seeing that clear over in Vietnam from here. That must
have been exciting for the boy.

Now she was, well I'm just about finished now, but I can tell you more
if you want more, that's as much as I have down here. That she was loved
very very much. She was one of these persons that just everybody loved.
People'd come in and she liked, I'd put my arms around her and kiss her,
and oh she just loved it. She was just a darling. Had any of you see her
at all?

UNKNOWN 2: Yes, I did. I saw her many times

SMC: Did you come to Maryville?

UNKNOWN 2: No, but I saw her always when she came to Moscow. She used to
stay with me, she and Ollie Lueddemann. We were old friends. But I
wanted to tell you was, in the letters that she wrote she'd tell about
"my angel sisters" the angel sisters were the sisters at Maryville. My
angel sisters.

SMC: Well she was a person that was very outstanding. There are very few
in the world like her, that's true. Here's one experience she had, I
wasn't going to tell you this, but as long as I have more time, it was
strange, she had such a wonderful way of dealing with people. Some of
these boys that were insane, soldiers, she would go to visit them and
there were some, you know with different degrees of insanity, and she'd
kiss them and they call her mother. Some of the boys said, "If any of
the boys ever touch you, we'd kill 'em." And one boy that she liked very
very much was pleading with her to go to the airport. And she thought he
was more rational than he was, and so she begged the authorities, and
they said, "No, you'd better not." And she said, "But he wants to go so
badly." And Mrs. Borah had her own private chauffer, and they said,
"Well, all right then." So they sent another man along, one of the
orderlies from the insane asylum. And she was on one side of this boy
and this orderly on the other side, and he wanted to go to the airport,
and he behaved very beautifully on the way. Then when they got to the
airport he got out, then they could hardly get him back in the car. See
he planned, he was gonna get on a plane and go someplace. So they got
him back in the car and he fought all the way back. She said she was
just black and blue when she got back. And they told her, they warned
her you know, she never would try a thing like that again.

And she gave another example of how careful they should be. There was
some boy there in the asylum that seemed to be getting very normal. And
they thought he was all right, and the doctors thought he was all right
now to be sent out from the asylum. And between the asylum and another
building there was a tunnel underneath the street, and so he went down
through that tunnel, and when he got on the other side somebody saw him,
looked kind of wild eyes "Well, I took care of that, I took care of
her." And they wondered what he meant, so they went down. A nurse was
coming through the tunnel, he was going the other way, and he killed
her, and then he got out on the other side. They could see he was wild
eyed, you know, and they knew there was something wrong. And so they got
him back, I guess he never got out again, but that was the type of thing
that happened there. And so when Mrs. Borah was getting older and she
knew she couldn't do it anymore, she talked to a friend of hers and she
said, "You know the boys just love it when somebody comes and sees them.
Won't you come and see if you can take my place?" So the lady didn't
want to go, but Mrs. Borah asked her to, so she did. And the first day
she was there she was introducing this lady to some of the boys and she
turned her back and another boy knocked that woman down right away and
the woman screamed. And Mrs. Borah turned around and got the lady out of
there, but she never tried taking any other women in there. But not one
of those boys would touch Mrs. Borah. Now any questions you'd like to
ask me?

GRACE: I talked to her just before she came west in Washington, and she
said "Oh, Grace I can't see, I can't hear, and I can't walk." And she
was concerned that day for some books she was sending to the University
of Idaho library, and we got that squared away. And then, I think Lola
could tell us a little inside information on how she was supported those
last years. At the time of her husband's death there was an ample
inheritance, but you just live for so long and use your principal and
she just plain ran out of money. So, Lola why don't you tell about that.

LOLA: Oh yes. I'm proud of our state. When it got down to the bedrock,
it's the best kept secret in the state of Idaho. The state legislator
put up the money. The first year Harry Day and Harry Solen and Lynn
Driscoll, who was the banker from Boise, and a long-time friend, they
were old time friends, they put up the first money.

UNKNOWN 3: And Levin? Randall?

LOLA: Yes, that's right, and that they would continue. But the state of
Idaho said, "We're proud of the Borahs. They brought distinction and
honor to our state and we want to do it, but we'll keep it all a secret.
No one will know where it is coming from. So, it was a piece of
legislature that enacted it. Never appeared in the papers, I never heard
any of the legislators mention it at all, but I know that our own Harold
Snow was one of the people I contacted about it. It was a very well-kept
secret, but those things might happen to any of us, but I think we can
all think how proud we were that our state did it.

LEE: That's a beautiful thing.

LOLA: I think so too. We were proud and happy to do it, and it was kept
a very deep secret. All these years the papers never mentioned one word
about it.

UNKNOWN 4: When she was in the hospital with psittacosis and having such
a bad time, it was difficult for her to have much appetite. And in the
museum there are some dishes that her husband brought her because she
was turned off by those hospital dishes. So he brought those, there kind
of a pink lusterware, aren't they?

LOLA: That's right

UNKNOWN 4: And she could eat off of something a little more pleasant.

UNKNOWN 5: And they also had on display a lovely ivory hand carved cane
that the emperor of Japan gave to Mrs. Borah. That was because he felt
so bad she had contracted the disease in his country. Isn't that story
Lee?

LEE: I don't know all the details.

SMC: Oh, I know another very interesting story. I forgot. There was
another old lady in Maryville, her name was Mrs. Kreff? and she had
three children. She and, her husband was a lumberman, and she took those
children, got permission to take them on a 6 months tour around the
world. And they stayed quite a while in China, and in India. Then I had
talked to her about Mrs. Borah one day, she was now a grandmother, she
was a daughter of this Mrs. Kreff?. I said, "Would you like to meet Mrs.
Borah," and she said "Yes." So I took her in to introduce her and she
saw that frame, you've seen the picture, so often, the picture she had
by her husband's bed with the frame around it. "Oh the forbidden
stitch!" and I said, "What do you mean?" She said when she was in China,
the guide that took them around said that in China, years ago, the
Chinese ladies made this so-called forbidden stitch. They were tiny tiny
stitches, almost not much bigger than a pin head, I mean a pinpoint.
They were French knots, you could hardly see them they were so tiny. I
guess the lighting wasn't very good at that time, and some of the women
were losing their eyesight. So the government made a law, no woman would
be allowed to make that stitch anymore because they couldn't afford to
be having all the ladies be getting blind. But they were making a lot of
money on it, so some ladies did it anyway, and they actually were put to
death because they disobeyed that law. That's what this lady told me.
That's why I feel so bad about, when I went to the museum I expected to
see these frames, these pictures. She had two of them, she has two
pictures of her husband in these frames, one he's younger, and the other
he's older, and this elephant necklace, and she had another on her
windowsill, it was a bell shaped bottle with a neck about that big
around with a cork in it, it was a bluebird inside, beautiful thing.
That was a very very old thing that she got from China. I wonder what
happened to that. They should have that in the museum.

UNKNOWN 2: The little things that were at Maryville like that. Mary
Schedner? Has them in her home. And she has a son who would be Ollie
Lueddemann's grandson, you see. And he is taking a great interest in
history, and I think most of those little personal things Mary
Schedner?'s son has. I kinda think so, but it may be that they'll come
home to us you know.

SMC: Well, I'm gonna call Mary...

[End Recording]

         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13397</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Carlson_Willa6</previous>
      <next>Clark_Archie</next>
      <disp_name>Christina</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
