<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/12/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Lola Clyde, 1976-10-12, Interview #7 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:24:42</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Clyde, Lola</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #7</intnum>
      <occupation>Teacher; farm wife; local historian; frequently addresses groups and aids
         researchers
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1900</birthyear>
      <residence>Paradise Ridge, Moscow</residence>
      <origin>Father emigrated from Ireland and became the area's first Presbyterian minister
         (1880); mother was from Victoria, British Columbia
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#authors"&gt;authors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presentations"&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#local histories"&gt;local histories&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#normal schools"&gt;normal schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming &lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#family life education"&gt;family life education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage &lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women's rights"&gt;women's rights &lt;/a&gt; 
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13409</file_name>
      <mp3>13410.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13410.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Uncle Bill Morgan of Lewiston.</title>
            <synopsis>Uncle Bill Morgan of Lewiston.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>120</time>
            <title>Dangers to health in the early days</title>
            <synopsis>Women's ill-health in early days - lack of outside activities, strain of childbearing
               and farm work. Lack of good treatment around birth. People's religion discouraged
               them from practicing birth control, by encouraging view that children were gifts from
               heaven. High mortality rate of infants: bad diphtheria epidemic in late 1870's.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Employment opportunities for women; family finances</title>
            <synopsis>Mother's desire to teach school for money, but father opposed it. Egg and cream money
               was "the wife's province." Men did major buying of furniture - status of buying a
               piano for children. Many women went to Moscow to "pick peas" when factory opened in
               late twenties.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Women entering the teaching profession</title>
            <synopsis>Most early teachers were men. In 1890's women entered teaching field in large numbers;
               opening of Lewiston Normal in 1895 made this possible. Until depression, many married
               women with older children kept teaching. Her lenient husband; she was on fourteen
               boards at once.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1260</time>
            <title>Women's education and fashion</title>
            <synopsis>For some single women the right man hadn't come along. Pressure from mothers to marry.
               Some intelligent girls chose not to marry for their careers. Girls got more schooling
               while boys worked on farms; some were too educated for men. Teachers set fashions
               for neighborhoods. Most farm women had one good dress (black). Constriction of corsets
               for "wasp waists", society women rather than farm women wore them. Distinct line
               between working country women and social town women. Hired girls in town signified
               middle class families.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Upper and middle-class women; involvement at the church</title>
            <synopsis>"Upper ten" families had servant quarters. Hiring girls for harvest. Signs of middle
               class women: their leisure. Women's support of missionary work and church maintenance
               through church organizations. Evangelism among the church families - calling in times
               of distress with something in hand; growing by helping others. Church was main focus
               of social activity - role in socializing youth. Greater church activity in Moscow
               than small towns; rural isolation from ministers. Church activities were dominated
               by women. Many American men weren't devout, but old country men tended to be.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>The role of religion in death</title>
            <synopsis>Early women believed that suffering on earth would be rewarded in heaven. Women grieved
               deeply for death of their children, despite belief in hereafter. Talk of the missing
               older family members. Desirability of a religious death, especially for the young.
               Family sat with dying person, and minister would join them.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>The benefits of taking care of the elderly at home</title>
            <synopsis>Keeping old in the home. Desire to care for kin until death. Stigma of "poor house."
               Continuity of having old in home for young, imparting sense of responsibility and
               inevitability. Interest of old in family life. Increased importance of family.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Treatment of country people</title>
            <synopsis>Treatment of country people as inferior. As a country woman at the Historical Club
               she stood up to an anti-Semitic speaker.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3780</time>
            <title>Prominent Moscow families</title>
            <synopsis>Some prominent Moscow families. Judge Forney's joke about his college presidency;
               Mrs. Forney's reaction to a caller.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Experiences at the University of Idaho</title>
            <synopsis>Dean French and her policies of social conduct; she was not very understanding. College
               fashions and social life. Her university experience as an older student: walking from
               the country, hard work, Sororities - pressure to get in. Relations between sexes before
               marriage, in town and country, not much different than now; lack of information about
               birth control.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Social Service activities</title>
            <synopsis>Social service activities - development of health unit, PTA and hot lunch program,
               despite opposition. Great interest and support from faculty wives for progressive
               activities; antipathy between faculty wives and town wives. Opposition to anti-depression
               activities as socialist. League of Women Voters was labeled Democratic by some Republicans.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5640</time>
            <title>Religious revivals</title>
            <synopsis>Father's attitude toward revivals. Presbyterians believed that the light was expressed
               through daily conduct.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5820</time>
            <title>Frank B. Robinson's interactions with the community</title>
            <synopsis>Frank B. Robinson and his great generosity in civic affairs. Did he believe in his religion?
               Validity of Crucified Gods Galore. His intellectual friendship with Reverend Clifford
               Drury. His help in depression. His defense of a retarded woman. He paid for a search
               for a lost boy and then hired the father. Opposition from some denominations. Spurning
               his offer to pay for the new Presbyterian Church spire. He started Moscow's first
               youth center.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6840</time>
            <title>Helping the Settle Family</title>
            <synopsis>Playing "Black Man" with the Settle boys. Respect for Settle family. A teacher said Gene was
               the only white man on the school board. Her mother helped him prepare for his eighth
               grade exams.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7080</time>
            <title>Family planning</title>
            <synopsis>It's the bad parts that make us willing to leave life. Controversial nature of family
               planning. Depression led to reduced size of families. Wives made decision about family
               size, not husbands. Middle class town women knew more about smaller families. Progress
               from dire need of Great Depression. Progress of women's thinking through education.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7440</time>
            <title>Men leaving the farm for the war</title>
            <synopsis>Relationship of parents to children. Many young men wanted to get away from the farm.
               The wars took people to the cities, offering opportunities. Most went to the west
               coast.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7560</time>
            <title>Anti-German Sentiment during World War I</title>
            <synopsis>Anti-German actions during World War I. Beatings of those Germans who didn't go into
               the army. Breaking windows in German stores in Uniontown. Burning merchandise from
               Germany at Williamsons. Lingering resentments. Tar and feathering a German. Difficult
               position of Germans, some older people hoped to return to Germany.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7860</time>
            <title>Catholic Church, Ku Klux Klan</title>
            <synopsis>Ku Klux Klan were people without much intelligence. People knew who belonged. It was
               against the Catholics. A lecture by an "escaped nun" who was guarded by the Klan and
               sponsored by a church. Some believed Catholic school was inferior to high school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8220</time>
            <title>How labor disputes affected farmers</title>
            <synopsis>IWWs blow up Clyde threshing machine in summer of 1922. Labor troubles led farmers
               to modernize equipment to eliminate need for labor. Attitude of farmers towards need
               to work. A strike on the Snow place. Hiring outsiders took fun out of community undertaking
               of threshing. Outsiders were required because individual farmers bought their own
               threshing outfits, having a lot of land under cultivation. Shift to combines.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Women's life in country compared to town. Women's civic achieve ments in
         Moscow. Women's teaching opportunities. Family size. Church activities; attitudes
         about
         dying. Social relations at university. Anti-German actions during war; Klan in the
         1920s.
         IWW's in harvest. Frank B. Robinson. 10-12-76 2.5 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHARGER: Not yet.
         
         LOLA GAMBLE CLYDE: Oh, it's just like going into a museum. One thing he has on the
         wall
         is real cute. It's a little team of pigs hitched up to a little wagon
         and they're driving it- and a man named Huff is driving it. And Hirff
         came from Grangeville. They took it back to the World Fair at Chicago. 
         They took it down to thejttic Yukon Exhibition in ?909 and won
         aprize. And there they are and he's got that picture hanging there on
         the wall. And there's a lot of other old-time pictures. And then in
         it, are many replicas of old-time things. And he really knows an aw
         ful lot of history and stuff. You'll just love Uncle Bill.
         
         SS:  Well, let me ask you about social life wanted to know one
         thing about the women in those days; I've had the impression that alot
         of them were not in the best of health. That there was a lot of sick
         ness among the women who were here in the early days, and there was all
         over the country in the early 1900's. Do you find that to have been
         so? When you think about it?
         
         LGC: Yes, I think so too, that it seemed to be one of the great subjects
         of conversation- was the ill health that they all had. And part of it
         was that they didn't have enough outside interests, I think, and then
         every ache and pain was magnified, and as they used to say, "She feels
         every pain," you know, and maybe some of it was that. But in those
         days they had children one right after the other, you know, and
         be ten children in ten years, and that's pretty hard on women's health.
         And then there was lots of hard work required of the early pioneer wo
         men, and I imagine their health wasn't very good. And doctors were
         very inadequate. They had so few of them. And in the very early days
         most of the children were ushered into the world by the help of the mid
         wife and that sort of thing.
         
         SS:  So really, the childbearing was really hard on them.
         
         LGC:  Yes, it was hard on them.
         
         SS:  Took it's toll physically.
         
         LGC:  Yes, it did. It took it's toll physically. That's right.
         
         SS:  Is that because they didn't know enough about- at the time- about how
         to take care of that with the least trouble?
         
         LGC:  Well, I suppose so. And many babies were born without much medical
         attention- without much prenatal care- and very little postnatal
         care. And doctors were few and far between.
         
         SS:  What kind of an effect, say, would that have on the mothers to have
         not had, you know, a doctor's care? What would that do to a would
         that just mean they wouldn't get strong- become more weak?
         
         LGC:  That's right. And some of them died in childbirth, if there were com
         plications developed. Mothers died in childbirth because they didn't
         have medical assistance at the time.
         
         SS:  Was that fairly common up here, for example?
         
         LGC:  Well, I think as a little child, I remember two of our neighbor wo
         men dying in childbirth. And so that was quite a—
         
         SS:  The large sized family, is one, too. I've noticed that it seems like
         the early families were very large. Werent they?
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right.
         
         SS:  But the way my reading indicates that birth control was not unknown
         during that period of time, so that it could have been practiced per
         haps if families had wanted to. Didn't they have any knowledge of
         birth control?
         
         LGC:  Well, I don't know. A lot of them had the feeling that lots of children was
         lots of security. And a lot of them their religion kept them
         from practicing what they did know. And I just wouldn't be able to
         answer; I don't know.
         
         Well, when you talk, you know, the security of the children- was that
         the idea that-from what people have said- was that the idea that a
         big family- you'd have alot of people to help on the farm? Was that
         the thinking behind it?
         
         Well, it could have been, although I've heard some of them say: One
         father can take care of twelve sons; the twelve sons can't take care
         of one father. And I think that was quite true, too. Each of them
         grew up and went on their own, you know merry way. And Idon't know
         that there was so much taking care of the old folks went on as
         could have. But I think religion entered into a lot of their thinking.
         Not necessarily because they were Catholics, but many of the religions
         taught that the Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away, and this is just
         the will of the Lord that I'm given these children.
         
         SS:  You mean the Protestant denominations?
         
         LGC:  It's true. Many of the Protestant people felt that way that these were
         gifts straight from heaven and they accepted them as that, you know.
         
         SS:  Okay, but then what about- we talked some before about women being a
         chattel and that kind of stuff.
         
         LGC: Yes.
         
         SS:  And being in almost servitude, because of all they had to do for their
         husband.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Now, wouldn't it stand to reason that the only way that they could be
         free of that would be if they didn't have big families? I mean, to
         have a big family was to accept that.
         
         That's right. Well, Ijust don't know what the feeling behind all
         that was with the early day women, but lots of them prided themselves:
         I can remember one old lady saying that she'd had sixteen children and
         she lived to raise eight of 'em!
         
         SS:  What did that mean? She lost the other eight?
         
         LGC:  Yes, she lost the other eight.
         
         SS:  In childbirth or when they were babies?
         
         LGC:  Small ones, there were different epidemics. Moscow went through the
         black diphtheria scourge here a couple of times. And at one time some
         of the early histories report that half the children in the town of
         Moscow died with black diphtheria.
         
         SS:  Oh, really?
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS: i didn't know that it was that bad.
         
         LGC:  Yes, it was that bad.
         
         SS:  When do you think about when would that have been?
         
         Oh, it would be in the very early- in the early '70's. 1877, maybe and
         '78, along through there they had a bad epidemic of black diphtheria.
         Well, thinking about this- what women accepted for their lives, it
         sounds to me like- Well, what I'm wondering, do you think that the wo
         men then questioned whether they should have an alternative to just
         being homemakers and raising afamily? Or did that only come later?
         That that was questioned.
         
         LGC:  Well,-
         
         SS:  You know what I mean.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I know what you mean.
         
         SS:  Is that the only way they thought to live at the time?
         Well, Ican only answe^from my own mother's viewpoint. My mother was
         an educated woman and she had taught- she taught in the first girls'
         school in Canada in the Angela College of Victoria, B. C. And when
         she moved to this pioneer settlement, she wanted my father to let her
         go out and teach school, and oh, that was against the principles of
         the old country. The man made the living; it was his privilege and
         his right and he wouldn't let her go. But, I've often heard her say
         that she wished that my father had let her go and teach school at the
         same time because they could have used the money so well. And nearly
         all of the farm women had their cows and they would milk them and sell
         the cream. And they got most of the egg money, and that was considered
         their money that they could do as they pleased. But the grain, the
         crop had to go in^or paying for land or machinery or for debts, but
         the egg and cream money, the women could have that.
         
         SS:  But they spent it not on themselves?
         
         LGC:  No, they spent it on the children and on food. Most of it
         went for the children and on food for the table.
         
         So, in other words, she was really exclusively in control of the chil
         dren and the food.
         
         Yes, that's right. That was her calling.
         
         What about the household furnishings and the furniture and all that,
         was that all her's, too?
         
         Well,- and once again, Ican hardly answer it. The men did most of
         this buying, as I remember it. The Scandinavian men, especially. But
         some of them took great pride in their houses and buying a piano for
         their daughters. That was the epitome of gracious living, was to be
         able to get apiano and give the girls music lessons, when Iwas alit
         tle child. And there was some of the families that could do that.
         So, say somejthings like sofas and chairs and that sort of thing- would
         that usually be the husband or wife who would make-
         
         Well most of the purchases, most of the major purchases, your purchases
         like that much money, would be made by the man. The men would decide
         when they would get it and some of them took pride in having well fur
         nished houses, and that sort of thing, you know.
         
         Well, Iknow these sorts of things are pretty imponderable, they're
         difficult to figure; But I'm asking you some of these things because
         of the reading that I've done now, when we're looking at women's his
         tory, and history of the nineteenth century. These are the kind of
         questions that they're asking. Why was it this way? And how was it?
         So, they're trying to generalize on what- you know- on some of these
         things. But for other women, maybe sometimes your mother. Was your
         mother unusual in her interest in getting out of the home to teach?
         Do you think that it was common and that most women would have if they
         could have?
         
         Well, yes, I think if they had been fitted; but^so few were educated
         in those days, you know, there were so few trained, I think most of
         them would have tried, because I remember in later years when they
         opened the pea picking factory and Moscow became the pea capital
         of the world and women could go to town and get jobs in the winter
         picking out the rogue peas from the other peas. Oh, lots of the women
         went out and got jobs and would drive to town every day to pick peas.
         And that gave them a feeling of independence and they got money for
         doing it. And many of the married women who's Children were then in
         school would even get a job in town to bring in a little extra money.
         
         SS:  They'd come from the rural areas. They'd come from Troy and further?
         
         LGC:  Yes, oh, yes, they came from Troy and come into Moscow to pick peas.
         
         SS:  When did that start? In the '30's or before?
         
         Maybe after 1925, people started picking peas, because Moscow then had
         established a good market for green peas.
         
         Well, what about the dealings of women teachers in the schools? In
         the early days Ihad heard that it was largely men. Is that true?
         Largely men teachers in the rural schools?
         
         Well, there were some, yes, but right around here that was avery well
         accepted position for the women- for the girls, they would grow up to
         be teachers.
         
         But, now, I'm trying to figure when- In the early_ pioneering, in the
         '80's, say, were there women teachers back that early? In large num
         bers?
         
         No, I think that most of the early teachers were men teachers.
         So your mother would probably have been unusual as ateacher at that
         time?
         
         Yes, that's right, because they weren't trained for it. No, that's
         right. Most of them were men teachers. And it wasn't until maybe in
         the 'Id's that we saw women coming into that. It was a highly respec
         ted job for the young girls to grow up to be teachers, or they could
         be nurses. That was a highly respected job.
         
         Do you think that it started then because that's when the girls were
         able to go to Lewiston Normal and the University?
         
         Yes, Ithink so. Yes, because in 1890- in  came the Lewiston Nor
         mal. And that was a fine opportunity for the young girls to go on
         and get educations.
         
         SS:  And they were going there right away to teach?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. Yes, as soon as the Lewiston Normal started. We had no
         school of education at the University of Idaho when it first opened.
         
         SS:  Oh, there wasn't?
         
         No, Must the liberal arts. But girls did go there. But not with
         idea of becoming teachers so much. But after Lewiston Normal star
         ted, that was to train teachers and they did go down there. And that
         was an ambition with many of them was to go on to school; those that
         liked school.
         
         Well, then, do you think- would it be fair to say that probably the
         large numbers- or the influx of women into rural school teaching star
         ted when Lewiston Normal started? Or do you think it was started be
         fore?
         
         LGC:  I think it started with Lewiston Normal.
         
         SS:  Before that they wouldn't have really had a chance.
         
         LGC:  They wouldn't have had any place to get it. And for many years, the
         student nurses had to go to Spokane, to the hospitals there to get nur
         se's training. They would go up to Sacred Heart and get training there.
         But with the coming of Lewiston Normal, started turning out our
         own rural teachers.
         
         SS:  Were they going to Cheney before Lewiston Normal for teaching? I've
         heard of your contemporaries did go to Cheney.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, many of them went to Cheney. And many of them from right around
         here went to Cheney. Yes, Cheney was established- Cheney Normal
         was established ahead of Lewiston
         
         SS:  Somewhat earlier?
         
         LGC:  Yes, somewhat earlier.
         
         SS:  Then it seems to me that the problem, in a way, was pushed back fur
         ther, because once they were teaching in the rural schools then a young
         woman could teach until she married. Right?
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And that was built into the work.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  How did people feel about that? You told me some of}that you didn't
         mind stopping teaching; but do you think that at the time, that after
         this freedom of being a teacher, making your own money and making your
         own way, that most of the women didn't mind to just give that all up?
         
         LGC:  Well, I think a lot of them didn't give it up. Alot of them went on
         teaching after they were married until the Depression hit, and then
         married women couldn't get jobs, because they felt that the single women
         needed the jobs or man who was head of a family should have the
         job. So married women weren't allowed to teach, during the Depression
         No one would hire them..
         
         SS:  But before that, people- teachers have told me that in the rural coun
         try, that not only was it custom that they stop teaching when they mar
         ried, but in a lot of school districts they had it in the contract,
         that they couldn't be, married
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right. That's true..
         
         SS:  That didn't seem like it gave much choice.
         
         LGC:  That didn't give them much choice, did it? Well, they had to be real
         ly in love with the man they married, you know, to give up their in
         dependence.
         
         SS:  You mean, it encouraged romantic marriage?
         
         LGC:  That's right. It encouraged it, you know.
         
         SS:  But in terms of- just from the point of view of fairness, it seems that
         that meant for most of these people they had a choice between career
         and marriage.
         
         LGC:  That's right. That's about the way it has been you know, through the
         years.
         
         SS:  I'm just wondering if they had that as a rule in the rural schools in
         so many of them that you couldn't be married and teach. To give the
         the person the option, would seem alot fairer than to say, "You can't
         teach, if you're married."
         
         LGC:  Well, many of the rural schools did hire married women up until the
         time of the Depression. Yes, many of them did. I knew quite a few
         married women who taught around Moscow in the immediate vicinity. And
         they went on teaching and that sort of thing. But after the Depression
         hit, then most of the schools wouldn't hire a married woman, because
         they felt that they should save the job for some single woman or for
         some head of a family.
         
         SS:  Did most of these woman that did teach quit teaching to raise their
         family and then come back to teaching. I mean were they older women?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think most of them were older women or women with
         out children or women with just one child. They weren't women with a
         lot of children, and a lot of household responsibility. I think that
         was pretty well established.
         
         SS:  How old would the youngest child have to be before a woman would feel
         comfortable with going back to teaching?
         
         LGC:  Well, I think it would have to be of school age and then they could
         take the child with them to school or put them in school someplace.
         I think that was the way most of them did, as I remember.
         
         SS:  It does to seem to me, for instance with yourself with the choice that
         you made to marry; did you find it difficult- somewhat difficult- to
         make the adjustment of being totally at home instead of being out in
         
         LGC:  Well,]l had avery wonderful, understanding, lenient husband. Very
         indulgent husband. And he just said, "Lola, you just go and do your
         thing and I'll do my thing." And he let me sit on school boards.
         And one time.I was never a bored farmwife, I just sat on all the boards
         in town. And at one time I was on fourteen different boards Latah
         County and the town of Moscow. School boards,.library boards, Red Cross,
         Gritman Hospital, Health, County Health Unit.
         
         SS:  Didn't you find it borjf\o sit on all those boards?
         
         LGC:  No, I just had fun.
         
         SS:  How about your younger years, when you were first married?
         
         LGC:  When I was first married, I'll tell you, Iwas just so busy. We had
         a great depression hit and we were down to twenty-eight cents, you know
         and I had about seventeen hired men to cook for and four little child
         ren, one right after the other. Four children all under four years
         of age. I didn't have time for any regrets or any thing else. Iwas
         just too busy trying to keep food on the table for everybody.
         
         Let's talk a little bit about unmarried women. I'm curious to know
         what you think- It seems from what I've read, and some of what I've
         seen, people who didn't marry. Now, do you feel that- how would you
         explain why a lot of people didn't marry in those days. It seems m
         some ways there was a lot of that back in those days of people deciding
         not to. Was it that the women were too educated for the men who were
         around or something?
         
         Well, the right man just hadn't come along.K Put it that way. And
         some were unsatisfied with the kind of men they met, you know.
         Of pressure on young women to marry.
         
         Yes, I think so, too. I think the mothers were always afraid the girls
         would be old maids, you know. They'd urge them to get out and meet
         young people and that sort of thing, you know. That that was the ex
         pected thing to do. And all the mothers thought their daughters should
         be the belle of the ball, you know and follow along in the way they had
         done. I think that there was that feeling among them.
         
         SS:  But talking about the choice between marriage and career; do you think
         that some of the women did make a choice for a job and independence,
         freedom-—
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think that's right. I think that there were many of the highly
         intelligent girls didn't marry because they did like their work and
         their jobs and they would have to give up too much. I think. I think
         that's true.
         
         SS:  Well, it seemed to me that with the— would you say that there was a
         generally high level of education among the girls than the boys?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. Their services weren't needed so badly on the farm.
         The girls. The^oys were needed so badly farming in the rural communi
         ties. And they'd always figure, well, when this boy got out of schoolsometimes
         that was just right out of the eighth grade- why, we'll buy
         another piece of land and start him up farming. And that went on a
         lot and then in the very, very, early times the boys stayed home and
         helped their fathers in the spring and in the fall and maybe in the
         very early days, it would just be a couple of months in the summer
         they had school, and later on, it was just a few months in the winter
         that the older boys were allowed to go to school. And then they couldn't
         be working out in the fields and so on so they'd go to school for a
         little while.
         
         SS:  So, the girls because they weren't needed-
         
         LGC:  That's right.
         
         SS:  Had the freedom to go 
         
         Yes, the girls had more freedom to go to school. Yes, I think that's true.
         
         SS:  Now, an educated young woman, could she easily find herself in a po
         sition where there wasn't anybody around who was her intellectual- who
         could be her companion, that way?
         
         Yes, Ithink so. Ithink that's right. Ithink they educated them
         selves out of the market. Ithink sometimes that happened. Ithink
         oftenlthat happened.
         
         Do you think men tended to be afraid of brainy women? Or not like
         brainy women?
         
         Yes, that's right. Ithink that that's true, yes. Ithink most of
         them -"Beware of these schoolmarms, they'll boss you around the rest
         of your life!" Although in the early days, the school marms were
         geenrally quite the belles of the balls. They set the social pace.
         What the new teacher wore and what she did was very much the pattern
         for the rest of the girls of the community.
         
         SS:  Really? Of the young wives, too?
         
         Yes, of the young wives, too. They'd watch what kind of hatband what
         kind of dresses the new schoolteacher was wearing and that sort of was
         a pacesetter.
         
         Why did she find herself in that position, that she was the pacesetter?
         Was it being from?
         
         Yes, a lot of them came out from the towns to^he rural communities.
         And they had alittle more money of their own and they could buy things
         like that. And they were expected to be well dressed and that sort
         of thing when they taught school.
         
         Coming from Lewiston they might have been closer to the fashion world.
         That's right. That's right. They came up from the big town of Lewiston
         and they might know what the latest styles were.
         
         Talking of styles; were the styles changing in those days? ^mean were
         they different from year to year or two years?
         
         A little bit, quite a little bit, yes. They'd wear high buttoned
         shoes sometimes and sometimes it'd be oxfords. Sometimes- that sort of
         thing, yes. Yes, the styles changed. I can remember my mother wearing
         the big leg-o£~mutton sleeves, you know, on her coats. And then I re
         member the Mother Hubbards for the kitchen wear. And later on it was
         stylish to have high waists and low waists, and even the little girls
         in school would pattern after what the teachers had.
         
         SS:  Did people actually have a little bit of extra money clinking around
         that they could follow the fashions, too?
         
         LGC:  Well, sometimes, you know. Sometimes the women got a little extra cream
         check, they would buy a little something.
         
         SS:  Or if you were buying maybe a new dress, you'd try to get —
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Well, I heard that everybody had a black dress. That black was the
         big thing.
         
         LGC:  Everybody had a black silk dress and you had that to wear to church
         on Sunday. And it was quite common, uh-huh. A nice black silk dress.
         
         SS:  Well, the average farmwife at that time, like your mother and the wo
         men of her generation; how many dresses would they own?
         
         LGC:  Well, just about one good one, would be all.
         
         SS:  And that would be black?
         
         LGC:  Yes, uh-huh. Nice black silk one to wear to church or a funeral or to
         a wedding. They were few and far between, you know. But they weren't
         big invitational affairs^like they are now, or like they were for a
         while. They generally had one good decent dress, they called it, for
         church and funerals. And Mother Hubbards the rest of the time,largely.
         
         SS:  The Mother Hubbards were—?
         
         LGC:  Kind of loose fitting dresses.
         
         SS:  — wear, as not being very healthy-
         
         LGC:  And the corsets.
         
         SS:  Was that kind of a constricting and dumb idea? Or what was the—?
         
         LGC: Well, these waspwaists, you know, that was going a little too far, I say.
         This cinching them in you know. that could be very uncomfortable any
         way. I don't know that it really hurt any of their organs, but I'd
         think it would be very, very uncomfortable. And I think that helped
         liberate women when they threw away the corsets.
         
         SS:  Well, when did that happen? Was corset wearing- were tight corsets
         worn fairly late?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think they were wearing them up in^the First World
         War anyway.
         
         SS:  Really?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they were cinching 'em up tight and wearing- and getting the wasp
         waists. The fashions of the pre-World War I days all show little small
         waits, you know and that was the sign of great elegance and beauty.
         Regardless of how tight they had to cinch 'em, you know.
         
         SS:  You say, wasp waist? Why was that?
         
         LGC:  Well, you know how a wasps are? Hornets, they have little tiny- in
         the middle- their middle is very small, so that's a wasp.
         
         SS:  That's what they called them?
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh. So they had to have a wasp waist. They had to pinch 'em in
         in the middle and then they could be big above, and big hips, that was
         alright, but right around the middle they had to have a wasp waist.
         
         SS:  Was this something that all classes did? Would relatively working class
         families do the same thing?
         
         LGC:  Well, a lot of the women who really went out, you know and worked in
         the fields- and lots of the early women did- they would go out and
         shock the bundles and pitch hay right along with their menfolks- I
         don't think they did it. No. It was more the pseudosociety
         ladies that went in for the wasp waists. And, of course, pregnant
         women would be pretty hard to come by. They just wore the Mother
         Hubbards and covered all defects.
         
         SS:  Well, the farm families- in the average farm family, would they wear
         the tight waists.
         
         LGC:  Oh, I think not, no, most of the farm women were too busy getting
         their cows milked and the chickens taken care of.
         
         SS:  This was a town.. .
         
         LGC:  Yes, more of the middleclass town ladies that had to follow along
         a little with the society trends. Most of the farm women were just
         really pretty busy mailking cows and raising gardens and getting the
         fruit canned for winter.
         
         SS:  Was there a pretty clear distinct line, do you think, between the
         rural farm women and the city people, who were really middleclass?
         
         LGC:  Yes, yes, I think so. I think that's right, uh-huh.
         
         SS:  To talk about the differences between them; would the town middleclass
         ladies be much more involved in the social life?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, much, more, yes. They had their own bridge parties and their
         party going and often in the early days around Moscow they would hire—
         they could get hired help very cheap— and they would hire the nice lit
         tle girls from off the farms that were growing up, sixteen and seven
         teen year old girls, and they would work in these society homes of Mos
         cow and it was part of their training. They learned how to make fancy
         desserts and how to cook and how to serve.
         
         SS: would be, where we could say, these people were, you
         know and other people are working-class? And would that be the sign
         of a middle class family if they had a girl working in the home?
         
         LGC:  Yes, oh, yes. Lots of the middle class had hired girls that came in
         and worked. And of course, the— I forget what they called themthey
         called them the "upper tens". The "upper tens" you know, they
         were- they would be like the McConnells, you know, and folks like
         that. They had servant quarters even. A little special room where
         the serving girls slept. And these girls helped take care of the chil
         dren and helped prepare the meals. And they learned many arts and
         many skills cooking that their parents couldn't teach them because
         they didn't have the abundance of extra fancy food and different things
         on the farms that wa$ available in town.
         
         SS:  But there would be a lot of other middle class families that would al
         so have girls helping, like besides, say, the "upper ten"?
         
         LGC: Yes, oh, yes. There were middle class families, too, that would get
         girls, and many of the farm women too would get a young neighboring
         girl to come and help in the harvest time when they had lots of extra
         men. Just standard practice that one neighbor's young girls would go
         over and help out the other neighbors when they were harvesting and
         so on. Help take care of the children.
         
         SS:  But they wouldn't be living in the year around?
         
         LGC:  No, it wouldn't be year around in the country, no, that was largely
         a city way- or at least the town of Moscow way- you went to town and
         stayed in the home there.
         
         SS:  So it would only be during harvest, the busiest time?
         
         LGC:  Yes, that the farm women had help. That's right. Yes. Right in the
         harvest time.
         
         SS:  Would it be for maybe a month?
         
         LGC:  Yeah, a month or six weeks, something like that while they got the
         threshing and that sort of thing done. The binding and threshing in
         those days.
         
         SS:  So in other words, to really spot a middle class family at that time
         you could say that they'd be likely to have a girl living in and the
         women would wear these tight-
         
         LGC:  These wasp waists. And dress up and go to little parties. Little
         afternoon teas and parties and take part in the church work. And that
         was the middle class doings.
         
         SS:  In other words, they had leisure?
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right.
         
         SS:  And the country women didn't have that? Would that be fair to say?
         
         LGC:  I'd say that's very fair. Uh-huh. Yeah, I think that's right.
         
         SS:  What about the church work that the women were doing in those days?
         How would you characterize that? I know from- and this was on a gran
         der scale, but I know that missionary work was tremenduously important.
         And many young women who were educated went over seas.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. Well, part of the missionary work, and that fell to the Women's
         Missionary Society, they called them Ladies Aides in those days
         or Missionary Societies, and that sort of thing. And they did lots of
         sewing for the missionaries overseas. They'd make layettes for babies
         and diapers and they were continually doing some kind of work to help
         the missionaries that they sent to the fields of China and Japan and
         Africa. They were always doing something to raise money to send medi
         cal supplies or something to the missionaries that they supported.
         And then the Ladies Aids of the churches^part of their job was to keep
         the churches clean up and bring flowers on Sunday and bake cookies
         and carry on the evangelism between the families of the church and vi
         sit the bereaved and the sick and help each other in any way that they
         could. And besides raising money to carry on the work of the church,
         of the local church, they'd have bazaars, even as they do today, you
         know. And church suppers where you all brought food and then sold sup
         pers out. They'd have baked food sales and sell food and the farmers
         would bring in produce from the farm. And often the minister was paid
         in kind. He would get a hog, butchering time. He'd get half a beef.
         He'd get so many sacks of potatoes. It was just an old farm custom
         that some of the nicest things raised, you gave to the minister.
         
         SS:  Well to carry on the work of evangelism between the families- what did
         that mean?
         
         LGC:  Well, it meant: We will lo^e one another; we will comfort them in
         sorrow, and sickness and distress. We would visit them, we would bring
         and the main thing was bringing things. You brought a glass of special
         jelly, and you baked one of your very special cakes and you baked one
         of your nicest pies if there was a death in a neighboring family. And
         you called and you brought something in your hands as the positive
         proof of your sympathy. You didn't come empty handed. You brought
         something to show that you shared in their loss and in their sorrow
         and in their time of need. You were there to help them and be a spiri
         tual comforter as well as a physical comforter. You could get in and
         turn out a washing for the family if the mother NjgWS sick. You could
         bake up a big batch of bread. You could do various things like that.
         
         SS:  So, in other words this evangelism worked mainly in times of need?
         
         LGC:  That's right. Yes, that's right, uh-huh.
         
         SS:  Did it work?
         
         LGC:  Oh, I think so. Yes, I think it made the people who more than the
         people who received. It's more blessed to give than to receive. But
         you felt very grateful for your own good health and your own good for
         tune , and you wanted to share with somebody else and try to make themtry
         to comfort them in what they were going through. And I think it
         worked both ways. It was nice to know in sorrow that you were rememebered
         by other people, and it was nice to go and you gained, too.
         There was a spiritual growth on both sides.
         
         SS:  The church work- how important was it for the women as a part of their
         overall social activity? Was this the main social activity?
         
         LGC:  Yes, it was. Very definitely. And the social life of the whole com
         munity sort of centered around the churches. The young people were
         taken care of. There would be parlor games for them to play and a
         meeting ground for young couples. They could pick their partners for
         life that way. And there was an effort to keep them all within their
         own churches. That was a great thing; the young people of this church
         would get together for Hallowe'en parties, for Christmas parties for
         any holiday, there was a great getting together of the young people.
         And the little children; there were games and plays and programs cen
         tering around the youth of the church as far back as I can remember.
         One of the big purposes of the church was to help bring up the coming
         generations in the belief and the traditions of the old folks.
         
         SS:  Well, do you think that the churches in Moscow did much more of this,
         say, than the churches in the small towns that had to draw on mostly
         country folk to come in?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think maybe Moscow was more able because there were
         more people in it to start out, Kthere were more homes, more people to
         exchange, and the country folks- it was harder to get into townj a
         team of horses and a buggy, you took a couple of hours to make the trip
         in and out, so there weren't so many families in the horse and buggy
         days that could get into Moscow to take part in the church life. And
         often out in the little rural schools, the teachers would put on the
         Sunday School program Sunday morning for the children, at least, of
         the community. And sometimes there would be preaching at the schoolhouse
         Sunday afternoon. The ministers would come out and do a little
         evangelism.in the community because it was hard before the coming of
         the cars for the families - it took about half a day to get up town
         and go to church an hour and then drive back home. The whole morning
         was spent that way.
         
         SS:  So many families would just stay and not go to church?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they stayed home and didn't go. That's right until the co
         ming of the car.
         
         SS:  Didn't some of the neighborhoods have just laymen too?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, some of their own people did it. Oh, sure. Many of them.
         Many of the more devout people had a little training would get
         up and read the Bible and they'd.have little discussions and the women
         that could sing would sing. And nearly every school had some little
         reed organ of some kind and they'd put on their own little church pro
         grams on Sunday morning.
         
         SS:  Well, in Moscow, most of the women who were involved in the active church
         work, were they mostly the middleclass women who had the leisure to take
         part?
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right.
         
         SS:  How many times a week, just roughly, how often would they get together
         at the church for one thing or another? I mean, it would be more than
         just on Sunday?
         
         LGC:  Yes, yes, well, yes, they had women's clubs that met and women's associations
         that met and they had sewing cir62.es and quilting bees, you
         know and missionary societies that would meet. Oh, I imagine there
         wouldn't be a week go by but What there would be a couple of meetings
         at the church for the women. And there was always choir practice to
         go to and most of the women were singers. Lots of them would be
         women and there'd be a few men that sang in the choir. But it was
         another place for the young folks to get together, too. They'd try to
         come and
         get some of the young boys and the young girls tossing, too.
         
         SS:  Were the Ladie's Aid and Missionary Society one and the same organi
         zation?
         
         LGC:  They were practically the same. Some people called them the Ladies'
         Aid and others called them the Women's Missionary Society. Nowdays
         we call them the Women's Associations. That means all the women of
         the church and they do mostly Bible study. And then we have different
         sewing groups, too, that meet to sew for the missionaries. So that's
         the way nearly all the churches are constructed.
         
         SS:  Well, it strikes me that in those days, from what we're saying, that
         the church activity was definitely predominant in the women's acti
         vity and the men were much less involved.
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right.
         
         SS:  Is that true?
         
         LGC:  I think that's true. Yes, uh-huh, I think the women were the ones that
         really supported the church and did all the extra things about the church
         Many of them had that kept the altar decorated and washed
         the linens and the laces that they used on some of the church altars.
         It was the women that saw to all of that and that it was ready. And
         nowdays I see lots more men taking part in it, but in those days that
         was the women's perogative. And it was the women's social outlet more.
         The men had other outlets that they could go to.
         
         SS:  Do you think that it would be true to say that a lot of men had to be
         dragged to church if they'd go at all in those days?
         
         LGC:  I think so. I think there were a lot of them that had to be- there
         were some of them that had been trained to go to church and went,
         especially among the Scandinavian people. It was so much a part of
         their lives in the old country and they were very devout and got their
         families, even if they had to hook up the horses and go on Sunday mor
         ning, they did it. They'd been well versed in the work of the church.
         But among more of the American- of the people who had been Americans
         longer, been citizens of this country longer, they weren't so devout.
         But the people who had come from the Scandinavian countries- and that's
         a lot of them around the Moscow settlement- they were very devout in
         attendance to their church.
         
         SS:  Well, do you think that women by-and-large that really apply what they
         were preaching about and what they were praying about in church and in
         their everyday lives too, or do you think it was a separate- was se
         parate from what they did?
         
         LGC:  In the very early days it was very much apart, it was their reward,
         they might not have much right now at the present but in the sweet-byand-
         by they would be rewarded. You know, all the old time songs were
         along that line; about There's a Gold Mine in the Sky, you know, and
         they're all going to have their reward later on, if they had
         here on earth that was more stars in their crown. And I think for the
         very early settlers a lot of the women had that feeling, that it was
         alright to sacrifice and suffer now because they would get their re
         ward.
         
         SS:  Do you think they really believed that?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I do.
         
         SS:  Really believed—
         
         LGC:  Yes, I do. I believe that they believed that very- and when someone
         died it was always, "Well, they've gone to their reward. Try and not
         grieve because they have gone to their reward. They have mounted the
         battlements."
         
         SS:  But that changed?
         
         LGC:  Well, yes, (chuckles) in seventy-five years-
         
         SS:  Well, I don't mean that, but you said the very early ones were very
         strong on that. But what about the ones in between?
         
         LGC:  Well, I think gradually there was the tapering off and the questioning
         over the years. But I can remember as a child these women all^were
         going to get their reward in heaven and it was just alright. They'd
         do a little something here on earth, it was only temporary- all that
         would pass away and they had mansions in the sky that they were buil
         ding and the^treasures, they were laying up in heaven, where theieves
         could not break in mobs corrupt. And every one of them had that
         feeling that that was the way it was going to be. So that was-
         
         SS:  Do you think that was true of both the farm women and the middle class
         women? It's a hard question.
         
         LGC:  It's a hard question. I just don't know. But I think many of the
         farm women felt that way, that this is just a temporary- just the vail
         of tears we're passing through and we will overcome, we will have our
         reward in the next world and everything's going to be alright.
         
         SS:  What was the attitude toward death then? Were they very matter of fact
         about it, in those days? Did they just take it in stride? You
         know death is a kind of traumatic experience today, and I wonder what
         it was like then?
         
         LGC:  Oh, they suffered terribly, too, then. Women suffered terribly then in
         the loss of their children and in the loss of the loved ones. I think
         that somehow all the Balm in Gilead doesn't seem to ever assuage it
         much. We should, you know, if we want to show our faith and exemplify
         our faith in what we preach., we should be able to stand tall and strong
         at the time of death, and say, "Let's not hold this good man from his
         reward. He's earned it. he's mounted the battlements, let us re
         joice." You know, but I never saw many of them doing it. I've seen
         the later ministers do much better at it. We ve ministers in our
         Presbyterian Church that say, "We have come today to celebrate the life
         of the person that's dead." And I think that's good. I think it's a
         much healthier way, instead of, "We're here to mourn and grieve over
         the passing." I think it's better to say, "We have come to celebrate
         the life that he lived." And that makes sense to me. But it is only
         in the last twenty years that I've heard that approach. "And now to
         day we've come to celebrate, not his death, but we have come to cele
         brate the life that this good man lived."
         
         SS:  I'm wondering about whether the commonness of death in those days, as
         compared to now, would have had an effect, because people must have
         lived with it, more of the certainty, knowing that their children might
         not grow up. Knowing that death could take you at any time. I mean,
         nowdays. death only seems to become real when people become old.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  But most of the population seems to think they're immortal.
         
         LGC:  That they're going to live forever.
         
         SS:  Yeah. But in those days, I wonder how and living with death all the
         time-
         
         LGC:  And so many of the children dying and so on- I think it's like Rachel
         of old, grieving for her child and will not be comforted. I saw that
         go on and on; the grieving for their children and really, if they were
         firm believers that they had gone to this place of eternal glory, they
         should have been rejoicing. They were out of all temptation, out of
         all sorrow's way. But in all my years, I've never seen anybody that
         wasn't just grieving for their child and cannot be comforted.
         
         SS:  What about the death of older people? In those days didn't- wasn't
         there a real tendency for the old in the families to stay with the
         family and be cared for?
         
         LGC:  Yeah, they stayed with the family and there was always that talk about
         the vacant chair and "We shall meet, but we shall miss him." You know
         there will be the vacant chair. And I don't know, somehow it seemed
         that they were always missing the one that was gone. And there was
         much talk about it. Nowdays I don't think we spend so much time tal
         king about it. We know it's like the ripening of the fruit and the
         falling of the autumn leaves, it's going to happen. It's inevitable
         and we accept it better. in those days every life seemed to be
         so precious. And there's much talk about "Oh, when Grandma was alive.
         Grandma did this, and we'll never any more of those wonderful things
         she did." And that's kind of a defeatist attitude.
         
         SS:  Well, I've read about death in the 19th century, that many of the rural
         people- it was very important to them, for example, the way that their
         relative died. If they died alert and knowing what was going on and
         particularly if they had a religious
         
         LGC:  Yes, oh, yes. He was ushered right in through the pearly gates! Yes.
         
         SS:  Wasn't that something that was
         
         LGC:  Oh, especially with younger people that were alert, they all were trying
         to bridge that last few minutes aftdl seeing if the person who died had
         looked into heaven and seen what was there. I remember a young girl
         who died and the mother always was so comforted because the last words
         the girl had spoken was, "I hear the angels singing." And the mother
         said she had - "I know that my daughter looked straight into heaven.
         Because she said to me, she turned and said to me when she died, "I
         hear the angels singing."u And that was a great comfort to the mother.
         But most of them, as I say, they were no better than Rachel of old,
         they grieved for their children and could not be comforted. It only
         took time to wear it out.
         
         SS:  Was it usual when someone was dying in the family, for the family to
         attend on the person?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they all sat up with the dying person and they sometimes sent for
         the minister and the minister would come and sit up. And somebody
         dying quite a ways off they'd get on horseback and ride to sit up with
         the family of so-and-so who is dying tonight. We must go and sit with
         the family. And they'd go and sit.
         
         SS:  Would close family friends sit, too?
         
         LGC:  Yes. The close family friends would sit and sometimes the minister
         would come and sit all night to help the grief- the people through the
         grief. Yes.
         
         SS:  Well, that certainly sounds different.
         
         LGC:  Yes, it sounds different. It really does. And^some of those old-time
         traditions are so ingrained in you, you feel it has to be done. When
         we lost our little Mary Louise Perrine last spring at the nursing home,
         I went over and sat up all night til she died. I felt, I just felt I
         had to. I couldn't leave her there to die alone. And although I knew
         she wouldn't be- you have to do it alone anyway- you do it alone. But
         I thought I just had to and I went and sat up all night with her. So
         that's some of the traditions that stick with you.
         
         SS:  What about having the grandmother, for instance, or the uncle staying
         with the family when they're really quite old. Do you think that made
         a great difference to them as individuals in their last years? To be
         with the family? I'm thinking of the contrast with today when so
         people do go in the home. In those days, did that person remain a
         functioning part of the family?
         
         LGC:  Well, they stayed with them because it's just that family loyalty, you
         know. I kept my brother Bert here who grew old, and you knew him. I
         kept him here til he was eighty-six and he could no longer function, he
         no longer any control of his bladder or bowels than anything. And I
         kept him til I just couldn't do it any longer. Then the doctor or
         dered him to the nursing home. He said, "Lola, you can't do it. You've
         got to." And I grieved to have to do it. I felt I was neglecting my
         duty, that I should have seen my brother down into the grave, and not
         put him out in anursing home. And yet no^me knows better than I- I
         helped build all three of them- how wonderful they are and what good
         care- far better care than I can give them. I suppose it s just
         selfishness on our part; we don't want to give them up. We fool our
         selves into thinking we can do everything they need and they're better
         with us than if they were there.
         
         SS:  Well, in the olden days, you know in those families- did many families
         have an old member in the family they were caring for?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, that's the only place they could keep the^you know. Yes,
         and until they built the two new nursing homes and that's been- the
         first nursing home we built in about 19555. Before that they was no
         place for them to go but to the poor farm out there.
         
         SS:  Which I understand was a terrible place.
         
         LGC:  Terrible place! Yes. Yes, it was awful. And nobody with any kind of
         family pride would think of allowing their relatives to go there. Just
         people who had- just the derelicts that went there. And I think maybe
         the new nursing homes with all their lovely facilities, maybe some of
         that old stigma sticks with us. I know of some people who don't want
         to go to Latah Convalescent- oh, that's the county- you know, just be
         cause they call it Latah County Convalescent Home, and that's so ridi
         culous, because everybody pays there. Everybody, even the county cases.
         They're getting medicare- everybody pays, both of them, none of them
         are county cases.
         
         SS:  Do you think that it had an effect on the family to have the elderly
         people in the home. Nowdays, it seems like it's just the husband and
         wife and the kids. In those days it was a bigger unit.
         
         LGC:  Well, I think it gave feeling of continuity. I don t think the
         children suffered any by it. I think the children had a feeling of
         well, when we get old that's the way we are. And they could accept it.
         Here was grandpa and grandma getting a little more frail and a little
         more feeble, and they'd have to make allowances, grandma couldn't run
         and wait on 'em so much, you know. And I think it gave them a great
         feeling of continuity and a feeling of responsibility. And we've got
         to grow up and be able to take our parents' places and we've got to
         take care of our parents they way they take care of Grandpa and Grandma.
         I don't think it was bad at all.
         
         SS:  Do you think that for Grandma and Grandpa that they could function
         longer because they still had something to do for the family?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. Some of them felt very helpful- I can remember Grand
         ma- Earl's grandparents knitting stockings for my children and making
         dresses. And, oh, they took such pride in what the children were
         doing, and what they did at school. They always wanted to go to the
         school programs and see what they were doing. And it's a great sense
         of continuity. And it's a good picture of life I think for the child
         ren to grow up.see this is the process; you have the parents, and
         there are the grandparents and there are the uncles coming, and you
         have the family get together on Thanksgiying and there'll be Christmas
         and then there'll be Easter. And all the folks will come. I think
         it made the family a very important unit.
         
         SS:  Uh-huh. More so than now?
         
         LGC:  Mo»e so than mow I think. I think so.
         
         SS:  One thing I really want to ask you about; we were talking about the
         middle class and country women. Now what about the status, distinc
         tions between them? I have a feeling that there were quite a few.
         That they were rather subtle.
         
         LGC:  Yes, , yes.
         
         SS:  This sense of superiority; did it make the country people- at least it
         seemed like it was intended for the country people to feel backward?
         
         LGC:  Yes, surely, surely. And as we know in any society, there are always
         some people wanting to put somebody down, you know. And these were
         just the rural people and these children even in the school-"0h, these
         children come in from the country!" And they weren't as well kept.
         But with the coming of electricity and water on the farms, you couldn't 
         tell the rural kids from the city kids. They were all cleaned and
         scrubbed. But before that, there was a difference, a distinction. The
         children wouldn't be quite as clean. There was lots of talk about BO
         and these smelly kids, you know, and that sort of thing. There was
         more of a distinction. And the mothers who had to pick the peas, their
         kids would come to school and their dresses wouldn't be iron^ in the
         days when dresses had to be ironed and starched and stiff. And there
         was a feeling, you know, among the other kids. These are the kids from
         the country and these are the kids from the other side of the tracks,
         and that sort of thing. that's been going on a good many years!
         
         SS:  What did the country people say back to that? What did the farm women
         have to say to their city sisters who were a little uptown? Did they
         feel that they were just putting on airs? (Chuckles)
         
         LGC:  Yes. Of course I, as a country wife, was quite different, you know,
         because I couldn't have cared less! I couldn't have cared less! But
         I remember, I'll have to tell you this- this really happened. There
         was a lady lecturing at Historical Club and I was just a little,fat
         country wife and I was invited to come in to this great historical
         lecture, and this woman had toured Europe with a group of University
         children- University students, so she was going to give a talk on
         conditions in Germany and all these places she'd been. So it was how
         Germany had already gone into Poland and there was already the murder
         of the 6,000,000,000 Jews we were on the brink of war ourselves,
         and this woman got up at the Historical Club in front of all the select
         of the town and started in telling about- "Why," she said, "Hitler did
         just right, murdering that bunch of Jews." And it went on, and she
         talked for about forty minutes about these terrible Jewish people.
         So at the end she asked for questions, and I was just a guest of some
         folks, got up and said, "Well, my Christian conscience won't let me
         sit here and listen to you talk that way. This was a crime against
         humanity, and Hitler has committed an unspeakable crime, and how you
         can stand there and defend him, I don't know." So the lady took one
         look at me and she didn't answer, but she said to the hostess, "Who is
         that woman, anyway? ' I don't think I know her." See, I was just a lit
         tle upstart from out in the country. "Who is this woman? I don't think
         I know her. She must be a Jew herself, she has such a big nose!" So
         I was still standing on my feet waiting for the answer, so I said to her.
         "Well, the word is Jewess, not Jew." she is a Jew herself, she
         has such a big nose. So, I said, "The word is Jewess!" And I sat
         down. And well, the other ladies came and apologized for her to me.
         But that is what this little, fat farm wife did at that yery meeting!
         Of course I was just a guest there, I should have kept my mouth shut.
         But I couldn't do it. So, later we were in the war and England
         was standing with her back to the wall, and the FBI came to Moscow to
         investigate this lady because she'd been a spy, taking university stu
         dents through Germany, and of course the first place they sent her was
         right out- "Go out and talk to Lola Clyde, she'll tell you about the
         lady." So I told them about how she said, "I think she's a Jew."
         
         SS:  Did she teach at the University?
         
         LGC:  She was connected with the University.
         
         SS:  I thought maybe she taught German or something.
         
         LGC:  No, but she was connected with the University. That was a well remem
         bered fact around Moscow.
         
         SS:  You stood up to her.
         
         LGC:  The rest of them, of course, were too polite. She was the guest speaker.
         But I was just a guest, too,and I just wasn't going to stand there and
         lisLen to her go on that way. So, that was the response anyway. But
         I was never much inhibited, you know, by any of it.
         
         SS:  The McConnells were certainly the elite.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  What are the other families? The Days would have been the elite.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes the Days. Oh, the Adair girls; the Doctor Adair family. All
         the doctors were quite elite. Judge Forney.Old Judge Forney. Tell
         you another cute story about Old Judge Forney. He'd been the first pre
         sident of the University, you know, before they had a university. He
         said, "I had the ideal presidency," he said, "I had no faculty, no buil
         dings and best of all no lawns'.' And I was sent by the head of the
         history department with a big bunch of books to Judge Forney. And he
         lived in that house- not the first house built in Moscow, like that
         miserable books says, it was built much after a lot of the o thers.
         Anyway, I knocked at the door and Mrs. Forney came to the door, and
         you'd have thought I was a Fuller Brush man. She started in motioning
         for me to get away, I had a brief case with me, she thought I was an
         Avon peddler, I guess, Avon wouldn't have done her any good. But any
         way she motioned me to get out of there. So I just hollered in there
         at her, I said,'Mrs. Forney, these are the Judge's books, and if you
         don't want 'em I'm going to throw 'em on the porch for you, and I did,
         I just opened the brief case and threw 'em on her porch. So, Mrs.
         Forney got her books back and then she opened her door to see what it
         was about, but, I was gone by that time! I was working in the histhat's
         how long ago I was working in the history department.
         
         SS:  That sounds like a very elite attitude.
         
         LGC:  Yes, and she thought I was a peddler, motioning me, so I just dumped
         the books on her porch. And then we had Mrs.
         Hodgins, who had been an Agnew from Boise, and she was quite one of
         the elite and Permeal French, the Dean of Women, cut quite a swath
         and she set quite a pace-
         
         SS:  Do tell me a little bit about her, since you've mentioned her. I've
         heard some of the old malelalumnis of the college- Miss French, they
         certainly remembered her.
         
         LGC:  She had very strict ideas of- if a young man called on a girl three
         times she went into her little private room and asked what their in
         tentions were! And even in those days in the gay roaring '20's say-
         "I've just got the worst intentions in the world! I don't know what
         you're going to do about it, Permeal!" But she was quite a gal, al
         right.
         
         SS:  Would they dare call her Permeal?
         
         LGC:  Oh, I think so, some of them. Some of them just laughing.
         Just laughing about it a little, "Well; my intentions are^bad, iVe
         got devious designs." But anyway, one lady that entertained, they
         very lavish parties and lots of cocktails. But she gave the word to
         these little serving girls, "Be sure and put three glasses of orange
         juice on the cocktail tray, because one of them is for Dean Permeal
         French. Be sure there is the orange juice for her." But the little
         serving girls always noticed that the three orange juice glasses came
         back untouched!6oPermeal must have had a few of those little cocktails!
         (Laughter) But the little girls weren't quite that stupid, but they
         put them on anyway since they were requested to do it. But anyway, she
         was very charming and she was a large, bosomy woman, the real dean of
         women type and she sailed majestically through the halls, and laid down
         these rules and regulations for the youth of the land.
         
         SS:  How understanding do you think she was or would have been of young peo
         ple's problems? I'm talking about- the dean it seems today is expec
         ted to take care of all of these psychological problems if she's good.
         
         LGC:  All I can say is, "Dean French, how I wish you were back here now.
         How I wish you were on the campus now."
         
         SS:  Do you mean that just because of the moral—
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so.
         
         SS:  Might turn her hair white prematurely.
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right. I think it would be alright.
         
         SS:  But I mean for kids' problems. If they had a problem, do you think
         they could come to her?
         
         LGC:  No, I think not. No I should say not. She'd sail majestically, you
         know. And I think most of them thought she was quite a hypocrite. I
         think so, too. Not that I ever ran afoul of her because I was an ol
         der girl, I had been out teaching school, and I was one of the older
         girls and studious, and I knew what I was up there for. But I don't
         think she was very kind or understanding or helpful wht the problemsif
         a girl got pregnant, there was just one thing, "Get out of the University."
         Yeah, that's right, and she called-^ .an affair, and one
         of the professors was involved, she called in all the girls and gave
         them a lecture, she said, "Now you must remember, - so-and-so
         isn't quite himself." And one of the girls spoke up and said, "That's
         right Dean, with all the talent that's going to waste around here, he
         never would have picked on that girl if he had been himself!" And she
         was shocked. (Laughter) And that little girl nearly got kicked out
         of school for such a break as that.
         
         SS:  For saying that.
         
         LGC:  Yeah. But she wasn't very understanding. But she was a good politi
         cian.
         
         SS:  Was this the case of a girl got pregnant?
         
         LGC:  Yes. One of the university faculty members. So, this other little
         gal said, "Well, if he'd been himself he never would have picked on
         that one.^so much talent around!" So they've had these problems going on for a long
         time.
         
         SS:  The flapper era, now in the '20's-
         
         LGC:  Yes, in the '20's; the roaring '20's.
         
         SS:  I had the idea that morals were really changing at that time.
         
         LGC:  That's right, they were. It was the era of the hip flask, you know,
         and you go to a dance, you know, and all the boys had a hip flash.
         That was the regular adornment. And the gals had the big strings of
         beads, you know. I had been out teaching school and I was older
         when I went back to college and I graded papers in the history depart
         ment, tons of 'em
         
         SS:  This was after your kids were
         
         LGC:  No, this is when I was in college, myself, before I was married.
         
         SS:  Oh, before that?
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  You went to the University again?
         
         LGC:  Yes, this was '25 and '26 '26 and '27 when I was there, and like
         I say, I graded history- four hundred blue books maybe a week for
         history and took twenty-two houffc. One semester I took twenty-four
         hours and they took two credits away from me, and I had all A's the
         second semester and I had twenty-four hours.
         
         SS:  With what you saw about what the kids were doing on campus: was there
         lots of social life?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. Yes, there was lots of social life. There was lots of this
         queen business going on. I had no time for it, if you twentytwo
         or twenty-four hours, your nose is right at the grindstone, you
         know, and I graded for English. I graded at the English department
         for Georgia " Miller and I was on the debate team, I did drama
         tics I did two plays.
         
         SS:  Where did you live at that time? Were you in a sorority?
         
         LGC:  No, I lived at my mother's house and came in from the country every
         day.
         
         SS:  How far out was that?
         
         LGC:  It's about four and a half miles out and I walked most of the time.
         
         SS:  Really, you walked into town?
         
         LGC:  I walked a lot of the time.
         
         LGC:  Daily?
         
         LGC:  Well, not daily, sometimes- I did have an old car that we drove part
         of the time, and I caught a ride with some neighbors that went to the
         convent, sometimes. But lots and lots of times I walked because I'd
         be too late to catch a ride going home. I'd have to stay for play
         practice; I had to stay for to go on debate teams- places and for prac
         tice.
         
         SS:  Was this for one year, that you did this?
         
         LGC:  I did it one year. I went one year to Lewiston Normal; one year to
         the University of Idaho and the rest I did by correspondence and sum
         mer school.
         
         SS:  Really. There's a couple of things about- I've heard a lot- I've
         heard the men talk about the fraternities at the time and a lot of the
         country boys didn't go into fraternities; too much money..
         
         LGC:  Yeah, that's right; too much money.
         
         SS:  And they have mixed feelings about the fraternities. They were rather
         exclusive.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:  Were the sororities the same way?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, in those days they were very exclusive and they were very
         snooty and they - yes, there was lots of heartache and heartbreak
         over them. There wasn't on my account, because, like I say, I was
         twenty-six years old. I'd been a schoolteacher and I was ambitious.
         I wanted to make good grades and with all the hours I took and all the
         papers I had to grade, there was no room left for anything else.
         
         SS:  You were there for business?
         
         LGC:  Yes. I was mature. And sometimes the girls at Forney Hall would
         invite me to come and stay all night with them if it got too late and
         they knew I had so far to go home, they would invite me to come and
         stay and I did. And some of those girls are still my lifelong friends.
         Those girls that would have me come there and stay and I did that. I
         had no time for it. I went into a couple of honoraries; education honorary, debate
         honorary and so on. And the thing I had to ask wasif
         I had to memorize a lot of stuff , I don't want in, because I
         haven't the time to go memorize it. And they took me without memo
         rizing all the rigamarole and stuff.
         
         SS:  Do you know of cases where girl's hearts were broken?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. The silly, mothers back home had pounded into their
         heads they had to make sororitx- One girl tried to kill herself,
         year she hadn't made a sorority, and it was just ridiculous,
         you know. It was rididulous. And some of them- they would
         divide them up according to chuch are you going to? And if you are
         going to a certain church then you join this sorority. Gee, the
         church members would just simply be so mad at you. And there was just
         too much emphasis on it.
         
         SS:  Did that mean that the sorority and fraternity life could easily make
         it more difficult for the kid to study, and just take him away from
         his study?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. You see the big long lists of chapter names they had
         to memorize, and the national officers and then all the pledge of
         allegiance, and symbolism. Get all that stuff memorized, you know, in
         order to be initiated. I don't know how they got their lessons. If
         they were getting their history they'd have been better off. I just
         thought it was a waste of time, myself. But when my girls got that
         age, they all joined and I let them. I said, "You just go and find out
         for yourself, you know, if that's what you want." But they had it a
         little easier because they had more money and things to go on. And
         they were all real good students, and most of them could use good students.
         And that was oneAhing about the sororities, they made them
         keep their grades up and that was good, because they put them down at
         the study table and the older sisters helped the younger ones and
         all that was good in that respect and it did- I think it had a good
         effect on their morals, because if they hadn't been pretty fine little
         gals, none of the sororities would accept them.
         
         SS:  That's what I wanted to ask you. Those days, in the '20's, do you
         think that relations before marriage were really very uncommon, or-
         
         LGC:  Oh, sure they did. I think there were lots of babies born- lots of
         girls had to quit school and hurry and go home. It happened all along.
         And there were mothers covering up, they just weren't so open about it.
         But then it was such a disgrace and such a stigma and so on and so forth,
         The poor little girls would be about to kill themselves over it, and I
         think there was just as Much going on, only it was all kept so in the
         dark. And it was so much more disgraceful and terrible, you know.
         Nowdays the gals have sense enough to say they did it on purpose and
         they want to raise their babies. I think it's smart.
         
         SS:  What about Dean French? Do you think she probably knew it was going
         on and-
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, she was just sticking her head in the sand, she wanted to believe
         it didn't go on and that her little girls wouldn't think about
         it. Oh, she must have known if she had a lick of sense and all.
         
         SS:  It was a lot more difficult in those days compared to how, when it's
         sanctioned. They don't have to hide it.
         
         LGC:  They don't have to worry. No, no, they don't have to worry, and I
         think it's better. It's better for the,Jmental health, better for their
         physical health; it's better all the way around. I think they've come
         a long way, myself.
         
         SS:  Was birthcontrol information available in those days? In the '20's?
         
         LGC:  Oh, no.
         
         SS:  Could you get it in college?
         
         LGC:  Oh, no, no.
         
         SS:  Planned parenthood?
         
         LGC:  Oh, no, no. No! Heavens, I had four babies in four years and I was
         one of the smart girls! You know what I mean. And hush, hush, and
         doctors wouldn't even tell you. No. After I had four babies, why
         they wouldn't even tell me then. No. No. There was great hush and
         secrets.
         
         SS:  I didn't realize it was so bad, but it doesn't surprise me.
         
         LGC:  No. That's the way it was. No. You didn't talk about such things
         even. Uh-huh. You didn't talk about such things! I had a boys from
         India here as a foreign exchange student and so he told me, he said,
         "I'm going back to India and I'm going to make two blades of rice grow
         where only one grew before. I'm going to cut India's birth population
         in half, I'm going to cut it in half." He said, "Now, Mama, I want you
         to tell me all about planned parenthood." I said, "I'll tell you,
         honey, the way it is: you start in planning after you know there's going
         to be another baby! The babies don't know a darn thing about this
         planned parenthood. And the best thing you can do is go up there on
         the campus and ask those fraternity boys, I think they can clue you in."
         So I saw him again just a year ago. He said, "I've done pretty well,
         I have eleven sisters and they're all doctors. And in India the women
         doctors serve the women and after they've had two children my sisters
         tell them, "That's enough." And give them the means, give them the Pill."
         And I said, "I think that's just fine." And he said, "I sell Shell fer
         tilizer and fly my own plane," And he was from Madras, "And I am ma
         king three blades of rice grow for inhere one grew before. And we're
         doing alright." (Laughter) So, you see
         
         SS:  Do you think that the mores in college, now, at the University were
         different than they were in the country, say in the rural areas around?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. Yes, I think that the girls out in the country- they
         were more intent on just getting a man- and dragging sane man in oUd
         marry him and then they were all settled right there. They weren't
         going on to college. They weren't going out for careers. They wanted
         to become a farmer's wife, most of them, and most of them just did that.
         
         SS:  Did that mean that they were much less likely to be fooling around,
         say before marriage? In the country?
         
         LGC:  Oh, no, I think it went on too, every, But most of the gals seemed
         to think that was one way of catching a nice young farmer was just to
         get pregnant and by golly, we'll just have a shotgun wedding, and
         there'd we'd be. They had her made.
         
         SS:  They were common, I know that.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. I think it was just as common. I think it was just as com
         mon then as it is now. I really do. I don't think they need to de
         cry the young people. I think they just know better now. They are
         freer, they are more open, they're smarter now.
         
         SS:  Do you think there was a difference in attitude- I'm thinking now about
         the people who were high status and stuff; was there a difference
         between those who had high status, like the Mc Connels, who had de
         finitely achieved high status, and those who were kind of the social
         climbers? Who were upwardly mobile.
         
         LGC:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Do you think there was a difference in them- I mean, in their attitude?
         I have been told by some people, that people who were genuinely high
         status didn't try to show it. They weren't ostentatious, but other
         people who were up and coming were always trying to put the other people down.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think that's true in any society. We had real ladies and
         gentlemen in town; just real ladies, fine people, fine, good , Christian
         women and! Clarice Sampson's mother was one of them. Mrs. Moody
         was one of the kindest, sweetest, Christian women ever lived. And
         they were always helpful and kind, and doing the right thing because
         it was right. And trying to be good Christians and good neighbors and
         they weren't too concerned about the little fashionable tricks and
         traits. There were a lot of good, fine, bright, brilliant women. And
         with the coming of the University they really brought in a new dimen
         sion. Lots of those fine early-day professor's wives were smart and
         kind and gracious and highly intelligent; well-bred. And they brought
         a new dimension into the community.
         
         SS:  Were they very involved in the community, or were they—?
         
         LGC:  Well, for a while there was a great division about this town and gown
         stuff, you know. The town women would have a society one time- and
         then the faculty women. And then one year we were going to have a
         faculty wife for president and the next year the town women get to
         have it. You know, they went on- well, exaggerating the difference
         between town and gown. But when I was a young farm wife and my child
         ren were growing up, I found that I had far more in common with the
         faculty wives than I did with the town wives. We were more interested
         in the same things. We were interested in bettering the conditions
         for everybody's children. That's why I worked hard on the health unit.
         had no health unit here. And when I had taught in the Normal School
         in South Idaho, we just routinely vaccinated every child. Gave them all
         their shots right at the school. And when my children started to school
         here they had none of that. So I started questioning too and many of
         the faculty wives had come from places where sure, just routinely
         went through the schools and vaccinated them. We had dentists come
         out and fill the childrens' teeth right there at the school for fif
         ty cents a child. And if anybody couldn't pay for it, the school paid
         for it. And we bought all the books in the normal school where I
         taught. And there were a lot of things. And I started a PTA here in
         Moscow and was the first president. Because, I thought, "My goodness,
         that's one thing I can use my education and my training and the things
         I'd seen done out in other places."
         
         SS:  When was that, when the PTA started?
         
         LGC:  Well, they'd had a little Mothers' Club before that. I think it must
         have been about '35, probably. And about that time we put in the Heal, 
         Ed Snowman, my next door neighbor down here was county com
         missioner, and so the first thing we did was put me on for the Health
         Unit; to head a committee.
         
         SS:  What you're saying then is, it seems to me, that the faculty women in
         tended to be more interested in those things—
         
         LGC:  That's right. More interested. And they were the people I could count
         on. As head of PTA I'd get the faculty- they would vote 100 percent
         for these things. And the town women took less interest. Lot of them,
         of course, were picking peas and gone all day and couldn't come to PTA.
         
         SS:  But even the middle class-
         
         LGC:  Even the middle class they attended. "Well, my husband- well, I can't
         take a stand on that, it'd hurt my husband's business." YOu know.
         The faculty were the ones that really saw the need for these things.
         
         SS:  So there was a certain amount of controversy over having the Health
         Unit and that kind of thing?
         
         LGC:  Oh, of course, there was. Yes, there was a controversy.
         
         SS:  Is that because-
         
         LGC:  It was socialized medicine and^were sticking out our necks, and yet
         we were just getting over the Depression- just coming out from underwhen
         nobody had had doctors. And so we were all just struggling along.
         But this is something we had done back in the school and it was a won
         derful thing. And I worked hard on that: getting the PTA going, because
         there were many things we could do. And we ran an exchange there
         at the school, we'd bring in all the outgrown overshoes, for instance,
         and put them in big boxes and some other mother could take those over
         shoes our kids had outgrown. We didn't sell 'em, we j ust gave them.
         We had a room set up. We had a room there of patterns little dres
         ses for girls. We got the little patterns and when they got too small
         we took 'em in there and the next mother could check 'em out. And remnanents
         of clothing. We'd bring them in. We had great button boxes.
         The library now has a button box where people go and get buttons. Well,
         we had it at PTA. They'd go in and pick out buttons. Warm winter coats
         and caps. Instead of giving them to a rummage sale we hauled them in
         the school and PTA had women volunteers and you'd go in and see if
         some of these coats and caps would fit your kids. And it made
         it more democratic because everybody went; we all went. And it wasn't
         that we'd gone to a rummage sale and bought 'em for next to nothing, we
         went in there and we took somebody else's clothes for our kids and gave
         ours to somebody else smaller. And those were all good,progressive
         things.
         
         SS:  Really?
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh. Good, progressive things. I put in the hot lunch program, too.
         The government was just starting in to sponsor it. And there was a
         big argument the school board that, "Heavens, wasn't that something. What more would
         the district have to do?" And so, I served
         on that committee to put in the first hot lunch and helped cook the
         first lunch.
         
         SS:  When do you think that was?
         
         LGC: That was about '35, too. '35 and '36, along in there. Maybe '34.
         
         SS:  Were there some people that didn't see the use in the PTA at the time?
         When it started?
         
         LGC:  Oh, . We were a bunch of upstarts, and they didn't want any
         PTAs around there. Yeah, that was nogoodl
         
         SS:  Why would they not want the PTA?
         
         LGC:  We would be- the next thing we'd be wanting more new schools. And that
         was right! We went out and carried the ball for new schools. Of course
         we did. We wanted a new high school and we got it! And all those were
         good things. And all that came about through PTA work. And it
         was good work. And we had fun at the same time. We did a lot of good
         things. And the thing that made it so important was, it was the peak of
         the Depression. People were still— and we put in the lunch and milk.
         Everybody had to have milk. Give them the half pint of milk, right
         there, and anybody couldn't afford it, why let the government subsidize
         it! And, of course, oh, my, that was just terrible. But we did it in
         spite of them anyway. And now they ^buldn't get along without the hot
         lunch, you know. But there was lots of objecting ye$. I remember the
         superintendent of schools saying to me, "Well, Lola, the first thing
         that you'll be wanting, you'll be wanting us to subsidize mothers to
         have babies!" And so, I said to that superintendent, "I could just
         use a little subsidy myself I I have four bright ones for you, and I
         feel the government should subsidize me; I've got four of 'em for you.
         And they're all going to be good, smart children and get along in schooll"
         Wasn't that nasty? He said to me, "You'll be wanting to subsidize these
         parents for having children." I said, "I could use a little subsidy
         right now!"
         
         SS:  So that's another example of really mostly women doing the work, isn't
         it?
         
         LGC:  Yes, yeah. There weren't so many women work ing then, the married women
         weren't teaching. And we did all that PTA business and that was
         good. And we would volunteer our time and go up there and help 'em
         pick out the coats and the overshoes that were outgrown we kept
         track of it. We checked out the patterns.
         
         SS:  Now, the distinction between the university women and the local women
         we were talking about; that was still existing in the *30*s?
         
         LGC:  Oh, vt was still there, because even in PTA they wanted to have a fac
         ulty- they wanted to write this into the constitution, when we wrote
         it up: One year we'll have a faculty wife and the next year a town wife
         and they did that a couple of times. Finally, I said, "That^s just ri
         diculous. What we are talking about is mothers, we're not talking about
         We're talking about mothers of children. And what dif
         ference does it make which mother? Where they are? A mother of a child
         is going to be president." So we got that done away with. And then,
         of course, after the war the Red Cross work and everything came along,
         we quit a lot of those activities, because then we became accep
         ted. It was accepted that they'd have hot lunches. It was accepted.
         And then a little later after that they consolidated and we had consolidation
         in the schools, and that was another ball of wax. And then
         I went on the school board, and I helped put through the books for the
         children. That we would furnish books and rent them to the children.
         We wouldn't give them to them for nothing; we would rent the school
         books to the children. And that was good.
         
         SS:  But you would say, that you counted more on the faculty wives as being
         progressive?
         
         LGC:  That's right. And really the people you could count on to help you in
         anything that was good and forwarding looking for the community, you'd
         get the faculty wives to help you, and they would.
         
         SS:  Was there much— do you think there was much active antipathy between
         faculty wives and town wives?
         
         LGC:  Well, yes, in the early years. And even yet there is some feeling, you
         know. "Well, we're not educated. These faculty women, they-" You
         know, I think there's still a little even, you know, I
         tell them I belong to the League of Women Voters, oh, my, some of the
         old-time women think that almost as bad as being a communist!
         
         SS:  Really?
         
         LGC:  And I told them that I belong to Common Cause. The other day someone
         was asking me about who I was going to vote for, and I said, "Well,I
         don't know, because I haven't studied it. I belong to Common Cause."
         Well, these dear, little women at the church said, "Isn't that some
         kind of a communist front?"
         
         SS:  Well, was the League going in the '30's?
         
         LGC:  No. No, we didn't get it going until the '40's. We didn't get it going
         til the '50's, into the first of the '50Ts. The League was going about
         49 when I was on the school board, because I joined it then. We ,wanted
         to get tiflfough a bond issue and those women got out there and just
         worked like dogs getting that bond issue through. It was League of
         Women Voters that put it through.
         
         SS:  For a school?
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh. The school. Yeah.
         
         SS:  Was the League a very controversial group here, to start with?
         
         LGC: Was there much opposition to it? It certainly seems like uppity wo
         men, you know, getting together and making up their own minds about
         these things.
         
         LGC:  Well, no, I always thought it was great stuff.
         
         SS:  I certainly agree with you.
         
         LGC:  I thought it was great stuff. A lot of the women though had been
         brought up, you know, in this conservative Republicanism and they took
         a look at League of Women Voters and said, "Why, they're all Democrats!"
         But that isn't true, you know. Of course that's not true- and if they've
         become that way- I haven't - I don't go any more at my age- but if they've
         allowed it's their own fault, they should have all been in there pit
         ching equally! They expect them all to come. It's open to everybody.
         And if Republican women sat back and didn't go, and Democrats dominated
         it, well, who's fault was it? But I have heard that from conservative
         Republican women.
         
         SS:  Were the college women very active in the churches, too? As active as
         the local women?
         
         LGC:  Yes, lots of them. Yes, most dedicated, especially in the earlier times.
         And, oh, heavens, they couldn't run their churches without'faculty women.
         
         SS:  Oh, really?
         
         LGC:  Oh, heavens, our faculty women really carry on the brunt of the church
         work
         
         SS:  Did they in the earlier years, too?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they were always dedicated, devoted people from the faculty down
         there pitching. When I think of the Dean Eldridges for example, they
         were the backbone of the Presbyterian Church. The Axtels; just back
         bones! Oh, and when you are at Lewiston you should talk to Mildred
         Axtel . Her husband is on the faculty at Lewiston Normal. I think
         he retired now. Hensley: Kenneth Hensley- do you know them?
         
         SS:  No, I don't. Her name is Hensley, isn't it?
         
         LGC:  Yes. Mildred Axtel Hensley. And their name would be in the phone book.
         66: What were her parents ?
         
         LGC:  Well, her father and mother were on the faculty of the University of
         Idaho. He was a foreign language teacher and great Presbyterian,
         hardworking people. Brilliant people. Their five daughtersall
         of them Phi Beta Kappa. Mildred is a Phi Beta Kappa. She is just
         a brilliant girl. And she'd have a little time now. Her husband waswell,
         he was vice president over all the whole thing down there. He
         was superintendent of all the buildings and grounds and he was vice pre
         sident of everything.
         
         SS:  Okay. I want to ask you, too, about the revivals in those days. I've
         heard some interesting things about Bulgin and the Bulgin revival. I
         don't know if you remember Bulgin or not. But there were evidently
         quite a few- and what I was wondering about is- I've noticed this fee
         ling of a distinction- a real distinction, between those people that
         seemed to be in favor of more emotional revivals- evangelical type of
         religion and the others who -
         
         SIDE D
         
         LGC:  Presbyterians weren't much for that. They were more like, well,
         others- more splinter religions would have big revival meetings and
         even put up a tent, you know, and have a sawdust trail. A sawdust floor
         in a tent and big bleachers,and they'd have kind of camp meetings even
         at the foot of Paradise Hill, I can remember when they had a big tent
         there for revival meetings. And my father didn't even encourage any
         of us children to go down to the revival meetings. He said, "Oh, they
         get carried away. Some of them." But there were many people like
         Billy Sunday, you know, and he was more like Billy Graham, I think.
         
         SS:  Was he here in this area, do you think?
         
         LGC:  I don't remember if he ever came here or not. I think he did. I
         think Billy Sunday was in Moscow at one time. But my father had
         very little empathy toward the revival meetings. He thought that re
         ligion and Christianity was something that lived in your heart for
         ever and that you didn't need to be revived. It was there all the
         time and you go on in your way and let your light so shine before men
         that you didn't need to revive it. And that was alright, too. But
         all the Presbyterians have generally been a lot like that, but many
         others.believed in, you know- The Southern Baptists, Shouting Baptists
         and Holy Rollers and there.elements like that, maybe they didn't have
         a church even in Moscow, but they'd come in and have a big revival
         meeting and there'd be a big fanfare and lots of good music and singing,
         And lots of people went to hear the good singing and the good music.
         And some people liked a little sensationalism and preaching, you know.
         
         SS:  Entertainment.
         
         LGC:  Yeah, that's right. But the Presbyterians have always been rather
         conservative, and it was something- "Let your light so shine before
         men that all men can see it." And that's the better way.
         
         SS:  I think I've heard people say that they didn't believe that it was
         a real authentic change, that it was something that would just last
         for a little while-
         
         LGC:  Yes, lots of times it was thatjway, you know. Lots of times it was
         that way, they were carried away by the emotionalism of the crowd
         and everybody walking down, you know to confess their sins. Some of
         them didn't have any sins to confess! They were pretty good old peo
         ple, you know! And they didn't need to get so carried away. But
         was one form of entertainment- we must remember this, looking
         back, they had no television. They had no telephones. They had no
         radios. They were just absolutely devoid of things to entertain them.
         The little school programs where the kids got up was about all they
         could really count on. Or little debate societies or little literary
         societies among their own people. And that was the sum total of their
         entertainment. So anything going on-
         
         SS:  Would attract people.
         
         LGC:  Would attract people.
         
         SS:  You know, we were talking about religion and I have to ask you about
         Frank B. Robinson and about Psychiana.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  What was your opinion of him and his work?
         
         LGC:  Well, I thought he was really a very kind hearted, you know, nice
         person. The first person- any kind of a drive, Red Cross, any drive
         in town, everybody would ask Frank Robinson and he'd head the list;
         $100. He was always ready to help. But I don't really think he be
         lieved in his won Psychiana business, because he used to laugh at
         some of the men and say, "Well, there's lots of fools in the world!"
         Something to that effect. And he kept it rather quiet in town. He
         didn't like to sell the copies of his stuff on the local level. He
         sold it around the world, the lessons of it. But, he didn't- he was
         very, very kind and a very fine citizen. And I loved his beautiful
         wife, and I loved the kids. Yeah, they were fine kids, both of them.
         And I loved Mrs. Pearl Robinson. She was just a lovely, gracious,
         beautiful lady. And I never studied the religion much you know.
         
         SS:  Well, do you really feel that he did not believe in what he was tea
         ching? The Psychiana teachings?
         
         LGC:  Well, I never really talked enough to him, but I don't think, you
         know all these flamboyant advertisements about, "I talked with God.
         Literally and actually, I did." We all talk with God, with our Gods,
         you know. And I'm sure Frank Robinson talked with his God, you know,
         because he did so many lovely, fine, openhearted, generous things.
         But, too many people kind of misinterpreted what he was saying, I
         think, too. I never made a study of the lessons. I never got them,
         I did read his Crucified Gods Galore, and I agreed with him. Nearly
         every religion has it's own form of Jesus Christ who was sacrificed
         and died to save the world. And he was so right. There were lots of
         them. And lots of them with almost the same name as Jesus Christ.
         And there was nothing wrong with that Crucified Gods Galore And
         Doctor Drury who was our minister all that time, he thought Frank
         Robiiison was an awfully smart, brilliant man, and he agreed with him
         about- there were many Christs who hav4 been crucified. That history
         had a lot of them.
         
         SS:  They discussed religion quite often.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, they talked religion together ' lot, and were very good
         friends. And very friendly about it. It was very open and fine and
         intellectual discussions they had. I read his Blood on the Tail of a
         Pig, and I thought that was inferior to his Crucified Gods Galore.
         And the strange autobiography of Frank Robinson- well, I enjoyed the
         family so much and I'm such an admirer of all the fine things he did,
         that I just am not a fit person to talk about his religion, because I
         never read it. I never studied it. I did read, like I say, his Cru
         cified Gods Galore and I agreed with him- there were plenty of gods.
         
         SS:  A Strange Autobiography, I have read, and I thought a very interesting
         book. And the whole matter of his prosecution was his statements on
         his passport, which he said George Lanphere brought against him, was
         a very bitter episode it seems to me. And he suffered a great deal
         in that. And I'm just wondering what your impressions were in reading
         that book- Why, was there this strong antagonism between the two men?
         
         LGC:  They each ran a newspaper, you see. George Lanphere ran the- was it
         called Daily Star Mirror?
         
         SS:  Right.
         
         LGC:  And he ran the News Review, Mr. Robinson ran the News Review. And there
         was lots of rivalry. And George Lapiphere was a Democrat, and his paper
         always upheld the Democratic side of everything. And the News Review
         was more Republican.
         
         SS:  Was he a Democrat?
         
         LGC:  Yes. Oh, yes, very strong. And, of course, it was Depression years
         too, and there was lots of bitterness over Hoover and all that sort of
         thing. And it was the New Deal and everybody was out whooping it up,
         you know for Franklin Roosevelt and the New Look on everything. And
         the CCC camps and the WPA work projects, and it was quite controver
         sial between them, you know. But I know that during- Doctor Drury
         headed Red Cross and I worked on the board with him all those years
         through the Depression. And he said there was no cloth to wrap a
         baby in- they'd take newspapers, a newborn baby and wrap them in a
         newspaper to protect them. No milk; they didn't want them to sell
         milk in gallon cans for twenty-five cents, there might be germs in it.
         Well, Doctor Drury says, "Let them have the milk! The mothers can
         boil it if they're afraid of germs. I don't think this milk's going
         to hurt anybody. Be as clean as you can;-put it in a gallon can and
         let 'em have it, and have it for a quarter." And they did that sort
         of thing. And whenever Doctor Drury needed some extra money for the
         Red Cross, he went to Frank Robinson and he was never turned down.
         We always got money when we needed it for things like that. And those
         are- and that's Christianity in action. Isn't it? I told you the
         sweet story, the best story of all. We had a woman here and they
         called her the Galloping Goose in Moscow. She was a very retarded,
         you know and very odd and she walked on the road every place, just
         hiked up and down. And whenever she'd see a lovely free meal some
         place, she was hungry, she would go in and eat. So one day she was
         in the Moscow Hotel and the table was all set to entertain the state
         legislators, you know. They had lovely little :salads at all the places
         and she saw that beautiful food and went in and sat right down. And
         of course, the busboys and people came running and the heads of it
         came running to usher poor little old Ida right out of there, you
         know, so she wouldn't disgrace the meeting. And Frank Robinson rose
         in his majesty ' six feet four, two-hundred and twenty-five
         pounds and he just waved the busboys away, he said, "Ida is my guest
         today. She'll sit beside me and bring me her bill." And I love it,
         I just love it. That put every in the proper perspective. I
         will pay her bill!" People like that aren't all bad, are they?
         
         SS:  No. (telephone rings)
         
         conversation resumes-
         
         SS:  well accepted by a lot of the business men on Main Street. He
         wasn't solid on Main Street. A lot of those people just didn't seem
         to like him, and I wonder if it was because of the polarization over
         this business with Lattphere- whether that is why he was not liked
         by a lot of people.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think part of it was that. Now one very nice
         thing that speaks so well of him is that when he had this trouble
         over entering the United States, one of the people who really defended
         him was Senator Borah. And Senator Borah wasn't given to just de
         fending anybody, but he certainly went to bat for him and saw that
         Dr. Robinson was- And he was really a very fine citizen and a very
         interested person. And like I say, I don't understand about his re
         ligion because I didn't read it. I never did read his lessons that
         he had- they were supposed to be lessons that you studied, and I never
         read them. But the people that worked for him all said how good he
         was -
         
         SS:  To work for?
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  They did feel he was good to work for?
         
         LGC:  Yes. And the Mc Goffs lost a little boy out toward the golf course,
         out toward Robinson Lake in the big spring- when the spring freshets
         were going off, and everybody- all the neighbors came and looked and
         they couldn't find him and Dr. Robinson at his own expense hired a
         plane to come down and fly low over the wooded area out there and
         they found the little boy. And Dr. Robinson saw that the family was
         really hard up and he hired Mr. McGoff to come on into town and help
         him down at the Psychiana Publishing House. And Mr. McGoff worked
         there until he died. And he was awfully good to them. As I say, all
         my relationships with him were just on that order. When we needed
         something for Red Cross, the first person we thought about was go
         to Dr. Robinson and see what he'd do for us.
         
         SS:  What about some of the religious denominations in town? He claimed
         that there were some that were just really disliked him.
         
         LGC:  Yes, some of them were very bitter and they'd get up and pound the
         pulpits, you know and that sort of thing. And even in our own church-
         Mrs. Robinson and the children all belonged there; were members, and
         like I say, our Doctor Drury was very personally friendly with him
         and agreed about the Crucified Gods Galore, he said, "He is so right
         about it. Many of the great religions of the world, they all have
         the crucified God who died for humanity." And, he said, "It's sym
         bolic." And I know what he means. But, anyway, when we built the
         new church, they wanted a spire- a dome- that wasn't the point- they
         wanted a donation from everybody, so they went up and asked Dr. Ro
         binson. He said, yes, he'd give them ten thousand dollars, but he
         would put on a spire. The spire that pointed to heaven. And it would
         be dedicated to his lovely wife; lovely, gracious, Pearl Robinson.
         And our minister and I, we both agreed, it would be alright. But my
         there was some of the old-time, the old fundamentalists there; "Well,"
         one of them said, "he'll want the sign Psychiana. He'll want to put
         a big sign on top, saying Psychiana, and flashing on and off all
         night!" And they wouldn't take the money.
         
         SS:  $10,0001
         
         LGC:  Yes, and that was a lot of money in those days. Oh, gee, the whole
         church only cost $42,000, so $10,000 would have done a lot of good.
         And he said, "I'm not a member of your church, but I would do it
         honoring my wife and my children." And I thought there was nothing
         wrong with that. But he wasn't asking for this sign, people interpre
         ted it that way. And every time they looked at that spire they'd
         have to say Psychiana Robinson gave it to us. Did I tell you that this
         Paul the brother to J. C. and the meaning of the News.
         They are Christian Scientists, of course, and J. C. past editor
         of the Christian Science Monitor and of course, that newspaper is like
         the Manchester Guardian. If you see it in the Christian Science Moni
         tor, you know it's right! It and the Manchester Guardian, we swear
         by 'em, you know. Well, he wants to come and write a story about
         Psychiana Robinson. He's a great believer and a great admirer of
         him and he studied him. He can just quote me long- oh, I have the
         loveliest letters here from Paul and I must write- I couldn't
         have him two years ago because my brother was d. ying- my other brother,
         but I've got to write and tell him that if he wants to write
         up about Psychiana, come on, now's a good -
         
         SS:  I saw him when he was here -
         
         LGC:  Oh, did you?
         
         SS:  Yeah, I ran into him at the museum. If he comes back, let me know,
         because I'd like to interview him, when he's here, because he's the
         only true believer I've run into.
         
         LGC:  He's a real believer. And Paul [k^ch wrote to me just the other day,
         I'd lost his address. Now just the other day I had another letter
         ' wanting to know if he could come now and do it. And I've got to write
         and tell him, "Come on, and write about Psychiana Robinson." And I
         did give him Doctor Drury's address and he'd written to Doctor Drury
         and Doctor Drury says,"I have the only complete file of the lessons
         that Dr. Robinson sent out. And you'd be welcome to come and borrow
         them from the library." Because he gave them I think to Huntington
         library. And he can get 'em there and use them. So I've got to write
         to Paul and tell him to come now, that he's welcome to come and stay
         with me and write the book.
         
         SS:  Was his wife really devoted to him?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so.
         
         SS:  It seemed in the book that's how he presents her.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think she was very devoted to him. And he certainly lavished
         everything on her. And I remember the little girl was so sweet- so
         well liked. My daughters liked her so much. And there was a need
         in town for a youth center, someplace where the kids could get together
         and say, those kids went down and talked to Dr. Robinson and he gave
         them one! He furnished it! He set it up! He got the phonographs to
         play dance records so they could dance. Set the whole thing up. The
         first youth center in Moscow was Robinson's.
         
         SS:  Do you remember the local opposition to that? (church spire)
         
         LGC:  Yes, I remember. I remember that our church wouldn't take the $10,000
         because they were the very conservative old-time people.
         
         SS:  Some of the others though, didn't they denounce him from the pulpit?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, yes, they'd be pounding the pulpit.^ Lots of them. Lots of
         them. But I never went along with it, I thought that he was a really
         very kind, very fine man and I always remember that standing up in the
         Moscow Hotel and assuming responsibility for our poor little lady that
         they were going to put out.
         
         SS:  Did he have a stubborn streak?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think he did. Yes, he had strong likes and dislikes, you know
         too.
         
         SS:  Do you think those he was opposed to he was really strongly—
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so.
         
         SS:  This woman you mentioned. What did you call her? The woman at the
         hotel that time that was retarded?
         
         SS:  Yes, we called her the Galloping Goose, because she walked all over
         the country, and her name was Ida. And she was rather retarded.
         
         SS:  Was she around here for very long?
         
         LGC:  Yes, oh, yes, she was quite a fixture here for maybe thirty
         years.
         
         SS:  How did she manage to get by? Was she living with parents?
         
         LGC:  No, she'd come all the way from Sweden or Norway, from back there.
         And she worked, she did daywork mostly. She'd go out and clean peo
         ple's houses and that sort of thing. But those depression days, I'm JUST
         sure she was hungry and she all this nice table set so lavishly and
         she was going in and she often went to church suppers and things where
         she didn't really belong and would eat, you know. But then they made
         her welcome at the churches, you know.
         
         SS:  Maybe I should get going. It's time for you to get supper.
         
         LGC:  Well, I've got supper all ready. I got it in the kettle out there. I
         got it in my crockpot. I got it ready. I've got supper ready, so I'm
         all set. (machine was shut off at this point)
         
         SS:  Blacks couldn't stay at the Moscow Hotel, that was typical of attitudes
         in those days. What do you know about the ?
         
         LGC:  Well, I really don't know. I really don't know. There have always
         been some people, and I imagine there are yet, you know, that would be
         prejudiced. I have never felt any prejudice in any way. I went to
         school with our one and only Negro family, with the children from that
         family. And all of us were just crazy about them. They could
         run so fast and were good to the little kids.
         
         SS:  The Settles?
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh, the Settles. And we justthought they were wonderful. And all
         of us girls just cried and cried when the Settle boys quite school,
         because they- the big boys wouldn't be able to run us through and play
         Black Man with us any more.
         
         SS:  Black Man?
         
         LGC:  Yeah, we played Black Man.
         
         SS:  What was that?
         
         LGC:  Oh, they'd run out to catch you, you know, and you'd run from one base
         to another. And then the man out in the middle he was supposed to be
         a black man. But the boys, they'd laugh just as hard as anybody about
         playing Black Man and they'd be the Black Man, too, you know. And then
         they'd
         sometimes take a hold of our hands and^run 'em through and they'd
         help the little ones get through and not get caught.
         
         SS:  You mean the older boys?
         
         LGC:  The Settle boys.
         
         SS:  The older boys lied to play with the girls.
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh. And we all played together. And I remember us girls crying
         when the Settle boys quite school because they wouldn't be there to
         play Black Man with us anymore.
         
         SS:  They quit to ?
         
         LGC:  Yeah, they moved. They moved to to town. They moved off the farm
         they'd been farming. Moved into Moscow. And boy, we just felt awful
         bad that the Settles boys had left us.
         
         SS:  Do you think they were fully accepted out there? Among the people?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think out there on the farm- I remember many people- I remember
         one little- later on, who was my special friend
         too. you know. He was on the school board down in another school dis
         trict and there were a couple of other gentlemen on the board and this
         little girl went out there to teach said, "Well, I have three men on
         my school board, and the only white man among them is Gene Settles."
         And he was very fair and very fine with everybody. Of course, my folks
         had no feeling of discrimination. Gene worked for us when I was a
         little girl and every evening he was planning for the state examinations
         to pass the eighth grade examination to high school, so my mother
         would set him down every evening and help him learn all the state and
         county officials and help him with his mathmatics and help him with the
         things so he could pass. And he did, he passed. And, oh, my mother
         was so happy because Gene had passed the examination; could go on to
         high school.
         
         SS:  Would they go to the dances?
         
         LGC:  Well, as a little girl I never went to the dances, so I really don't
         know. I really don't know. But they were certainly awfully well ac
         cepted out at that little rural school. I was in classes the two
         younger boys; with Booker T. Washington Settles and who later becsme
         a teacher at Carver College, and married a woman who was a profes
         sor there. They were both professors and came out here to Idaho to
         summer school a couple of summers. And she was a gracious lady, too,
         in her own right. And I think Moscow has always been very, very
         friendly toward especially the Settles family. They were just high
         class farm people.
         
         SS:  There were some hard things about living.
         
         LGC:  There are sorrowful bad things and we're not so sorry.
         
         SS:  About leaving.
         
         LGC:  About leaving. If it were all the birds and the flowers on Paradise
         Hill, we'd want to stay forever. Now that's right.
         
         SS:  You know when I was asking you about the size of families.
         
         LGC:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS:  The thing I didn't finish asking you about was what happened in time.
         Now when your generation was growing up and you were having children,
         didn't you tend to have smaller families than your parents had?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, I think so. I definitely think so. I got some information
         from a fine old druggist down in Genesee and when I was pregnant with
         the fourth child he stopped me on the street and he said, " ., I think
         you've had enough babies." And I said, "Ive been thinking so myself."
         He said, "You come in here and I will show you what to use." And he
         got me one of those little rubber contraceptives deals. And the jelly
         that went with it.
         
         SS:  A diaphragm.
         
         LGC:  A diaphragm is what it was; and I used it. And there were four and
         that was it. And four was enough.
         
         SS:  Do you think that this was something that was not only you, but was
         common to many of the women who were your contemporaries?
         
         LGC:  Oh, sure. Many of them,1 they didn't know what to do. It was such a
         secret and the doctors wouldn't tell you and there was no planned pa
         renthood. There was no nothing.
         
         SS:  But still that change. I mean, it must have been hard to find out or
         they wouldn't have-
         
         LGC:  We needed to find out. And I even went to these health units that I'd
         helped organize and start, and well, they were very reticent. They
         couldn't tell you.
         
         SS:  They were afraid?
         
         LGC:  They were afraid, I think. And my doctor, the doctor who delivered
         these children one right after the other, he said only to me, "Oh,
         Mother, you're just the kind of a girl who should have lots of babies.
         You can have them easily. You've had no trouble. And look at the fine,
         bright, husky children you have. You should have a lot of 'em!" That's
         what my doctor said to me. And so I said to the doctor, "Yes, we al
         ways are able to pay our doctor bills." Said I to him! Yeah, isn't
         that something?
         
         SS:  But just in a way- isn't that a way that men kept women in the home?
         
         LGC:  Yeah, kept 'em pregnant.
         
         SS:  Taking care of the kids and them.
         
         LGC:  Yeah, hide their shoes and keep 'em pregnant! (Chuckles) That was
         kind of a joke, you know. Hide their shoes and keep 'em pregnant!
         
         SS:  Hide their shoes so that they can't go and be in the world.
         
         LGC:  That's right, and keep 'em pregnant.
         
         SS:  try and look at it historically: do you think there was some sort of
         revolution that went on in your generation that the women got wise and
         made a?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think there was. I just know there was, because— The Depres
         sion hit and there was no premium on big families then. Women were
         just frantic when they found they were pregnant again. And how were
         they going to feed 'em? How were they going to pay the doctor bill?
         It was a frightening, terrifying experience. And I think all of them
         just determined, "Now there's got to be a way out of this."
         
         SS:  Do you think it was generally the woman who decided not to have a big
         family rather than a joint decision? It was a personal decision.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think . women had to do it, I think so. I de
         finitely think so.
         
         SS:  It wouldn't be something that the husband and wife would sit down over
         supper and just have a big discussion about?
         
         LGC:  No. I think not. I think not.
         
         SS:  Then it was really as the women'fs feminist movement would say was ta
         king control of your own body.
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right. Yes, I think that's right. I'm sure of that.
         
         SS:  Now one more thing; the difference between a farm family again and
         these middle class town families we were talking about before: Would
         these middle class ladies in Moscow in the teens and twenties, were they
         more likely to have smaller families than the country people?
         
         LGC:  That's right. They seemed to have a smaller family^,
         
         SS:  Do you think that was their own way of these women to trying to carve
         out more independence for themselves and to have more freedom?
         
         LGC:  I think so, I think maybe. And they had intended all along to have
         fewer children. And I don't know that they were more intelligent.
         Maybe they had access to more knowledge. They got out among 'em, they
         talked together. And over the years there were certain doctors who
         would perform abortions, you know. And they were knowledgeable of
         where to go to find these doctors. But rural women didn't have
         access to that kind of information. And I think that that's right.
         
         SS:  And this would probably be true of Moscow as compared to a small town
         like Troy or Genesee or Kendrick, would be more like the country?
         Right?
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Bigger families.
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right.
         
         SS:  But ink city like Moscow, they were more exposed to these newer cur
         rents.
         
         LGC:  That's right. To these newer thoughts. I think that's true. I think
         that's very true. But the Depression wasn't all bad, you see because
         out of it grew some forward looking things. Hot lunch program for the
         children. Milk for every child. Free innoculations. Smaller families
         Planned parenthood. All those things grew out of the great necessity
         and the dire need of those depression years.
         
         SS:  Do you feel that the Depression directly made a lot of people decide
         not to have big families?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, I think so. They couldn't support the ones they had
         
         SS:  Do you feel that the Depression directly made a-
         
         LGC:  A lot of changes. Oh, yes, I think so, definitely. They couldn't sup
         port the ones they had, you know. And I think it just drove them to
         see the great necessity of doing these things. I'm sure that's right.
         
         SS:  Do you think there was much of a realization- growing realization that
         as women- as people ought to have more of a life of their own indepen
         dent of just families.
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. I think with the reading. With the cultural revolu
         tion more girls went to college, for instance and they come back with
         other thoughts. More girls right along were going to college all the
         time. And studied sociology and you heard about limiting families and
         you heard about taking care of the ones you had, about the psycholo
         gical care and about self-fulfillment and all that sort of thing. And
         I think those all had their effect. I'm sure they did.
         
         SS:  When we talked about affection in families
         Was the dispenser of affection in the family?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I do. I think it was the mother.
         
         SS:  In country and town both?
         
         LGC:  Oh, I do, I think so. I think the mother was the one they went to to
         talk to and.comfort when they cut their finger and stubbed their toe.
         I think it was the mothers they went to. It was the mothers that put
         them to bed and dressed them; gave them their baths and took care of
         them when they were sick. I think so.
         
         SS:  Do you think that the father in those days was a remote figure for his
         children?
         
         LGC:  Well, more so than now, I think. There wasn't that camaraderie near
         so much. He was more the ruler of the house. He was the man you plea
         sed. He was the breadwinner. I think so.
         
         SS:  I have read that- people saying that fathers tended to be closer to
         their daughters than to their sons. That fathers were really kind ofyou
         know, prized- not that they didn't prize their sons, but there was
         a closer relationship between father and daughter that encouraged the
         daughters when they grew up to be more independent. Now I wonder if
         that's true. I don't know if it was coming from the father or whether
         it was really coming from the mother.
         
         LGC:  I don't think I can answer that. I just don't know. I didn't know
         enough people well enough. In our family I think my father had great
         pride in the sons. You were supposed to have sons to carry on the name.
         That's the old country idea. The sons inherited. It was for sons.
         And that of course, is an old country concept about - the sons will
         carry on the name. So many sons and don't mention the daughters, you
         know. And many of the people I knew lived around us were from the
         old countries. And I think most of them had more of that feeling.
         
         SS:  Yes, I think this is being presented as more of a city- as a town kind
         of thing.
         
         LGC:  Yes. Where the fathers babied the daughters. The daughters were sweet.
         Yes. I think maybe in the cities that might be, but in the country
         the boys- the boys were an advantage, they were so many hired helpthey
         were going to have help on the farm to do the work. The girls
         would not be much help. They would marry some other man, but.these
         boys were to come up. We have to get more land for them. We've got
         to buy that other 160. I have so many boys coming up. There was lots
         of that went on. Lots of talk about, we must acquire land for the sake
         of our sons, you know. Lots of that
         
         SS:  Yet, when you look at these large families and the very limited amount
         of land, there must have been an awful lot of kids had to leave when
         they grew up, because they couldn't be supported.
         
         LGC:  They couldn't be supported. didn't want to stay. The farm life
         had been hard on them and a lot of them wanted to go to something else.
         
         SS:  You mean, these boys having to work in the fields?
         
         LGC:  Yes, the boys had to work in the fields. It had been hard work. And
         a lot of them didn't want anymore of it.
         
         SS:  So there probably must have been many more of your generation left
         than stayed. Wouldn't you say?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think so. And then especially when the Depression hit and the
         prices were so bad nobody wanted to farm. Then the war came on and
         entered a new phase entirely, you see. So many opportunities in all
         directions were opened up. And the kids went away to battle and lear
         ned other things and didn't want to go back to farm life.
         
         SS:  Do you think the First World War had that effect too?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I do. I think so, too. I think the First World War.
         
         SS:  So it meant that having been in the army that the boys saw other pos
         sibilities?
         
         LGC:  That's right. Other ways of life.
         
         SS:  Which 
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right. You know, "How are they gonna keep them down on
         the farm after they've seen Paree?" But there was that feeling, that
         there was more liberty, more freedom, more adventure, more wonderful
         things than following plows and the crops. Yes lot of 'em didn't
         want to go back to it, although lots of 'em did.
         
         SS:  But then there really wasn't enough opportunities, say in Moscow in
         business for them.
         
         LGC:  Oh, no, no.
         
         SS:  They really had to get out,
         
         LGC:  They had to get out anyway, yes, that's right, they did. And there
         were Hny other opportunities open.
         
         SS:  Did most of them go to the West Coast?
         
         LGC:  Yes, yes.
         
         SS:  Rather than East, most of them went to-
         
         LGC:  Yes, like California, yes. California drew lots of these young people,
         And the coast; Seattle, Portland and all up and down, yes.
         
         SS:  Or to Spokane?
         
         LGC:  Yes. That's right,, the centers. That's right.
         
         SS:  It's been a very interesting question to understand the differences
         between those who left and those who stayed. What would make people
         decide to leave. The people who left we can't talk to.
         
         LGC:  Yes, that's right. The ones that stayed- that's exactly right. Yes.
         
         SS:  I wonder what some of the differences would be?
         
         LGC:  Well, some of them just loved the land and loved the farming and loved
         the rotation of the crops and the coming of the seasons, you know.
         And they wouldn't have done anything else. But the bad years, the
         Depression is really what took them off the farms, I think. They
         thought that just over the hill was something better. Although the
         boys that came out here, like from the CC camps from New York, my,
         they would loved to have all stayed if they could. So that's the way
         it goes.
         
         SS:  One thing about the First World War: I've heard that there was quite
         a bit of anti-German sentiment during the war.
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes, very much. Yes.
         
         SS:  What have you heard about that, or seen during that time?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I saw- there were some boys that got draft deferments for this
         and that other reason, and they rode 'em on a rail and they took off
         their clothes and tarred and feathered some of them. Some of them as
         old men dying still resented and remembered those violent episodes.
         I remember when they mashed out store windows at Uniontownbhat said
         Kraut on it. And Kraut on the window. Nobody would eat kraut. Throw
         you know, the Kraut out, they were Germans. And all that was pretty. I remember
         the Williamson store, he went in and gathered up every
         thing that was made in Germany, and had a big bonfire in the mid
         dle of the street, you know. Although he had many good German friends
         all over the county that had helped make him rich. And there was all
         that went on, you know. And some people changed their name. And if
         it was a German name- we'll just change our name. We don't want any
         thing to do with it. And there was lots of that, just that kind of
         hysteria going on .
         
         SS:  This deferment business- this was German boys who didn't have to go
         into the army?
         
         LGC:  That's right. Some of them said their fathers were sick and dying,
         and their father had so much land they had to stay home and farm it
         for them and they got they called them farm deferments. And a lot of
         those men felt badly later because they didn't share in the great ad
         venture that the other boys had had. And there was great resentment
         against them. A lot of them stayed home and married the belle of the
         town, you know and didn't have to go to war and all the other kids re
         sented that and held it against them even after they got to be old men
         they still remembered, you hadn't gone and you chickened out.
         
         SS:  But this actual beating up of these fellows? Did that actually happen?
         
         LGC:  Oh, yes. That happened here, too, yes.
         
         SS:  Would it be mostly in the country or Moscow?
         
         LGC:  I think the Saturday night businesses, you know and like at the dances
         they'd get a few drinks and then they were looking for fights, you know.
         hearing
         
         SS:  Can you actually remember of anyone tarred and feathered here?
         
         LGC:  Yes. I know of one case where they tarred and feathered and rode him in life
         on the rail.. And he said if he had it to do over again, he would have
         gone, he would have been glad to have gone but his father- he was the
         only boy among a big bunch of girls, and the father and mother both
         cried so and took on so, that he asked for a farm deferment although
         he was able.
         
         SS:  Did that happen in Moscow or Genesee?
         
         LGC:  Well, the folks lived about half way in between- out. And the Moscow
         board is what gave him the deferment.. But the man was sorry all his
         life for it.
         
         SS:  But he was German?
         
         LGC:  Yes. He was of German descent.
         
         SS:  It is my impression of it that German people were expected to be superpatriotic,
         more so than anyone else.
         
         LGC:  Yes, some of them had to bend over backwards. In fact, when they sold
         war bonds they'd go out to these German farmers, you know, and just put
         them right on the spot. They'd made fortunes and "We expect you to
         buy so many thousand dollars worth of war bonds." And they did. Lots
         of them went all out, as you say, to prove their patriotism. They
         didn't want anything to do with this war. But a lot of them werethey'd
         been brought up, this was their home country, this was just a
         temporary thing, but their home and their loyalty were back in Germany.
         And there was some of that alright. But they were among the older people.
         
         SS:  They were actually- do you think some of them actually hoped to go
         Germany some day?
         
         LGC:  I think maybe they had planned maybe to go back some day. But they
         had closer ties. They were older people. The old folks that had come
         maybe half grown from Germany. And they always thought, "We'll make
         a fortune in America and go back to the homeland." And that was hard
         on them.
         
         SS: Well, this young man who was tarred and feathered- how could he have
         ever like those people that had done that? I mean, if it was me, I
         think I would have always-
         
         LGC:  Resented it. Well, didn't..
         
         SS:  Were these people that he knew?
         
         LGC:  Yes, oh, yes. Boys he'd grown up with. Yes. Yes. Of course there'd
         been some drinking too you know. And in the heat of it all, you know
         how those things go. He didn't live to be a very old man, so it was
         all answered for him then. It was all answered, but I do know that
         he told me in later life that he was sorry that he hadn't gone. He
         said, "I missed that wonderful experience. I wouldn't have done it
         myself but my folks- my father and my mother both were so set."
         
         SS:  Do you think they beat him up too as well as tarred and feathered him?
         
         LGC:  Well, -
         
         SS:  It really doesn't matter.
         
         LGC:  I don't think it matters. I don't really remember. But anyway they
         roughed him up an awful lot and it was bad and they did put the tar
         and feathers on and they rode him on a rail.
         
         SS:  That's the classic-
         
         LGC:  Yeah, example.
         
         SS:  By the way, just one more thing that this reminds me of The Ku Klux
         Klan.
         
         LGC:  Yes, we had a Ku Klux Klan here in Moscow at one time. And they were
         out burning crosses even and going around in sheets and pillow slips.
         And it never lasted very long. And of course, it was against the Catholies
         and not against the Negroes.. The Ku Klux Klan was an anti-Ca
         tholic group. And I think that the people who belonged were not very
         high grade intelligence. Not very^intelligent. And they did have a
         Ku Klux Klan going around here for a while.
         
         SS:  This anti-Catholic feeling- would they burn crosses at people's homes
         who were Catholic? Would that be the type of thing they would do?
         
         LGC:  I think they were going up on Moscow Mountain to burn them as I re
         member it. Go up on Moscow Mountain so you could see it. And some of
         said they wouldn't let 'em go because they'd set the trees on fire.
         But they were out marching around in white sheets and pillow slips.
         Crazy!
         
         SS:  What time was it in years? I've heard it was the early ;20's. Does
         that sound right to you?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I'd say it was the early '20's. Yes, the early '20's. '22.
         
         SS:  How did people react to them? Do you think that some were scared by
         them?
         
         LGC:  Well, I certainly wasn't. I took a look at the kind of people that
         belonged and I thought, "Just how stupid can you get?"
         
         SS:  It was more or less known who belonged?
         
         LGC:  Oh, it was more or less known, sure, and they hand out these little
         anti-Catholic books and they were passing them around and just a lot
         of hocus-pocus, you know. Just ridiculous. And all you had to do
         was take a look at the kind of people that belonged to it and you knew
         it wasn't very important.
         
         SS:  Were many of the people from the South who belonged?
         
         LGC:  Oh, I don't know. All the ones I knew—
         
         SS:  Because the Klan did start in the South and I just wondered whether
         it was the same organization here.
         
         LGC:  It wasn't against the colored people at all, it was just against the
         Catholics. But there were magazines published even, that came from
         some headquarters in the East, anti-Catholic things. I remember once
         they had some kind of a nun- escaped from a convent and she was going
         to tell all. And one of the churches sponsored her and of all disgus
         ting, revolting things. You could tell the woman was mentally deran
         ged. She just went on and on about the goings on. And there were a
         lot of men standing around there guarding it and someone said to me,
         "oh, those are Ku Klux Klan members. They've come here to protect her
         so she can get up and talk." I certainly had no part in that and
         didn't want any part. I did happen to go with some women to hear this
         woman that night. I took some old lady that wanted to go hear all
         about it, you know.
         
         SS:  Sensational.
         
         LGC:  Sensational. Heavens, just disgusting. She hardly opened her mouth
         when I thought, "She's a psycopath of some kind."
         
         SS:  Do you think that the Catholics were relatively separate from the rest
         of the town in Moscow in those days?
         
         LGC:  No, I don't think they could have driven a wedge in any way. Although
         I was brought up in this family where we had such great respect for
         religious tolerance. And my father had come from just out of Belfast And he'd heard
         that all his life,
         the trouble and he said it was just nothing but a source of trouble.
         We all worship the same God and some of our neighbors were Catholics
         and very good friends, the first to come and help you, you know. And
         we were so very friendly. Good Catholic neighbors.
         
         SS:  In Moscow you were.
         
         LGC:  In Moscow I was still just as friendly with the little girls that
         came down from the convent. I thought they had better manners and
         were better trained. And I never have had any feeling at all myself.
         But I think maybe there were some, I think there were some ths.t- "Oh,
         my, they were Catholics." And even in high school, the kids that came
         over from the convent high school to the Moscow Public School, because
         it was broader and more kids there. Some people had a- some of the
         other girls in the school would say, "Well, if you're real stupid, you
         have to go to the convent, but the smarter ones go to the Moscow High
         School." And it was so unkind. It had nothing to do with it.
         
         SS:  Do you know why they didn't like Catholics then, or what the reasons
         they gave?
         
         LGC:  No.
         
         SS:  Was it the Pope that they objected to?
         
         LGC:  I really don't know.
         
         SS:  One more controversial group that the Klan reminds me of, and that is
         not a group that had anything in common with them was the IWWs.
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And what I want to ask you about; in the lumber country the IWWs had
         a pretty good reputation among a great many people having improved
         the conditions. But the view from Moscow was quite the opposite.
         
         LCG: Yes.
         
         SS:  I understand. They were really disliked up there very much.
         
         LGC:  Yes, They had no part with it. My husband's people here ran a thre
         shing machine. The Snows where I lived and taught school for four
         years, they ran a threshing machine and they had to be awfully careful
         who they hired. They had IWWs and they called them Wobblies, and they
         would throw a bomb into the machine, into the workings and blow up
         the machines that summer. That was '22, I think, the summer.
         
         SS:  Was that real as a danger or was it something-
         
         LGC:  They did it a couple of times, yes they did it here on the Clyde farm.
         
         SS:  The IWWs did?
         
         LGC:  Yes. They thre^one in and it went off with an explosion. Didn't blow
         the whole thing to pieces, but it did explode in the machine.
         
         SS:  They were sure that it was IWWs that did it?
         
         LGC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And not just a smut fire?
         
         LGC:  No, they said that this was IWWs. One of the boys got sick here and
         he was a card carrying IWW, and the men took him to the hospital and
         so on and took care of him, but he carried one of those blackjacks,
         with the brass ball on the end, he carried that an IWW card and
         they were to notify IWWs. And there were a couple of others that were.
         And of course, they strove for shorter hours, and you know, the far
         mers were noted for getting up at daylight and working by the lantern
         til midnight. And they fell in disrepute in these communities because
         of the violent way. Had it just been, "We want shorter hours." And
         that sort of thing. Better food. And they had such wonderful food.
         All these women were super cooks and they.each one outdid the other
         trying to get the nicest meals in the world for them. So they couldn't
         complain about the food.
         
         SS:  I think it was more in the lumber camps they were complaining about
         the food.
         
         LGC:  Yes. But they did complain about the long hours. And of course, har
         vest is the time when they have to work long hours to save the crop.
         So there was certainly two sides. The farmers were very resentful of
         anybody that wasn't willing to go out and put everything into it for
         the short harvest season.
         
         SS:  They didn't feel that the IWWs were shirkers when they worked, or did
         they?
         
         LGC:  No. They just wanted to quit too early. They wanted to quit too
         early and not begin - they wanted shorter days.
         
         SS:  So they found it difficult to hire without hiring IWWs? I mean, there
         were so many of the hands- the traveling people were.
         
         LGC:  That's right. Lots of the traveling people that came through were.
         And there was a feeling on the part of the farmers of resentment. But
         I think once again, that was a good thing. Because it got new ways -
         combines and tractors where you didn't need these great crews of men.
         It got so one man could farm half the country and they didn't need all
         this great army of men to work for them.
         
         SS:  But you feel sure from what the Clydes said that they had no doubt that
         it was actually set by the IWWs?
         
         LGC:  Yes. They thought that this one explosion was set by the IWWs.
         
         SS:  Did they know who did it?
         
         LGC:  Yes, I think they thought this man that later got sick and they had to
         card
         take him that was the carrying man, they that he was kind of
         a leader.
         
         SS:  They actually found—
         
         LGC:  Yes, they found his card in his pocket.
         
         SS:  But I mean in the machine- they found the scrap.
         
         LGC:  Yes, there was evidence of something being thrown in. Yeah.
         
         SS:  And this was about '22?
         Yes, '22, around in there. After the First World War, probably '22, '23.
         
         SS:  The attitude towards these migratory workers that came through: What
         did the farmers really think?
         
         LGC:  Well, they were all- the farmers were just hard working people them
         selves. And in those days the formula was for everybody- if you
         worked hard, you mafce a lot of money and you could have all these things
         see. There was never any idea of asking for government subsidies and
         that sort of thing. You got out and you earned it yourself. If you
         wanted your children to be educated and have things, there
         was nothing to do but you worked like that. Get up early and work late.
         And they couldn't see the other person's side of it. They were willing
         to do it, because it was their bread and butter on the line; their
         farms on the line. But they expected the men to do it and that's where
         the trouble came. I cooked for the Snow boys when one noon all the men
         lined up outside and after dinner, they ate a nice dinner first, then
         they all lined up and they weren't going to go back to the field, they
         were on strike. And it took quite a lot of negotiating out there to
         get 'em back. And it was getting late in the harvest season and there
         was just nothing to do but meet whatever demand there was. And it was
         met and they negotiated and got it done.
         
         SS:  Do you know how much they negotiated for?
         
         LGC:  Oh, probably wasn't over fifty cents or a dollar a day. So it wasn't
         so much as all that. But anyway it was all settled.
         
         SS:  Was one man their spokesman?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they had one man that talked for them.
         
         SS:  Can't imagine it created goodwill between them.
         
         LGC:  No, and when it didn't really form an adventure when all the neigh
         bors came in and did each others crops- "We'll do this one first. And
         here's old Mr. so-and-so, he needs the money, we'll go to him next.
         But when they started having to go out and hire outsiders; strangers
         that came into the country, that's what took the fun and the joy out
         of it.
         
         SS:  Why did they have to go to outsiders? What happened that they couldn't
         use just local people anymore?
         
         LGC:  Well, I imagine that over the years the kids had grown up and gone to
         that First World War. Lot of them didn't come back to the farms. There
         weren't big families. And then as the farmers got to farming, they
         had other ways of combining- of threshing. The Clydes had their th
         reshing right here and Snows next door they had their threshing machine.
         Each one had their own.
         
         SS:  Had their own threshing machine?
         
         LGC:  Yes. Had their own threshing machines. And so many people with five
         or six hundred acres- each one had his own threshing machine, instead
         of all going together and hav ing twenty-two headerboxes and everybody
         doing this one and that. Each one was doing his own thing.
         
         SS:  Then they had to get outside help.
         
         LGC:  Then they had to get outside help.
         
         SS:  Were they still steam threshers at that time?
         
         LGC:  Yes. They were steam threshers.
         
         SS:  And they had the long belt between?
         
         LGC:  Yes, they had the belt.
         
         SS:  I wonder why they decided to get their own instead of- Didn't it work
         pretty well?
         
         LGC: Yes, it work when they went together, it did. Well, I think they
         had such long- they would start early like down toward the rim and come
         on up. As each farm expanded and got more land then they needed thre
         shing machines. Instead of this man and that man each owning 160, here
         would be one man with 500 acres and the next one with 5 and the next
         one with five and if you had 500 acres, you almost had to go get your
         own threshing machine to get it cut. I think that was probably the
         way of it. But that's the way I remember the IWW deal. I just re
         member that one summer.
         
         SS:  That year of the strike is that the same summer?
         
         LGC:  Yes, it was the same summer, about '22 and '23, those were the years.
         And these men, a lot of them had come from Colfax. Colfax is a little
         earlier harvest field than here and they'd gotten men that had come
         there and these men had hired them from all up in town; transients that
         had come in looking for harvest jobs and brought them out. And the
         men on the Snow machine knew the men here on the Clyde machine- they
         had known each other before.
         
         SS:  Did they both strike?
         
         LGC:  Well, I don't think these folks struck, they just tried to blow up the
         machine that day. And then one of them got so sick and in this process
         of identifying him and trying to get word to his relatives and so on,
         they had to go through his pockets, and they found he was an IWW and
         that he had this blackjack andjie had come equippd for trouble.
         8S: Where did most of these fellows come from? These itinerant guys that
         were working in the harvest? Did you know where they were from?
         
         LGC:  I really dont' know. I don't know where. I never did know where they
         came from. There were very few local people- there were two or three
         local men from town on the crew, but once again, they knew the Clydes,
         they knew the Snows and they went right on with the work and they tried
         to hold the thing together because they were personal friends, and men
         who knew them. And men that were going to have to go on living in the
         community, too. But these others were transients who had come in and
         were just waiting for harvest jobs to open. They had put in time over
         at Colfax and wandered over here just a little later.
         
         SS:  After, what happened? Did they have to still keep going to out
         siders to thresh?
         
         LGC:  Yes, quite a while. There was quite a little of that around. But then
         they started in going into combines. About '24 and '25 everybody was
         buying combines, and didn't need so many men, see. Even back in '22
         Snows had had a horse drawn combine. They got rid of it. But then
         they got more horse drawn combines and then pretty soon there were tra
         ctor drawn combines. And then pretty soon they were selfpropelled.
         But all this trouble with the IWWs helped to hurry up the getting of the
         combines into the field. It hurried it. They figured it was the only
         way to relieve the labor problem was to get combines that they could
         run them in their own family. So I think that's the way that worked.
         And then of course, in '29 came the Depression, and that was a new ball
         of wax.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13409</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Clyde6</previous>
      <next>Corrin</next>
      <disp_name>Clyde7</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
