<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">5/21/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Glenn Corrin, 1975-05-21, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>0:49:49</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Corrin, Glenn</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>General laborer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1890</birthyear>
      <residence>Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from South Dakota (1890)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#police officers"&gt;police officers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wool"&gt;wool&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#knitting"&gt;knitting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mail carriers"&gt;mail carriers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wool"&gt;wool&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Lewiston"&gt;Lewiston&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Nora Creek"&gt;Nora Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13407</file_name>
      <mp3>13408.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13408.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Glenn accuses Payne Sly of killing Marshall Hays</title>
            <synopsis>Marshall Hays had a bad reputation. Glenn's eye
               witness account of Payne Sly killing Hays, and related
               events of the day.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Hays shooting gun to enforce speed ordinance</title>
            <synopsis>Hays liked to shoot off his gun in town. Trying to
               enforce a speed ordinance, he is nearly run over.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Hays tries to enter Doe Wells house without search warrant, family is armed</title>
            <synopsis>Hays tries to enter Doe Wells house without a search
               warrant, and Doe arms his family with guns. Doe
               rescues Benson when he's arrested by Hays.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Doe Wells attempts to arrest Hays for being drunk, and is nearly drowned by Dick Sanderline</title>
            <synopsis>Doe Wells was born a slave. Hays drinks with men and
               then arrests them for being drunk. Dick Sanderline
               nearly drowns Hays in a well for trying to arrest
               him for drinking. Hays was a coward.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1080</time>
            <title>Lou Wells, Doe's wife, uses sheep wool to knit socks; hose is located halfway between
               Troy and Collins
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Lou Wells (Doe's wife) carded wool from the sheep they
               kept, knit and sold socks. She pounds a tune on the
               bottom of her dishpan while Martin Froman dances. The
               Wells cabin was the halfway-house between Troy and
               Collins.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Glenn describes route from Troy to Collins for mail route</title>
            <synopsis>Glenn describes the route he drove his mail and supply
               wagon, from Troy to Collins, in 1906. Leaving mail
               in leather bags hung by the road. The old road—its
               condition, and difference in location from present
               highway.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Description of the beauty of Bovill</title>
            <synopsis>The beauty of the early site of Bovill, before the
               town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Glenn stays overnight at the Collins</title>
            <synopsis>Staying overnight at Collins on the mail route.
               Collins was the end of the road, and the point of
               departure for claims in the back country. The Adair
               girls and their friends.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Homesteaders cut and burned timber; little was cleared on mail route</title>
            <synopsis>Little land had been cleared along the mail route.
               The old road through Deary. Homesteaders cut and
               burned their timber and planted timothy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Early Nora and Dahlberg sawmills; crime in Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Early Nora and Dahlberg sawmills. Dahlberg girl
               stops a man from being shot. About one man a year
               was killed in Troy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Doe Wells considered "white"; defended by Swedes</title>
            <synopsis>Doe Wells was "white" inside. When Swedes and
               Norweigans got in a fight, they'd say Doe was the
               only white man in Deary.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Knutson hires Henning to burn down his saloon, in
               Reitman's building.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Knutson hires Henning to burn down his saloon, in
               Reitman's building.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Orchards and fruit growing around Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Fruit growing around Troy. Prune dryers in the area.
               Reasons for decline of fruit industry. Packing
               cherries.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3000</time>
            <title>The Corrins came out from South Dakota with the Arnotts
               and Duthies.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The Corrins came out from South Dakota with the Arnotts
               and Duthies.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Marshall Hays: his unpopularity and murder. Joe and Lou Wells. Driving supply wagon
         east of Troy (1906). Beauty of Bovill townsite, 5-21-75 .9 hr 12p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SS:  That spot, Bovard, down there in the canyon.
         
         GUSTAV CARLSON: Oh, Bovard. Bovard was never a town, never even a store there.
         
         SS:  Was it a mill?
         
         GC:  Well, there was a mill later, but we had a telegraph station there;
         they had to have relays on the telegraphs, but the main
         thing,' they put a sidetracking in there- had been put in there- for
         trains to on an old years before, so the trains could
         meet there. It was in 1911- well, I tell you, it began in 19- ,
         well, the winter of 1909 and '10, there was a fellow who had to
         sell off land there and he got rid of his place and stuff on the top
         of the hill there and there was some timber on 'em and some timber
         on the Bear Ridge side. Bovard's just below the end of Burnt Ridge,
         a little ways further down, quarter of a mile where the canyon flat
         tens out. They had a little telegraph station there, oh ever since-
         I think they installed the telegraph line, but that was about all.
         Maybe those sidetracks were there so.they could drive cattle down and
         load them^as far back as I can remember they weren't used for any
         thing. But they bought the rights to timber up the Bear Ridge side-
         Little Bear side and the Burnt Ridge side to log in there otfseveral
         places and they milled there until it-^ I figure it was about the win
         ter of, oh, about 1911 they began moving moving in there.
         
         SS:  You say, "they", who—?
         
         GC:  The Bovard Company, the Bovard Lumber Company. It was locally owned
         by people around Troy, that had invested in the company.
         
         SS:  Independent or was it tied up with Troy Lumber?
         
         GC:  No, it wans't Troy Lumber Company, because I don't believe the
         were it  But oh think Nelson- Emil Nelson, I don't
         think he could be living now, but he was down there as director, I
         think he was part owner of the operations.
         
         SS:  And what was the access to Bovard from Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC:  The access pretty bad. old road down the end of Burnt Ridge
         about half way down the canyon that can be used. It .went down to
         where that hay field, ere on the hillside and around to where
         there was a gold house that was built by Coverland, I mentioned that
         to you before, the Hagen family lived there, when I first remember
         it. And then there had been also a very old road in which the rocks
         had just been rolled out of the way and dug in a little, down to the
         railroad tracks, so it evidently had been used once before to give
         access to that railroad. From there on it was just- you just had to
         drive along the railroad and sometimes in places if they had wagons
         going in there they had to straddle of the rails in order to
         find room, it wasn't wide enough, so they had to know when the trains
         were coming to get their stuff out. But that's the way they went on
         down and around to the very edge of the point and there they built a
         cookhouse. And they had a bunkhouse also, built across on a stream
         there. They the stream^ around and made a little dam across
         that so they could handle the logs and put in a very small saw there
         that handled it. And for two or three years they were turning out
         the timber there, and then it was through.
         
         SS:  You say it was out by 1911?
         
         GC:  Well, no, they started in 1911- I think the main saw work didn't *
         start until 1912. They had- I think there were a couple of cutters
         up there in the woods, I remember two of 'em, that were cutting down
         the trees and putting 'em in lengths, before that, in the early
         spring and winter and they were getting ready to go there and that
         was- really, about 1912 before they actually started.
         
         SS:  Did this kind of operation pay?
         
         GC:  I think it paid. They sold the timber, they got the logs
         off. They used a donkey engine, you know. You know what they were?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         GC:  Wind up with a cable and pull timbers down. For part of it and then
         they used teams for part of it, pulling the logs in. And they had
         that installed there and a little dam and a cookhouse. They built a
         bunkhouse up On what was like a little island between the two streams,
         one coming from Troy direction and one coming from the CfouJn A canyon.
         Oh, it was a crowded place to work on, but they worked out and heaved
         those sandbars around til they had a place for the lumber to be
         piled, and then they ran a series of tracks right into where they
         could draft the cars in and load 'em right there. I don't know,
         they took out a lot of timber there. They worked there for a couple
         of years or so. Let's see- I think that was about 1914 they was through.
         Couple of year's operation. They didn't have expensive machinery,
         as far as that goes. Not like these that are expected to go
         for years, so they put in as simple stuff as they could, they knew
         about how long it'd take. Probably took a little longer than they
         thought it would take.
         
         SS:  Did this employ Burnt Ridge people at all or did they all come down
         from Troy?
         
         GC:  No, Burnt Ridge- I don't know if any Burnt Ridge- I don't think any
         Burnt Ridge worked down there. They were operating mostly in the
         summer when they were busy on the farms.
         
         SS:  Well, when-
         
         GC:  They used to buy milk at our place. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  How many guys would you guss would there have been down there?
         
         GC:  Oh, five or six around the mill, the engine and then the number of
         sawyers varied, and teamsters logging it in. They didn't have the
         same amount all the time.
         
         SS:  Would it all be timber from very close to the mill?
         
         GC:  Very close, they followed up the ridges. They took some off of the
         killt ice place that we bought, the Sanders place and off I guess,
         too. place happened to be the next one. And fr»m the places
         on Ridge side, that would have been partly Johnson's and
         I don't think they went as far north as opposite the Rudeen place,
         but they went as far as the Porter, but I don't believe they ever got
         the Porter canyon taken. That timber wasn't sold- somebody didn't
         sell that timber to them. So fr just aboutAup to what is now
         the north edge of Anderson's farm. And maybe they went a little
         further on the Bear Ridge side, I don't know about that, but I don't
         think so.
         
         SS:  We're only talking about a couple of miles.
         
         GC:  Oh, yes, we're only talking about a couple of miles of timber and it
         wasn't all good timber on that area, either. But there was quite a
         bit of heavy timber there. It hadn't been timbered out before.
         It wasn't second-growth. had been passed over. The only
         thing they'd taken out was, well, like going down there and cutting
         a tree for some purpose, poles or something and taking 'em away.
         
         SS:  But they mostly bought timber not land? They didn't hold too much
         land as compared to the timber they bought?
         
         GC:  No, no, they didn't buy any land, they just bought the timber. It
         happened that we bought 200 acres there in the winter of 1909 and
         '10. They went through at the same time. They bought the timber
         for a certain price and we bought the land for a certain price.
         That's the way it was sold. Land and timber separately.
         
         SS:  Was it all canyon?
         
         GC:  It was all canyon, uh-huh. And it didn't quite include all our
         timber, either, because they bought it up to a certain line on a
         certain forty and there was a little clump of good timber on the
         west side of thafline that was not included. And I think if you go
         down there today, you'll probably see that the timber is higher on
         that claim than below it, thatA '. second growth.
         
         SS:  After you got the land did you, did you use it for pasture?
         
         GC:  Yes, it was just part of pasture-that particular part hung in a
         steep canyon between the end of place and the end of our
         place, and it wasn't must good for pasture. In fact is, the whole
         hillside there was- oh, cattle seldomr grazed there, it was too
         mach straight up and down, and it just kind of got brushed over with
         snowberry and-
         
         SS:  Was the land much good to have then, for you?
         
         GC:  Well, that just came as part of lying on the same forties, eighties
         as some good land. At the top, running through the top, let's see —
         The top eighty of that- the top 120 had about oh, seventy-five acres,
         of good farming land of the 120. No, forty and- actually,
         we split one eighty diagonally lying on one side of a creek and you
         take one forty below that, there was only eighty acres and actually there
         about- most of that was plowable land, there was just that steep hill
         side acreage going down there where it was not good land. The rest
         of it got all broken up eventually. About seventy acres there.
         
         SS:  When you bought that land on top did it have timber on it at the
         time, some of it?
         
         GC:  Some of it.
         
         SS:  And thi was logged by this company?
         
         GC:  This company, yes.
         
         SS:  Masw it a little easier for you.
         
         GC:  Yes, they took that off there; the big trees and left little trees
         and brush there. We got ten or eleven acres also, of canyon land and
         a canyon orchard, planted on the hillside, too on a more or less le
         veled out land on benches in the canyon along with it.
         
         SS:  You said canyon orchards? There was orchards down there already or
         you planted?
         
         GC:  No, we didn't plant it. The fellow that hacd homesteaded it there,
         Coburg and he built that little house down on a flat. He had put an
         orchard up on some steeper ground above his house, around the house
         ther e he had  and hay. But he planted the orchard up on the
         hillside there, and I think it's probably still there. I don't know
         if they've taken care of it or not during these years. We used to
         pick things down there. A few times we had such a heavy pear crop
         down there that we hauled boxes of pears to town for several days
         there; two loads a day to town after they were picked.
         
         SS:  These fellows- families that lived there in the canyon, did they
         turn over more? Was that a rougher place - rough place for people
         to make a dollar?
         
         GC:  It wasn't a place where anybody could make a living, they all worked
         at something else. But they had a passion to own a piece of ground
         and live there.
         
         SS:  But what I was wondering did they stay?
         
         GC:  No, they- none of them stayed any length of time. You see, they
         were isolated; hard to get to town; tough road out; Tough road down.
         And, they just quit, you know, moved away. Fa$t is, in my memory,
         and I think- if I can remember it, I hadn't started to school yet,
         I know that, that fellow Hagen that was a railroad worker he rented
         a place and just to keep his family and he worked for the railroad.
         He didn't buy in, but I guess he found it was too inconvenient a
         place to keep his family and get something to eat. He could raise
         some garden there, maybe that's what induced him to-
         
         SS:  Hagen worked for the railroad; would he just hike down to Bovar?
         
         GC:  Well, I think he- they was having little flatcars, you know, he was
         probably workin in that area part of the time between Troy and Kendrlck.
         
         SS:  Probably could get on at Bovard, more or less.
         
         GC:  Yes, or anyplace where they ditched their flatcars, little handcars
         you know, they used to use. ump up and down and make *em
         run.
         
         SS:  Do you think these gltys were- these families were thought of as- by
         Burnt Ridgers as being kind of outside the community?
         
         GC:  Well, they were there early, some of those before some of the Burnt
         Ridgers came. But the ones that I remember, they were recent comers
         as compared to these people that had built houses in the canyon and
         homesteaded. I don't know- people were al
         ready surrendered and left.
         
         SS:  And they'd homesteaded some then?
         
         GC:  Some of 'em homesteaded. They had an ideaAall land was going to be
         valuable someday. They didn't know how long it was going to be, but they were
         optomistic I guess. (Chuckles) I know, we always speculated what
         in the world they went down in those canyons for to build houses.
         That was the general consensus of opinion for 'em. Most people
         couldn't understand what came over them to do that. They learned
         too that they weren't in a very good place.
         
         SS:  Well, do you think that the reason might have been that they were
         not farmers?
         
         GC:  No, they^weren't farmers. No, as far as I know, they didn twork
         at farming. I don't know what Cusick and Monahan worked at regular
         ly, I think they did mostly teamster work. Take them away from their
         places and leave their families there. Hagen he workedhe
         worked, I don't think he stayed, I think he'd given up on his
         place and was ready to sell it. And Sanders bought it before he
         left. Sanders left about 1906. He bought that canyon land- our
         buy amounted to 200 acres that time, he only had originally 160
         and we got 120 of that and another eighty acres and that amount
         there. s he got it very cheap, you know, just wanted to get rid
         of it and it made better pasture for his cattle.,, Actually there
         are no fences down there separating the two, just cows that pastured
         But he was probably- in order to keep somebody
         else from buying up that area and fencing it off and cutting him
         off from pasture, because nobody put up any fences. It would pay him to have done
         that.
         
         I wonder if they expected that a road would go through down- to 
         Potlatch from there. If they expected that- The
         only feasible route besides the one over American Ridge around
         the canyon, would be to run one right down the railroad tracks from
         Troy to Kendrick or else, if they wanted to come up over Burnt Ridge
         would be to take off down that draw, which is right at the end of
         what was our place, which is Trout's now. His and Anderson's. And
         that thing right down to the level of the grade there and
         come down to the bi^ botton there. They would have road- that way
         they'd have about- they'd save the distance between Bovard, where
         the Bovard mill stood and Troy, of new road, they could have used
         the Burnt Ridge road. And it isn't about three miles down
         from there that there is a old sidetacking called^Spur. And there
         they had warehouses built up- it was a grain receiving town and there
         was a road down from the Bear Ridge and I think one from the Ameri
         can Ridge, because there were some bench farms in there on American
         Ridge that are closer that way than anywhere else. And they used to
         come down over the Bear Ridge grade and unload their wheat there.
         And they had a good warehouse; I saw them, oh, the last time I sup
         pose, about 1930 or so and they were still standing just fine there.
         They'd been wellbuilt and looked like no deterioration at all^ those
         grain warehouses. houses, I suppose they'd be called.
         
         SS:  And from Clyde's Spur then how far would they be down-
         
         GC:  Be only about three miles more to Kendrick and there was a road that
         ran down that way.
         
         SS:  From Clyde's Spur to Kendrick?
         
         GC:  To Kendrick. A road had been laid out; I suppose it had deteriorated
         from lack of use, because^that taking on grain from there died out.
         They had a better road down over the end of Bear Ridge right into
         Kendrick, and they'd do that and American Ridge had a grade into
         Kendrick and all that. Some of those things- Akind
         of roads- they was all just dirt, horse manipulated were pretty bad
         sometimes. And that probably accounted for Clyde's Spur, little bit
         shorter haul.
         
         SS:  And probably one of the farmers would man the warehouse or something?
         
         GC:  Oh, they could get somebody there to man the warehouse. Actually,
         there happens to be a little house and long after they'd abandoned
         taking any of the wheat down there they'd had occupants. It
         just a little, oh, a hundred yards on a little slope and it flattened
         out to quite a little space before it went up again. And there'd
         been an orchard built there and there'd been some land broken out
         to have a little hay field. Berries planted, and things like that.
         
         SS:  This was right above Clyde's Spur?
         
         GC:  Just above Clyde' Spur. I know that very late there were people 11-
         e ving there. And I suppose they either went up by way of Bear Ridge
         or else went down to Kendrick from there. Somebody occupied that
         house for sometime. I think even in the grain hauling days, maybe
         it was at that house or maybe somewhere else, somebody used to have
         a little coffee and sandwich standAthere. The grain haulers wanted
         a cup of coffee before they went back up.
         
         Clyde's Spur, there was one? That's something.
         
         But Bovard was only really a siding before the mill went in.
         It was just a siding, as far as I know, it was, it had a telegraph
         station and they used to have a telegraph office operator down there.
         I don't understand all that much about the telegraphs in that time
         but they must have relay things.
         
         He was stationed there? And lived there?
         
         No, he didn't live there, he walked down from Troy.
         
         There was a little office there for him or something?
         
         No, no real office at all, just a place for to sit in there. Spent
         some hours there. I don't know what it was,Aguess maybe he had to
         give reports if the trains were coming through on time.
         
         SS:  This is when you were a boy?
         
         When I was a boy. I know by the time they started that mill he was
         gone, they didn't use it anymore. I don't know if the little building
         is still there or not. It was more or less built like ^ phone booths
         that you see on the streets. (Chuckles)
         
         Did you ever hear any stories about the people that lived in the
         canyon?
         
         No particular stories. No, I didn't. I think Cusicks stayed around
         there a while. I knew people that may have known them. And Bruce's
         dad he was about twelve years olejer than I was, if he were alive to
         day he could tell you about that. Butr^they were there after we came
         to the farm before I was ever able to rememberr because I know he got
         acquainted with them; the Cusicks. And his son-in-law Monahan built
         another house up a little further. He built a better house than any
         of the rest of them. And he did the same thing; built a little or
         chard around his house on a flattened bench and evidently he raised
         garden there. The soil had gone back to brush springing up and all
         that when I saw it, but you could see that it had probably been
         plowed out at one time.
         
         SS:  You know tha thing- talking about these canyon people makes me think
         about it- the geographical setup of the country out there with the
         ridges and the steep canyons, that had a lot of effect on the way
         people lived, didn't it? I mean, that was quite a barrier, those
         canyons, wasn't it?
         
         GC:  Yes, they were. Actually they cut them into communities. People
         on one side of the canyon formed a community like American Ridge
         and on the other side like Burnt Ridge, the other side like Little
         Bear Ridge. Those people all knew each other much better than they
         did the people on the other ridges. And the schoolhouses, of course,
         had to be made with some thought as to how many - how the kids could
         get there. So they had a couple of schoolhouses on Little Bearthan
         longer ridge Big Bear, I think they had even more on American
         Ridge. Burnt Ridge being the shorter one, had only one. And the
         kids at the upper end of that place probably often went to Troy.
         
         SS:  What was it like getting across a canyons—
         
         GC:  We used to go across there horseback riding, but^we gradually ceased
         with that, too. There were trails, that already sort of used.
         One led from our place down west .the canyon where they had a
         gates in the railroad fence and a gate on the other side and then
         we crossed the creek down there, there was a crossing and then there
         was one that led on the slant all the way around, a fairly easy slant
         came up that draw where the old Harmon place was. Oh, once in a while
         probably some people met each other when they used to go down to
         fish, because there used to be much more water in those streams and
         they could catch fish through the summer. The Compton family, that
         littd was an old family on there, Ajust about opposite us and just
         below them the Harmon family, and the Cummings family stayed across
         the other way, south.
         — usually meet in Troy and sometimes1! My brothers got acquainted
         first over there and the reason is that on the other side of Ameri
         can Ridge is Driscoll Ridge and the upper part where it ceases and
         after that further down on American Ridge is Fix Ridge, and I had
         two uncles that had farms over there, my father's brothers, and that
         was the shortcut to get over there, there was no road and had to go
         a long ways fround by road and up through Troy and down as far aswell,
         as Miller's trestle down here and then take this road south
         to get there. The wagon road. So we used that trail down there and
         came up on American Ridge and went down the other side by Bethel
         Church and followed a trail down that canyon, on the side that after
         you-came opposite the farms that my two uncles had. They had farms
         that just about extended Fix Ridge to the bottom and there were
         trails up there too that were being used for crossings. There seemed
         to be quite a few trails for crossing. I don't remember a good trail
         for crossing from Burnt Ridge to Bear Ridge, but they're it by
         by going dowji the end of the r^dge and finding a way up that hill
         side there. Because I know they rode over that way to Hu^'s
         agood deal. Huffs was the last family on the Little Bear Ridge, like
         we were the last family- our's was the last land on Burnt Ridge, use
         able land.
         
         SS:  How long would it take you horseback to cross from one to the other?
         
         GC:  Oh, took several hours. Yes, you'd go down, you had no place
         where you could run a horse, see. Too steep down one and too steep
         up the other. Trails weren't that wide, either or that smooth, that
         you'd probably walk all the way. But you see, down the hillside
         there's be hours down, oh, it'd be closer-to half a mile than a quarter
         and same up the other side.
         
         SS:  Than across the bottom?
         
         GC:  Well, across the bottom was very little. The railroad track there
         is- occupies one side and the creek next to it.
         So, you're talking about traveling a little over a mile and taking
         three hours?
         
         About a mile- oh, no, it wouldn't take that long. You'd get across
         the top to American Ridge in an hour and a half. But they had 4 lon
         ger canyon to cross to get over to- oh, they could start sometimes
         during the day and get there before night.
         
         SS:  When your mother went midwifing, would she walk or ride?
         
         GC:  Well, they generally tried to see that she'd get A ride, sometimes
         things came up too- I don't know thes^early ones that they had there
         by sometimes the lack of horses- had so few horses on the farms. But
         there was another family that came at a later time and built" a canyon
         house. Moody; Pete Moody. And he homesteaded 160 acres that
         had just very little farm land on top, about an acre or two, but he
         That was on the American Ridge side, the timber was. And he sold his
         timber to the mill, he and a feller next to him^had canyon land with
         timber on it. And that was a mill, too, that mill was located up frombetween
         Bovard and Troy, oh, it would be a good mile and a half of
         the distance from Bovard up, off in the direction of Troy. That was
         called Hall's mill. Hall ran it. He was just an^dividual contractor.
         Set up a small mill and worked there for a couple of years and Pete
         Moody was there, he worked right the mill, he was a woodsman. He'd
         cut the trees and had them all ready for them to drag down off his
         farm and so he got quite a bit for his timber. And then he worked
         for them logging off the other places. One of his daughters, I
         think lives in town yet.
         
         SS:  Was it one of his children that died in the early years that he was
         here?
         
         GC:  Oh, there were two children tho^t died down there and one that was
         grown up died from a- oh, I don't know- violent bleeding caused by
         I don't know just what. He had*about seven children and I think
         about four of them's living. One of 'em ran that little- you know
         where that little- what they call fjoe^apples now? TneY made it:
         all into, entirely into a restaurant now, but it used to be, I don't
         know a variety store with a coffee counter. And she and her husbandor
         she ran it after that, I never saw her husband there. She ran that
         for some time there just lately, I think she's probably still around
         town.
         
         SS:  Well, talking about dying children; what about tuberculosis? What
         about tuberculosis, was it a problem?
         
         GC:  Some of 'em had tuberculosis, yes. ftr. W«tf)his place was just north
         of ours, Ed Ramsdale owns it now, his wife died of TB. She had TB
         and her brother I think had it, too, that was Kellberg, was her broThis
         is the last of the Gilder interviews
         ther, but he. suryiyec until he w.as near eighty, I guess. Anyway,
         sort of overcame it. But in that fmmily now, that second daughter,
         two elder daughters had come to TB  Hilma and Minnie.
         
         SS:  Which family is that
         
         GC:  Kellberg family. Ernie Anderson's wife was the third daughter in
         that family, and Hilma and Minnie, their pictures are on that when
         they were in school; TB. And the Pearson family, two of those boys
         got TB. Willie Pearson and Walter Pearson, the two oldest boys. They
         lived where Rudolph Smith lives now, there was 160 there.
         
         SS:  Were those sicknesses around the same time or were they spread over-
         
         GC:  They seemed to have contracted them somewhere near the same time.
         But Mrs. I think had been infected with it when she came out,
         she was sickly then, though she seemed to maintain pretty good health
         for a number of years. I think she had it when she arrived from
         Oklahoma. That's where they came from.
         
         SS:  Did people think that's how it got started on the Ridge?
         
         GC:  Well, no, I don't know whether it got started- There were other peo
         ple in other places around town, other ridges had TB, too.
         Just seemed to be something that people got in those days and didn't
         know how to take care of it. And the kind of treatment they had
         didn't seem to help.
         
         SS: What did they do?
         
         GC:  Well, most of tem did but very little. Some few got out and- and
         when they found Hilma had TB they sent her to a sanitarium in Colorado.
         ...she was for some time. And I donrt know, somehow or other itshe
         didn't improve, they kind of kept her at a level for a while.
         She died about l30. And she got it active again- she'd had it
         somewhat maybe in her  she got it active - she was teaching
         school out there someplace and her brother was going to take and
         farm an area oyer on Texas Ridge that Kellberg had bought. He bought
         some land over there, he kept it, I don't know maybe the family still
         owns it. But they had bad weather and she was working hard helping
         him with, everything and inconvenient household there. They had to
         carry water from the well- that had never been installed in that place
         he had, old primitive structure that he had on that land and
         she got awful colds and probably didn't stop working to take care of
         tem and she got worse and worse and she was just sick and her active
         case of TB came soon afterwards.
         
         SS:  Came back.
         
         GC:  No, it came on afterwards.
         
         SS:  She got it before?
         
         GC:  Not that they ever knew, just seemed to- maybe laid in her system,
         i dormant. You can test an ordinary healthy person and you can find
         they have TB in 'em, but it doesn't—
         
         SS:  How long did she live after that?
         
         GC:  Oh, I think she lived only about- I think she lived three or four
         years. They had her in a sanitarium in Colorado, but she evidently
         had taken it awfully bad before she ever took treatment.
         
         SS:  If you had TB and you were going to be treated at home what could
         they do for you? They had you sleep in a separate place?
         
         GC:  Yes, they to isolate everybody. There was the Sturdevant family
         rented that land for about two years when I was about nine and ten
         years old that we later bought, rented it from the man owning it
         then. And they had a daughter that died of TB there. She was mar
         ried and had four children but her husband- they didn*t really have
         a place where he could keep her and he took her out and put her in
         a tent there and she lived, oh, she only lived part of a year after
         that. She was pretty bad. And, well, I don't know what his work
         was but 1 belieye he was a railroader, too. I don*t know it at that
         time but he was dying of cancer at the. time as his wife was dying of
         TB, but he kept on working as long as he was able to. He had four
         small children, I guess he thought he had to.
         
         SS:  Whatever happened to the children?
         
         GC:  Well, the children lived on with their grandparents until about the
         time they left Burnt Ridge and then it was too much for the old folks,
         Sturdevants, they were not young at all, their grandparents weren't
         and the sisters and brothers of the daughter who died of TB divided
         the children up among them and adopted them into the families, raised
         'em at least. I don't where they were divided exactly, except I know
         that Grace, the second girl, was raised by Frank Lyon of Texas Ridge,
         he was married to one of the sisters, Ida.
         
         SS:  Who's sister was she, now?
         
         GC:  She was a sister of the girl that died. The woman that died of TB.
         She had, oh, four sisters, I think and three brothers and a number
         of these kept up the four children and I don^t know whether any of
         *em took two or not.
         
         SS:  He kept the children while he was alive and working?
         
         GC:  Well, actually, he 'em with the grandparents there a while then
         came back and visited and helped support *em by paying. And he died
         less than a year- One of the other Sturdevants told me that years
         later, I didn't know it at the time. You sort of wondered about him
         that he didn't find a place for his kids, but that was
         alright, he was ,dying then and was making the best of what he could; worked as
         long as possible and then died in some hospital.
         
         SS:  People like Sturdevants- do you think that they were really, I mean
         for her to be living in a tent when she was sick
         
         GC:  It was summer.
         
         SS:  Oh, the summer.
         
         GC:  late spring I guess.
         
         SS:  Do you think just perhaps too poor to try to do anything else?
         
         GC:  Well, they didn't have money, hadn*t had money at all, and a doctor
         did what he could for her and prescribed treatment. But I don't
         know- they didn't do so much, either, those days,
         
         SS:  I wonder what kind of treatment?
         
         GC:  I don't know that, I haven't any idea what they did. Except they
         wanted them in fresh air and - they wanted clean air for them and
         away from other people,infection and keep things clean. And pro
         bably the same kind of sanitary precautionsTcney take now, only
         they weren't equipped then- equipped like a hospital to do that, so
         it probably fell short,
         
         SS:  Do you think there was much concern about it spreading?
         
         GC:  Oh, yes, they were very much concerned. There was a good deal of
         concern, I know my dad was worried about it. We played with those
         Kellberg children and he- well, he said stay outdoors, don't go in
         the house as much as you can. Stay out in the fresh air if you play
         with those kids. The Pearson boys, too, I don't know it was, oh, get
         ting cold and I think each one of 'em had had a case of pneumonia
         before they got TB.
         
         SS:  Was sending them to a sanitarium considered the best thing you could
         do?
         
         GC:  Well, yes, they did. Now, I don't know whether Will ha^ ever been to
         a sanitarium or not and maybe his case was a lot like Hilma. He found
         he wasn*t getting any better and so he left and he lived in a
         separate room in his own home there . He was a fellow who took pre
         cautions himself to see that he kept away from infecting people.
         Walt, he got it later, he was his younger brother, why, about two and
         a half years 61? so, I gjjess. He went down to California. I think he
         went to one . of those sanitariums in Arizona first, I'm not sure
         that that was true, but he came back to Pasadena and lived there.
         Actually, he had done well in farming before he got this, he died
         just about '33. And he bought himself a good place there and his
         sister that was next to him in age, was unmarried, one of his sisters,
         and she came down there and stayed with him. And he gave her the
         house, paid in full for her, when he died and she had that house for
         years afterwards. She lived to be a very old lady eighty-six or
         seven.
         
         SS:  I wonder how tuberculosis did spread, how people thought that it did.
         Would you have to catch it from somebody else?
         
         GC:  That was the general feeling, I don't know. I don't know all there
         is to know about TB
         
         SS:  But you know, when you compare it with today when it's not hardly a
         problem at all-
         
         GC:  And it's been cut down tremendously now,
         
         SS:  I heard that there was a man who was—
         people were
         
         GC:  I think just too many carriers of some kind. They were strong enough
         to throw it off and not get sick, but it was there and it would
         out, maybe infect somebody else, without knowing it.
         
         SS:  I've heard of a man - that a man was killed in a logging accident on
         the Ridge. Do you remember that?
         
         GC:  Oh, yes! That, I think- one of the boys died before they reached ma
         turity, the other one lived about eighty-six years old or something
         like that. Right down here at Troy, it wasn't too many years ago that
         I was up here and talked to him.
         
         SS:  Did you hear any story about a horse falling in a well?
         
         GC:  A horse falling in a well?
         
         SS:  Yeah, on the Ridge.
         
         GC:  Well, we had a horse fall into an old cistern once and we managed to
         get him out.(Chuckles) I didn't know there was any story about that.
         
         SS:  I think there was one but it wasn't your horse, I mean, it was another
         What happened that time? How did your horse fall in?
         
         GC:  Oh, it was a boarded across well, but he was curious and got up there
         and pounded away with his hoofs ton the boards and they broke, it was
         a little platform you know, boarded across. Curious sort of horse,
         (later) Paul Rudeen married his wife, you djdn*t know Paul.
         
         SS:  No.
         
         GC:  You know Marvin?
         
         SS:  I don*t really know him.
         
         GC:  Well, his grandfather on his mother's side,  He died ina
         well digging accident. I don't know how. I don't think it was dril
         ling; they were digging, hand digging a well. I donrt know any de
         tails of that, but- I'm not even sure it happened after we came to
         the Ridge, '99, or it was before I knew anything about- old enough
         to know anything about people around, because I always remembered
         her as a widow. 
         
         SS:  Do you know how he died in the accident?
         
         GC:  I don't know just what happened.
         
         SS:  Was therepuch water witching done on the Ridge.
         
         GC:  I never heard of witching down there, maybe somebody did, but I heard
         of witching in different places here.
         
         SS:  Around this country, you mean?
         
         GC:  Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  I thought people did it most places. I'm surprised they didn't do it
         it here.
         
         GC:  I never heard of any water witches down there. Most people never
         put any stock in it, as far as I know. never heard of somebody
         witching down there, maybe they did find some of those wells by witching.
         I couldn't say. (Chuckles) I am sure that nobody on that ridge claimed
         to be a water witch. They had to have some outsider-
         
         SS:  To come in. Where do you think it was concentrated, you know, belief
         in water witching?
         who
         
         GC:  I don't know. I've heard of- my sister-in-law just died, Jill's grandyf
         among mother, she knew that it was being done on American Ridge, those peo
         ple over there. Now I guess there are quite a few people that witch
         around here for water now. I know there was water witching done for
         Mike Rudeen's big well out there. They found it where the witches
         claimed- witches said it was.
         
         SS:  Did you have a good water supply on your place?
         
         GC:  We had one good water supply. One very good spring that never ran
         dry. And very early on when I was about five years old we installed
         a little dam under that sufficient to have water in it to operate
         a hydraulic ram and laid pipe up the hillside, it was down on the
         canyon side, up the hillside and put it in a reservoir up there and
         we got water in the house.
         
         SS:  Wasn't that unusual to have a hydraulic dam?
         
         GC:  Well, we wasn't the first ones. Dad had seen them operate somewhere
         else before we put that one in and it appeared to be working alright
         on big spring down on one of the other ridges. But that was the
         only one I think that was ever installed, because most of those
         springs on the sides were not big springs. I never saw any spring
         on thee ridge along the hillside that compares to that spring in size.
         There were other springs that ran smaller streams that they used and
         building a little protection around rem and making a trough for the
         cattle they were useable. There were several little springs on our
         place that worked- one was fairly steady, it probably still is- just
         a small stream like oh, just like a trickle of coffee out of a, say
         that little percolator out there that we have, was steady. If
         I'd a witched for water I'd a witched up in that hillside above it.
         
         SS:  Did you have enough water for your needs?
         
         CG: We had enough water for our needs the house and yard and all the
         cattle and everything like that.
         
         SS:  Off the hydraulic ram?
         
         GC:  Well, yes, we could store it up in the tank, you see, and keep it
         running enough to keep the tank about full. It would gain on us. If
         we had it running steady it always gained, kept sending the water
         higher and higher to an overflow pipe we had. Sometimes we just left
         the overflow pipe go.Whem lived on that farm for
         a time, they hooked a hose to the end of it and used it to irrigate
         a little garden there to keep it going good.
         
         SS:  Did you hear about the ice caves?
         i
         
         GC:  They was just about opposite Clyde's Spur, which I referred to a
         lot.
         
         SS:  Where opposite? Which direction.
         
         GC:  On the American Ridge side, just about opposite Clyde's Spur. I was
         never in them. Sanders knew about them when we came here and my fa
         ther accompanied him down here once and I think my brother, Carl, went
         with them and they looked in those ice caves. I believe unprotected
         the rains would wash down mud, you know and sort of cover the entrance
         to them. So I don't know if they'd be exposed- I expect they're pro-
         bably still there.
         
         SS:  Were they impressed by them?
         
         GC:  Yes, they thought they were- I heard of them first and I never did
         get down there to see them. I don't know, you had to have somebody
         guide me to the spot they were covered over, but there were a
         lot of people that did not know about them, p
         
         SS:  Did you ever have that French for a teacher?
         
         GC:  Yes, here's his picture. Carlton French, he taught about four years
         I think on the Ridge.
         
         SS:  Was he the fellow that you were mentioning to me that was good? That
         talked to the kids about current affairs?
         
         GC:  Yes. He's the one. I think he really taught more than most teachers
         did, that stuck entirely to the books. regard to classes, he grou
         ped them a lot, too. He'd have those that sometimes in two or three
         grades sprung out on reading and certain things, and he could find
         they could read in one class and had to arithmetic in another, it was
         alright. He used to consolidate grades one to eight, like they'd
         have there, so he didn't have to have a class for every grade, a
         class in every subject for every grade. And it seemed to work just
         about as well. In fact, I think it got some of 'em ahead faster .
         that way. They weren't kept in a single grade when they i perform a
         little bit better- perform in the grade above and learn.
         
         SS:  Do you think that he cared about the students more?
         
         GC:  I think he did. He was interested in teaching alright. He
         teaching.
         that he
         
         SS:  I heard a story about him- used to walk out to school reading a
         book.
         
         GC:  Yes, he did. I saw him doing it lots of times. He'd found a way to
         walk from Troy, cut off fence- he'd come down the railroad track, opposite,
         justN opposite the schoolhouse where he took a trail up
         and followed the fence down there. And I would see him sometimes,
         he would be reading a book as he walked along. One thing about him,
         he was a fast walker. He was a small man, short and slender, but
         he made that trip in a hurry when he started out walking. He just
         ate up the ground at a steady speed and a fast speed. He was quite
         active. He'd sometimes play ball with the kids at recess and at
         games he was quick and active.
         
         SS:  You know, a couple of other people from the area have told me that
         he was an excellent teacher, that he was really outstanding and he
         stood out in their minds.
         
         GC:  Yeah, he stood out in their minds. Jill's grandmother went to school
         to him over on-
         
         SS:  She mentioned that to me.
         
         GC:  Yes, and she thought he was pretty good, too. And we liked him on
         Burnt Ridge, we recognized him as much better than anything we'd had
         around there up to his time.
         
         SS:  Whatever happened to him, do you know?
         
         GC:  Well, you know, he was very much interested in this Nazarene Church
         down here, he and his wife, and he went down to South Idaho and V+*^Y
         Started the Northwest Nazarene. And that was- it started from a sort
         of a school and built up into a college.
         
         GC:  — the high school and their elemeStary school-
         
         SS:  So, it started in first grade through.
         
         GC:  Yes, right on through and I don't think it began four years- real
         college work for a while.
         
         SS:  He taught down there?
         
         GC:  And he taught down there in that for quite a few years. And eventu
         ally he went to California. Now, one of the boys told me, that met
         him down there and he knew more about him- well, actually it was be
         cause of their relationship. His sister married a brother of the
         Ruvord family- yes, an uncle of the Ruvord children- there's several
         Ruvord children here. On, two, three. And their uncle married his
         sister. And that was during the time that he was teaching out there.
         Both of them were living elsewhere and the family didn't know anything
         happened.
         about it until it For that reason, they were more or
         less in touch with their uncle and he was in touch with his sister.
         And. said he went into real estate down there after while,
         a real estate man.
         
         SS:  I know Willa thought he was an awful lot better than his brother
         Burton, who was so famous.
         
         GC:  Burton was the congressman and his brother Frank taught school. Maybe
         she meant Frank. Frank was younger than Carlton.
         
         SS:  Burton was Carlton's brother?
         SB: Yes, he was, he was a little bit older, not too much than he was.
         Burton made congress at a rather youthful age and he had a long career
         there. A still older brother became a doctor, and he finished as
         Dean of the Medical School in the University of North Dakota.
         
         SS:  Do you think at this period of time that women teachers haq\hit the
         rural schools as much as they did later?
         
         GC:  No. There were still quite a few men, oh, I think probably the majority
         were still men- or women- at that time, only there were more menmen
         afterwards just disappeared. He was one of the last ones I
         think.
         
         SS:  And this was 1910 that he was teaching?
         
         GC:  Oh, he had gone- I think he left there about 1913. And I think he
         was one of the last of the men teachers in the schools around Latah
         County here, the country schools around Latah County that was, I think
         the others had dropped out,
         
         SS:  Why do you think the men stopped teaching in the rural schools?
         
         GC:  Oh, it was wages were low* they could make more at most anything.
         Make more logging than they could teaching; or working in a mill.
         They would have a tough time on supporting a family on that. French
         worked always during the summers, I know that. He worked- sometimes
         at the*sawmill in Troy. They used to have a planing mill there and
         a sawmill both, working together there. He worked in the planing mill was
         down there and he worked as a carpenter. carpentry somebody
         building houses. He worked for somebody in building houses. So he
         was constantly at work.
         
         SS:  How strict was he as a teacher?
         
         GC:  Well, not really strict. The kids didn't get away with- he didn't
         care too much if somebody spoke to somebody else during the- only if
         they made a habit of just playing, then he would generally remind
         them of that, but he never had really any difficulties. Kids liked
         him enough that they fell in with it and they were not an obstreperous
         group out there at all. They were pretty mild as compared to some
         of the kids, even in their own time.
         
         SS:  Do you think that was because their parents—
         
         GC:  Their parents, yes, they found a kid not getting along in school,
         theyfdbe more afraid of their parents than they would of the teacher,
         what they might do about it.
         
         SS:  What kind of obedience was expected by the parents?
         
         GC:  Oh, they expected pretty total obedience, most of 'em, I think.
         Probably didt't always get it. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Now, I'm really curious about that because that's the sort of thing
         that you really can't put a finger on it anymore, I mean, nowdays
         the way kids are raised, it's a little different than it was then.
         
         GC:  It's permissive.
         
         SS:  How much would a parent
         
         GC:  Oh, they generally didn't interfere with their fun and play and all
         that sort of thing, games and all that. But they wanted the kids to
         behave themselves. They wouldn't stand for a kid being insulting to
         people or anything like that, to talk up. I mean, you found a kid
         bejng sassy to some neighbor of theirs for no good reason, he'd probably
         get a darn good lickin' . (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  What about to the parent? Did you call your father, 'sir'?
         
         GC:  No.AWe did what he told us to and that was about all.
         
         SS:  Did you need to be told very much what you needed to do?
         
         GC:  Quite a bit. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  You waited for the order to come?
         
         GC:  Oh, well, as regard to work and things like that, we knew what had
         to be done. Pretty hard to know exactly what went on in your neigh
         bors' private homes. But as a rule, they were pretty respectable
         acting when you were out among others, only some were a little harder
         than others. There were among the young men a few fights that took
         place from time to time.
         
         SS:  Was your mother, for instance in your family, was your mother easy
         with the kids?
         
         GC:  Oh, yeah, she was easy. She was greatly concerned with the welfare
         of the kids, it was her first thoughts.
         I told you about those mills at Bovard and the one further
         x Troy, but there must have been an awful lot of small mills here
         and there around the country, I don't know where they all are. Years
         one later I talked to of the old-timers on American Ridge, and he
         told me where mills had been working there. And he knew.one of the
         Burnt Ridge old settlers over there, because he was there a young
         man and he'd worked at that mill before he homesteaded on 
         That was Clarence Johnson's father. So there was milling over there
         and they settled mills here and there.
         
         SS:  What about that O.K. Olson mill? That ran for quite a while.
         Oh, that ran for a long time, I don*t know when it even stopped. I
         don't know when it ceased
         
         SS:  I heard that some of the Burnt Ridgers worked there in the winter.
         
         GC:  Some of 'em undoubtedly did, yes. Yes, that's close by, down
         there in the wintertime. Quite a few of tem sometimes got employment
         some like that.
         
         SS:  You know, I wanted to ask you a little more about laying out of school
         and the effects of that. And I was thinking about that; do you think
         that if you looked at the kids on the ridges, that you knew about,
         do you think that most of the boys or just some of the boys would lay
         out for periods of time?
         
         GC:  A large part of them did, when they reached a certain age.
         
         SS:  Say twelve-
         
         GC:  Twelve, thirteen, fourteen. Twelve- as early as twelye, some stayed
         till later.
         
         SS:  Well, when you're talking about laying up- what kind of a time period
         
         GC: would the kid be laying out for?
         Well, in the fall to get help^when the fall crops were being planted,
         the fall work done. And in the spring when the spring planting, the
         spring farming. Those were the periods that they were out, sometimes
         at both ends.
         
         SS:  And how long might that be in the fall?
         
         GC:  Oh, you might miss a month and a half of school in the fall and a
         month and a half in the spring, or somewhere around there. Some of
         tem stay out more.
         
         SS:  Would the teacher have any say-so about something like that?
         
         GC:  I think they were, but I think they mostly ignored it, because they
         knew what the situation was, and it would be kind of a fuss probably
         if they did. It wasn't until about 1912 that they laid down stricter
         state law, undoubtedly for this same reason that they found too much
         of it- too many people were out. And then I think that they just
         ceased with the that they put on it. They laid penalties on
         it as to what would happen.
         
         SS:  This wouldn't affect the girls? Just the boys?
         
         GC:  There were girls, too, that were much affected. There, for
         instance like our neighbor north of us  His wife died whenoh,
         what was his- I imagine the oldest girl was only about fourteen.
         And for quite a long time before that her mother was so sick so much
         of the time j she stayed home a great deal of the time. And at
         that time I don't know she didn't go to school for a while until
         fAlMP got better situation and he sent all his girls away to school.
         And I think Minnie eventually, I don't know whether she finished the
         university, but she drew a teaching certificate, this same girl that
         had to lay out and taught until she was married. And one of the
         younger girls, well, one of the younger girls went to school quite
         a while and married young and another one became a teacher also and
         was one until she retired- reached retirement age. She held a very
         ming. But, there was the other family, this girl that I said died
         of tuberculosis, Hilma Kellberg, she was out of school a great deal,
         because her mother was having one baby after another those years
         and she was the oldest girl and one brother was older and ten child
         ren younger, and you can imagine. She stayed home to help her mother
         and stayed out when the children were born and if they were overloaded
         with work around there she stayed home. She finished- she didn't finish
         grade school until she was sevetteen as a result. And in the light
         good job there, State Supervisor of Home Economics training in Wyo
         intelligence there was no excuse for it except not having had enough
         schooling. But she went on; she went through high school in three
         years then and took a couple of years at the normal school at Lewiston,
         it was a teachers' college then, two years, and was teaching for
         a number of years. And that was what happened to her, that one summer
         she was helping her brother out on this farm that she got terribly
         laid up wi just overwork and exposure and never stopped when she had
         bad colds and got TB going.
         
         SS:  Well, it looks like there was a- maybe you could say it was a con
         flict between desire for education and the demands of work-
         
         GC:  Demands of^work. A lot of it was, in the cases of many of those peo
         ple it was. Now some of them did not care for school and had no am
         bition to go on to high school and things like that, but they didn't
         know anything about it. If those kids had been young at the present
         time, why, I think they would all coming to school for
         high school and done as well as anybody else and quite a few of 'em
         would have continued.
         
         SS:  Do y°u think that there were cases, many cases, where a family would
         send a kid to school a hardship to what the youngster could be doing
         home I'm wondering, would a kid go to school— if it
         was a case of hardship, would school always lose out? Or would the
         work lose out sometimes, too?
         
         GC:  A little of both, but I believe the hardship won out quite a bit.
         Well, the attitude toward education- they didn*t really believe that
         education was for a person of ordinary talents. We had a great res
         pect for educationjand it took an awfully smart person to get an education.
         among some of the older people. They didn't really inducted
         conceive a farmers' kids as being- intellectual
         variety. There were plenty of kids then that were plenty smart,
         they'd have done alright in any competition. Most any competition
         that the college
         
         SS:  Well, take like your family; you were telling me that your two oldest
         brothers bore the brunt of clearing the land.
         
         GC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Then when it came to the third brother, Joe, he got to go away to
         school. But what happened? Was it because the land was all cleared
         up?
         
         GC:  It was sort of cleared up and things were going better, we were get
         ting crops and getting more money.
         
         SS:  So it -as a matter of the economics?
         
         GC:  Economics, yes, economics, yes. And Homer Peterson, the teacher
         down there, went down to our farm one day and told my dad if he could
         stand it he ought to give Joe an education.^ I think that influenced
         Dad, too. He was glad to hear that he had a boy that the teacher
         thought that much of.
         
         SS:  Do you think that's what did it?
         
         GC:  Well, it influenced him, yes.
         was it the prep part? bid
         
         SS:  When Joe went to Lewiston, work when he was down
         there?
         
         GC:  Well, he did part of the time, yes. He had jobs at different things.
         
         SS:  Then did he keep going after he finished the prep part?
         
         GC:  Yes, he kept on going and he taught in, oh- before he got his degree
         he taught about a couple of years in a country school and then he
         went on- oh, he taught a year at Winchester, in the grade schools
         there and went to Bonners Ferry. He became principal of the grade
         school there and went to Douglas from there, Douglas, Arizona from
         there as the principal of the grade school. And it wasn't until af
         ter the war that he went back and- He went to several summer schools
         in California, once at Columbia University in New York. But it wasn't
         until after he came back from World War I that he took a year at the
         University of Washington and got a degree out of it. He got a double
         degree bachelor of arts and bachelor of education.
         
         SS:  How much older was he than you?
         
         GC:  About nine years.
         
         SS:  What about your two older brothers? How much education did they get?
         
         GC:  They d/dn't take any formal education. They had a habit of thinking
         they were too old for education. Walter, a couple of winters went
         up and attended a business college in Spokane and he used it for a
         little while, but not right away, but he went up to- They did farming.
         Paul farmed down here most of his life and Walter went up to Calgary.
         And after working around there for a while he looked at some land
         there and actually filed a claim, but he said it was too cold a coun
         try to live in. He came down to Montana, which isn't too much warmer,
         and thetothe settled, oh, he was about thirty by that time. And then
         he bought a relinquishment from a fellow wanted to get out and then
         he just held onto that land and he bought more land. Well, he kept
         on farming it himself for quite a few years and he found it
         pretty hard and tough to handle the machinery. He said that
         bothered him, the constant rattle of machinery and tractors and that,
         he come out with a headache every night. And so the last ten years,
         I guess, of his life- well, more than that- I think it was about fif
         teen years or sixteen years- when he was around sixty he rented it
         out. Well, he used to stay up there around the end of the summers 
         in Montana, but all the friends held made lived there and he'd go
         down mostly to Long Beach in the winter; lived down there.
         
         SS:  Did either he or gaul- did they get through the eighth grade or what?
         
         GC:  They were probably through the eighth grade as working is concerned.
         But that was a funny thing, too. Nobody seemed to know when they
         were through the eighth grade or how they got out of the eighth grade.
         I think some of those teachers never informed the kids that there was
         such a thing as state examinations, as there were in those days. At
         least nobody - they never trained a class to do that. French was
         the first one to do that.
         
         SS:  To prepare kids for exams?
         
         HC: Yes. Oh, three kids when Steelsmith was there learned about when the
         examinations^coming and they went somewhere and they went across to
         American Ridge. They rode horseback across the canyon on those trails
         I told you about and took the examinations over there.
         
         SS:  Was Paul one of them?
         
         GC:  No, that was Carl.
         
         SS:  Carl, that's right because Willa Carlson told me that Carl had gone
         over to American Ridge.
         
         GC:  Yes and two other boys there. And one thing about it, there was
         some classes he had never given any classes in to what corresponded
         to the eighth grade, and that was in government. When he learned
         that they were wanting to take that examination, he advised them to
         read the Constitution of the United States that was in back of the
         history books. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Sounds like good preparation.
         
         GC:  But Carl said it was one of the easiest tests. He said it was like
         all the law he'd heard about and things like that that went on. So
         I guess.that was just as good a way to prepare as any.
         
         SS:  What did Carl get? He was older than you?
         
         GC:  Yes, about six years. Oh, Carl went to Normal, too and started
         teaching and after he'd taught about four years before he went into
         navy in the First World War. I think he was starting his fifth year,
         yes, I know he was, because he wasn't in shape to take a physical exam
         ination for a while. He'd been playing ball over in Montana, base
         ball over in Montana and stuffed a leg in sliding a base over there,
         and he was hobbling around when it was time for school, and well, af
         ter it seemed to be healed up why he entered the navy about November
         of that year. And then when he came back he also finished college.
         And he taught most of his life after that. First he was up here and
         then he went down to a few places around for a few years and then he
         settled in California; Santa Maria for twenty-odd years until he re
         tired
         
         SS:  Did Joe continue teaching after he got his degree?
         
         GC:  Oh, yes, he continued until he was- oh, he spent in all- let's see
         he spent, I guess about from 1920 to 1948, I think it was in the
         schools of Douglas, Arizona. He started there as a principle to the
         grade school and he was superintendent for the last twenty-one years
         I think.
         
         SS:  Paul, also farmed, didn't he? That's what he did?
         
         GC:  Farmed, yes. Yes, he farmed the home place there after he got mar
         ried for quite a while and then he bought land over in Kooskia, over
         there, up the Clearwater up in that area This was on Harris Ridge
         as it was called. Yeah,he spent about eleven years over there, some
         thing like that. Then he came back over here and farmed the home
         place for a while and then he bought a place out near Robinson
         lake. He was on that until he sold it and after that he lived in
         town here. He worked for the Rural Electrification for quite a long
         time; stayed on that. He worked on th^t when he was farming, too.
         
         SS:  What about your sisters?
         
         GC:  Oh, this sister became a teacher, too, but, Ellen, my older sister,
         never did. She took a business course later on. She also was sort
         of an ungraded finish from school out there.
         
         SS:  Was she the older one?
         
         GC:  Yes, she was about ten years older than Edith.
         She married, oh, I don't know- she worked at various things like that.
         In her youth she kept house for people for a while and then she worked
         as a bookkeeper for a lumber out in Seattle, eventually she
         died. She was about twenty-five when she married and he lived there
         and farmed for a while then he spent most of his life as construct
         ion worker. Building construction. They lived in Lewiston for quite
         a long time and then moved down to, oh, San Jose, California. That
         was about 1944, they went down there. And they lived there the rest
         of their lives.
         
         SS:  It sounds like the older kids in the family, I mean the oldest ones
         did without much education.
         
         GC:  Yes, yes, they did. Yes, all of us eventually became college gradu
         ates- the four youngest. Ldith waited the longest. She taught for
         quite a few years.
         
         SS:  This Edith?
         
         GC:  Yes, Edith.
         
         SS:  Are you the youngest in the family?
         Yes. Oh, I think, let's see, she started teaching, well, let's see,
         I guess it was - it was 1915 when she finished high school and 1925
         well, 1926, when she graduated from the University of California.
         She'd gone there, but eleven years, most of that eleven, most of
         that eleven was spent- part of it was spent in school at about three
         different periods, and the rest of it in teaching.
         Well, one thing I was wondering from what you were saying before;
         did you think it was more likely that girls would go on to high
         school than boys in the early days?
         Well, I believe so. There was a tendency that way; but not such an
         awful tendency around Troy. There were a lot of girls that didn't
         go on to school.
         There were a lot of girls that didn't go to high school, too?
         Yes, there were. Among the farm girls, especially. No, I'm not so
         sure of that either: I remember from my high school days there wereseems
         to me that-
         One, two of 'em- one of 'em was a year ahead of me, rented a room
         together in a place there and did their own cooking, in a little up
         stairs part of the house. They were from outside.
         Outside Troy?
         Outside the area- outside of the Troy area. Both of em lived
         up here between- on the Moscow road somewhere- off. And both of
         those went on to school afterwards, college and so on and they con
         tinued to get there. And it was an awfully scant amount of kids.
         Well, there were quite a bunch out of those that went to that school
         that finished the high school, but went on further. If they went
         that far they seemed to go on, a lot of them.
         So, there were a number of kids in Troy that-
         
         Yes, -
         
         As much as the majority of the graduating class from high school?
         Well, now, my graduating class- I think, I think they all did. I
         think there were only seven in my graduating class down here. There
         started a good deal more but they dropped out along the way. Moved
         away, some of 'era, I don1t know but what some of those may have gone
         on to school, that moved away and some just didn't. One or two died
         rather young. One died in his second year- he died one summer after
         the year's school was out. But I think eveyrone of those went to
         school somewhat.
         
         SS:  Well, what was the thinking of people like yourself? Why go to
         college?
         
         GC:  Oh, I think about that time you understood it more or less, why you
         were going by that time. There was less every year about this- you
         saw others going away. several others that are going away
         from Burnt Ridge to go to school, for instance, before i did. See
         Joe was probably the first one I think that ever did, but he was nine
         years older than I was. In the meantime, I don't know, several of
         the Pearson children went away to school. Well, professionally, one
         of the girls became a nurse and one of the boys became a dentist.
         And one never went to school and he just stuck right here and went
         to work at a bank and progressed right along when he once got there.
         He was the cashier in a branch of the Bank of America in Los Angeles
         in the Los Angeles area at least when he retired.
         
         SS:  But to go to college were people going there because they expected
         a career out of going? Was that the main reason?
         
         GC:  I think that was true. We all expected a career. And mostly - people
         I knew at the University were there for, they expected a career out
         of it when I went to school, because an awful lot of students
         school there were partly paying their own way by working.
         Some during the school year and some would lay out a couple of years.
         And then come back.. I think the boys^are almost universally pointing
         for a career of some kind and some of the girls may not have been;
         never explained themselves to me. I think more of them just were going
         to college along with their friends because their parents wanted em
         to.
         
         SS:  Do you think that they were looking to making money in a short term
         before they were married and that sort of thing?
         
         GC:  Well, maybe some of them did. Actually there were some of those that
         were there- one of those was my sister- -primary certificate for tear
         ching first, went out and taught, return); There were women
         there in school had three, and four and five years teaching behind
         them coming back to finish out.
         
         SS:  Why did you decide you didn't want to be a farmer?
         
         GC:  What?
         
         SS:  Why did you decide you didn't want to follow in your father's foot
         steps and be a farmer?
         
         GC:  Well, the thing is, to get farms required money. You don't divide up
         those kind of farms in between children because you'd just create a
         hardship on them. Places that are meant for one family
         Paul were better farmers than I'd ever be. It's always interesting
         to study and'C school I decided to go that way. Especially
         after Joe and Carl went into school they kept harping at us younger
         ones to get an education.
         
         SS:  What about the prospects to stay in the area? Was that important to
         most of the young people? Did they want to stay here? Where they
         grew up?
         
         GC:  Well, I guess there was a certain amount of that, yes, they'd like to
         stay in the same area. A lot of 'em did. Maybe some of just
         because they had certain things to keep 'em here and others didn't.
         Lot of 'em moved out. It usually depend on the size of the family.
         Five boys in our family ancL five boys in the Kellberg family and five
         boys in the Hupt'Tft family. Four in the Pearson family; four in
         Frank Swanson's family. All- well, the grade range would be about
         fifteen years of all those people- age range. They couldn't all
         stay on the farm, so some of 'em knew they'd have to do something
         else and they got out and left, all of those moved out. Herman
         Ruberg remained on the Ruberg place out there, but he was the oldest
         boy and his mother was widowed by that time and he married rather
         late in life. All the Pearson boys went. Willie and Walt went down
         and stayed when they lost health, eventually died. Adolph farmed for
         a while. he said he didn't like it, it was too uncertain a life;
         might have a good crop, might have a bad he wanted something more
         steady he said. And Joe never tried it. I don't think he would
         have cared for it either, he'd decided by that time that the farm
         didn't have any attractions for him.
         
         SS:  Did one of the boys take the farm?
         
         GC:  None of 'em did, they eventually sold it out to the father of Rudolph
         Smith, who lives there now.
         
         SS:  So there was a farm that nobody wanted.
         
         GC:  None of the kids wanted it, no. Well, Mrs. Pearson moved to Portland
         where one of her daughters was married and Edla was down there train
         ing to be a nurse, one of the girls, and she took the three younger -
         she had a couple of the younger hhildren with her. The youngest
         daughter, I guess then, too, was about grown up. Well, she grew up
         down there and married. And then by that time Joe had gone and started
         working in the bank. And Adolph comple
         ting dentistry. And it went on. There was the- no they just cleared
         out. And it was one of the best farms on the Ridge. I don't
         know, if I had a selection of a farm on the Ridge, I'm not so sure
         but that I'd take that one. Except for one thing: they had had
         problems on water,
         
         SS:  Well, for yourself- could you have stayed and taught in this county,
         in this area if you'd wanted to?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know. I just took one of the first ones I had an oppor
         tunity to take, and thdfr/in the state of Washington. Found it avail
         able. No, I didn't really want to-
         
         SS:  To stay here.
         
         GC:  To stay here. I wanted to try some other place. I'd moved around
         quite a bit in the early days and I wasn't too satisfied with teaching
         at all. I left teaching when I was about thirty-five.
         
         SS:  Why weren't you satisfied with it?
         
         GC:  Oh, various things. The pay was never too good up to the time I left
         it. Then, it's a tiring, wearisome job, I found it. Trying to teach
         people and interest them in their work. I can see why ulcers if one
         of the common complaints of teachifig. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Think it's because the kids that you're teaching aren't interested
         in the work?
         
         GC:  Lack of interest. Oh, there's sort of an undercurrent of a little
         noise, things I taught mathematics a good deal. One thing it was definite, you
         knew what the kids were getting and what they weren't getting, but
         it was somewhat different when it came to actually teaching the stu
         dent that had no mathematical sense at all. He was completely frus-
         trated. There was two ways of looking at that.. You kinda had to
         shove aside a little dirt and muck to get i( into where it was, that
         is, every winter, I suppose, there's a certain amount of soil swept
         down that hillside, sort of covered it over.
         
         SS:  But it's ice all year around, right?
         
         GC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  I wonder what it was like, what it looks like on the inside?
         
         GC:  Crystals, little crystals, he said, hanging in ice. There'd been
         apparently a lot of water frozen at one time.
         
         SS:  Stayed that cold.
         
         GC:  It stayed that cold inside. Just what caused it I don't know. I sort
         of wondered about , why an ice mine, why doesn't it melt?
         
         SS:  But you know, we were talking about leaving the area and I'm really
         interested in that, because you see most all the old-timers I've tal
         ked to are the people that stayed, never left.
         
         GC:  Yes, those are the ones you'd find here.
         
         SS:  The ones I'd find, right. But that's only part of the story, of
         course. About yourself, you didn't really have any particular desire
         to stay. Why do you think that was?
         
         GC:  I don't know, I don't know,t starting in on something in your own homeamong
         your own home people, I think would be the hardest job of all,
         even though you've known 'em all your life. I went to another town
         I was accepted as a teacher, if I tried teaching at Troy, they'd say,
         "He's Bud Carlson." (Chuckles) I don't think any- some people have
         gone back to their own hometowns and liked it; established themselves.
         Apparently that's what Roger SwanSfitf.done- /the superintendent'S But
         for most people I think it's better to be away from your own home
         town, among your own people. You can make it among strangers a lot
         easier. They might come of a family which had never been fond of
         another family and those things sometimes last through generations.
         They're not old-time Kentucky feuds, but they- those things persist.
         
         SS:  That would make it unpleasant for- in your work, or just ?
         
         GC:  It could. Make you an unhappy person.
         
         SS:  What about friendships through? Can you develop more friendships
         that are as deep as the ones that you left behind?
         
         GC:  I think so, if you stay around long enough.
         
         GC:  Do you think you might have gone into farming if you could have?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know whether I would've or not. Maybe I could've if I'd
         put my mind to it, that is, but I didn't really have the desire to.
         You see the trying parts as well as the good parts when you grow up
         on a farm. Sometimes a lot of work you put in for nothing and start
         over again, you see. The poor crop yields, the poor price years and
         so on.
         
         SS:  You agree with the Pearson boy that said that it's too risky?
         
         GC:  Yes. He had something there. He said he said he didn't think he'd
         care to farm, he tried it one year. He'd been in high school
         studied agriculture course there and he got real interested in how
         it ought to be done and when he faced the practical problems getting
         in his crops and harvested and his delays and did the workAthrough
         the weather and all that, why, he began to be concerned that the prac
         tical everyday life of a farmer didn't appeal to him.
         
         SS:  What about most of the younger generation from Burnt Ridge? Did
         most of them leave the area?
         
         GC:  Yes, I would say so. There were four-five of the six Rubergs children
         left; Well, Herman eventually left too, but he left when he was quite
         along in years and he and his wife sold out and he went to Pullman
         and he worked a little while longer - he worked for the state college
         for a while until he retired, but, oh, the others all went out to
         work. Clarence became a barber, Victor became an automobile mechanic.
         The two youngest, Hugo and Richard went to college. Hugo went
         to work for a gas and electric company in California and spent many,
         many years there until he retired. Richard worked for that same company
         for a while then he extended into otner things. He ran a
         taxicab service for a few years and then he went back for a refresher
         course in education and finished as a teacher. The girl, she worked
         out in Spokane for quite a while as a housekeeper for a family and
         then she married up there and married again after her first hus
         band died, I guess it was.
         
         SS:  Do you think girls left the area as much as boys did?
         
         GC:  Well, a lot of them left, yes. Some married men that lived here and
         a few lived on here but a lot of them left. Some had property that
         they inherited or something like that or stayed for other reasons
         I guess. Some stayed with their folks a long time when they were
         old, as they were getting older, then,there were quite a few of the
         families that moved out. Kellberg's daughters, all except Helen, who
         married Ernie Anderson and bought out the other heirs when they went
         to settle up there, is really the only one that stayed here. Well,
         Elva married a man who became a- Elvera married a man who became a
         missionary and one of them married a man- she lived in Moscow, and
         still does. And she went on to school both before and after she married
         and got work at the University there, I she was a lab
         assistant, something, I'm not sure what she was. One of the boys
         tried farming- two of 'em tried farming the home farm out there. One
         of 'era went into renting- rentier land elsewhere and one quit to become
         a mechanic. And, oh, one of them married a girl and continued
         to live right there on the farm. She held land. And one boy went
         back East- he wanted to become a minister but he found the grind for
         the education a little tough and he left there. I don't know what
         he did. He worked as a truck driver part of the time and he had a
         shop at one time. One of his brothers told me. A repair shop; tool
         repair shop. They scattered out. Another one tried farming, too for
         a while.
         
         SS:  One of the Kellbergs?
         
         GC:  Yes. .He left and he went to work in Spokane.
         
         SS:  It sounds like maybe getting a college education was somewhat unusual
         for the younger generation on Burnt Ridge?
         
         GC:  Well, yes, it was, I guess. For the ones, toy age and below my age, it
         increased. For my age and older it was rather rare.
         
         SS:  So it was a trend towards getting a college education.
         
         GC:  -a college education, a trend. The two youngest Ruberg boys were
         younger than I, the rest were older. The two younger went to college.
         None of the oldest Kellberg children went, but, well, Hilma started
         it, actually, and she started it late after she became nearly a young
         woman and, well, have to drop down- well, Teddy went for a while, but
         he left it, after in high school, he did go for a while and
         he dropped out and tried first farming and then he got a job in Spok
         ane which suited him there becaur e he stayed there from World War II
         onwards, about that time. There was Elva- she's another one that- she
         and Hilma are the ones in that family that really persisted
         in school. And Alner sent his children there- well, the older girl
         was older, but she was one that would- was handicapped by the feeling
         that she had to stay home after her mother died with all the younger
         children around, so she probably started before I did. But the
         younger ones went on to school a good deal and Gladys, who didn't
         marry, made a profession of it. And, well, there were certain families
         there. One of Paul Rudeen's boys went on to college, the other didn't 
         It was more a question of choice, I think. And the children of those
         fellows who stayed here and married, they all seemed to * on
         to school a lot of 'em. And some of Ed Swanson's girls went on to
         school, too.
         
         SS:  College?
         
         GC:  College, yes. I don't know how many were college graduates. Well,
         Rowena went into nursing, that's different. But I think one of 'em
         married too young to finish college or even really gotten there. But
         there were others, I guess.
         
         SS:  Would you try to put on your statistician's hat and think about it
         In a very rough way, how would you size up the-
         The trend has always been upward all the time of people going up
         through high school, which they all practically try to do now, and
         going on to college.
         
         SS:  Of your generation, would you guess one out of four would go to
         college, maybe?
         
         GC:  I doubt it. No, I don't think so.
         
         SS:  Or maybe one of six?
         
         GC:  Yes, I don't know the percentage of the population in school
         certain age groups was pretty low about the time I started to college,
         I suppose maybe you 4 find statistics, but it was low.
         
         SS:  I'm thinking in terms of the area. In terms of Burnt Ridge.
         
         GC:  Oh, yeah, Burnt Ridge.
         
         SS:  And even the Troy area.
         
         GC:  Well, I don't know, they just differed too much from the general
         Trend. And I suppose they sent a certain number to school, too.
         I don't know- in the If cases I went to in high school, several of
         those people went on to school.
         
         SS:  What about them leaving the area? What about that? Do you think
         there was a large percentage of the younger generation left this
         county?
         
         GC:  I think there must be quite a few, yes. There are some that have
         been here a long time, but that depends upon the feeling back forty,
         fifty years. There's a lot of 'em that never- people that have come
         in since that time.
         
         SS:  But your age group- the younger kids on the farms on Burnt Ridge
         probably a pretty solid majority of them left and didn't stay?
         
         GC:  Yes. I'd say so, the majority left. The Smith family stayed. Two
         of 'em are still around and one was here a large part of his life,
         moved too. One . down into Oregon, I think, he was just farming
         though down there. And the girls both married- 
         Give me a guess, and I know this is just guessing again; would you
         guess maybe four out of five would leave of the early generation?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know that. Maybe three out of four. One generation
         dovetails into another, it would be a little hard to- (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Do you think of the trend toward staying or leaving changed through
         time? Or do you think it's always been a high out-migration?
         
         GC:  I think there's been an out-migration, regularly. Probably not so
         are nowdays
         much since- well, the famii A smaller than they were then.
         There were families at Burnt Ridge- eight, , twelve, six, nine
         five, six, five, - four would be about the smallest I can remember
         except for one or two instances. Three in one. But most of them
         was those high numbers- what we call high numbers now.
         
         SS:  I've got another thorny question along those lines. Thinking about
         the impact of the car. Do you think that the car made it easier for
         people to stay in the area, because they could go farther to work
         or would they more likely leave the area because they could get away
         easier?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know, that it had that much effect. The car- the reason
         I think it was a little easier on 'em, they liked life a little
         better. They can get places quicker. I don't know, I think it tended
         , to make life more liveable for the farmers, they could get out a
         little once in a while easier. And I think that helped to keep people.
         
         GC:  Some were more experimental than others.
         
         SS:  The amount of economic pressure is what counted?
         
         GC:  I think it was in most cases. Some were more inclined to take a
         chance somewhere else. Well, that's just the way human beings are.
         het And some if they thought they had a fairly good thing they'd stick
         to it.
         
         SS:  Do you think the main motivation was thinking how you could makedo
         the best for yourself toward making a living?
         
         GC:  More or less that. Of course, the family ties played a part, too,
         that is, some of them would like to remain where others members of
         the^ family lived, and that xvas not as great though as the ones that
         came in in the first place, because lots of those people on Burnt
         Ridge were related to each other. Maybe one man in the family'd come
         first and they'd tell others about it and soon they'd collect. May
         be a cousin that would collect and so on. And I think it was very
         much the same the other places because there was always a few of
         the old-timers date from two or three families of them. Two and
         three families that were related all over. Sometimes it was just
         people from the same vicinity, the midwestern or eastern state that
         came together. They were not related but they knew each other be
         fore they came.
         
         SS:  When you went to the university were most of the young people that
         you knew there, were most of them from rural parts of Idaho? People
         that were-
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know, I think probably it was about even ratio, the
         population that come from towns, small towns and big towns and that.
         I think- they seemed to have come from the country and also from the
         towns. There were quite a few, oh, well, Boise is the biggest town,
         you know and more thickly settled around it than some other
         towns. It had a good representation. Moscow was probably in pro
         portion to its size had more than any because they had the university
         on their doorstep and it kind of influenced the number that went,
         too, I think, they saw college life up there and it was right there,
         women
         
         SS:  Thinking about that were going to school; you said that you
         there probably was a tendency for more of them to go on.
         
         GC:  Well, a lot of them went on, yes, but not, all, too. I tell you
         the women were in the minority all the tim«, that I was there. I
         don't knov;, there were quite a few more men registered regularly than
         girls. I think that is even now since that time over
         the whole country.
         
         SS:  There were a couple of things about your thoughts of your father's
         views that I wanted to ask you more about; One of them was, talking
         about the Socialist Party and socialist thinking. I was thinkingwhat
         do you think that the Socialists thought about farmers - and
         they still their land?
         *Mr CKi^ed
         
         GC:  See, the Socialist doctorine of the Socialist Party, around 1900 to
         1912, there on, it seems to have fallen into abeyance now, was the
         state useage of land as a public thing. Shoufil have public ownership
         because it was the food crop of the country and also the source of
         mineral and forest products and such.
         
         SS:  That would include the farmers, too?
         
         GC:  Yes, it would include the farmers, the socialistic .
         I don't know how it started.
         
         SS:  Would that mean the farmers would be working for the state?
         
         GC:  Yeah, yeah. Be employed by the state. It would mean that if they
         carried that into effect. I don't know how my dad would actually
         At have liked that. i loved his farm. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  That's what I was thinking, as a farmer, you know.
         
         GC:  I think he was more in than with these theories, which he was
         interested in is the logical to handle this stuff. That anything for
         public ownership- that anything that was publicly used ought to be
         owned by the public in common, as administers for it. Such things
         as clothes and houses and automobiles and things like that . was
         a man's own concern. I don't think the Socialist party ever got
         down to itemizing what could be considered private and what could be
         considered public. But that was the general thought.
         
         SS:  But farmers lack interest in general in the Socialist party
         might have something to do with the fact that they would be afraid -
         they weren't too interested in giving up their rights on land.
         
         GC:  No, they wouldn't, particularly- farmers were not socialists mostly.
         You found socialism mostly in the cities among the working, labor
         cjretfp. The farmers, he got his home built and started doing
         something with it, he wanted to hold on. They'd wthe last ones to
         vote for anything like that.
         What was the socialist idea at that time of the workers as beigg in
         the worst position?
         Well, they felt that they were, and actually, you know, the position
         of the- of workers on various things was not very good. Women were
         awfully poor paid; garment factory and things like that; for the em
         ployed women. They had a distinctly lower scale for them and it
         seems like just a bare living wage if they economized. Oh, that
         reminds me of a book that was cursed by some when it came out and I
         think even banned in some places. It was written by David Graham
         Phillips.^ Written in the form of a novel, Susan Lennox. Did you
         ever read that?
         
         SS:  No, hadn't heard of that.
         
         GC:  Well, he died about 1911 and I think the book was
         lished at the time of his death and published afterward, maybe '
         1912. And, well, he deals with the situation of the laboring classes
         in a certain way. His was based largely on the prostitution systems
         found in Cincinnati and New York City. He doesn*t name Cincinnati,
         gut was the place where he studied conditions and what forced
         girls in there. He was a great believer it was economic pressure
         that was the main cause. Well, it's quite a book. It wasn't written
         in the style of some of the books now that like to use every ex
         pression used in oral conversation in the book, but very restrai
         ned, very clear-cut, gets the ideas across without using anything
         like that. No pornography at all.
         
         SS:  Did you feel when you were growing up (noise)
         
         GC:  I don't know, that's the way I heard it from most of the people
         that talked about it, when I was growing up. They talked about
         those things, older people-
         
         SS:  That conditions were bad?
         
         GC:  Conditions were bad. There was strikes going on at that time and
         sometimes the repressment of strikes resulted in a lot of deaths,
         you know. Pitched battles. The useless strikebreakers, as they
         were called, or scabs. That was common. It was the later
         administrations of Theodore Roosevelt, it seems to me that
         I heard most about that kind of thing. I believe things became calmed
         around Woodrow Wilson and there were quite a few distinct laws,laws
         passed early in Wilson's presidency that probably helped. And there
         was a certain reformation of the banking industry that helped and a
         few other things.
         
         SS:  think there was some labor legislation- protection, at that time.
         
         GC:  Yes, there was.
         
         SS:  Did college people when you were growing up, was this kind of thing
         on young people's minds?
         
         GC:  Oh, they talked about that stuff. Yes,oh in the mining towns in
         North Idaho, they were always informed on everything- all the
         laws and things like that, and conditions under which they worked.
         Some of 'era had worked at the mines already before they came to col
         lege, they worked sometimes during summers.
         
         SS:  Were they strong for labor?
         
         GC:  Strong for labor. I don't knoi ; if they all stayed that way. I look
         at it that they were on the losing side in the economic war. There
         was- I'm sure though in wages paid for labor on farms and towns around
         here a distinct upper trend- of course, there's always an upper trend
         that's just slightly inflationary about every ten years it was jacked
         up a dollar or something like that, with the kind of wages they paid.
         Of course, at the same time, your prices of goods rose along with it.
         But I think on the whole, everybody was a little bit better off than
         they were say five years or ten years or even five years-^-before.
         I think things went a little bit better except that we had these
         hard times every so often, These depressions come along due to what
         knows- nobody wll ever agree on that. JUST why.
         
         SS:  What about like the girls- your sisters working - doing fruit picking
         around here? Were they paid well for that?
         
         GC:  Well, they generally paid by the box or the bucket or whatever
         it was that they were paid by. Some made pretty good wages, handy
         and nimble on their feet and with their fingers and things like that
         and some of them found it didn't pay too well. Oh, they did that.
         I remember some of the orchards that existed, but they were probably
         ones that- there must have been a lot of them that I never got over.
         I never got over to those at that age, I was just- that was really
         before I got started going to school, most of it, and I never got
         over to American Ridge or Little Bear Ridge, they were still for
         eign countries to me.
         
         SS:  That's where they did their picking?
         
         GC:  That's where more of it was done than elsewhere. And they were lar
         ger ridges, you see, there were more of them. There were some on
         Burnt Ridge, alright, but nottmflre than the local people could handle
         because it's a comparatively small ridge; about five miles long and
         not so awfully wide. But, American Ridge starts at Troy and ends at
         Juliaetta, sloped out into Juliaetta at the end of it. And Little
         Bear ends at Kendrick.
         
         SS:  When did these orchards go ? When were they finished for commercial
         usage?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know just when, they went out one by one. We don't see
         too many of 'em anymore, I don't think. There may be a few left. I
         wonder if the Nelsons on Bear Ridge had any orchards left, now Little
         Bear Ridge?
         
         SS:  Nothing commercial any more.
         
         GC:  Well, he had the famous cherry orchards, his father was
         "Cherry hielson". Oh, I think it just went gradually, it was begin
         ning to go when I was a small boy. I know some of the ones came out-
         Sanders, our neighbor, had ripped out some of his before and left a
         little piece there, orchards, that were sort of in the way of far
         a piece of acreage .one group, so he tore out the rest. And
         left a few down in the orchard by the house. Those orchards were
         kept there a while, and then they began to grow old, oh, I don't
         know, they weren't bearing too well. We just kept 'em around for
         quite a few years, for as many apples that we would box up for the
         winter and use^ the summer. It was never a real commercial asset.
         
         SS:  You know, when we were talking about your father supporting the Nora
         Church; I was wondering what was it about the i\ora Church that he
         liked when he didn't like the Troy one?
         That church is a different denomination, it was called the Mission
         Friends.
         Oh, that was different than the Troy Lutheran?
         The Mission Friends, it was a separation from the Lutheran Church.
         
         SS:  Was it still Lutheran?
         In doctorine it was much the same, only a lot of formality disap
         peared there, and they had more liberal interpretations, I suppose
         you d call 'em, I don't know of what it consisted. I don't know-
         I m not sure- I never had the creed of either church to find out
         real differences.
         
         SS:  But the Nora Church was really a whole different—?
         It a different kind of government, although the worship appeared
         to be about the same. Not too much idfferent from any Protestant
         church; from the normal kind. The Episcopalian is a bit more form
         than some of the others, but not all that much and I would say it
         was more like the disciples of Christ than any of 'em.
         This missionary work that they did, did they send out missionaries
         right from Nora?
         
         GC:  Well, no, I don't that any went out directly from there, but there
         were missionaries. I know these two men that served there had al
         ready served as missionaries. One left there to go in the missionary
         field and another one came from the missionary field. lie was an old
         man when he came back from the missionary field, too, he must have
         had quite a few years there, I don't know how long.
         
         SS:  Did your father go to that church at all?
         
         GC:  oh» we didn't go very often. We'd go Christmas or something like
         that.
         
         SS:  And that, you'd go to Nora?
         
         GC:  Go to Nora.
         
         SS:  What was the name of that Swedish- that church?
         
         GC:  Well, the word is (gives Swedish pronunciation) that means Mission
         Friends. In some places that group and the Congregationalists often
         combine. There were quite a few of those things. They had a large
         church here in Spokane, the Mission Friends, did.
         SS Do you know what caused there to be a separate
         OH,it was a separation that took place in Sweden and I think the same
         thing happened in Norway. And they used the term Free Church to de
         signate those people; that is, they were not- they were more or less
         believed in local government and not a hierarchy, with the central
         churches and bishops and all that. I don't think they had any here,
         I think they were all organized on units, but then they recognized
         each other and had their conferences.
         
         SS:  Was this church right at Nora?
         
         GC:  Well, not where old Nora post office- it was a post office once. It
         was on the Deary road, but the church of Nora is past the old
         millsite, climb that hill, it was sort of beyond Granman's place a
         little ways, and it was kind of on the place where it rises to a
         more or less of the highest point along there. And Eric Nelson
         the place on the other side there. And actually there was a
         house there that the minister lived in regularly. I think that some
         rented it to him. I'm not sure, but I think that one minister
         rented the farm. He was out there, took care of his farm, too.
         
         SS:  Help make a living then?
         
         GC:  Help make a living, yes.
         
         SS:  You were talking to me about that planting and plowing; was that
         generally done- How many horses did you use on that?
         
         GC:  Well, I think maybe 190 acres in all, canyon hay fields on the home
         place, thereabouts. I think they made a measurement of it later on,
         when this conservation took place the Roosevelt Administration.
         We ordinarily kept seven or eight horses.A Some people farmed with
         maybe six and so on. But until the automobile days we regularly kept
         a riding horse out there a lot of the time, too. We just got along
         at least with horses that we could ride, we usually had one horse that was
         pretty good under the saddle and worked, too.
         
         SS:  How many would you have- hitch up for plowing?
         
         GC:  Well, not more than six. And when we used walking plows* gang plows
         more than two to that and had three horses on a single walking plow.
         It took two men to run two plows that way, so eventually got a gang-
         plow. I don't know, I think .we were a little late on buying that
         My father was skeptical about gangplows doing a better job of plowing
         as a walkingplow. I think it does, I don't that had any real
         effect.
         
         SS:  What do you think he thought why- what was there about it?
         
         GC:  A man could handle that in his hands, (if) there were clay spots, he
         could lift up a little, not turn up clay. Places where it needed
         to be  Mftt  out, a little bumpy, you could shove it in hard maybe
         and loosen up it, and^the harrow would smooth it out afterwards and
         things like that. He thought that the two plows set together and
         set for so much, why, the handles they always hit every piece of
         ground the same way.
         
         SS:  Which is true, more or less, isn't it?
         
         GC:  Uh-huh, yes.
         
         SS:  Where do you think your father would get his information about farming?
         About, you know, what he ought to do? Would they exchange it a lot?
         
         GC:  Iwould say that he did not know much about farming when he bought
         that, he'd been working at carpentry since he came to this country.
         He was raised on a farm in Sweden, but ,ithat vzas a different kind of
         farming. Very small-scale farming in a wooded country where he spent
         a good deal of the time in the woods. They were more woodsmen than
         they were farmers. They wanted to raise- the farm was an economy to
         produce food which they used themselves and keep a few cattle, hogs
         for milk and meat. And I think he learned most of it from other farmers;
         talked them and saw how they did. Of course, sort of learned
         how things were after years. Experimenting, too; that is, the land
         was quite young when they were young; that helped, too, so it still
         had a good deal of spring in it from having just been virgin soil
         before it was broken, and that helped out to make crops pretty good.
         But we still didn't have it to summer fallowing, like some of the
         others did early. It didn't wait. of the farmers on Burnt
         Ridge were pretty conservative that way. They used fallow ground
         I think
         and they used grass. Quite a long time.when those laws were put in
         to effect about con servation and how much you could be paying for
         laying up land, putting in grass; I'd say most of porNr Midae didn't
         need it.
         When you say-
         They'd already been doing it. the greater part.
         Some farmers used fallow ground. How did they use it? They just
         didn't fallow it at all?
         
         GC:  Just fallowed the land and plowed it and let it lie there and smoothed
         the top to hold moisture in and put a disc on it every so often to
         cut down the weeds.
         
         SS:  Oh, so, they were fallowed?
         
         GC:  They were fallowing it to get weeds- weed seed killed. It was better,
         probably to let weed seed often sprout and grow up and then
         it, you see. That way there's less weed seed in the soil. It grew
         once and it was killed, then it wouldn't grow again.
         
         SS:  I see, so the proper way to fallow is to let it lie there and not
         do anything until-
         
         GC:  Well, until it began to come up. You wouldn't want it to get to the
         seeding point.
         
         SS:  Right. Were there farmers that didn't fallow at all then? Put a
         crop in every year?
         
         GC:  Well, there were some farmers I guess that did that- in some
         places, I don't think it occurred on that ridge very much. But then
         when beans came along practicing no more fallow
         ground. They started raising beans and they kept the fields clean
         by cultivation and hoeing.And later peas came into effect as another
         croP»^ like beans, because
         they are thick and there s no way of down. They will grow
         in there spraying and all the rest of eomc Op.
         
         SS:  You know, you're talking about the old country.
         
         SS: was that they had just kind of no say-so and their husbands really
         expected them to keep quiet, and do what they were told.
         
         GC:  Oh, yes, that was a very common thing with people that came over. 
         But, I m not sure how successful it was- (Chuckles) Didn't follow
         the rules.
         
         SS:  Did you feel like your own mother could have her own way if she wan
         ted to enough?
         
         GC:  yes, yes, I think so. I don't think there was much doubt of that.
         
         SS:  What about the daughters?
         
         GC:  What did you say?
         
         SS:  Oh, I was just thinking about the daughters of the old country folks.  
         
         GC:  Well, I tell you, they changed a lot, and everybody did, I think.
         They adapted themselves to the new conditions, they didn't probably
         adapt as fast or so far quickly, but they up with different
         ideas. They just saw what went on around too, after all.
         
         SS:  When did you start working for the Bureau of Census?
         Oh, I just decided I'd try something else and I learned down at the
         post office of the examinations that were in progress and took one.
         Oh, they called 'em analy sts- social science analy st/examination
         is what they called it. I don't exactly know what it is. Oh, I
         have to do mathematics and questions on economics, political science,
         government. There were a whole series of different tests. You had
         a little choice there, too, as I remember it. You wrote on ten,
         maybe there was fourteen or so, different tests one could take. And
         I got a notification of a grade and later- noisy
         
         So, what did they have you do?
         
         Oh, I worked most of time as what they called a field analy st, or
         a field man. They changed the name of the thing and they said field
         consultant, later on. You spent a good deal of time traveling to
         state bureaus of vital statistics in answer to calls for this and
         that, what kind of statistics to get out and what kind they'd like
         provided for them by the bureau and the filing systems and various
         things of that sort. And number of campaigns in birth
         registration and death registration, which were not good in lots of
         states at that time. We ran tests on them; tests say, on a few
         counties. Find out how many- send out registration cards for chil
         dren born within a certain time, say one year and check them against
         state records to find out how many of them- the cards would show where
         they weee born. Check against the home office to see how many regis-
         tered. Some counties would be lots better than others
         Then we generally showed them there, and some of the first counties
         we conducted some sort of campaigns traveling around and things like
         that. We had one in New Mexico and Arizona and one in West Virginia,
         as I remember, the early ones, and one in South Carolina and one in
         Mississippi- it was just a plain test in Mississippi. And in Loui-
         siane, we just traveled about and talked to the local registrars
         and doctors in towns which they were already foundAdeficient, places
         they'd already found were deficient and explained what it was all
         about, and showed them how badly their registration of births and
         deaths was going on. And then later, I stayed in the office a good
         deal. I kind of liked the traveling around, it was kind of a relief
         to be in one place, too, for a while. I worked on different phases
         of vital statistics summarizing reports on conditions in different pkcts
         and still later on I began handling the life tables. United States
         life tables that they put out every year. The short method way of
         calculating life tables on that year, year's births as opposed- and
         based on an estimated populations. And they put those out yearly.
         
         SS:  What year did you start working for them?
         
         GC:  In 1938. I stayed there about twenty-five years- no, I left there
         in '62. But I did have some time out in the U. S. Army though.
         
         SS:  Do you think that a lot of people that left here went to the West
         Coast and California?
         
         GC:  I think the general migration from Idaho lias always been westward,
         to Oregon and California and even to Alaska. Seattle has been a
         great place for an awful lot of people from this area to go, so has
         Portland, and other places, too. To go into the homesteading rash in
         Oregon and Washington both when I was a small kid in certain parts
         they opened up. And there was going to be irrigation there and some
         of those stayed and some of them were disappointed in certain areas
         they went to out there. And then, they went to California, too,
         they drifted that way. A lot of them drifted to the coast and then
         southward into California.
         
         SS:  I'd like to ask you just a little more about what the motivations
         were for people those days. Do you think they were looking to make
         a lot of money, they expected to make money?
         
         GC:  Oh, a lot of them wanted to and tried various ways to do it. Some
         A fellow who succeeded, I guess, and some went. had a small town
         business down here, finally made a good thing of it in San Fran
         cisco, ran a grocery store in company with another man.
         
         SS:  Who was that?
         
         GC:  His name was Johnson
         
         SS:  In Troy?
         
         GC:  In Troy. Yes, he pulledftabout when I was- about the time I was
         grown up, around twenty-one. Went to Spokane first, later to Seattle
         and to San Francisco. And I don't know, of course- his sons
         are nearer my age now, a little younger, but they carried on the
         business and are well-to-do there. Big automobile industry they had
         there.
         
         SS:  You think that it was big money, or just a chance to make a living
         that; most people were looking for?
         
         GC:  Well, I think they wanted to get ahead; figured that they'd do bet
         ter somewhere else. Try to at least.
         
         SS:  Do you think that's a reasonable assessment of what the opportunies
         were here in those days?
         
         GC:  Uh-huh. Of course, I remember, too, a lot of just sort of
         moved around on farms. They'd rent a farm here one year and a farm
         somewhere else, and then they'd be gone from the country and you
         wouldn't see 'em again. Or a fellow who bought a farm ° maybe
         worked a few years in the town then they sold out and left. What
         became of 'em.'Jdon't know. Just people- well, you never got well
         acquainted with who they were. There were some of those particularly
         too. I don't know about the present population down here, whether
         there's mush movement at all or not, right now. I guess there's
         some, there must be, the names grow different over the years.
         
         SS:  Do you think that people with strong family ties, the ones that
         a lot
         felt they had strong family ties, would be more likely to stay here?
         
         GC:  I think that family ties had something to do with it. There were
         some stayed a long time, and that probably had something to do with
         it. Lawrence Johnson's family, one girl married away from here and
         was away a good many years, but she returned here with her husband.
         All the children were in this vicinity, still are. Well, there's two
         dead now, but they died here. I think the family ties were strong
         for those living ones
         among those and still are,^and also for the children- well, I wouldn't
         say that for^neither of the two that died had any children.
         
         SS:  Do you think the depression had a very big effect in this area?
         
         GC:  Well, it sure made things tough for people. They lived pretty close
         to the bone in those days, I think. They had to. But I don't think
         it caused so much movement because they knew that the same thing was
         going on^elsewhere. In fact, that movement there in the Depression
         didn't help much, it just wasted the time moving around, a large part
         of those that kept trying. I 'spose some were better off, I don't
         know.
         
         SS:  What were you doing in that period in time?
         
         GC:  Well, I was teaching school the main time it took place, a little
         later I left teaching. tranras on the railroad?
         Oh, there were some. Years ago they used to tramp the railroads or
         ride them, sometimes get put off.
         
         SS:  Would they come by your place? On 
         
         GC:  Well, sometimes they would- see our house from the railroad and
         climb up there, and , well, they'd tell us where they were going
         and what they were doing and we generally give 'em a bed overnight
         and a meal and they'd go on. Once in a while we had worfc to do
         around there that it was useful to have another hand, and we gave
         it to them, in fact, I think we gave them some every so often when
         we didn't need to.
         
         SS:  Would you have—?
         
         GC:  Some of- what?
         
         SS:  No, go on. What were you going to say?
         I would say some of them were pretty darn good workers, just came
         off the railroad tracks.
         Would you usually have any hired hand during that time?
         Well, there would be times when we would, yes. The times- well, in
         the early days, earlier years when they didn't have much- two threshing
         machines, they used to go out stacking the grain and wanted to get
         that done as soon as possible before- when it was still dry and before
         any rain fell on it. And probably might rush things through and
         get some hired hands.
         
         SS:  Just for a short period?
         
         GC:  For short periods of time. And then the beans came along, why, it
         was impossible to handle hoeing weeds, and had a crew every so often,
         and that would be for a short period of time, too. And sometimes
         taking care of the crop in harvesting, needed a little rush.
         
         SS:  Would these be usually farmers' sons?
         
         GC:  Once in a while they were, usually you picked up in town where
         somebody didn't have a steady job the year around would be available.
         And sometimes the teamsters wouldn't be in the woods or anything like
         that, would do that. I don't know.
         
         SS:  These tramps; what kind of people were they? Were they just people
         down on their luck, or people that were bums, or what?
         
         GC:  I think there was some of both. I think some of them lacked a good
         deal in the way of ability, they could do what they set out to do,
         simple things. Some were kind of down on their luck, maybe some of
         'em made their luck,not being too efficient in whatever they did.
         I know one fellow came in there, he was a Dutchman, born in Holland,
         he still spoke with a very accent, but he worked for us a while and
         he worked for somebody else after that and harvested there and was
         around for, oh, I don't know, maybe a year working for different
         people then I think he left on the track- left somewhere along the
         line, must have moved on, I never saw him about and I guess he just
         gone. I can remember one that tickled us to death there » he was
         from Ireland and somebody had been talking insurance there, oh, for
         some reason we were talking and insurance came up and Walter and
         Paul who were grown up then were exchanging interviews and Dad^was
         always leary of insurance, only fire insurance and crop insurance
         he thought he'd go for but.life insurance, "Oh,"this fellow says, "I don't believe
         in life insurance at all," he says, "I knew someone
         once that was insured for $10,000 and he died anyway!" (Chuckles)
         We kind of laughed at him, I remember I was small, but I remember
         that Walter and Dad tried to explain to him what life insurance
         meant. That was the idea he
         grasped , he said he wasn't joking. He thought he was insuring
         his life.
         
         SS:  There is just one more thing that strikes me about this question
         about leaving, about going someplace else, and that is- I have an
         idea- you read about in the early days, there was a lot of talk
         about rags to riches and about the chances of getting rich. Now,
         do you think that was on people's minds a lot. Do you think that
         believes that
         people they could go from rags to riches?
         
         GC:  Yes, I believe a lot of people believed it. They heard it. They
         said, "Here a man has a chance." And they thought that. A lot of
         them claimed they were going to get somewhere, the kids. And got
         that imbued into them. But, well, I guess, living has a sort of
         a way of taking care of all these things; some made it better and
         some didn't.
         
         SS:  But of the kids you grew up with-
         
         GC:  I know, they were enthusiastic most of 'em, what they were going to
         do in this country.
         
         SS:  Do you think it made people unrealistic or discontented when they
         might have been happy?
         
         GC:  Oh, I don't know, I would say those on that ridge were fairly con
         tented with farm life. Somehow or other whenever I chance to talk
         to them a lot more of them were contented with farm life than most
         of them. I don't know: I know some weren't because they didn't see
         where they were getting anywhere and their practical sense told 'em
         too many of 'em couldn't stay there. I think any one of them might
         have been content to stay, but they let someone choose the situation.
         That, by the way, was our farmhouse out there; Dad built that about
         1906.
         
         SS:  That's a good-looking house.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13407</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Clyde9</previous>
      <next>Craig</next>
      <disp_name>Corrin</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
