<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/24/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Charles Crow, 1974-07-24, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:12:00</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Crow, Charles</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer; carpenter</occupation>
      <birthyear>1879</birthyear>
      <residence>Palouse, eastern Washington</residence>
      <origin>Family homesteaded in the 1880's. Ada Crow's husband</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#ranches"&gt;ranches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pioneers"&gt;pioneers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#harvesting"&gt;harvesting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rattlesnakes"&gt;rattlesnakes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#corrals"&gt;corrals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html# rivers"&gt; rivers&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Viola"&gt;Viola&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Palouse"&gt;Palouse&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Canada"&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13418</file_name>
      <mp3>13419.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13419.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Working on the stock ranch near Bridgeport Washington; Neighbors having 25 acres irrigated;
               and harvesting sugar cane to make sorghum for bread
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The Crow stock ranch above the Columbia River, 12 miles from
               Bridgeport, Wash, Father drove the wagon from the Palouse,
               and Charles at 12 was a cowboy for 75 head of horses, The neighbor
               family on the bar had 25 acres irrigated; harvesting their sugar
               cane to make sorghum for use in bread,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Dealing with rattlesnakes and the affects of their bites; thinking he should have
               stayed on the Columbia
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>One of their girls was bit by a rattlesnake and they could see
               the poison travelling up her arm^ she was never quite right
               afterwards. He saves another girl from being bitten by grabbing
               her and the saddle she is sitting on. Sometimes he thinks he
               should have stayed on the Columbia,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>840</time>
            <title>Father dealing with sick grandparents; giving up ranching; building a dugout canoe;
               and wintering horses on the river
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father goes home when grandparent gets very ill described. The corral
               described, They give up the ranch after they have troubles with
               the Palouse place. Building the dugout.The horses wintered on
               the river.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1680</time>
            <title>Trouble with men trying to take over their Palouse place.</title>
            <synopsis>Trouble with men trying to take over their Palouse place</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>His horse leads him and his father to their spring when they are
               lost in a storm.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His horse leads him and his father to their spring when they are
               lost in a storm.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1980</time>
            <title>Using dead snake rattles for a hat band; killing rattlesnakes; and protection from
               them
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Rattlesnakes. He made a hatband out of rattles frpm dead snakes
               and they said you'd never get headaches with one,He killed them
               with rocks and a forked stick, always pulled the rattles off first.
               He kills mama snake and children with a sagebrush club. You were
               expected to kill every rattlesnake you saw. Pigs are protected
               against rattlers. A rattler spooks a horse while they are packing
               out a deer. A 13 year old rattlesnake,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Charles shoots a bull snake in the dugout, awakening his father
               with a shock
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Charles shoots a bull snake in the dugout, awakening his father
               with a shock,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3360</time>
            <title>Threatening to kill men who tried to claim their land</title>
            <synopsis>His father and grandfather threaten to kill men who are trying
               to jump their claim,(continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Protection against claim jumpers; the need for self-protection</title>
            <synopsis>His father meant the threat you had to mean business in those
               days. A neighbor family had put the claim jumpers-on to the Crow
               place. Need for self-protection,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Discussion of neighbors; grandfather McQueen carrying logs by himself; getting rid
               of claim jumpers; seeing cows stolen
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Neighbors. Grandfather McQueen carried the butt ends of logs by
               himself. Skookum means tough. The claim jumpers got out of the
               country. Charles sees a heifer stolen.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Hauling grain to the Snake River, homesteaded near Biggar</title>
            <synopsis>Hauling grain to the Snake River, He homesteaded near Biggar?</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Driving horses after a severe winter and only one survived</title>
            <synopsis>They drove the horses 175 miles from the Palouse to the horse
               ranch after a severe winter, and found only one range horse
               had survived, while hundreds had died
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>Having an orchard on their homestead after the home was torn down; Charles breaking
               the last forty acres and finding a squirrel
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The lovely orchard on their home place was torn down after they
               sold it. Getting the place, Charles helped break the last forty
               acres. They expose a hibernating squirrel while breaking the land.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Father thought the squirrel was dead, not hibernating, quality of
               the farm.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father thought the squirrel was dead, not hibernating, quality of
               the farm.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5580</time>
            <title>The wet harvest of 1893 and how it affected area farmers, specifically the Crows</title>
            <synopsis>Charles remembers the wet harvest of 1893, His wife% father got
               a crop because he had a binder and cut early; and the Crows bought
               seed from him the next spring. Host peopled yearns work was,
               ruined, but the grain in the fields provided feed for stock, A
               man who tried to harvest when the rain stopped got his machinery
               bogged down right away, People couldnM: afford to leave, The Crows
               sold a little wheat for chicken feed and bought groceries, That
               was the only year of total failure, though yields were low one
               other year.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>The long drive from the Palouse to horse country; trying to keep rustlers away; camping
               and driving the wagon on the trail
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The drive from the Palouse to the horse country made about 25-30
               miles a day with 75 head. Riding night watch, his father shoots
               at rustlers; and they later find they are one of the few herds
               to get by without losing horses to them. Listening for the bell
               mare. Kids frightened a horse into a barbed wire fence, and it
               died. Camping and driving the wagon on the trail.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6960</time>
            <title>Horses on the ranch and the use of it for different uses; The loneliness of the trail</title>
            <synopsis>The horses on the ranch. The land gradually got peopled but
               there was still plenty of range. Almost never saw people on the
               trail.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>What the horses ate on the range; disastrous effects of turning land into farm homesteads</title>
            <synopsis>All the horse range was bunchgrass. Disastrous effects of turning
               the land into farm homesteads,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Driving horses across eastern Washington. Batching in a dugout as a boy.
         Rattlesnake lore. Fighting claim jumpers. 7-24-74 2.1 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: How old are you now?
         
         CHARLES CROW: Ninety five.
         
         SS:  You got a right to be having some troubles.
         
         CC:  (laughs) I guess so. Yes, the minister was here just this evening. He was
         here and he's been here since; for several months. He just happened to
         come along, come in here. And he's a nice fella. Awfully nice man.
         
         SS:  Don't pay that no mind. Tell me about the horse ranch. What you remember
         about it.
         
         CC:  About what?
         
         SS:  The horse ranch.
         
         CC:  Horse ranch? Well, oh it was quite a story. was in two places.
         Out on the Columbia River, one was on a ranch on the Columbia River, dad
         had a ranch out there, a stock ranch. And I was out on that when I was
         twelve years old. I rode a pony from here out there when I was twelve
         years old. And dad drovej cU4 drove the wagon, drove the team on the
         wagon. And two cowboys they drove 75 head of horses. And we
         took 'em out there on this Columbia River. He had, dad and this other
         Pedicord had a} two ranches, two half sections right there and then they
         nad a big springy And this was in real early day out there too. Bunch grass
         way up like  Beautiful stalks. I enjoyed it awful, most wonderful.
         And the best of it was:^the family went ahead of us, went out ahead of us
         and they was down on the river, on the bar .And there was this spring
         up above there^.Nice water in it, come down. And it went down in the river
         you know. And that spring, I guess^as probably twenty five acres of level
         land down there. And this old fella took that.(Quite a big family. He raised
         sugar cane. You ever seen any sugar cane grow?
         
         SS:  I've never seen it grow.
         
         CC:  You didn't?
         
         SS:  No.
         
         CC:  I did. I've seen it grow. Irode through it. Rode along side of it and
         reach out like that and break off a stalk and stick it in my mouth and
         go ahead and chew on it. Sweet, nice. And then we'd take that and when it
         got just ripe, we'd cut it. And.we'd put it through a roller and we'd'squeeze
         the juice out of it. In a vat. And then when we'd put a fire under this
         vat, and boil that down. Make sorghttn. We'd make sorghto syrup. And then
         this one woman was a good cook. Make sorghtfm gravy. They made homemade
         bread and they milk I think about six or seven cows and they were quite
         a family of them. And everything worked out nice, you see? And that's where
         our little girl got bit by arattlesnake. That's right there, in that place.
         And fourteen miles down to Bridgeport. To adoctor. And the girl rode that
         fourteen miles, wasn't very long riding it,5he had a good horse. And that
         it's quite a long story. But she never was right afterwards.
         
         SS:  Who, her father?
         
         The girl. The little girl that got bit by the rattlesnake. We had logs,
         wood, those logs, this big around and she sat on it, sat down there, was
         aplaying down there and there was arattler  up on the side and she
         if had a doll. And the doll off of that and reached over to get it and
         the rattler bit her.Struck her. Struck her in the hand. Ididn't see it,
         but Iseen her afterward. You could just see the poison matter, just see
         it creeping up her arm. In under the skin. The doctor up there hit her
         way up here. But he saved her. But she never was just exactly right. It
         affected her, she never was exactly right. But she was an awful nice kid
         too. So then, that was there and then I rode, they had a girl just about
         my age. And she could ride pretty good. And her and Iwould get on the
         horses and ride out on the prairie. Had about, oh I guess, two miles to
         go to ride out on this prairie. And then when that was up off of these
         benches. Off of the river, like Itold you about before. And they was right
         down on the lower bed. And they had water out of this big spring. There
         was plenty of water to irrigate with and out and everything. That's where
         I saved We were sitting on the side of the house and
         then my dad and me and this don't
         know, somebody else was going by. And we were sitting there out there and
         there was a saddle there, see. Of course everybody had a saddle. And right
         under the horn is open. And they had a kitty. A cat about two thirds
         grown and it was standing back about that far. Looking right under that
         saddle. And there was a rattler coiled under there. So I didn't do a
         doggone thing, just slip right around, back behind where the rattler couldn't
         hit me and I just grapbed that saddle. And when I grabbed that saddle, this
         little girl that was right on the saddle, I grabbed it, the saddle and the
         girl too.(laughs) Well, they all jumped, of course. And she got out of that.
         They killed the rattler. Alright. He didn't do any damage. But I just was
         telling you a different story,^that's the way that things happened. Well,
         lots of interesting things^happened and I probably forgot a lot of 'em.
         But we all had a lot of fun. More fun than.sometimes I think I ought to
         stayed there. I think would have been better off if I would have stayed
         there.There was a big family of us. There was ten children in our family.
         And I was just, dad had got a call from home, 175 miles where this ranch
         was from the farm. So dad got a call that his father and mother was keeping
         him, they were getting really low. There was a grandmother, she was up in
         her, I don't know how old. Eventually when he was a little older, and he
         was too and they just lived, he lived just about six weeks I think it was,
         he lived after she died. And he didn't live long. He couldn't take it. He
         didn't want to. And he was , it wasn't United Brethren. It was, he was a
         minister.
         
         SS:  This is your grandfather?
         
         This was my grandfather. Yes, he was a minister. And he lived in Oregon.
         And then he finally sold that and come up there. He didn't have anything
         then. Land was cheap. And I don't know, I imagine it was about the best he
         could do. And father told him if they'd sell it and come up there, he'd,
         dad had a pretty good house, he had a two story house.
         This is the place on the Palouse?
         
         Right. That's on the farm.
         
         Did your father have to go back from the ranch when he heard the news?
         Yes. That's how I come to be alone out there, see. This man, Vaughn who was
         going back down there anyway, he had to go down there, he had some business.
         He went, took the wagon and team and one of these boys. That would be Ben,
         they called him, brother. I rode my saddle horse and Iwent with them and
         then when they went back Istayed dot* there, Imust have stayed acouple
         of weeks . ..
         
         Did you take care of the place?
         Yeah.
         
         By yourself?
         
         No. On the homeplace? No. It was my brother, Ihad two brothers there. They
         were there and they took care of the place. And then it was just about
         running out I think, I can't remember too much.
         
         SS:  I'd like to know what the krse ranch looked like?
         
         CC:  The horse ranch?
         
         Yeah, what your horse ranch looked like.
         
         Big corral and, you know what a corral is? Alright, it was a big corral and
         they built up high, I could stand there and just about reach the top of it
         when Istand like that.^And they were logs about that big around.They were
         AaboMt draw, what we called them, up above the river. And up in that draw
         there was timber, quite a bit of timber. We cut that down, make our corral
         and everything. That and then we had a dugout.
         
         SS:  What was the dugout like?
         
         CC:  Lots of water like awatering trough over there. Watering trough was about
         that wide and about that deep.That was full of water all the time. The horses
         was coming off of the ranch and drink. Well that spring water was good for
         them. Better than lake water was. So they had different layouts all around,
         each one. Every cattle man, stock man. And this man Vaughn, he had a lot of
         horses. Cattle. And we had a few head of cattle. We got rid of our cattle
         got horses, see. They're easier to take care of. And then finally the, we
         went from bad to worse. And they finally lost out all together. And we just
         let it go. We paid for it alright, but we didn't want it. We couldn't keep
         it up. Everything kind of went haywire. And so dad sold it. Iforget what
         he got now. What he got for it. He got enough I guess to pay him. And he
         sold it and then we went back on the farm. But what was out there
         we traded our farm for horses and money in the Palouse country, see. And we
         had moved off of our ranch over about a mile from there onto with a bachelor
         there. He had abig house. So we moved over on that and til we got things
         fixed up. Til we got ready to go. And then mother x*as supposed to sign a
         quick claim deed. And mother got sick and didn't sign the deed, the claim
         deed when she was s'posed to. And they wouldn't accept the sale. And so
         dad, he was in pretty hard shape, see? He took quite a few horses in on the
         deal.So he was in pretty hard shape. So we had to move back on it, and
         during that time, this was lieu land, land.
         
         What does lieu land mean?
         
         I just can't explain it all.
         
         Is it owned by the railroad?
         
         No. Lieu land is well, Idon't know, Ican't explain that, buAat'it was.
         Dad bought it, off of this guy. He gave him four hundred dollars for it.
         It had a house and it had a barn, quite a barn.
         
         And he had four horses and stuff like that.Things was cheap. And he just
         louse up the whole thing for four hundred dollars. Dad give him four
         hundred dollars and took possession.
         
         SS:  This place was on the Palouse?
         
         CC: Yeah, that was there. That was five miles south of Palouse. And that's the
         way we got into that cattle business.And dad and me, we was out in this
         horse business and stuff. And went out on this range, see. And that happened
         that he had to go back in to there and I didn't go back with him. Istayed
         out there for a while. And then my neighbor went back, I went back with him.
         
         SS:  I'd like to know what that dugout was like.
         That was just a slabs, there was a little bit of a mill up in there. And
         these slabs off of these logs, you know. And they had a pile of them.
         them to haul them down there and made us ahouse and
         then dug out back of the hill like that and then started to dig back in
         this way, like that, see. Then when we put these slabs on that, down on the
         inside. And it was just a crude building, but then ,we didn't winter there.
         And the horses, they wintered there too because the grass would be about
         like that. Down on the railroad, on the bench. And they wouldn't allow them, no horses
         and cattle on there in the summertime. They made them stay out of there.And
         for the winter. And then like that, that furnished some feed. Cattle, of
         course )the cows,  to have,  to be looked after. Horses, they'd winter
         right through. And stay fat.
         
         SS:  So you and your dad bached it?
         
         CC: Oh yes. We bached there for quite awhile. And then we were going to go
         out there, see we sold the place then. And then we went out there and we:-
         were going to build. And make a real stock ranch. And then this happened,
         that stopped the whole business.And then dad had to take the place back
         in order to save it. And they wouldn't give it up. They jumped it, the
         lieu land and they, the possession was nine points of the law. On that 
         So that was the way that was. And we was, dad was this other
         family.I was only about, oh, Icouldn't have been more than six, seven
         And dad told mother, said,"Mother you keep awatch out." He said,
         "You watch out up the creek here."Two roads, one was'a hill. More hill and
         come down to the town. Was only five miles from town. And he says there
         was another one come down the valley. Had kind of a valley down side of
         the creek. "You see anybody and they'll come down the valley, these men
         when you see 'em,"he says,"they'11 be awhole bunch. And before these valley
         fellas get down there,"He says, "they'll be some officers come out from
         Palouse. Four miles." And he said,"They'll arrest them fellas. Take 'em in
         there. As soon as they do that, why these others will come in and take
         that house that they built. And they'll throw it out down in the lane there.
         In the corner." Well it's nine points of the law, see, possession.(laughs)
         They made'the law themselves .And we had to. And we had quite
         circus over that.
         
         SS:  What happened?
         
         CC:  We got our place back, but it throwed us in debt, it throwed us with these
         horses and stuff on our hands.We to make them take it back again. And
         we couldn't do it. And they tried
         to make a go of it. And there were two skinners(laughs)They couldn't do it.
         Put us in abad fix. But we finally come out of it. Soon as  boys got
         big enough to work.
         
         I'd like to know about the time you and your dad got lost.
         
         Well we was out there. We were out hunting, rounding up the horses, come up
         a rainstorm. And we got lost and we was hunting our way in to get back. And
         we could hear the roar of the river. And we went by that a good deal. And
         then we got down there and we strung a trail and the trail, we didn't lose
         our direction on. And our ponies, we stopped and it was raining like the
         dickens. And the pony, like the trails here you know, and he turned and
         wanted to go back this way.And dad's horse that he was riding, he couldn't
         trust him at all.But you could trust my pony. He was good. And pretty soon
         I heard some water.I heard it playing. I said,"Dad I hear that spring." "No."
         "Yeah, listen." My hearing was keener than dad's see. "I believe you're right."
         I said you follow me and then we'll see. We won't get lost, stay on the trail.
         I just turned my pony and I started him up and he didn't go any further than
         from here to that garage. Out there onto it we heard the water running out
         of the pipe. And into this watering trough and my pony went up and got him
         a drink of water. And dad's pony followed him.And then he went in. He was
         soaking wet. It was warm weather, it didn't hurt us any. It got us awful
         wet. And we wanted rain anyway for the bunch grass. We needed it, see.
         But^ things like that. And there was, I don't know, that's about
         the only thing I can remember. This Frank Vaughn, they lived down on the
         bar. I used to go down there and visit. I went down there, go down and get
         sugar cane and sorghum and go down, them kids, he had some kids. And play
         with them, about two miles from them. That wasn't no distance for us. We
         would saddle up our horses and travel two miles pretty quick. And. but lots
         of rattlesnakes. I killed, had a hat band clear around with rattles, rattles
         that I pulled out of the rattlers. And sew 'em together. Made a band. They
         said if you made a band you'd never have a headache, (laughs) I, kid like,
         I done that. I don't know how I turned out...
         
         SS:  You don't remember if you ever had headaches?
         
         CC:  Oh yes, I never had a headache anywayAs far as that's concerned. I don't
         think. I don't know. I wouldn't tell anybody else that. I wouldn't tell it
         cured a headache or anything like that.(laughs) But you know, *t looked
         funny to see that around the hat on the rim about that wide, a rim. And
         they were, rattlers would be about not as wide as my fingers. About that
         wide.
         
         SS:  About as wide as your last two fingers.
         
         CC:  Yeah. And some of it, they vary a little, you know. The size of the rattler.
         I killed all of them. I killed all ;them rattlers and took the rattles out
         of 'em.
         
         SS:  With a gun?
         
         CC:  No, with rocks. Get a rattler, you find some rocks. Boy, I'd pelt him til
         I'd stun him and he'd straighten out and when he did, I'd grab him like *v/ +4
         stick, itrlttd fr^ofc-like that. I'd jab it right there and his head would
         stick out like that. And I'd hold it with one hand and I'd reach back and
         get ahold of his rattler. Pull it and then kill the snake.
         
         SS: You'd pull the rattle off before you killed it?
         
         CC:  Yes. Always. I don't know why. And Iwas going along one day and there was
         a little trail running along the place, about as high as a car and it was
         shaped like that and there was a little trail that went around and a little
         bit of a bench above it. And I started to go along there and I looked down
         there and there was an old mother rattler. She was about, around three,
         four feet long. And there was a whole bunch of little ones. And I wanted
         all of 'em.(laughs) And I knew I couldn't get 'em. There was some sagebrush
         there. And I took sagebrush and I just cut off all the brushy parts of the
         sagebrush you know, so it wouldn't catch the wind. And twisted it together
         like that. And that made me a big club about like that.
         
         CC:  About two feet long. feet long. And then I got on my pony, I rode along there
         til I could
         just reach out and I couldAwhack the whole business, see. Well I killed,I
         think it was five little ones and I finally killed the old mammy rattler.
         If I stayed with it long enough to kill her I killed these five. Because
         if you found a rattler and you didn't kill 'em, and the people around there
         found it out, by they give you, spare you right. They wanted to get rid of
         em and they didn't want you to let them go at all.I'll tell you something
         else,If rattler and hogs, you build a house inside of a hog pen, a rattler
         won't never go in there. If he does he's doomed.Them hogs will kill him,
         by George, right quick. They'll eat him. They'll kill him and eat him. He
         won't hurt 'em.
         
         SS:  Did people build their houses in hog pens?
         
         CC:  No. That I'm telling you, anything with hair on it, rattler won't bother.
         Like a horse's nose. Or your hand or something like that, he'll hit it.
         But he wouldn't hit hair. If you had quite a lot of hair on your head, he
         wouldn't touch that.He wouldn't hit you there if he did.
         He'd hit you somewhere's in the face.
         
         SS:  Would rattlesnakes try to get people or would they rather run away?
         
         CC:  Yeah. And we just worked away, well, when I quit, when I left that place out
         there and went back home, they wasn't too many rattlers in there. And
         another incident happened. We went up there and we found a deer. And it
         was out at the lake, little bit of a lake out above us. And he had
         his horns. Deer you know, they'll molt their horns. And we had a gun,
         the big gun, dad did, military 90, an army gun. Dad shot him. He killed
         him. And then he put him on my pony. And the rest of the horses,there were
         he four or five of us, the rest of 'em wouldn't carry him. If buck
         my pony wouldn't pay any attention to it. They strapped him in front. I
         blood fforget what it was now. Strap him on my saddle. And then we just put him
         right across the saddle. They tied him on. I rode behind Jim Beam. I was
         a little boy, on his horse. And he told me that rattler, if he rattles,
         he'll set you on the ground. He'll jump up^under you. He hates them rattlers.
         going up along the side of a hill like that.There was
         a rattler right up here. He rattled. Well he jumped out, but he didn't
         get me off. In time. I was watching. So I stopped. And you know, that
         horse wouldn't hardly let me get on again. On him. We killed the rattler
         alright, we did. But that's how sensitive they are, a horse is. You see
         'em on the range,see a horse with a big head. And that's where the rattler
         the one that the rattler hit. On the nose.
         
         SS:  It made his head big?
         
         CC:  Yes, oh yes. And that horse was, they'd stick their nose, they'd run and
         stick their nose in the mud. Try to counteract the poison.I've seen quite a
         few of 'em.
         
         SS:  Were you afraid of rattlers when you were a kid?
         
         CC:  No. I was partly afraid, yes. But I wasn't bad. I killed, I wouldn t let
         one get away if I could help it. I'd get him some way or another.
         
         SS:  How did you take the tail off, did you cut it off?
         
         CC:  No, you pull it off.
         
         SS:  Just pull it off.
         
         CC:  You get a hold and give it a little twist. And that rattler was just that
         old. As many buttons as there was on that rattle. If he had four
         buttons there, that rattler, four buttons on him, he was four years old.
         Every year. I seen a rattlesnake on Wilton Creek down here An the Palouse
         country down there, pretty close to Wilbur, dad and I did. We saw him going
         along there when we looked up and we seen a cowboy riding across there,
         was no ., just range. And he a couple times after, we noticed
         him. And that rattlesnake had thirteen rattles on him.
         
         SS:  No kidding?
         
         CC:  That's right. Thirteen rattles.He was almostNbig as my arm. Like that.
         I seen him at a distance, I couldn't get to him. I seen him on Little
         cliff where they make their home in the rock, see. And I'd see him, I
         could see him a laying there. They was watching too. And they'd see me,
         they'd go in there and get back down in them holes and you couldn't get
         'em.Another fella says,"You're making that up." Oh no, oh no boy, no I
         ain't. I says that's early day. I says I can take you down on Wilson
         Creek to where that big rattler, to where we saw it. I says if dad was
         alive, he'd verify it. And we went over there. And he took the rattles.
         He couldn't twist them off, he had to cut 'em off. He had a knife,^he
         cut them off. That was the biggest rattlesnake I ever seen out there.
         But one of them ,said it was a diamond, but it wasn't. There was no diamond
         rattlers in that country.
         
         SS:  What kind was it ?
         
         CC:  A northern.
         
         SS:  How long was it? In feet?
         
         CC:  In feet?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         CC:  I'd say five feet.About five feet. I seen a lot in my day like that. My
         other brothers wouldn't do. They wouldn't venture. And I did. I stayed
         out on that place for quite a while. And would have married one of the
         girls if I had stayed there til I was old enough. But I didn't. I was
         only about fifteen when I left
         
         SS:  You told me that one time you shot a snake in your dugout.
         
         CC:  Yes. I woke up where dad did. In bed and I woke up 'fore he did. And I
         looked over and great big bull snake. Wherever there rattlers there
         are bull snakes. And this bullsnake got in during the night. They got
         cold I guess and crawled in there and he was laying stretched out along
         that shelf.Shelf about that wide. Ladder was back of it and we had it
         built so that, we left it on there so it wouldn't eo/«- off. We had a
         shotgun right up over our heads here. We had the shotgun there. And I reached
         up right easy and got that. Pulled it down there and I blew that doggone
         snake's head clear off. I didn't know whether it was a bullsnake or a
         rattler when I shot. But I seen -that it was a bullsnake. I wouldn t
         have shot if I known it was a bullsnake. If I'd have known, I would have
         kicked him out and let him live. But he was . He wouldn t bite you
         if you wouldn't do nothing. They're just, they feed on mice and stuff like
         that. They get an awful size. They get that long and big as my arm.
         
         SS:  Did that wake your father up?
         
         CC:  It woke him up so quick that I could have jumped out of the bed. He jumped
         straight up. And he said,"What in the world is going on here?" I said,"Look
         right over there."And the snake was there. You know how when you first kill
         one of them, when you first skin it to kill it it'll wheel? Well that snake
         was doing quite a bit of that wheeling. Right down on the floor in the
         cabin. So that was the, that was about the best I've hit. It tickied me
         to see dad jump when the gun went off. He said,"Why didn't you tell me?"
         Dad was kind of a sarcastic fella. He said,"Why didn't you tell me?" I said,
         "I didn't want to disturb you." I says, "I wanted to shoot him."(laughs) He
         said,"You're going to get into trouble some day." I said, no.
         
         SS:  How old were you then?
         
         CC:  I was about fourteen.
         
         SS:  Will you tell me about the guys that tried to jump the claim on your place?
         
         CC:  When I lived down on the home place? Yes. Yes, I know that. Well...
         
         SS:  Was this the place on the Palouse? They tried to jump?
         
         CC:  They did jump. They built on it. We left, we moved out in the neighbor
         house. We had to get possession at a certain time. We moved out and went
         over in this, in them days they didn't have very much to move. And
         them going in and out of that house, they couldn't do that. There was
         a law protecting that on that. So they built just a little bit over on
         the side there. And they got 'em out. They just forced them out, that's
         all there was to it. The law arrested 'em and while they were out, the wind
         blowed their house and everything off. On down on the road.
         The wind blowed off We were  And dad told "You see th at?"
         You get them kids all in the house. And keep 'em in there. You don't
         have to keep them in there more thanVjust a little while. It'll all be
         over, (pause in tape) One of 'em come back after that happened, in a day
         or two and were going to come mn through the gate. And dad went into town
         the day before. And the lawyer told him possession is nine of the
         law, here. So he says, "Keep 'em out and tell him to stay out. Just tell
         him twice." And then he says, "If he don't stay out,shoot him.There ain't
         nobody going to come to bother you. And so he come up the gate, rode up
         to the gate and was going to open it. Dad went out there and dad had him a
         .45, .44 Colt revolver. He had it in his hand. He says,"You take another
         step in this way, or put the other foot in that fence and I'll kill you."
         You stay off'n this place. This is my land not yours." The fella backed up
         and went away. Dad says, dad was taking pretty big chances, but he said,
         "You stay away and don't never come back here no more." He says,"I don't
         want to never see you again. Because if you come back and cause me any
         trouble, I'll kill you." He never come back. Then the other, there were
         three of 'em, the other two was up along the fence. And they were going to
         build up there on the ranch, build another house. And take this lumber.
         That we'd throwed out to build up there, see. And then fight it out in law,
         in court. So we just went up there, dad did, and grandfather. And grandfather
         took a shotgun and dad took a revolver. Grandfather said,"By gad if you
         throw that plank over that fence,by gad, I'll kill you."
         
         SS:  ...as good as their word, is that what you said?
         
         CC:  Yeah. He said something else, but I ain't gonna tell ya. (laughs)'Cause
         this thing will pick it up. But it was pretty warm times there for a while
         He told us kids, you know, they could have killed some of us kids. Only
         they took it off and got a ranch from us or something, see? Dad told 'em
         said,"Don't you cause me any more trouble. You caused me trouble enough
         now.Because if you do, you won't live to tell the story."Dad was a man of
         his word, too.He sure tell 'em. And after we was over and I was only about
         four, five years old, six years old, after it was over we found out who
         put 'em away, who tol^ 'em to build. And one of our neighbors only lived
         a mile and a half away, old man Hibbs.
         He told 'em, he put their minds to it, see. Told them about that claim.
         And they knew doggone well after it was over with that we'd find out and
         if they stayed there, that something would happen to them. It would too.
         He'd have killed them.You doggone right we would. You didn't mess with them
         in them days. You'd adone the right thing or else you wouldn't live to do
         anything more. That's what it was too it. And if aman told you he'd do
         something, he'd do it.That's all there was to it, that's why there was no
         fooling.And the boys, they did fight like blazes, you're doggone right.
         Ihad several scraps when Iwas going to school. Ihad ascrap prefnear
         every night on my way home from school.(laughs)Two boys, three boys there,
         they'd double team on me. And Iwas pretty skookum. Ihave to run and get
         out of the road. But if one of them boys didn't come to school and^the other
         one did, the one that come to school, boy he got it coming tome. Iain't
         kidding you abit. That's the way, we just worked up and lived for ourselves.
         You had to. They wasn't no officers and stuff around like they is now. And
         you couldn't, if they did, he could cause alot of trouble. So people took
         it in their own handA people knew it and they didn't do them things.
         Thats all there is to it. They was good.
         
         SS:  Did you ever say anything to the Hibbs about what they tried to do?
         
         CC:  Sure, we told him, said, "If you ever cross our path again, you won't live
         to see your family grow up." That's all there is to it.
         
         SS:  Did they stay in the country or did they get out?
         
         CC:  He stayed for awhile. Then he got out after abit.After afew years we
         made it too hot for him. They couldn't stay-There was Froney Hibbs and
         Ida Hibbs. Nearly all grown. And there's aHibbs place with that name yet,
         land.
         
         SS:  Who were some other of your neighbors?
         
         CC:  Our neighbors? The Dickens'?
         
         SS:  Around the Palouse?
         
         CC:  Oh, we had neighbors there. There were some of them there lived close together
         There was Bob Stone,Grandfather McQueen and Bill Robinson and any amount
         of 'em, see. Lived around there, a mile or so of one another. About a mile
         apart.
         
         SS:  Was Grandfather McQueen an old man when you were a boy?
         
         CC:  Yeah. He was quite an old man. He was about, he was a skookum old fella.
         He just about my height, but boy, he was tough.(laughs)That was my mother's
         father, he was a tough old bird.And he'd haul logs, they'd haul wood down,
         log wood down from the timber. And he'd take and he'd get ahold of a butt
         end of a log tell the others to get the other.(laughs) He was a skookum old
         boy. So ...
         
         What do you mean by skookum?
         
         Tough.
         
         Did they try to jump other claims around the Palouse?
         
         No. Uh uh. They got out, . They mistake. Every
         body liked us. 'Cause we was good neighbors by the by then. And if they'd
         a stayed there, there would have been trouble. Somebody would have killed
         them. Yeah. When I was about ten years old, I had a two year old heifer.
         Nice two year old heifer. Right in broad day light, went in and got her.
         In a pasture. Took her out of there and drove her off. And made a getaway
         drove with it. And they never got him. They " off and I seen the heifer
         afterwards, the cow. And we got her back, but we never got him. He was
         riding a good horse and got out of there. And that, was pretty tough.
         You got used to it, you didn't notice it.(laughs) We had to get used to it,
         that's all there was to it.And our land was good. We raised good crops.
         We raised wheat there and made thirty bushels to the acre and forty.A bushel.
         And had to haul that wheat. I think it was about thirty miles that we had
         to haul it. We haul^ it one day and took the wheat and went back home the
         next day. And then took it down to the Snake River. Hauled it down there
         to the boat.We put wood for the boat.
         
         SS:  Was that Wawawi you took it too?
         
         CC:  Wawawi? Yeah. The Wawawi grade. You been around there.
         
         SS:  I know a little bit of it.
         
         CC:  Yeah.(laughs)
         
         SS:  How far from Palouse was your place?
         
         CC : About five miles.
         
         SS:  That was right on the Washington-Idaho border?
         
         CC:  No. Well, pretty much so, yes. But I'd say three miles.straight line. From
         the Idaho line. About three miles. I wisht I'd astayed there. I wisht I'd
         astayed there. I got married down there, you know. I was married in Colfax.
         I could have stayed down there. I would have been better off if I'd stayed
         down there. I'd afarmed.I'd amade money. But I wanted a place of my own and
         I didn't have no horses or nothing. All I had was a driving team and so I
         didn't... I come up here. But I've had a good life. I been in Canada,I
         been in Canada 26 years. We had a farm up there. Dry weather drove us out.
         We get no , we get no crops. And one year, twelve months there we never
         got but an inch of rain in the twelve months, is all the moisture we got .
         Outside of the little snow. That don't raise crops.
         
         SS:  Whereabouts did you homestead in Canada?
         
         CC:  Saskatchewan.That was on the Great Northern. Not the Great Northern, that
         was on the Canadian Northern Railroad. And that was a big scope of land.
         Biggar.here, and we went down here about 9-10 miles was where our ranch was
         And then the other railroad was up here. About mile and a half. And that
         road run pret'near parallel for a ways
         
         SS:  What was the name of the town?
         
         CC:  Biggar.
         
         SS:  Bigger?
         
         CC:  Biggar.
         
         SS:  Did you take those horses all the way from the Palouse out to the big Bend
         and back again? Did you take them all the way to the Columbia from Palouse?
         
         CC: Yeah.
         
         CC:  We drove 'em 175 miles and we drove in the spring. Early we could drive
         them out there and we did in the fall when we brught 'em back. Winter, it
         was the straw pile. See? And then we found out that didn't work good.So
         we quit that.
         
         SS: Why didn't it work?
         
         CC:  Well it wasn't enough feed. Feed wasn't substantial. That out there, we took
         a chance. If they didn't get a northern storm up there, why, you couldn't
         beat that for winter. They wintered out on the river. See? Down on the low
         parts where they kept them out of there in the summertime. In the grass,
         stuff like that. Had to be a lot of snow to fill that up. But they did
         one winter. It filled up, fifty miles there , well, I'll say fotty miles.
         Fifty miles from where the Coulee Dam is. On down the river. Wait a minute.
         Yeah, to where this place was. And Foster Creek. And there's a dam there
         now, Foster Creek Dam. See? On the Columbia.
         
         SS:  What's the town that's near that?
         
         CC:  That was Palouse.
         
         SS:  I mean the town near the horseranch. Down twelve miles from there.
         
         CC:  About fourteen
         
         SS:  What was the name of that?
         
         CC:  Bridgeport.
         
         SS:  One winter you got a bad storm there?
         
         CC:  Got a bad storm. We wasn't there that winter. It was just the winter before
         we went out. And we drove that fifty miles there, took thof bunch, 75 head
         of horses about 70 miles. And all we seen was one iron gray mare foal and
         she looked more like a reindeer than anything else. She pulled through the
         winter, but she foaled and she pretty near reeled when she walked. That's
         the only horse, living beast that we seen that wintered through. I could
         show you where there was 150-200 head of horses.Dead horses. And rocks, them
         big lon^. rocks, Haystack Rock, Pilot Rock, all them big rocks over the
         prairie, see. That's why rocks. That was real range. Best
         horse range I ever seen. But now, I went over that I don't know how many
         years ago, I guess it must have been about fifteen years ago. Me and another
         fella went. We went across from here in a car. And they got a road right
         through there now. On that land there. They got up. Ain't no cattle
         in that country either. That is ranches, it's all owned, people own it.
         They fixed it up.
         
         Did you just rent it?
         
         Out there? No, we didn't have to.
         
         You didn't have to rent it?
         
         CC: No. Just, it was about 75 miles east and west and about fifty-sixty miles
         north and south. That was all that bunch land. Just bunchgrass and stuff
         you know. Some rock onto it. desert. There's one butte there. And that
         butte, it' s there yet. And it had rocks built around rocks on it, on the
         side of it.(pause in tape)That picks up anything.
         
         SS:  Pretty good. Sometimes it picks up too m uch. I want to ask you more about
         the horses and the ranch. Where did those horses go? Who did you sell 'em
         to?
         
         CC:  They sold 'em to different ones. People bought, took 'em. And father sold
         'em. He didn't get enough for 'em, but he got rid of 'em. And then we jus t
         farmed. Come back on the ranch and farmed. And we rented 80, we rented 120
         acres down there. And we had about 100 acres of our own. . So it made
         over 200 acres that we farmed. You wouldn't know that there were ever
         any buildings there, though, now. They tore 'em down. Done away with them.
         Had as good an orchard as there was in the country down there. And we had
         all kinds of apples and we had pears and had plums,prunes and cherries.
         We had pie cherries, I don't never see any more. And we had an orchard, a
         dandy orchard. But when they, when we left the ranch we left it and the
         parties that got it didn't have no use for it. My mother's sister, her,,
         bought the place. And they had quite a few buildings. They just tore these
         down, grubbed out the orchard and run 'em all to wheat, all this ground.
         Well I guess maybe they the right thing.Because wheat's been a pretty
         good price ever since, I guess. Decent. Now it's better than four dollars
         a bushel. And don't take many bushels. Now you take an acre of ground. A
         good yie-ld that's farmed right now. It'll yield 80 to the .. And
         now you figure that out and four dollars a bushel. That's money, ain't it?
         Well, that's what they're doing now.
         
         SS:  Did your father take that place as a homestead?
         
         CC:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And he planted all them trees himself?
         CC: Yeah, we planted everything. Yep. There wasn't nothing there. All there was
         was a house and a small barn when we got it. I don't remember that very
         much because I was too young. See, I was born in we come up there in ,
         the folks come up there in 1860 something. I forget what the date was. But
         they come up there and grandfather had come up ahead of 'em. And he told
         'em about it. They come up and they bought this for four hundred dollars,
         and they got that place.They bought a nice place, one of the nicest ones
         around there. So that's how we got there. And there was no rock, there
         wasn't a rock that big on the place. All black soil. Wheat land. Farm.
         
         SS:  Had it ever been turned before?
         
         CC:  No, it had never had been. It was all part of it, I helped to break out 40
         acres there. After I got, I don't know just how old I was. But I couldn't
         have been more than 18, 19 years old. And when we broke up the last 40,
         see.
         
         SS:  Was it easy to break?
         
         CC:  No, it was pretty tough. Planted in sunflowers.You know what they are.They're
         hard to bust. And they plowed that up and break it up pretty early in the
         spring. And went over a little knoll about that high and about big.
         And what do you think we done? We just skipped. The plow just cut off the
         ground4this back. And this forty acres belonged to my grandfather, And
         he was too old to break it up, see. We were breaking it up for him. So I
         took the ' and took those out. And he had a fireplace. And we laid
         it down there on the fireplace and watched. And watched it come to life.
         And you'd be astonished to see the way they come out in the spring. And
         of course, we killed it, there were lots of squirrels. But that squirrel,
         he hibernated, see, in there, he went to sleep in that He had a place built,
         nest in there. And the shears on the plow just took off the top there and
         I happened to be right there. And I told the crew.Dad and dad said,"By gosh,
         that's right."
         
         CC:  ...The squirrel was dead. Froze, see." I don't believe he is. I'm going to
         take him over to the house and thaw him out and see.(laughs) I took him
         over there to grandfather's house, was just a little ways. Laid him on this
         hearth. He come alive. And would have run off if I hadn't a stopped him.
         
         SS:  You were born on that place?
         
         CC:  I was born there in grandfather's house.And that was just about a quarter
         of a mile from dad's house. That house, grandfather went down the lane
         little ways here. Here was the road. And then grandfather's was just a
         little ways, a creek run dxawn through here and there was a bridge. And
         grandfather lived there and we lived over here, see. And we had a nice place
         in there. All that land in there was wonderful land. There ain't no rocks
         on it. It's just nice. Some of it was a little rough. Some of it was a little
         hilly. But not bad. Dad's place didn't have a hill on it hardly. All north
         slopes. Boy, you, it was good farmland. 160 acres.
         
         SS:  Was there any bad years in the early years when they had bad weather, bad
         harvests?
         
         CC:  Yeah, in '93. You had really, yeah. I was there in '93. Yeah. We sold our
         wheat, what little we got thrashed. We sold it to the coast, sold it by
         the carload, hauled it into town and shipped it to the coast to them for
         chicken breeders. And then take it in groceries. In '94, that we got that.
         In '93 nobody harvested hardly/anything there. My wife's father, he had a
         header, or a binder. And he got his grain cut ahead of the others, see. And
         it turned out nice for a while. Dried up and they thrashed it. And he got
         that, he saved his crop. He didn't lose it. Well, we bought seed wheat
         next spring from him.That's the way we got by. But we didn't, I think we
         thrashed 200 sacks in the sacks. Held two bushels in each sack. They held
         two bushels. So that'd be four hundred bushels was all there and we cut it
         with a header, headed it and stacked it.
         
         SS:  How many acres were you farming in '93.
         
         CC:  We were farming about^lOO acres or a little better. We didn't have all the
         place kept quite, see. And so everybody had lots of 'em, all of 'em had
         all the feed they wanted. Because there was a lot of 'em didn't get thrashed
         at all. That stock would eat that headed wheat. And it was good feed,
         pretty good feed. And they got by if they had any cattle, why they got by
         and stuff like that. But if it was trying times, I ain't kidding you a bit.
         whole year's work all just went to pieces. Just rained and rained
         and rained and kept raining. And my father's thrashed out, he hadA engine
         and thrasher. AndNthrashed that much and started raining that night and
         never quit. And by gosh, rfc quit raining and he thought it would dry out.
         And dad told him, says,"It ain't no use." So he says,Joe Humphry was quite
         a name that had the hay. And he started to pull out, he bogged right down.
         Then he, when we had to take horses and pull the machine out of the orchard.
         I remember that.
         
         SS:  That was tough.
         
         CC:  Boy, I'll say it was tough.
         
         SS:  Did many families leave then?
         
         CC:  Yeah. No, they couldn't. They couldn't leave. They didn't have nothing to
         leave with. They had to stay. They had this headed wheat and stuff. And it.
         when they thrashed it they couldn't sell it. And they did thrash it, why
         it just made chicken feed and stuff. And we shipped -ftiat, we sold a bunch
         of ours, we didn't need it and we sold it, hauled it in and shipped it and
         they got chicken feed. Got a little money otit of It and then they got
         groceries. That's the way we got through that time. And we had a hard time
         of it, now there ain't no fooling. And all your work was gone. And that's
         the only year of failure that I know of. Of the Palouse country.And then
         there was one year that the crops only made about twelve bushels per acre.
         I forget what happened that year. But they got enough to live. By the time
         that happened they had quite a few acres. And broke out and they got by.
         Then after that, they watched it careful. And that land grew up, price
         grew up on it and you could buy, for 25 dollars an acre, you could buy
         that good wheatland. I could have bought 80 acres there in one spot, right
         close for 17 dollars an acre.
         
         SS:  That was when you were grown up?
         
         CC:  No. I was only about 16.
         
         SS:  What was that drive like from the Palouse over to your horse pasture country?
         How long did it 
         
         CC:  Wait a minute and I'll tell you. We make about 25 to 30 miles a day. And
         it was 175 miles from  and back. Now figure how long it would
         take us.
         
         SS:  Be about 7 days.
         
         CC:  Take a whole week or a little better. Took more than that cause we'd stop
         and let the stock feed. There was some good grass and stuff. And we'd stop
         and we had about 75 head of horses. And we had to have a night herd. Two
         of, dad and me took one part of the night , the after part. And these
         other boys took the other part.And they come in about 11 o'clock. And
         they saidNthere was two fellas trying to steal the horses. And got out
         there just in time.Dad had one of these 50-90's. Did you ever see one of
         them? Army gun. He had one of them. Got out there and it was a ridge off
         in the distance. Must have been pretty well onto a half a mile. And dad, he
         pulled down with that big army gun and he let right em. Boy, of course
         whiter we didn't see any more. Now I don't know he killed one of 'em or not.
         But we never seen any more riders. And that was down by, well, you wouldn't
         know.Sprangs. What they call Sprangs.
         
         SS:  Sprangs?
         
         CC:  Sprangs. Yeah. A lot of Sprangs here together. In this country. We got in
         there. And they said there had never been in a hurry, went through there
         when they lost pret'near half of their herd. And what fella he steal 'em.
         Steal 'em, run 'em off at night and then ride 'em up there and hide 'em.
         And the next day they monkey around there and they had lined up several
         places like that. And up here and they run 'em across the border. Shout.
         We didn't get very much for 'em, but that's it. But I'm telling you, when
         that old gun roared, there was somebody amoving. And we had an old mare,
         she had a colt there. We had two or three mares with colts. This one and
         she had a bell on. You ought to have heard that bell ring when they got
         out there. And the horse run back, she was bell mare of the herd. And
         we kept her there too.We watched for her. And whenever we found we could
         hear the bell, and knew where they was.
         
         SS:  Did you have any trouble keeping track of the herd at all?
         
         CC:  Oh yes, every once in a while we'd have to, they'd steal 'em. So they
         got down around seven, what they call the Seven Devils country I think,
         go through there. And that was a tough place. Pretty tough for a layout.
         We got another place, dad and me, we in the wagon. And then when we
         left, the two boys,.they took our bed and we got on the horses and went
         out and put in the rest of the night. Keeping watch. And that old bell _.
         mare just about done the work. IF she just done it a little^we probably
         would have found out who it was.They started to go on this ridge. They
         spied us, see. And heard her. And they were making a getaway. And one of
         them got over the top here and we were almost here.And we seen'em going.
         And dad pulled down on him and he let loose. Now I don't know he killed
         him or what or that we didn't or anything about it. We never wait to see.
         So the next morning we got out just as quick as it got daylight, we pulled
         out and got the herd straightened up and pulled out. And dad and me took
         the wagon, and I was twelve years old. And we took the wagon. I had a
         pony part of the time. And we, that bell mare, we kept her. We never
         broke* her or never done that. We didn't want to feed her. She'd
         leave with this bell on and she had to make her own living.The grass was up
         like this.AIn March and one place, then after that we went in the next
         year, so dad and I went out to get 'em, bring 'em in, we wanted to bring
         'em in. We had to, I think it was about twenty five or thirty head. And hy
         that, them horses was raring to go. They was all fat. This was in the fall
         of the year. One nice mare, four year old, went right by our school.
         And the kids run out at recess, see. Kids run out and scared the horse
         over the barbed wire fence there. This mare got scared and run into this
         barbed wire fence. And cut her all up and we had to leave her. And we told
         the fella,"You take care of her and we'll pay you for it.If she dies, that'll
         iust be it."She did, she died. She was an awful nice animal, too.
         
         SS:  Was she the bell mare?
         
         CC:  No.
         
         SS:  Another one.
         
         CC:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Was there twice the guys tried to rustle your horses?
         
         CC:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Two times you told me about.
         
         CC:  They'd steal 'em.
         
         SS:  You said two different times? Your father fired at 'em.
         
         CC:  Yeah. Pretty rough going, I'll tell you,
         
         SS:  Did you just camp where you found a nice place to camp?
         
         CC:  It was pretty well near qui+ting time, yes. It was about noon, the horses
         were hungry. We'd stop and let 'em graze, maybe two o'clock. And then we'd
         start 'em agoing again. And 75 head of horses ain't no easy job. And so
         then of a night they had, two of us had to herd. And had to night herd. You
         couldn't touch that.
         
         SS:  Was it hard going for the wagon? Over that land, was there a trail for the
         wagon?
         
         CC:  Oh yes. Just a trail, and that's all. Lots of places was just trail. We had
         a good team and a light load, was loaded light. You could go anyplace. 
         And so we got the herd, went on there, I know we stopped and got our break
         fast. Find some good grass and stopped the horses and went out and got, let
         the whole herd have a rest and have something to eat. And the fella that
         lived there, he said,"How in the hell did you get all them horses tfar ough
         that place without losing some of 'em?" Well we told him, we night watched.
         WE11 he said,"They been nightwatching lots of times there's horse thieves
         vail the time." Dad said,"We never lost a one. Not a one. We herded of a
         night too.
         
         SS:  Was much of the country under fence or was most of it open when you came?
         
         CC:  All open. All open when we went out there. Clear from Harrington clear
         out by , that would be about close to a hundred miles,
         
         SS:  Was, I know there was a Palmer that had horses out there too. Did you know
         them? Was it the same time they had horses?
         
         CC:  That was after we moved out there. I remember seeing them too.
         
         SS:  Did anybody else run horses the same time you did?
         
         CC:  Oh yes. That was the reason horses was cheap. They had so many of them.
         After we got out there and got settled, got 'em out on the prairie, out to
         the ranch, didn't take long for them to settle down because they was after
         the feed, they wanted feed, see. And water, little lakes and stuff. And
         everything was good. We just made a camp out of it when we first
         went out there. And then, til we could do better, Just like a homesteader,
         That's what we was a doing. That was about the way they done the whole
         thing up and down that river. You couldn't, that land was land would
         be, a river aways maybe from here to off the road, I think twice that far.
         There be level. Pretty near level. And bunch grass there. That was our
         winter feed. It never, they said it never snowed down there hardly ever,it
         never got cold. The horses wintered down there.
         
         SS:  I thought sometimes you drove them back to Palouse.
         
         CC:  We did. When we first went out there we had to do something with them.We
         couldn't provide for 'em. We had to drive 'em back.I think, if I remember
         right, we drove 'em back twice. And old man Pedicord. Wilson, they was
         his boy, old Wilson Pedicord. He was one of 'em, Wilson Pedicord and doggone
         it, I can't recall the other fella's name now. I forget that other one. But
         I can't think of 'em, dad had so many men working for him.
         But you had four guys on the drive when you drove, right?
         
         Yeah.
         
         After a couple of years you left the horses there over winter?
         
         Yeah.
         
         
         And who took care of 'em over winter?
         do  They sometimes he let the neighbors. And they all get together, the horses
         would, lot of 'em. And they'd winter through. And sometimes we'd get
         somebody there. As time went on, they would be more, more men, more
         settlers in there. But there was always range, lots of range. That was
         awful big country. That's right there on the Coulee Dam.
         
         SS:  When you drove the horses, did you ever see. people on the trail?
         
         CC:  I hardly ever seen anybody. Drive them 75 head of horses there and just dad
         and me and the two riders. And that was it. And lots and lots of days we
         wouldn't see anybody. At all. Well there wasn't no people. There just
         wasn't any. They, if there were, they couldn't get out there, They didn't
         have any money and that. But as time went on, they did. We went across that
         Coulee Dam, the wife and I went out there on that Grand Coulee.,,
         
         CC:  That's when I was first married. We went out there when we were first
         married we went out to this place. Drove out there. That was our honeymoon.
         
         SS:  To the Grand Coulee.
         
         CC:  Right out across the Coulee and on out. Went out Id cattle ranch, the
         first ranch out there.
         
         SS:  Was most of that country sagebrush or was most of it bunch grass?
         
         X: All buchgrass. No sagebrush where we was. All bunchgrass. It was a beautiful,,,
         Boy, it was just lots of feed. And there was I think only
         three fellas that had any stock. And they'd been in there about four or
         five years. And they had stuff built up, their pastures. The L hey boys
         and twcr more of 'em I know. And boys and I knew all of 'em.
         I was about, I don't know. I tried to remember all their names, but there
         were too many, I couldn't do it.
         
         SS:  Were the McGregors around there then?
         
         CC:  No. They throwed it open for farmland. And they let 'em have a homestead.
         That just raised thunder with us.
         
         SS:  What?
         
         CC:  That just raised thunder with us then. People went in there figured they
         could homestead and plow that up. Make a living. They went in there and
         plowed it up alright. Broke it up, they got out of there too. They couldn't
         do it. They it was no grazing country for the stock. It was,
         they thought they could farm it up.
         
         SS:  Not enough moisture?
         
         CC:  That's right. There wouldn't be no moisture there in the summertime. And
         there's what's called a shell rock. Shell rock under the ground. On the
         top, big bunchgrass. Take a team and take a mower and go^there and you
         cut your winter's hay, they figured, for the stock.
         That's the way they got their hay.
         
         What happened whenothey farmed it? Did it go into sagebrush?
         
         No. It wasn't a sagebrush country.
         
         I mean after they farmed it, it didn't grow crops, right?
         
         They it for the whole thing. The bunchgrass never come back, it
         never done any good. And there was ,I could name, that wouldn't do no good
         But that's what become of it. And Idon't know what it is today. Idon't
         know what it is now.
         
         SS:  How did you and your dad eat when you were living on the dugout?What kind
         of food did you have?
         
         CC:  Just the same as they had here. We had a store fourteen miles down the
         river, little town, Bridgeport. We'd go down there and get our stuff.
         
         (End of tape)
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13418</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Crow_Ada</previous>
      <next>Currin</next>
      <disp_name>Crow_Charles</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
