<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/24/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ada Hill Crow, 1974-07-24, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:02:00</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Crow, Ada Hill</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1880</birthyear>
      <residence>Fourmile Creek, Viola</residence>
      <origin>Family moved from Junction City, Oregon and homesteaded (1887)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#post offices"&gt;post offices&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mail carriers"&gt;mail carriers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hotels"&gt;hotels&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#canning and preserving"&gt;canning and preserving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farmers"&gt;farmers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dogs"&gt;dogs&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#literary"&gt;literary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#quilting"&gt;quilting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cards"&gt;cards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Fourmile Creek"&gt;Fourmile Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Viola"&gt;Viola&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Oregon"&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Canada"&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13413</file_name>
      <mp3>13414.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13414.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Early Viola residents; mail in a covered wagon; four buildings set on fire; accidents
               with equipment
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Early Viola residents. Boles' store and Post Office.
               Nichols carried mail in a covered wagon. McCray saloon,
               Sanson box factory and Comer Hotel. Burning of church
               two schoolhouses and old hall by a boy with, perhaps, the
               help of someone else. Minister for Viola church worked
               out. Dohn Rothwell got leg caught in tumbling rod,
               also Beasley girl — grinding flour.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Why parents came and what they arrived with; Father taught school; eating camas; Nazarenne
               Church
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Parents came from Junction City to homestead and arrived
               with tea, bread and an onion to eat. Father taught
               school that year. Two foot high bunch grass. Following
               the plow and eating the camas. Smylie. Nazarenne Church.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>What they did for free time; planting the garden; thrashing beans; snowdrift problems</title>
            <synopsis>Played on creek in free time. Brothers cutting church
               and running races. Father marked off the rows in the
               garden to be done each day. Helped raise kids. Getting
               stuck in snowdrift. Raised beans on summer fallow.
               Sometimes thrashed beans with frails on barn floor in
               the winter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>How her father saved his crop in 1893; why bound wheat held up but wet wheat did not;
               where they said wet wheat too
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father saved his crop in 1893 because he had a binder
               and had his grain all bound. Most other people used
               headers in 1893, but with a binder you could cut it
               somewhat green. With header the grain had to be almost
               ready to shatter out. Father sold much of his grain
               for seed grain. People sold wet grain to coast.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1620</time>
            <title>How they canned produce and where they stored it</title>
            <synopsis>Canning with half gallon tin cans which were sealed with
               red sealing wax. Put garden stuff in cellar, put cabbage
               in a straw and dirt pile and buried potatoes in pits.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Harvesting potatoes; getting woood in the snow; raising dry beans; fruit orchards;
               and using lard
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>(continued) Brothers a nuisance when digging up potatoes.
               Father wrapped himself in gunnysacks to his hips to work
               in the snow getting wood. Raised lots of dry beans.
               Didn't believe you could grow apples until Wes Palmer
               put in his orchard. No bugs then in the garden, fruit
               or berry bushes. Used 25 gallons of lard a year.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>How Viola got its nickname; trading timber for groceries; selling hay; mail delivery;
               father didn't swear
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Viola named "Dogwalk" because the dogs walked on the planks.
               Boles store mainly traded with the people who lived in
               the timber who traded wood for groceries. Father would
               sell them hay cheap or give it to them. Got mail twice
               a week. Father had to get his paper and read it by the
               lamp. Father never swore — could only say "Gosh mariah".
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Fourmile church; how people were baptized in the winter; not a lot of dancing; couldn't
               bury people in the winter in Canada due to cold ground
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Fourmile Church. Emmett Godow a good minister. Cutting
               a hole in the ice and baptizing people. Didn't dance
               much. The frozen ground in Canada. Couldn't bury
               people in the winter because the ground was frozen solid.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Literaries and debates on Fridays; Charlie Crow and her brother singing; making their
               own newspaper
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Literaries and debates every Friday night. "Which is
               most useful: the dish rag or the kitchen door?" One
               old man would get mad if people didn't see it his way.
               Charlie Crow and her brother sang "Casey Dones" and
               tore the house down. Made their own newspaper.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>One fellow rented a pony and ran it until it fell down
               dead. Wes Palmer would hitch up wild horses.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>One fellow rented a pony and ran it until it fell down
               dead. Wes Palmer would hitch up wild horses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Training wild horses; Aunt and Uncle running off to get married; Wes Palmer; Palmer
               son killed by a log; Asher Palmer working till 90
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>continued) After one run the horses could be put in
               a harness. Her uncle and aunt ran off and got married
               by the Dustice of the Peace, Wes Palmer. Wes' only son
               was killed by a log. Asher Palmer worked in the garden
               when he was 90.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Broke off courting husband; hauling timbers for the railroad; bought household goods
               when married
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Broke off courting with her husband because he took
               another girl to a dance. Charlie hauled timbers for
               the railroad trestle near Viola. Not given any presents
               when married. Spent $25 on a new cookstove, used daven
               port and four chairs.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Methodist camp meetings; taught to be afraid of Native Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Methodist camp meetings went on for several weeks.
               Taught to be afraid of Indians.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4860</time>
            <title>Homesteading in Canada; Five years without a crop; one pickup load when leaving</title>
            <synopsis>Heard about homestead land in Canada. Lived there from
               1912 - 1937. Went for five years without a crop. Took
               one pickup load with them when they left.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5460</time>
            <title>Eighteen people in one house over the winter; what they would do when they couldn't
               go outside
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Eighteen people spent one winter together at her place.
               Would visit when it was -30 and the women would quilt
               and the men played cards. Young people stayed all night at dances.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>Having a baby in the dead of winter; quilting; making money by taking neighbors to
               town
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>One woman had a baby in the dead of winter in a sleigh
               on the way to the hospital. Quilted twice a week. Husband
               would take neighbors to town on Saturday night for ten
               cents.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6360</time>
            <title>Brothers buying photograph for parents for Christmas</title>
            <synopsis>Brothers in later years surprise their parents by buying
               a phonograph for Christmas and hiding it behind the tree.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Dr. Gritman having smallpox and people waiting for him; Alice Skeene isolated; Mrs.
               Gritman going to Portland
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Alice Skeene waited on Dr. Gritman when he had smallpox
               and then her folks wouldn't let her stay at home.
               She ends up staying at her house and accomodations
               are made. The most dangerous time was when she was
               scaling off and she was isolated. Mother wouldn't
               let her in the house after that. Mrs. Gritman put on
               a veil and went to Portland.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Getting typhoid fever and only eating strained food; daughter's relationship with
               father during the same time; threatening to burn the weeds
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Down 36 days with typhoid fever. Could only eat strained
               buttermilk and eat whey. Baked a cake and ate the whole
               thing. Her daughter would cuss her father when he
               licked her. Her daughter took a notion to burn the
               weeds around the house.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Velma Gertz (daughter) Family homesteading: farm produce and 1893 wet harvest.
         Viola events and settlers. Religious and social gatherings. Typhoid; smallpox. Getting
         married. Canadian homesteading (1912-37). 7-24-74 2 hr 45p LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         ADA HILL CROW: A man and he had two sons: Uesley and Elmer. Wesley, he was the oldest,
         and he
         was justice of the peace for a long time. And also he raised the first
         apples in that country, first appiles. And then
         this man named John Miller homesteaded there. He homesteaded in back of
         Viola, y'know, but he lived in Viola. And so did Elmer Palmer live in
         Viola but the homesteads ron back y'se% and ' yet, they still are.
         And tb* -bcio had a store in the post office. And I forgot the man's name
         that had the blacksmith's shop. And we went to church every 9hday in the
         schoolhouse. And my father, Frank Hill, taught the first term school there.
         And Mr. Nicholson, an old man he was ,carried the mail in a covered wagon from
         Viola to Palouse and back.
         
         LAURA SCHRAGER: Do you remember that, him doin that?
         
         AC: Oh, yes. Oh, yes, to Palouse and back.
         
         LS:   Was it a big wagon that he had?
         
         AC:  Just a little covered light wagon he had, uh huh. He carried the mail,
         for years and years. And then a man name of McKay^had a saloon there
         of course at that saloon, y'know. Later Mr. Manoon had a box factory after
         he got to raisin' apples, then he had a box factory there. And Mr. and Mrs.
         Com, they had the hotel there. And they later built a church-one room.
         Mr. Smiley was the school superintendent and Mr. Veatch was the minister.
         Now that's as far as I know of that. But this church, it got burnt cfim
         the boy didn't want to go to school. And burnt both schoolhoUes and then they fixed
         it up and an old hall
         to have some school. And he burnt the hall. Then they said, t'hey-d fix up the
         church and he burnt the church. So he didn't want to go to school and that's
         what happened. And just a boy, about twelve years old. But we always thought
         there was somebody else helping him. Now that's all I know of that, that's
         the beginning of that big town.(Chuckles)..
         
         LS:   Did  the church?
         
         AC:  No, had the hotel.
         
         LS:   Right.
         
         AC:  No, the members built the church, the church members-the Christian Church,
         urn hum. Of course it was small; there  small.
         
         LS:  Where did they have church before that? Did people go to church at all?
         
         AC:  They had it in the schoollouse, inthe shoolhouse, um hum.
         
         LS:   Would someone come out and preach?
         
         AC: Yes, um hum. Yes, before we got the church they'd come out from Palouse
         and preach. But aW we( got the church we had aminister there. Just someone
         that would^t'ay there and preach. Oh, he worked out on the farm and like
         that too, but he preached.
         
         LS:  How did they raise the money for that church? Do you know how they got that
         biil  to run a, church , 
         
         AC:  Oh farmers, they farmed, y'know. It don't take as much then as it 
         now. Goodness, they didn't the as nice a, they do now. (Chuckles).
         The minister, he drn't get nothin much, justwhat the congregation would take
         up, and that's all he'd get. Maybe five, six dollars on Sunday, that's all.
         Now look what they give em. And a calico dress, you could get a calico dress
         for twenty-five cent—a good dress certainly. You could get five yards1-
         five cents a yard. Now you couldn't get the end of a bolt for that.
         Thirty-six inches wide, yep. I guess those people are all gone now
         that  there/C that's about all I know about Viola.
         
         LS:  Was there agrist mill there when you were in Viola? On. in City, but not in Viola,
         no.The b - was 
         
         AC:  Ho, never was. One in 
         in the timber, no grist mill, „ did have one there, did
         they? Not that I know of.
         
         LS: Well there's astory about-do you know how John Brothwell lost his legs?
         
         AC:  Yes.
         
         
         LS:   Oh, how did that happen?
         
         AC:  It seems to me like, you know they had these old horse plowers with the
         horses would go and there was atumbing rod that'd run from the machine
         up to this horsepower and some way he got caught in that tumbling rod. He
         went to step over it or something and he caught his leg in that, tht's all.
         
         LS:   What was he using the horsepower for?
         
         AC:  Oh, I don't know. What was they using the Beasley
         girl got hurt there too. Oh,, what was they doin? It
         was grinding grain  something. I just can't remember that, grinding
         gftn or something though. She had to keeP the hors goin and step over
         that rod and she didn't get over once. It was bound to have acddents sometimes,
         y'know. There were so many people around, they have to have accidents.
         
         LS:   What was that box factory about?
         
         AC:  In Viola?
         
         LS:   Yeah.
         
         AC: In the south end, yeah, it was on the south end. ' along time. I
         don't know what Viola looks like now, I haven't seen it for a long time.
         My father lived in Washington, but his fence yet is the line between
         Idaho and Washington, it still b. Because we used to play beck and forth:
         one would get in Idaho and one would get in. So ghat's about all.
         Now they lots of strawberries around  Viola there in the
         mountains. They had lots of strawberries there and cattle. He had quite
         a few cattle.
         
         LS:   Would you go out there and pick strawberries a lot?
         
         AC; Oh, yes. We went out and picked strawberries, um hum.
         
         LS:  You know I wanted you back to-you started to mention last time, right
         before I left some stuff about your parents, things that they'd told you.
         I think it was your parents coming by covered wagon.
         
         AC: Oh yeah, they come from Oregon, Junction City, Oregon. It took em six weeks
         to come because they stopped and worked a while on the way. And when they
         got to the homestead all they had to eat was. . .Mother said they had a
         cup of tea and some bread and butter and an onion. That's all they had when
         they got to their homestead, you know.They had the money but they didn't buy
         groceries. And the., there's Mr.^ Scott lived there close. He had abig
         garden and aMr. Piatt, they the folks out then. And the folks got
         there in July.Well they helped the folks out with the garden stuff all that
         summer. So they got along good then. But Father loaned the only twenty-five
         dollars he had to Mr. Scott.
         probably cause he loaned it out. He was like that, he'd give you the last cent
         he had and do without himself. And he'd help somebody else. Well, anyway,
         Mother, she didn't like it but he'd get it back, that's all right.
         
         LS:   What'd they do those first years?
         
         AC: Well, Father taught schooKhat. But  alog house
         and the neighbor helped them* And then father taught school that fall
         in la there. And they got along pretty good that way. Oh they didn't have it
         like we do nowadays, goodness they raised a garden the next summer
         and they got along all right afer that. My father taught school for several
         years after he was married. I don't know, people were all the same. There
         wasn't one tryin to bug another and tryin to get their money away. There
         wasn't anybody that had much money. But they were good  you know,
         and all honest and all had a good time.
         
         LS:  What do you remember the homestead being like when you were a kid?
         
         AC:  Oh, just bunch grass about two feet high all over. I remember Father
         used to take the three horses, put it on the plow, and my brother and I, we'd
         go along behind him. And we'd plow up what they called camas. Be a Uttie
         onion-like, something like an onion, only it wasn't as strong. And we'd eat
         that; the Indians eat it. told us about the Indians eatin camas
         so we ate it too. And then once in a while we'd catch a rabbit, little baby
         rabbit,y'know and take it home. (Chuckles).. Oh, we had such a
         up there, near as I remember it was a rough lookin country to start in to
         farming. All bunch grass all over and only three little horses. And about a
         twelve inch plow to go around and walk, round and round and round.
         
         LS:   Now were you born at Viola?
         
         AC: Yeah, well I was born on the homestead, um hum. It was about two miles south
         west of Viola. I told you to look back when you get up there on the mountain
         you can see that house. You can't see the house through the trees. But you can
         see an old red barn and a lot of trees. But the old house is there but it's
         pretty well done now. They built it when I was twelve years old. That's a long
         time ago, you see.
         
         LS:  Did tey have help on that when they put that up, the new house?
         
         AC:  Yeah, they had a carpenter, oh yes.And then they finally got telephones
         put in Viola there. We lived in Viola after we was married and then they
         put telephones in there too. I don't think never had electricity
         though. Nobody did around there. Well, I guess they have now.  they
         have. So, long time ago, nearly ahundred years ago I guess 4nce
         Viola was started. They w«e there four years Sfore my brother and I was born-
         were twins. And they were there four years before we were born so you
         see they was there right from tta beginning of Viola. I think there was a man
         there, an old man named Smiley was there about the fi|t, I guess. He was
         a kind of retired, kind of a mhister. Then we had a good big church later on.
         there. and her sister. You can remember it, can't you Velma, that church?
         
         VELMA : Not much. I remember the church and what it looked like.
         church and US shop now. Oh I know
         what got into em, the Nazarenes, they had a church there, you know. And the 
         was Eddie Gray's father. He bought a and they fixed it all up and
         they-I don't know whether it was that or the Christian people, they said
         they owned the land and they wouldn't have no 
         into his shop, some kind of a shop, I don't  but that makes it bad.
         though the Christiane
         church, what's the difference? They didn't need that. Would you think they
         should?
         
         LS: Oh no. That's the way things go like that sometimes though.
         
         AC:  Yeah, they did. Well, that's about all I can tell you.
         
         LS:  Well, can you tell me more about when you were a kid, you know, things
         that you did for fun when you had some free time.
         
         AC: Oh yeah, we played up anda   (Chuckles). And neighbor
         girls would come up, you iknow, firlfvcigiAn.hWliAor^ k*iidass and we'd all go to
         the
         crick, you know how kids are in the water 
         And find 
         
         AC:  We'  snakes.
         
         V: We did too, you taught it to us. 
         
         AC:  start they couldn't go and then they'd send the boys and they'd go up to the
         swimmin hole. My twin brother would always get his shirt on wrong side out
         and tit^^tnow th^hadn't been to church, (Chuckles),they'd
         stay and swim, around until they seen Mr. home from church. Then
         they'd get out would always get
         his shirt on wrong side out. 
         didn't da tell on ' un, if I did. But we didn't go to school
         ve„ much. We went down  down west of Viola. When we first went
         there, why the School was too far away for us to go so we went to Viola
         for  Miranda Homei. was the name of the teacher that feught there
         when we went. Father had quit teaching then, he'd been Well I had t,
         work, nothing to work with much either, didn't have then like they do
         now. Milk cows, butter and eggs, and sell garden stuff. Us kids used
         to carry onions up-we-d go to school and we'd take onions up and sell 'em
         in Viola there in bunches, green onto, y'know. Things like that.
         
         LS:   What kinds of chores did you kids have to do?
         
         AC:  Oh, we milked cows, feed the pigs, the boys did. I had to help Mother
         in the house in those days. The boys had to do the chores when they got
         big enough^ to help take care of the kids and there was aUays
         the baby to look after. And then the dishes to wash. And there was an
         awful lot of work to do. And we had to help in the garden, work in th,
         garden. Father couldn't do it and farm toiso us kids had to work in the garden,
         We didn't play srond like they do now. We had to help. IThey made us
         get out and do things. Father had so .any rows for us to do and we'd have
         to do 'em or else take a lickini I don't think that he'd hurt us much but
         we were scared of him, just the same .(Chuckle.), And we had to because he
         just couldn't do all that work.yknow. Mother helped in the garden a lot
         too.
         
         LS:  That garden was probably pretty big for all you kids.
         
         AC:  That's right, um hum. Big garden. And we had to make butter old
         dasher churn, up and down, y'know, like that. she knows that.
         Mother-d set down evening and churn and churn and churn her old butter.
         She put it down on a cool evening and she said she was going to rest and churn.
         (Chuckles),.And oh, we had ponies to ride. Oh yes, we'd go horseback riding.
         And on Sunday we'd go riding. Boys used to take the horses and run races on
         Sunday. Cause if Father the horse. 
         
         LS:  Did you have your hands full taking care of the kids, the smaller kids?
         
         AC:  Yes, I always had to take care of the baby. Mother had so much to do. I
         Was the oldest girl. Mother had so much to do that I had to help. No, I don't know,
         I didn't mind.
         
         V : I'm the oldest girl, 1 did too. Oldest in the family always had to take
         car- a little more than the others. 
         
         AC:  But we had to work, had to live. And ijwas twelve years old before I eve:
         had a pair of overboots, you know, over your shoes to school. No we didn'twe
         had, just . But our shoes was good and heavy too.
         to school. And^ schoolhouse, it was
         just one room. And a big old heater, long, and It had a hearth
         out on it. It took this three foot wood and put it in that. And then
         no, that wood don't throw that heat out like coal or anything but didn't
         cold and, . . have any coal.And we'd drive down there in a team and we'd be^Sh sometimes
         we'd push each other out in the snow ac get wet and cold so we'd go out there.
         And that old heater wouldn't heat the house if it was very cold. I don't
         know how we lived through it but we never got sick. It didn't hurt us. No,
         get stuck in a snowdrift and you always had to get out and wade in that
         snow up to our waist. But now, could they do that nowadays? (Chuckles).
         I guess we could if we had to. Well, Father told us, we thought we had to.
         He told us no, he says,"If you get stuck in a snowdrift just set still and leave
         ,be horses alone. There'll be aplow and get through and you the
         sleigh and leave 'em alone. Thy'll get through,"and they did.But we
         Uad to get out and help, that it was too heavy for 'em. Yessir, Father took
         his grain to Palouse to get it ground for flour. And then he raised beans
         on his™ fall to buy his sugar and coffee. Oh yes, he'd
         or three acres of beans in. And we'd have to hire help from Viola come
         down from Viola and help hoe thebeans out and help pull 'em and thrash out.
         and if you couldn't thrash 'em out then they'd put
         'em in the barn and then they'd thrash V, in the wintertime when they had more
         time, y'know,  the barn floor. They took abig canvas down and then they'd
         beat'em out with flails, y'know. You took a stick, if you know what a flail
         is, well they took and stick and then they took a shorter one ,y see. Andrten
         they'd put a leather here on this one and up over this one. Well you this
         it'd fly b«k,aSa(jSTyou hit it that way, why this srick on top would go
         down under the beans, and that's what they called a flail. It w,sSorter
         than this one. And you hit that, you hit it hard.
         L  Did you do that?
         
         AC:  1 didn't, the men folks did. Yeah, that's the way. They wouldn't do that
         nowadays, would they?
         
         LS:  Well, that's a pretty hard way to get your beans.
         
         AC:  Well, they had to work hard, oh yes. And they used to have headers in that
         country. They'd had the wheat up with h,ade,s and stack it and
         
         LS:   Was that pretty early that they had headers?
         on one side, low on the other cause the shoe from
         the header would have to come up into this bed. And you see the grain had
         it rolling around like this. Well, this grain would get
         on these and then they'd go and fall oyr in the header bed, see. 
         then this was low, and then it was 
         go up in here and there'd be somebody there to keep it back and they'd have
         to load it. Then Father got abinder abound the grain. And then they could
         get it taken care of quicker. In 1903 they had the wet olace.
         
         LS:  No, that was '93. It was 1893 that it rained. . .
         
         AC: It rained and spoiled their c-ops. But Father got his safe bacause he had
         binder and he had it all^nd his thrashing all don, So he saved his
         crop that year, But most of the people just loat their grain, it rained so
         much on thm. That was 1893, yes.
         
         LS: Were most other peopteusing headers then?
         
         AC:  Yes, um hum. Nearly ail c; em did. I don't know how Father happened to get
         bis binder but he did. He got it someway. He saved his grain'cause he could
         cut it on the green side and then they'd shock it up in shocks, you know, it'd
         mature, y'see. Then they ccdd go by and pick it up and put it through the
         machine, thr.,h it. With aheader you had to let it set quite a little while
         before you could thrash it after you got it cut. It had to be just as ripe as
         could be before they could cut it it would shatter out, and
         it did shatter, a lot cf it did.
         
         
         LS:   You were lmcky then.
         
         AC:  Oh, yes. We were lucky. Father sold a lot of his grain for seed wheat
         that next spring, yeah. ^ got groceries and stuff from the 
         over around Seattle and around. They sent groceries and stuff. Aid I don't
         know, they traded that old wet wheat for something. I don't know, maybe
         pig feed or Sicken feed or something. But over on the coast they took it and
         let r.ne people have groceries, y'know.
         
         LS: Did many people have to leave or sell their land because of that harvest?
         
         AC:  No, I can't remember anybody leaving. No, they made it throgh. That's
         the only time it was so wet. Yeah, we raised real there, it
         rained ouite often- Raised goodSard*didn't have to irrigate anything.
         
         LS. Can you tell used to can in the oldest way that you can
         remember?
         
         AC:  Yeah, I remember the first peaches had a half agallon can.
         
         
         LS:   Tin can?
         
         AC:  Um hum,they're tin. They weren't high can, they weren't flat , but you know,
         half gallon. If I can make you understand, they'd come up and then this lid
         would come over little crease around here,
         air holes,and then this lie from the inside would come out over the top. An
         Mother would put red sealing wax all in this crease, clear around that can,
         all over that and make it airtight. That's what they had then.
         
         LS:   Would they boil it then after they'd do that?
         
         AC:  Oh, no, Mother always cooker! her peaches first.
         
         LS: You'd cook them and u'd put em in the tin and then yai'd just seal it.
         
         AC:  Real hot, take em right out and seal em real hot, with sealing wax.
         ThenfloO bit, would go all over that and then you'd cool it, and it'd
         seal, yep. In tin cans, I don't know, n0w they don't use tin. Anther thing,
         I don't think she ever canned any garden stuff, we put it in the cellar.
         They'd put cabbage--my father used to make kind of a frame out in the garden,
         He'd put up a piece tike this and then here it'd be long, it be,
         according to how long you wanted it. And then he'd tie two heads together,
         see he'd dig a trench about a half a foot deep, six inches deep, put some
         straw in there and then he'd tie these cabbage roots together and the
         heads lay down in the straw.And then he'd put more straw over the heads
         until he got that whole thhg foill . And then he'd put dirt over that,
         cover em over so they wouldn't freeze. And then we'd have cabbage all winter,
         that way.
         
         LS:   Did he put a lot of dirt on top?
         
         AC:  Yi, he had to or it would freeze if you didn't. It got awful cold then.
         Well he covered it with the straw so the dirt woldn't get next to the cabbage,
         they used tobury their potatoes. They'd be down , maybe a cople feet down in.
         And then they'd put the potatoes in pits, you know. And then he'd put straw--
         he'd pile'em up and they'd come up like this,y'see. And then he'd put straw
         all over them, maybe a foot and a half, two feet deep and then : dirt on
         tup of that, quite a lot of dirt. And they'd keep all winter. Oh that was a
         job gettin them out of there. Oh, I hated that worse than anything in the
         world, gettin them potatoes out. I hated to see Father say, I want you kids to put
         those potatoes all in bags. And
         we had to.
         
         LS:   What was so bad about doing the
         
         Oh just didn't want to do it; it wasn't bad, we just didn't want to do it.
         I'll tell you, you know, you'dthe bottom up even, you know, and
         it wouldn't be so bad. I'd have mine all clean so I could pick 'em up from here, y'know.
         And they'd
         shove that old st raw here and I'd have to get back and pickvem up. You know
         what boys are like.I thought they was the meanest two boys there ever was in the
         world. (Chuckles). And they'd rastle and scuffle, play. And I was getting mine
         dd5?fc, and I had so many to pick up. And I'd get mine done and they'd say,"Well,
         if you help me, I'll pay ya. I'll give you ten cents." I knew they wouldn't.
         They never taad ten cents. And I knew they wouldn't, but yet I'd help em. That
         was the way I was. It wouldn't hurtneto help 'em pick up a few potatoes. Ttey
         wouldn't help me though. Oooh, they were ornery, regular little beasts.
         (£huckles).Yep. Awful cold in the wintertime there though. Father used to
         wrap up. And we didn't have anything much to wrap up in so he'd take gunny
         sacks, cut lem in pieces and then start in--he had kind of a heavy boots on.
         And he'd start in just around his feet and he'd wrap clear up to his hip
         because he was in that snow, cuttin wood,y'see and bringin' that long wood
         out of the timber for wood. And he'd come back just saakin wet when they
         were done.  wet from that snow. And then I remember, he had a place
         up in the house, he'd hang them old sacks up to^dry in the night and then
         put em on the next morning. Go get another load of wood. But they didn't
         think too much about it. They had to do it and they didn't know any better,
         and it was all right. W wouldn't do it now, would we? Now that we know
         better. Nobody even burns wood now.
         
         LS:   Where would he cut the wood? Would he have to go far to cut it?
         
         AC:  No, not then. Not those days, they'd just go in back of Viola there
         about maybe a mile and There was lots of timber there then
         in those days. There wouldn't be now because so many people, farms and houses,
         people livin back there, you know, there's no timber. Not like it used to
         be then. I know they used to have to go over the summit to get to the wood
         they'dhave to take their team and go back over
         before Flannigan Crick and up in there to get their wood.Because people have settled
         up
         so far back in, back of Viola there, y'know, and they have homes in there.
         And they wouldn't let 'em have the wood. em might let 'em cut a load
         now and then. But at there was lots of wood there. They still. . .
         
         LS:  Did you father cut any wood for groceries or anything like that?
         
         AC:  No, no he just cut if for our own use. No, he didn't. He raised beans and
         garden stuff, you know, like that. It didn't take many groceries, y'see,
         had eggs and^gtfd garden. And then Mother canned the fruit but they didn't
         can beans or peas nor nothin1 like that in those days, They just use
         'em. And we had all kinds of car rots^cabbage and potatoes. And they raised
         lots of dry beans, y'know, garn had lot of dry beans.
         
         LS:   Did they have a lot cf different kinds of dry beans too?
         
         AC:  yeah. They'd have the white,aavy and then they'd have the little red
         caM-i beans and the white navy beans. And they'd raise 'en and they were good.
         They had all kinds of beans. Oh Father had em buy the hundreds of sacks of
         'em settin°there. You know, so many in the field there. He'd get four, five
         and six cents a pound for 'em. Well, that amounted to quite a bit, you know.
         But no, we didn't have canned vegetables. We had canned fruit-peaches and
         pears. We had lots of apples after he got to raisin1 apples But they didn't
         think that thy could raise apples till this farmer raised some. The reason
         we that so well, I had a calf that I claimed. Father said he
         wanted to buy it. So I told him, all right, he could have it for a
         dollar. That was big money. Then Mother took my dollar and boufct apples
         for the harvest hands so I didn't have no dollar.(Ctakle.) ._ That's the
         reason I remember one farmer raisin'apples. But she took my dollar and
         bought apples. People thought they couldn't raise'em, you know.
         we could do it. No, it'd be too cold. And we raised the nteat apples. Then everybody
         raised too many, apples
         every place. Oh, you could raise all kinds of fruit then. Better than you
         can now with no bugs or things like there is now.Oh, Father, he used
         to have nice pears and cherries, apricots, peaches, raspberries, gooseberries,
         currants-ttrc, different kinds of currants, the black and the red and the white.
         And raspberries and oh, I don't know, anything you wated like that. But they
         did can them. And made jam and
         
         LS:   The peaches didn't get frosted out?
         
         AC:  Oh no ,oh no. The peaches'd be all right. They'd be ail right now if it
         wasnit fror thue curl leaf and like that, you know,
         And so many bugs and stuff, just don't pay to try to raise peaches. It's
         just, hard. But apples, it's ajob to raise even You have to
         spray the tree soon as it's dormant, and then you have to spray'era before
         they bloo, and after they bloom. It just don't pay to bother with 'em.
         
         LS:   You never used to have to spray?
         
         AC:  No, we never had anything to bother,
         
         LS:  Did you ever have insects attack you gardens at all?
         
         AC:  No, not in the early days, no. I know if they do yet or not, down
         there, do they?
         
         LS:   Oh, they have some troubles, yep.
         
         AC:  Do they?
         
         LS: Oh yeah.
         
         AC:  Well, we didn't have no trouble this summer with them things botherin'our
         garden. No potato bugs, none. When Father was raisin'a gardetithere all
         he had to do was just hoe keep the dirt lose around the plants, y'know,
         And he had good gardens-everything. We'd have turnips, rutabagas. Had that
         old cellar just full of stuff when the winter come. And they'd kill thaiown
         hos and four, five and six hogs got through the year. But they. . .
         themselves?
         
         LS : Would they smoke that
         
         AC:  Yes, oh yes. Yes, they'd smoke it. I don't know how we used to use so
         much grease. I've seen Mother have four or five gallon cans of lard and you
         know, by that next fall th.-'d all be gone, quite a lot of lard. I don't
         know, they used so much grease. Now we don't use thrt. I don't know how we
         did use so much. Of course when you had men to cook for you had to lots
         of pies and doughnuts iti stuff like that.
         
         LS:  , had a lot of kids too. yes, nine of us.
         That helps the grease go. Yes, nine of us. We we£n't all there at home at once though,
         when tte youngest one, when Merle was a baby, you know Merle, don't ya?
         
         LS:   Um hum.
         
         AC:  When he was a baby, why Willie and I were gone, we were married and gone,
         y'see. We weren't all home at once. But Ace, he got I was married
         three or four years befoehe was. He just didn't care to get married.
         
         L3: What is that story again about Viola being called "Dogwalk?"
         
         AC:  Well, yeah, they us Pdon't know, we didn't haVe any walks or anything,
         they laid planks down. And the dogs of course would always walk on the planks
         instead of the mud. So they called it "Dogwalk." (Chuckles^ 'cause the dogs
         walked on the planks ,ike the people aid, they called it "Dogwalk." And then
         it got changed to Viola. Now there wasn't much to it, I'll tell you,in them
         days.
         
         LS:   Was that ifore much?
         
         AC:  We didn't buy much there, no. No the people in the timber would cut wood
         and bring out there, trade wood for groceries to See they got their
         mail there and they'd bring out a load of wood and get their groceries and
         bring their groceries back with them. I don't krfw if they'd get very much for
         their wood or not, but thats the way they lived. They didn't live very good.
         And they couldn't rafee a very good garden in the timber, you know, too much
         turpentinejstuff in the soil in the timber, under the trees. They couldn't
         raise too much garde^I'don't know how th~ people p in the timber did live.
         My father used to sell hay, he'd never get no thin for it. They'd come out
         here, them poor old horses, just skin and bones, y'know. He said,"Oh
         they need it, they gotta live someway. They got to get along some
         way. They'd come down and Father'd load em up with a load of hay, He said,
         "I'll never see nothin for that hay. I know I won't. But maybe it'll help
         'em out some."
         
         LS: Your place didn't have that much timber on it then?
         
         AC; Ho timber.
         
         LS:   None.
         
         AC:  I don't think there's any timber we* of Viola, no, not that uh huh.
         
         LS: Well, there isn't now hardly.
         
         AC:  No, there wasn't any then. No, just about like it is .
         
         V : Great big hills.
         
         LS: Would you go into Moscow or Palouse very much? maybe
         
         AC:  Oh, yes,I think we'd average pretty near once, a week.
         We got out mail from Palouse and we'd get it twice a week. They'd put the
         mailboxes over on the- so we'd come iron school. And we'd get the paper twice
         a week. I don't remember, I don't think we got the mail but twice a week
         either then. Then it got so you could get your mail every day, put the
         mailboxes up. When we'd go to schol, you know, they'd put the mailboxes,
         ftnd have the mail carrier come out from Palouse and we'd get our mail everyiay
         ... then. And we'd get the paper, Spokesman-Review, I think it was ,twice
         a week. Then it got so later though, Father got the daily paper. And 
         Saturdays they'd get on a pony and go over to the mailbox, it wa; a mile from
         home. I'd get the mail, I'd get the pape . My father had to have his paper
         at night.
         
         LS: Would he read it out loud to the kids at all?
         
         AC:  If there was somethin1 he wanted us to hear he would. But you d read
         it to yourself.(Chuckles). laughing, then he'd get up to the.
         table with that old lamp in front of him and he'd put his paper out there
         and read. And you can see him yet, can't you Velma? With his paper up there,
         readin'his paper or His Bible. He'd have his Bible out in front of him lots
         of times there. I never heard my father swear, never. He used to say
         That was his bad word.(Chuckles)., That was the baddest word he
         could say. And then Mr. George Hill,he's our neighbor, all he could say
         was daggone' he'd say. That's all he said. Yes, we used to have
         some good old times down there. But when we got olde , we had church in the
         school. And we'd go up to church at eleven o'clock,
         Sunday school at ten, church at eleven, and then maybe Christran Endeavor
         at five for the young people. That'd be the young people's meeting. Then
         we'd have church again at Same way in Viola they did too. They
         had church at and vlola both"
         
         LS:   What was the Christian Endeavor?
         
         AC: Well, it was just a young people's meeting. Youlnow, they'd get up, the young
         people instead of te minister, the young people took over. And they'd get
         up and talk about different topics.
         
         LS: Would just young people be the e or would there be. . .?
         
         AC:  Well, one or two, but mostly young people, just the young people. And thy'd
         read the Scripture and then they'd talk about it, y'know. We'd have somebody
         there, nearly always, to explain it to us. They'd be an older person, y'know.
         And they'd explain this to us. That's what Endeavors were. We'd have that for
         an hour and then we'd have a church. Yes, we had one man, Emmett, he
         was a ministe , and boy was he a good one. That old church would just be
         packed. And go through the mud to get there . There was twenty
         five of us baptised in that ice, a thich ice off and put it out of the way so they
         could baptise us.
         And that minister stood in the water and baptised twenty-five of us.
         My mother had a quilt and when I was baptised she had a quilt she put around
         me,we had to drive quite a little ways in the hack to get to a neighbor's
         place where they could let us come in and change ou clothes before we could
         go home. It never hurt us. We neve cold. Oh, we got cold, yeah, but
         I mean we neve got no colds or aching. That water was icy cold But that
         poor old preacher he stood there and^faptised all of us. He wasn't avery
         big man either. Some of them boys he baptised was bigger than he was, taller.
         But he put'em under, which was cold. And then later on he baptised a lot
         more, and the water was better then. Charlie Hill was baptised"nine of my
         brothers. I guess both of my brothers was baptised then. Awhole lot of
         people; they'd come from all around. We had a good church there then.
         
         LS:   Was this still at the Viola schoolhouse or was this at the
         
         AC:  That was Four Mile School.
         
         LS: mean the Four Mile;
         
         AC:  Um hum, Fou' Mile School, uh huh.
         
         LS:   Was he a really strongly religious man that he. . .?
         
         AC:  Oh yes, he was. He didn't have anything, just him and his wife. Well, the
         farmers kept him in vegetables. And they'd give him a little money on
         Sunday , you know, take up collection. And then a Lot of em'd give him meat,
         you know, everybody had their own meat. And they'd give this minister, with
         just him and^wife it wouldn't take much. And they'd  him alittle collection
         on Sunday and he got along pretty good. I remember Mother he lived in
         Palouse City-I know Mother and Mrs. Poe, that's a neighbor, they took a
         hack, we had a light wagon, we called it a hack, and they took him a whole
         hack full of vegetables and so on. And they put »em in their cellar for the
         winter. So they got along pretty good.
         
         LS:  Did he do other things besides preach on Sunday? Would he go around and
         help people out during the week?
         
         AC:  Yes, if they need it. Yeah, he'd do odd jobs, oh yes. He wasn't a very well
         man. He was kind of sickly like. And he wasn't too young a man either. Oh,
         he must have been up in his fifties. He was a good man. Oh yes, he'd go and
         anything he could so in the spring of the year or anytime, he'd go and help
         if he could. But liv,ng in town that way, it was^about ten miles from
         Palouse to our place, just with a team, y'know. We didn't have any way to get
         out4here. And when he was preachinhe stayed around with the members,
         just stayed out there with the people in the wintertime, you know, when
         everybody could come. Oh, they was comin from Kamiak and all around up there.
         That old schoolhouse'd just be full of em, but he got by doin this.
         
         LS:   Did you go to parties and did you have. . .?
         
         AC: Oh yes, oh yes, we had parties, us young folks. We'd all have parties.
         Have something to eat, y'know. We didn't dance much. But we'd have, oh I
         don't know we played games and different things like that. And then later
         on they got so they'd go to dances, but Father would never allow us to dance,
         no. I'll tell you, it got so rough and drinkin so much around there that
         Father said,'Ho, you can't go to dances. It's not fit."So we didn't. I never
         learned to dance. He wouldn't let the boys go either. And he wouldn't have
         the boys play cards either. They never did care  I don't know, I
         guess they got so old and didn't know how or what. I don't know, but Father
         wouldn't stand for it so we had to do the best we could. We neve thought
         anything about it though. birthday parties.
         
         LS:   How did they celebrate birthday parties? Would they make a cake for someone?
         
         AC:  Oh yes, oh yes. They'd have cake and then we'd make our own homemade ice cream.
         We'd all have to turn that old freezer, y'know. I don't know if you've ever
         sen one of them.
         
         LS:   Yep.
         
         AC: Home freezers, where you have to freeze it. Well, we'd all have to turn that
         till it got so hard you couldn't turn it anymore and then it was done. That
         was good ice cream though,We used to put the resl cream in it and eggs and
         fix it up real good and rich.
         
         LS: Did you have ice boxes, ice houses?
         
         AC:  No. we'had ice in an underground cellar. And then
         we put straw over top and that way it was covered, oh it'd be covered that
         deep with dirt, y'see, we'd have a frame, logs like to hold that up.
         And that'd all be covered an: we'd keep that there nearly all
         summer. But 1 don't know why they didn't put ice up down there, but they
         didn't. They'd have to go to t„on and get their ice to make their ice cream.
         Well, up there in Canada, when we was up there^as up in July, wed have a
         pulley, they pulled the water out of the well with a pulley, you know, the
         on the end and then the wheel?
         
         LS:   Yeah-
         
         AC:  Go over this little wheel and pull it up this way. Well, on r well was real
         deep, but you could go there in July, let your bucket down and you'd take
         somethin' and knock the ice off the side of the well,your bucket
         and then you Aid make your ice tea. That was in June and July is when
         their water plpes freeze up. Y'see it'd be nice and warm on top but the frost
         went down,y'see. It'd go down end freeze their pipes and it'd be »« on top
         and you wouldn't hardly believe it. But you see it'd gone down. And they put
         their apes down ten feet deep. Oh, yes that ground freezesup there. You couldnt
         get a bit of that ground up in the wintertime. Not even with you'd
         have to pick it like a rock, just solid. But you what anybody
         disd, they'd have to put'em in the cemetery in a little house there till
         spring to bury 'em. They couldn't dig a gra^e. One time Velma had ^^O there
         and that little house was just full of people, just stacked up. They never
         got to bury'em until the next spring. Of course it had deep, wide walls to keep
         it cocl in there, y'know, for the bodieo . And they wouldn't dig it till the
         ground thawed out next spring. No, that's terrible. When a body dies and
         you have to stick'em in an old house froze up till spring..I
         couldn't hardly stand thv-:hou|it of that. But didn't any of us die.
         
         LS: That's good.
         
         AC:  That was awful.
         
         LS: Did they have literaries in the time that you were pretty young?
         
         AC: Oh yes. We had a literary every Friday night. We'd have a program and
         then after we'd have something to eat and then they'd have a debate on
         something--men folks would debate.
         
         LS:   Was it men mainly that did that?
         
         AC:  Well, the kids. '. too, the older ones, the high school kids.They'd debate
         on different things. Now one they had-"Which is the most useful? The
         dish rag or the kitchen door?"(Chuckles). I don't remember which side won.
         
         LS: What kind of use would the kitchen door be?
         
         AC:  Oh, you'd have to go out and in, y'know.
         
         LS:   Oh.
         
         AC:  I guess you could get along without a dishrag but you couldn't get along
         without the kitchen door. Anything for fun, you know. Just some little fool
         topic like that, argue it. But it got so that one old man there, he would
         get mad. Oh he'd get mad. And he kinda spoiled the literaries when he'd get
         up there and talk. He'd get mad because they couldn't see everything like
         he did. He wanted to get some topic^like, oh like in politics or something
         like that. Well, that's no good. Nobody see politics alike and that'd kinda
         spoil it.
         
         LS:   People tried to sty away  issues that might get. . .
         
         AC: Yes, they'd get so they didn't. . .
         
         LS: Controversial issues.
         
         AC:  He'd get mad and pound the desk, he'd just come down on that old desk
         No, I don't think it was any good to. . .It was for fun, y'know, have a good time.
         
         LS:   Um hum.
         
         AC:  I remember Charlie, my brother, the one that's down there in the home
         now,  sang "Casey Jones" in Viola one night and boy, they like to've
         tore the house down that night. You've heard Casey Jones?
         
         LS:   Oh yeah.
         
         AC:  The first time they ever heard that. And .he had to sing it twice.
         Yes, they u%d to have good times.
         
         LS: Did they have a newspaper too that they read out of? I've heard some of those
         literary things they'd put together a little sheet of paper about what wa" goin
         on.
         
         AC:  No, they'd make up their own paper about things that happened around, but
         they didn't mention no names.
         
         LS:   Oh, oh. Ad I know my siste , she was so mad, there  one man there and he had
         a load
         of logs. And it wa- the breaking up .spring and on the bridge as bare
         and you know them horses couldn't hardly pull that across that bridge. And
         school was out and Maureen saw him. And he was a-whippin them horses, just
         a-beatin them because they couldn't pull that. You know that wood and the
         sleigh runners would stick. So she put it in. . .And she did mention his name too,
         she was mad. She says,- "He wants a team that don't neither eat nor drink
         and can pull a load on the bare ground or on a bridge without any snow."And
         he was mad, he said he didn't think about Reen puttin it in there. And he
         said,"I can whip whoever put that in there, and I can whip em good!" That's
         what he said. She said,"Jim Keeney wants a team but they don't eat nor drink
         and they can pull a load on the bare ground or on a bare bridge." She was
         so mad because he was beatiri them horses. Yes, they'd make up a lot of funny
         things about somebody, putting in there just fo- fun. They didn't mention no
         names'though. But Reen did that time. §he was mad at him, she didn't care.
         My father said, "You shouldn't have mentioned his name. She says, "I
         don't care, It will too because I want everybody to know what kind of a man
         he is, beat in the horses to dee£h."And I was just like her, we had a man come
         up from Colfax up to speak at a picnic. We used to have lots of picnics too.
         And this fellah, Father went and got him and he stayed at ourjplace that night.
         And he, laughin* about it, he said, "We rented a little pony, my wife and I,
         and we run that pony till it fell over dead." And I said,"I don't think that
         was very smart." My Father says,"Hey hey." I says,"I don't either." You know,
         I never did like that man after that. He sgre,"We just run that pony till it
         fell over dead." Now wasn't that mean? And I told him I didn't think it was
         very smart. And Father, "Hey, hey," he says. (Chuckles). I didn't car'-, I
         didn't like him. And then in the morning Mother, she'd gotjchicken ready to
         30 and walkin around there and I said, "Don't ever let 
         over and take a piece of chicken  If I'd a known that I'd a hit him over
         the fingers as he was cuttin'em up. I'd a hit him over the fingers with a
         butcher knife because he ju^t, I don't know. He was all right I guess I just
         took a dislike to him because he run that pony to death. Anybody that'd do
         that wasn't no gocd. He thought it was smart.
         
         LS:   What you say makes me remember some obout what you said last time about
         Wes Palmer and his horses.
         
         AC: Oh yes, he used to have what they call a stone boatst they'd take some
         pieces and put 'em together and nail some heavy timbers, and then they'd nail
         and then they'd put the tongue in em, y'know, they'd call em stone
         boats, they're all stone on, y'know, you put stone.
         Well, he'd get two wild horses, never been hitche' up and he'd put the harness
         on them and then he'd get on that thing and turn em loose. No fences, no
         nothing. And he'd let em. . .
         
         AC:  Yeah, when he got back home they were broke.And then he'd put em in the
         harness and use em on the farm. When he got em back from that trip they was
         broken, ready to go to work. And if they died he said he didn't care, 
         harness more. He was really a good man but he didn't care what
         they thought or what they said, it was all right with him.(chuckles). Yeah,
         he was a good man; he was just odd.
         
         LS: Yeah, he sounds a little different than most men.
         
         AC:  I could tell you more but I don't think I better.
         
         LS:   Well, he was justice of the peace right? For a while there?
         
         AC:  Oh yes, he was justice of the peace for a long time. He married my uncle and
         my aunt; they run off from home. My uncle was eighteen and the girl he married
         wasn't quite sixteen and they run off and got married. He married em.
         
         LS:   He wasn't supposed to, was he?
         
         AC: Yes, oh yes.
         
         LS:   Agirl didn't need permission from her parents? 
         
         AC:  No, she didn't need no permission. (Chuckles).. They were supposed to go to
         the dance and instead of going to the dance, well, they did go to the dance,
         but they went and got married first. That was Charlie's mother's sister. But
         they got along all right. They had kids and they all grew up together. The
         parents and the kids all grew up together.(Chuckles).Yeah, at the time I
         remember, Uncle Johnny got into trouble some way, and he come up to Father's
         Sunday morning. And Mother had a woman workin for her, and this fellah was
         comin to see this girl, and he had a team from the live y stable. And they
         was just a steppin and John seen him a-comin, he thought that was
         the sheriff. He jumped on a horse and he rode for the line over toward
         the other side of the fence. And Father said,"Now, if it's all right I'll
         wave my hat." And Father waved his hat and the more Father waved the hat
         the harde he'd run from-(Chuckles) Harder he'd go.
         Father said he couldn't make Uncle John understand at all, he'd just
         leave that on there ready to go, that old fellah. He was in Idaho, you see,
         couldn't get ahold of him in Idaho.This was the sheriff from Washington.
         
         LS:   What was he afraid of them getting him for?
         
         AC:  Well, he did something he shouldn't have. I don't know what it was now.
         Some little thing. I don't think it amounted to nothin, ne was scared. I
         don't know if he took some thing or somethin happened, I don't know.
         
         LS:   Was Wes Palmer supposed to enforce the law in Viola or did  try cases,
         did they have acourt?
         
         AC:  I think foe did, justice of the peace, I think he did, um hum. Oh, he was
         law abiding, a good citizen. But he was just a rough character in the. . .
         He was a good man though, everybody liked. But they'd all go to Wes Palmer,
         he'd help you out. Go and see old Wes. (Chuckles).
         
         LS:   Did he have a whole lot of ho-ses and cattle there?
         
         AC:  No, he had some, not too many, no. farms and he had his orchard
         and he had lots of pigs, had some cattle.
         
         LS: Did he have many children?
         
         AC:  Yes, I think he had five. One was Sidney Palmer. I think he wao about eighteen
         and wo king n the logs and a log rolled over him and killed him. 
         only boy, Sifley Palmer. I'd forgot' about that one, but it was in my mind
         then. It killed the only boy he had. He was about eighteen, nineteen or so.
         
         LS:   Did he take that hard?
         
         AC:  Yes,he did, yes. He had that Mrs.  when
         Jim was born.
         
         V : He was her father wasn't he?
         
         AC:  Yes. And then he had Sarah and Maybe it was only four children
         he had. Four or five, um hum. And , his brother, he had three. His brother
         didn't do much, he win kinda quiet. Lived back on the farm and he didn't have
         to do. But Wes he was out and a the time.
         
         LS:   Did you ever know Asher Palmer? Wes Palmer's father?
         
         AC:  Yes, I've seen him, um hum. Mother used to say,"I don't know, that old lady
         Palmer, that poor old man, ue's up in his nineties. And she'd say,"Asher, you
         must go out now and hoe in that garden. Them weeds is just about to take the
         garden, you'll hafe to go out and hoe." Mother thought that was terrible.
         That's the reason I remember his name was Asher. (Chuckles). Mother "He'd
         have to go out and hoe in the garden" andihow mean that was. Make that old
         man get out there.
         
         LS:   Did his wife tell him to do that?
         
         AC:  Yes, she wouldn't do it. She wouldn't go but she'd makehim go. Make an old
         man like him go out and hoe in the garden. Gosh, he might fall dwn. . .
         
         V : garden wouldn't they?
         
         AC:  He'd do like he did last summer. Go out there and fall down in the
         corn. (Chuckles).He got out here the other day and he fell down. He couldn't
         get up a: Jtep in the back. And he hollered and he hollered, Velma and I didn't
         hear him, neither one of us. The door was open too. He finally made it in the
         hou^e. He said,"Didn't you folks hear me callin?" And I said,"No, I couldn't
         hear you at all." He says,"Well, I liked to've never gotten in the house."
         I said,"Well, that's too bad, you should have stayed out there."
         V : I don't think he said a word because we didn't have the television on,
         we were just sitting here like we are now and the door was open. I don't
         think he did.
         
         AC:  And there isn't hny thing wrong with him. And old lady here, up here in
         the home she's a hundred and five and she got her first permanent.(Chuckles).
         And she can hear, she don't wear glasses, she can see good. Only when she
         reads she wears glasses. She don't get around very good. She can  and
         her mind is as clear as a bell. No, she's a hundred and five.
         
         LS:   Sounds good. Where did you meet your husband?
         
         AC:  Oh, we grew up together. We went to school together. Oh I don't know, he
         was arouir ever since I can remember. Yeah, we went to school together.
         
         LS:   Did you court for a long time or is he the main boy that you went out with
         anywhere?
         
         AC:  No Sot mad at h^m cause he wouldn't do it and I
         went with somebody else.(Chuck1es).
         
         LS:   What did you get mad with him about? Was it just some little thing?
         
         AC:  No, he went and took another girl to a party and I wanted to go and he
         left me at home. Took out another girl and that made me mad. I told him to
         kefp on going with her. That's all he did too, all winter. And I wouldn't
         go with him.(Chuckles). Would you, when they leave you at home when they
         know you wanted to go and go get somebody else? Wouldn't that make you mad?
         
         LS:   Yeah.
         
         AC: (Chuckles). Ch well, I guess everybody has their trouble some way or another,
         don't they?
         
         LS: How old were you when you got married?
         
         AC:  I was twenty.Twenty-two when was born.
         
         LS:   When you married, where did you love to?
         
         AC:  Oh, well, this is back of west farmers too, there was a man had some
         grain there and his boy died. And he couldn't handle all this grain after
         his boy died. This was back of west farmers. So we had to go back, we bought
         this out. And we weren't going r.o pt married until ,. And then when
         we got this wheat, my brother and we bought the wheat together, then we got
         married and moved up there in that house, and stayed the e that summer.
         Then we rented a pice over toward Moscow and we stayed over tnere for a year.
         And then what did we do? Oh, we'd come back to Viola and started work haulin'
         that timber for the railroad that went through from Spokane, that electric. . .
         
         LS: Oh inland, yeah.. And him and my brother hauled out the timbers for that
         trestle. It was there, it isn't the-e any more. That trestle was there.
         And oh Charlie worked on the railroad quite a lot. He had a big Camp there,
         at Viola there in back of Grey's. I think that they lived there. It
         seemed like.they lived there, the head men lived in Miller's house. That's
         where John Miller lived, knd one of the boys'wives died while he was there,
         with And he was workin on the railroad, puttin*that railroad through
         there then.
         
         LS:   They started workin on that railioad then a long time before they got it
         finished.
         
         AC:  Oh yes, um hum. That used to be nice. I wonder why they ever quit usin1 it.
         I don't know why they took the trestle out. Maybe it got so it wasn't safe
         or something I don't know. It was handy. In the wintertime, you know, we'd
         just walk up there to this little depot they had there and go to Moscow and
         back, and come back home. There was no place to put a horse or anything.
         We could walk from my father's house up there though a little bit. But it
         was handy and nice to have the railroad through there. And then they'd
         ship wheat and stuff, you know. They used to have the big elevators there.
         That was handy; I don't know why they quit using it. Maybe it wore out.
         
         LS:   When you got married did people give you things toes£t you up?
         
         AC:  No, they never give us nothin. We neveY had anything, only what we. .,
         We didn't hae anything hardly.
         
         V : No showers or anything like that.
         
         AC:  But I'll tell you, we had twenty-five dollars. And I'll tell you what
         we did, we bought a cookstove, wood stove, y'know, to burn wood in, a
         good little stove, a good sized stove. It didn't have any warmer on it, but
         it was just a stove. It had a little tank on the back to put water in and
         then it had a hearth. And then we bought kind of a davenport and four chairs
         for twenty-five dollars. Of course the davenport had been used.
         
         LS: The stove was new?
         
         AC:  Yeah, it was new and the chairs were new. One rocking chair, and for twenty-five
         dollars. I sold the stove for ten dollars when I sold it. It wa-s a good
         stove yet. I don't know why I sold it, but I did. Oh, I know, Mother had a
         Home Comfort and she decided it wasn't big enough so she told me I could have
         it, the Home Comfort. So I took her stove and I had mine to sell. And she 
         a bigger one. Yes, that seems like a long time ago though.
         
         LS:   It was (Chokies).
         
         AC:  Pretty near a century. (Qh, uckles).
         
         LS:   Did the Comber's hotel burn down?
         
         AC:  Yes, the hotel burned.
         
         LS:   How did that happen, do you know?
         
         AC:  I can't remember how. Someone lightin a cigarette in a bed or something.
         
         LS:   Oh yeah. We used to stay the e. Did many people stay there over night?
         
         AC:  Yes, there were people stayed there. They were nice people and they had
         a little store in there, notions, you know, in the^hotel. A lot of candy hearts
         and oh, little notions like that: candy and and like young people want.
         But Bowles had the groceries and everything across the street. Well, that
         hotel burned. It was a nice little hotel too, wasn't very big, but it was big
         enough for there.
         
         LS:   Oh, it was three stories or something.
         
         AC: Yeah, it was three stories, two or three stories, yeah.
         
         LS: Were there tent meetings in Viola then?
         
         AC:  Oh yes, I'll there was. The Methodists used to hold csrnp meetings
         there, the big tents. And boy would they shout. And then some of them old
         ladies,y'know, would get religion and would they shout. They were nice
         old people. And they'd hold that thing maybe two, three weeks at a time.
         And they'd camp there and have good meetings. Have meetings at night
         and then have meetings in the afternoon for those people that were camped
         there, y'know. But the farmers, I we used to go at night quite a lot.
         Not every night, we couldn't but we would go. And they had lots of nice
         meetings, nice singin.
         
         LS: Is that different from the Faith people? Do you remember when they came in?
         
         AC:  No, I don't know about them. No, these we e Methodists. They were true old
         Christian anyway. Yes,they used to have good meetings there. And I used to
         meetings,
         like to go and hear em. I thought it was funny to sit under a tent in camp
         
         LS:   How come they didn't meet in church?
         
         AC:  There wasn't one. It wasn't big enough. It wasn't no church, it was a schoolhouse.
         The schoolhouse wasn't very big.
         
         LS:   This was really early then.
         
         AC:  I went up to the schoolhouse one time- they used to have church dinners
         in theschoolhouse. I remember us kids were outside and the women after dinner
         they'd put the things away and they was sitting there talkin in the
         schoolhouse. And I'd come in and I'd seen a worn*n sittin' there and I looked
         at her. And I said,"Mather, who's that old squaw sittin'over there?" "Shh,"
         my mother said, "Come here,. You set down there and be still." And I said,
         "Who's that old squaw, I want to know." She said,"Set down and be still. That's
         M?". sister, sit down and behave yourself! Shut up." (Chuckles). No,
         I had to find out who she was. She looked like an Indian and I hated an Indian.
         See, they used to have Indians, when the folks come up there they had an
         Indian scare. They even had a fort built. They were afraid of the Indians and
         they had this fort where they could go get in there if the Indians
         ever did come but they was afraid they might. And they could all go to this
         fort.I was taught to be afraid of Indians. I wanted to know what she was doing
         there. I wasn't going to stay there if she 
         
         LS:   Did you see Indians very much?
         
         AC:  Yeah, they was peaceful though up theffc,,They didn't bother anybody. They
         used to go. . . I think up here over in there by
         Gangeville and around, wan't there and Indian reservation or used to be
         somethin?
         
         LS: Um hum.
         
         AC:  Well, they'd go from over to tnat reservation and back, You con Id
         see em goin along the road, y'know how they string outs^and dogs
         have a wagon and all the women was sittin' flat down in it. I used to be
         afraid to walk to Viola. Afraid I'd see an Ind1an (Chucftes). If I'd a
         seen one I think I'd a hid in the corner of the fence. They had a fence that
         and this way,
         went this way And I said,"Mother,if I see an Indian comin I'm goin to
         hide." "Yes," she said,"if you do they'll get ya." So then I stayed behind
         because I figured they get (Chuckles She said,"You just go right
         on by and don't you look at em. You just walk right by and they won't bother
         you." And they didn't. Well, I don't suppose I even seen any, if I had of,
         I guess I'd of died right then. (Chuckles) found some mail one time,
         somebody1d lost it off of their wagon. And we went and hid it in the corner
         of the fence nobody could find it. So we come home and we said,"We found
         it some mail, we hid it. Mother said,"What did you do with it?" "We hid it."
         She says,"You get that and you take it back to the post office right away,
         the morning when you go to school. That's somebody's mail and they
         want it. Were they letters?" "Oh. they was letters. We hid em."(Chuckles).
         We was lookin after that mail. We hid em in the corner, fence.
         She said,"You take them back to the post office." So we had to get em and
         get em back to the post office. Isn't it funny box-; a kid would want to do
         that?
         
         LS:   Yeah, be real helpful. (Chuckles).
         
         V: They protected em
         
         AC: We couldn't read, we didn't know whose they wasi We couldn't read, but
         we'd hide em in the fence.
         
         LS:   What made you and your husband decide to go to Caifda?
         
         AC:  Well, there wasn't no ..laces down here. Everything'd been taken down here.
         And my brother rent up to Canada and he found this land and you could take
         it to homestead. And thought it'd be nice for us to go up there. And
         then you could buy Hudson Bay land for I think it was a dollar and eighty
         cents an acre. You had to pay for that. So we took the homestead--a hundred
         and sixty acres. And then we bought a hundred and sixty acres of Hudson
         Bay land, belonged to the Hudson Bay, I guess. Well, I think that was a
         royalty from for the royalties for that a dollar and eighty
         cents an acre, that belonged to England, some way or other. I don't krfw but
         they said it belonged to the royalties, the roycl family in England.
         
         LS:   Down here all you could do was rent land, is that it?
         
         AC:  You could buy it, only it was too high, oh it was high. It was cheap then
         but look at itnow. Six and eight hundred dollars an acre. Who wants it at that
         price, isn't worth it. Then you have to pay such a big price gettin the
         mate-rial to work it.
         V If you could buy a farm now you could retire.
         
         AC:  No, my nephew bought a tractor; it was thirty thousand dollars. Well, I
         think I'd rather have the thirty thousand dollars, wouldn't you? But he
         had to, he had ths land, y'see. He's rentin about, I guess, fifteen or sixteen
         hundred acres of land and he had to have it. It's quite a tractor, it's got
         an air conditioner, it's got a radio (chuckres).
         
         LS: Well, going back to. . .When did you go up to Cata? Were you behind the
         move, did you want to do it too?
         
         AC:  Nom I didn't, I didi't want to go. And Charlie and my brother went on ahead
         of us with. . .They chartered a car, y'see, a railroad car and took our
         stuff up. And we rtayed here mntil they vent up and built the house first.
         They built our house first. Then my sister-in-law and I went up and took the
         children. Then they built house later. Well, we all stayed at our place
         and they built the house late, their house, a mile and a half from us.
         But they didn't stay long, they come back. We went up in '12 and come back
         in '37, come back to Pullman in '37. And we stayed there ten years and then
         moved up here and been here since.
         
         V: Her and my aunt went up on that train after the men got the house built—
         two kids with the whooping cough on the train. They had their nerve.
         
         LS:   Two of their kids had whooping cough?
         
         AC:  Mine.
         
         LS:   Yours?
         
         V: Yeah.
         
         AC:  All of mine had it rnd we hadn't left yet. They'd been exposed, they didn't
         have it yet, but they took it on the way. And we got to 
         probably stay over night. And the kids are coughin and coughin. He said,
         "Have your kids got the whooping cough?" Well, they took cold on the train
         or something, they were sure coughin." We couldn't go downstairs to eat or
         nothing. We had to have everything sent up to us. They were just talcing it
         then. We didn't allow em to go out amongst anybody, made 'em stay in their
         rooms. And we should have went on. That night that we thought we'd just stay
         over night in wouldn't be such a hard trip. And we had to
         stay till the next night at about ten o^clock the next night. And we could
         have went on,, but we didn't. But after the kids got to coughin so we wished
         we had a went on. But we told'em, "They must have caught cold on the train."
         I guess we did.  come out of it.
         Did you have it too?
         
         V: I think so.
         
         LS:   Was it hard up there, especially at first in Canada?
         
         AC:  Well, you couldn't buy anything hardly. You couldn't buy any fresh fruit
         or any fresh vegetables.. You couldn't Buy any clothing hardly.
         
         V: People send from mail order catalogues,y'know dollar, their
         yardage and their clothes and things they'd send. There was no use going to
         town much because there was only one little store there.
         
         AC:  There was Eaton's.
         
         V: Mother'd just send to the mail order house.
         
         AC:  And Simpson's. We And we made money thee and we spent it
         there too. I was there five years without a Every year you'd think
         now you was going to get it. Well the last year come up nice, oh it
         must have gotten a foot high, it looked real nice. Well, Don and Velma lived
         down in Alberta, it was about the foot of the mountain of the
         Rockies. And we went down there. They was going to have a jubilee of pome
         kind down there. And we went down to that. Huh?
         
         V: That's south 
         
         AC:  Yeah, by 
         
         V: By Waterton.
         
         AC:  And we went and we stayed three of four days. We went back and the hot winds
         had hit that wheat and it was just layin'over, well, just like. . .Well, just
         and here come the Russian histles right over.top of it. You couldn't
         tell there'd ever been any wheat sowed there.
         
         LS:   What came over the top of it?
         
         AC:  Russian thistles . The Russian thistles there. We'd never seen em
         before, they wasn't that bad.
         
         V: They don't have em here, do they?
         
         AC:  But I told him, "I'm done, Charlie, I'm not goin to stay here another time'.
         year, I'm going. come. Melvin was a young man
         and I know he and Gladys was goin'to get mar ied up there. And there just
         wasn't anything there for him. And we didn't have any feed for the stock,
         nothin. And we just had to shut off the stock, and we
         was gonna take down to British Columbia, down to where Velma was
         and we went and got a pasture and everything to take 'em down and .
         they passed a law that Saskatchewan couldn't bring their stock over
         into Alberta. So we couldn't over there.
         find we got rid of all of 'em then.Give 'em away and sold 'em the best
         we could.We thought well we're footloose now, we'll just come on down
         here.I'm glad we did. Cause up there you're not sure of a crop yet.
         
         LS:  You went five years in a row without a crop?
         
         AC:  Yes.Five years without a crop. I'll tell you. And there wasn't that
         much for stock to eat either. " - bunch grass, it wasn t bunch
         grass,it was kind of.short grass and it'd get hot and dry,it would
         dry up.And it was nothing hardly.They had sluices there.Little water
         it'd be green around that.Down in around there. We just got out of
         there. So we just left everything. Left two beds upstairs, curtains
         up in the windows,and linoleum on the floors. Of course, I give it
         all away.And then just walked out.Kind of hard to do, load the back
         of a truck and take out just out of the house what you , your truck,
         a pickup it was.And take just what it will hold Leave
         the rest there. I told the neighbors they could go in and get
         They did I guess.
         
         LS:  You sold the place when you left it?
         
         AC: Un huh. We mortgaged it for all we could get and let 'em keep it.They
         could have it.Then after we done that, they was satisfied. Then we come
         down here, we was gonna garnishee Charlie's wages down here because
         they didn't get crops on that land.Well we got ahold of a lawyer
         and he wrote 'em a letter. He said,"They'11 not...
         
         AC:  From the Dakota line in Saskatchewan. And it's awful dry there.
         Now you take and up in there. They don't even have water.
         They just don't have water. We went back up, went up to our daughter's
         and we had to go through the southern part of Alberta. Well, we was
         going to get a motel and there was no motels and nothing and
         its getting dark. 
         
         LS:  How many ended up being in that cabin?
         
         AC:  I guess there was about 18 of us.And three burner stove to cook on.
         And cold outside. Oh brother,it was cold! I don't know how we
         ever got our clothes dry. But we lived through some way. I don't know.
         And we had some pigs that weighed about 175 pounds.Had to take one of
         them about every two weeks.Take a pig every two weeks.For meat for
         that bunch.And everything else. I don't know why they come to our
         place. We didn't know 'em. They come right there and sit down on
         us. And no money, no place to go.. .do but keep 'em,
         
         LS:  Kow did you sleep that many people?
         
         AC:  I let Oliver and his wife and baby have the bedroom. One bedroom.
         And then Skinner and his wife and kids slept on a davenport x^e had
         in the living room. Then the boys, the two Skinner boys^and my brother
         and his boy, our bed set in the middle of the room, just like this,
         there's no partition upstairs, just floor. And our bed set in the
         middle and then we put curtains around it and the girls slept on
         the other side of the bed.(chuckles) I don't know how we ever got...
         
         LS:  In the dead of winter there wasn't much place to go except stay
         in the house and get mad at each other.
         
         AC:  Oh yeah we did go. We went up there when it was 30 below zero even.
         We wouldn't stay home. We'd get up, we'd be there home, and somebody
         come by,"Come on, let's go to the neighbors." and the
         men would play cards and we'd say maybe one-two o'clock in the
         morning we'd get home. Everything froze up at home. The fire went
         out.Had water,the dipper in the bucket.If you filled your water
         bucket, you couldn't get it up til...I'd say a' everytime I'd
         go out,I'm not going out again I'm going to stay home, I'm going to
         keep this house warm.Take a long time to get warm once it got cold.
         You'd like to never get it warmed up. And beds, they'd be so cold they'd
         -A just like water, damp.But next time somebody come up,"Here we go."
         (laughs) And us women never,all through the summer we had Ladies' Aid.
         Once a month we'd all get together. Oh yeah, they're nice people up
         there.They're really nice. Oh yeah, we had a good time.As far as that's
         concerned.We none of us had anything.(joining in with another conversation
         going on in the room)And then sometimes it was so hazy you couldn't hardly
         tell where you was going. People freeze to death up there, you know.
         But it'd even freeze the horses ears off.Ker husband had a pony, I
         don't know how, but it froze it's ears off up there.No.lt was a little
         colt that froze the ears off.
         
         LS:  Did they just fall off?
         
         AC:  Yes, come clear off.
         (Unidentified voice) Wasn't ours.We never had no little colt.
         
         AC:  Well didn't Toots have a colt? That froze it's ears?Yes he did.You
         remember that?She did, she had it outside and it froze its ears off.
         Oh there was an old man,oh it was cold and thirty below zero and his
         wife was looking for a baby. They lived down south and they had
         about twelve miles to go or fourteen with a team. In the wintertime
         we went across this big lake, it froze over and it was near. She got
         right in the middle of this big lake and she had her baby in the
         sleigh. It was cold.That old sleigh and old dirty comforts and
         everything. And he run his team the rest of the way into town.
         And they got 'em in there and they came out and got her. I don't know
         how they got her and the baby.But they did some way, in the hospital.
         
         LS:  She got left out on the lake?
         
         AC:  No she was in the sleigh.They was going into the hospital, see, and
         she had her baby before she got in there right in the sleigh.(laughs)
         Babies, they think they got to be so clean. Well they was dirty people
         anyway and an old dirty bedthings in that old sleigh. Said she was
         doing fine.Everything's alright."Well why didn't they go in before?
         Why did they wait so long?"Ernie says,"Next time she's going into
         town. She's not going to fool me like that anymore."(Laughs)But they
         said the baby done fine.They was funny people. I know some of our
         women, like I told you, we out and quilt. One of 'em would
         come down there and quilt. She'd made two tops, pieced 'em and she
         took his old coats, now mind you, the collars and the cuffs, and put
         in that quilt, for them to quilt it over. They said they didn't care.
         I bet some of the stitches was that long. They just go over. Well they
         said they quilted and quilted and Come|time. to eat. She made some tea.
         She couldn't cook.She just didn't really know. And it was green tea
         and this Earl Finch, he was a regular devil. He'd get these women
         around the table andAwatch and they couldn't hardly drink this tea,
         they couldn't hardly stand it.It wasn't even hot. He'd say,"Well I
         think she wants some more tea."Well Mrs. Green, one of the women,
         she said,"If you don't shut up!" And he'd laugh. He'd say,"I think
         Mrs. Green's out of tea." "Shutup!" And then she said they went back
         to quilting and someway or other they got her to sing. She couldn't
         carry a tune to save her life.And Ernie got her to sing some songs
         for 'em and she said, they got so tickled, said, they'd never gotten
         A in their lives.(laughs)They'd go to quilt there'd be a
         great big collar, you know a And they said
         fhey couldn't quilt around that.She's trying to sing and they got
         tickled.Oh,she said,"That Earl Finch,I'd kill him."(laughs)
         
         LS:  Did they quilt more up there than they did down here?
         
         AC:  Oh yes. All winter long we'd quilt up there.That's how we spent our
         wintertime. We had a good time.We'd go maybe twice a week.quilt quilts.
         And we'd go into eat.We said,"You men don't need to eat. The women are
         doing the work, they're going to eat first."We'd go back and find our
         scissors all sewed down to the quilts.The minute we'd forget and
         leave our scissors, the men would all take our needles and sew our
         scissors down to the quilt.Oh yeah, one old man come to our place one
         time, he livedAsouth of us and he come by and it was suppertime. We
         had wallpaper then. We had just wallpapered the living room and just
         got finished.And Lita was home so they could do the chores. And this
         neighbor come by, he was Ukrainian. He said,"You go to Clark's for
         supper?" Yeah."No we stay home for supper.""No we go to Clark's for
         supper."We got over there and they was just washing up the supper
         dishes.They'd canned chickens and she had had a party there to help
         can these chickens, the women come in. And I knew. So the'were just
         washing up the dishes. Well Mrs. Clark said,"Have you been to supper?"
         I said, oh yes, yes. And he thought he was going to get some chicken,
         see.So come midnight and out a lunch and I said this
         tastes pretty good, don't it Mr.Gidluc, and he said,"Yeah we had no
         supper."And she said,"Didn't you have your supper?"He said no. I said
         next time get your supper before you leave home.It ain't right to go
         right from home to somebody else's place and eat supper. That's no
         good."Well I was hungry."I said well let 'em get your supper before
         you leave next time.(laughs)He said,"You're no good." I said I know.
         I used to go out to supper with him. Go into town on Saturday
         night. He wouldn't go to supper. His wife wouldn't go with him.And he
         say,"You go to supper with me?"Sure I'll go to supper with you."Okay'.'
         One night  in and he said,"You go to the show with me?" Sure, I'll go to
         the show with you.And was as drunk as the devil and I didn't know it.
         I never know a drunk man. As long as he can walk. And we got in there
         and the seats, they sat this way. And here was the alley way. I had
         a neighbor sitting over here and we walked over here and sit down and
         this Donahue, he gets up and he looks and I said sit down! He keep
         looking. Well the show started and you know how they kind of have
         a dream and a kind of a mist.Ke says,"They kick 'em up dust, don't they?"
         About that time Velma and Charlie and them walked in.They sit down in
         front of us.(laughs) I'd go to supper with him and I'd go to the
         show with him.After we got, not from home, but after we got into town.
         See, we had a truck.And the neighbors would come up, they'd all get
         in our truck. Charlie charged 'em ten cents a piece to pay for the
         gas. And there wouldn't be standing room in that truck.He had seats,
         some of 'em could sit down.Some of ' em had egg box and they could
         set down on them.Crates of eggs, you know. Police says,"I'11 tell you
         Charlie, it's alright for you to come in but you better"' be quiet
         or we'll not let you bring 'em in any more."So we had to be quiet.
         Some of 'em get pretty noisy. In the back.Some of them young folks.
         EverySaturday night, we wouldn't get home til twelve o'clock. 'Cause
         they'd want to go to the show and it wouldn't get out til eleven and
         Cnarlie says, I'll tell you nox^, when you leave. This truck leaves
         at eleven thirty. You get out of the shox at eleven. Eleven thirty
         we go for home.At a certain time.If you're here alright, if you're not
         alright."We left some of 'em in town one night. One old man, he never
         come back at all. He left and he walked out the next day, ten miles.
         You couldn't wait for 'em. They'd put you out til maybe two, three
         o'clock in the morning.YOu never know what they're doing. Where they
         are, young folks. Most of 'em was there right on time.
         
         LS:  Did they have shows down here before you left for Canada?
         
         AC:  Shows?
         
         LS:  There wouldn't have been any here yet.
         
         AC:  I ' remember. See, that was in 1912. 1912 we went up there.
         (unidentified voice) think they had picture shows here, did they?
         
         AC:  Yes they did too, but they didn't have any speakers. You had to read
         it. YOu had to read everything.I remember they did. But they wasn't
         good show cause they didn't have any speaker.
         
         LS:  Was that a pretty big thing?
         
         AC:  Yeah. Was that ever a big thing when television,radio first. Up there
         was radio, radio, radio all over town, put up bills all around.radio.
         Then when the television come in, boy, that/was something. That is
         something! Stop and think about it. Come right out of the air right
         into your room.Yes. I wonder what they'll have in the next fifty years
         
         (Unidentified voice)At first they got the radio they had those ear.first.That
         was rough cause only two...
         
         LS:  Could listen at once.
         
         V: And finally they put a speaker on it.
         
         LS:  Did they have those old phonographs?
         
         AC:  Oh yes. Victrolas. Them great big horns was they'd be long like this
         with a big bell on the end. And they fastened up here on a thing.
         And you'd have to get right up close to listen to em. Remember,
         you carried the bell up there.
         
         UV: Yes I bang-ed everybody's feet as long as I went. Riding on the
         aslie on the train.  bell.
         
         AC:  They give us a little phonograph. She had to carry that old bell.
         
         UV: Everybody had skinned shins. Shilrtii skinned .
         
         AC:  On Christmas we'd come ddn here and Father said,"Bow, I'll tell you
         folks,let's just all have a dinner together and let's not have any
         presents or anything." "All right," we agreed. Well, the boys sneaked off
         and they went and got Father- and Mother a nice phonograph, y'know. One of
         these,well, it was in a cabiift, y'know set up and the phonograph was kinda
         squa-e like that. And Mother had an old fashioned, when the house was built
         and it had a window, that went out like that this way,. We set the tree here
         and they put the phonograph in behind the tree but Father never seen it.
         He didn't know it. They didn't fool Mother. She had her eyes open and she
         said, "They never did that Christmas tree off before with a
         team, and they're goin up toward  Up to that station, y'see, that
         iniand train. They diddn't fool her. Of course she was watchin. But anyway it
         was settin in there aH somebody sneaked in there behind that Christmas tree
         and put one of these disc records, y'know, about so big around and long. And
         they're blue. Now Father said,"Listen, we wasjsupposed to buy any presents."
         "Nobody said we wouldn't.  said we would and we didn't say anything ."
         at you know he got so much of that. Oh, he wouldn't hardly let the kids look
         at it, afraid they'd get a scratch on it or something It was nice; it was
         really nice in its day. (Chuckles). It was, but they didn't fool Mother un uh
         She had her eyes open, watchin. She never did drag " off before
         with a team to^o clear up to the station." Well he thought that was
         mighty nice, but he It cost too much, can't afford it." But we all went
         in together and bought it, y'know. Didn't cost any of us  much. I forget
         what it cost--around seventy-five or eighty dollars, somethin' like that.
         And he thought that was too much for us to put out. I guess that burned up
         when the house burnt
         
         LS: Hey there was somthin else I wanted to ask you about. Last time you mentioned
         about, was it Alice Gritman who stayed at your house once and got
         smallpox?
         
         AC: Alice
         
         LS: Alice was it?
         
         AC: Um hum. She was from Gritman's hospital.
         
         LS:   Ohh.
         
         AC:  She waited on Gritman when he had the smal pox. And then she went home and
         and her folks wouldn't let her stay there so =he come down to Of folks, just before
         Merle was born. And we didn't know it, she took sick there. Well, they got
         wanted to the doctor out and he said it was smallpox. Well, Mother, put her in a--what
         did they call them homes they vsed to have? Oh you know, when they have their
         diseases they put em in there, in them houses. Father said,"No, better not
         move her." What'd they do? We had the old house and Father went down and they
         fixed that all up and cleaned it all out and moved Mother and my l:'.ttle aster
         down there and Mother cooked for the boys. They had to sleep out in the
         smokehouse. And we were goin to have a play ther in Viola, and this girl
         trfr. was stayin at our place, she was goin to stay overnight with me. And
         Charlie he was always up there snoopin around. We weren't married. Well, it
         caught them and they were all quarantined, there at the house. And you know 
         to have
         Mother had to in that old house and Alice, and we haa a nurse come
         out and take care of Alice. And heriname was Edith was the one that stryed,
         and the doctor kind of come out to see Al|£e . But it wasn't Alice he come to
         see, it was Edith.(Chuckles). Settin'on the woodbox one Mother had a
         cookstove and a the Doc was settin on the woodbox and she was sittin
         in the chair and I was sittin over lookin out the window.
         So it got dark and I said,"I think I better light the lamp." "Oh, no,
         I'll light it. I'll light it," he said. And he jumped up and lit the lamp,.
         (Chuckles). But we all vaccinated, all of us. But then Alice got so she could
         get up and we put her in the smokehouse and we had to fumigate that
         house. Oh, we used formald and we even had to take the books and open
         *em up, put em over the line. We had great big, oh I don't know, jars or
         somethin they put this stuff in  it in the rooms. Oh, strong! Uh!
         You stay in that room; you couln't have stayed in the house. 
         was just like--oh it'd just make your eyes burn, y'know. And we'd burn that
         early in the morning in there for about two hours and then we'd
         up all the door and windows and get out until the. . .And then we went in
         after it was all fumigated and washed all the - in the bedroom and
         lleaned everything all up.Of course, she was sick, y'know. Well, Men-le didn't
         come though, until after everything was all settled. He was due but he didn't
         come.(Chuckles). So Alice said, "Want me to come out of the smokehouse ad
         talk to him?" And that was a dangerous time. The doctor says,"When they're
         scalin off, that's a dangerous time. Not fever, you wasn't even exposed.
         It's when they scale off." She took great big scabs off of her arms. They
         say them things they lay out on the ground for years and years and then if they
         get wet they're just as bad as ever, they're dafigerous* And she
         burned eve-ything up. She was careful; she wasn't bad. But they all laughed
         at me for  so much tater soup and takin it out to Alice. She'd holler
         out,"I need some more tater soup!" (Chuck1es). I'd have to take her out some
         rotato soup and set it dwun and tfren run to get away from there. I felt
         sorry for her o it there alone but couldn't help it. And then when she came
         back--Merle was a baby then--and about two or three weeks old. She come
         back. Mother wouldn't let her come in the house. I felt like kickin Mother,
         it was cold outside and she'd come, they was goin to get a load of hay and
         she v/as goin to stay at our place while the boys went and got the h-y. And
         Mother says,"No, you don't, you just get out of here." And she walked
         back up to the cemetery ...
         
         V: She' d done enough for her.
         
         AC: And stayed in the cemetery--cold. Till they come along with a load of hay.
         Well, Mother said,"I don't carp, ghe put me out and it's just my turn to
         put he- out. I wasn't goin to have her in here. She knew she was going to
         have that. Why did the doctor let her come out there?"
         
         LS:   I don't see why she couldn't stay at home?
         
         AC:  They wouldn't let her. Her .dad wouldn't let her, no.
         
         LS: That's what's funny to me.
         
         AC: She said Mrs. Gritman put on a heavy veil and went to Portland, down there
         to the hospital. I guess maybe they had someplace like that around. She
         said she put on a heavy veil and she really had the smallpox when she left.
         But she put this veil on and you couldn't see her face and she went. I
         don't know why they didn't keep Alice there in the hospital. But they didn't,
         thatfs what made Mother mad. She told Doc Gritman about it. He says,"I didn't
         know she went." He was still sick, y'see. He s^s,"I didn't know she ent
         out there." He wasn't a bad old doctor.
         
         LS:   What doctor would you have. . .Would he come out, the doctor out the^e?
         
         AC:  Oh, yes. They don't hardly come out any more though. No, you can't hardly
         get a doctor to come out. I called old Doc j , he's our doctor down here
         at. And Charlie, was just throwin up and throwin up and throwin up
         and I couldn't get him to stop. And then he'd the other way too, all day.
         So I called Doc, it «as gettin flark. (Break)
         Yes, I had it.
         
         LS: You had T. B.? Oh, typhoid?
         
         AC: No, typhoid fever. I wa^ in bed thirty-six days with typhoid fever
         when the second child was born, wa" a baby. She was about a year old.
         And I had typhoid they didn't know to handle it therwfhey
         do now. And then you hardly ever hea of it anymore, do you? No. And
         T. B., they hactule that pretty good now.
         
         LS: What happened when you got typhoid? How does that affect you?.
         
         AC: Well, itjmade me sick and just about took me away. I was just skin and
         bones when I got up and I wasn't too heavy when I took it. But I couldn't
         eat; they wouldn't give me no thin'to eat. Trey'd even take buttermilk and
         strain it and give me the whey. That's all I could have. No--nothing to eat
         then. They didn't feed you anything then.
         
         LS:   All you'd eat was the whey?
         
         AC:  Just the whey. That's all I cor.ld off of the buttermilk. It was
         no thin strain it through a cloth. I don't know, I pulled through
         somehow. You couldn't have milk, you couldn't have anything. It was just
         box^el trouble, y'know, in you bowels. And I remember I was sittin up and
         she said, I think her sister was the e. And she said," We' going up to
         see Mrs. Poe. She lived up over there. She said, "You won't do nothin1 to hurt
         yourself while I'm gome? "No, no. I woldn't do that." She wasn't gone outside
         of the gate when I started bakin a cake. And I thought to myself,"You better
         bake you one in that pie pan because she'll see it if you cut it." So
         I baked myself--eat the whole thing. It neve- hurt me a bit. I was up then,
         y'know. It could have made me sick but it. didn't. "No, I didn't do nothin."
         She said, "Did ,?ou eat any of that had for supper?" I knew
         bettern tmn to cut it because she knew I. . . "No, I didn't." "Okay."
         (Chuckles). If she'd knovm that she'd a had a fit. But she didn't know
         later. After I seen it didn't hurt me name I told her. She said," I
         had an idea you'd do somethin. I knex^ you would."  .1 was just kyin
         there for thirty-six days.
         
         LS:  Is that how it was? You had to lay there for thirty-six days?
         
         AC: Yeah,afor thty-six days. And then when I got up my fever was a hundred
         and two, when I got up. My aunt come up and she says," If you don't get
         out of that bed yourr going to lay there and die. Get out of therel"
         So I got Father to get me up, one morning he got me up, took me out in the
         kithen. And he says,"Hey, you kids upstairs, come down. We've got company this
         morning" And they all come down to see who was there and here was me out
         in the rocking-chair with a quilt over my chair like that. (Chuckles) ,But my fever
         was a hundred and two. I was gonna get up and go. out , only I got up and
         fell down on the floor and crawled back to bed. I was so weak I couldn't
         walk. I had to learn to push a chair and walk. In bed, y'know, you think
         you can do somethin but you can't. When I put my weight on my feet down I
         went right on the floor.  wa three, cause she'd eat dinner
         as quick as she could and the dining room was here and here a; the living
         room and then the bedroom was back there. And here was the dining room with
         just a partition between the dining room and the bedroom there, in that
         corner. Well, thed give me a stick to pound on the wall. I couldn't make
         'em hear, I couldn't. But I could pound on the wall. She looks up and shdcomes
         in the bedroom, she pushed a chair up to tie dresser and then they ised to
         give yxu a powder in little papers. And she wanted a paper for something.
         And she'd been doin'that and they didn't know it. I know Father'd give me a
         dose of that medicine and Itfjust feel like I was gonna go - clear under.
         He said, "I can't understand it; that medicine makin you so sick. "So part of
         that, she wanted a paper and she'd put it all in one dose, see, which 
         be two doses, and then she'd take the paper. 3n = Ipau-mred on the wall and
         Father come in there and boy she got a spankin. .b^-mtr^e said,"That could
         have killed you."l said,"Yes, that's the reason I've been so sick afte takin
         them powders She got a good
         lickin. She d get a lickin and she'd Father.(Chuckles).He told her
         she'd get a lickin and she would. She'd yey Grandpa keep up with
         me and she'd be rry behind him. (Chuckles).
         
         V: Evevytime I'd cuss him he'd lick me and I'd cuss him every day.
         
         AC: She got lickin a day, And then when I was in bed with a fever she .
         
         V: I'd do it and I knew I'd get a lickin.
         
         AC:  When I was in bed with a fever she took note. Right around the house xvas
         some weeds, Father's house. She took she was gonna burn them and
         she had about five or six matches struck but the weeds was green and they
         wouldn't burn or else she'd have burned the house up.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13413</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Crocker</previous>
      <next>Crow_Charles</next>
      <disp_name>Crow_Ada</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
