<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">11/3/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Mary Edwards, 1976-11-03, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:44:36</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Edwards, Mary</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker</occupation>
      <birthyear>1897</birthyear>
      <residence>Grey Eagle District, Genesee</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Nevada and Nebraska (1890's)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#friendship"&gt;friendship&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cards"&gt;cards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homemakers"&gt;homemakers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#water"&gt;water&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Lapwai"&gt;Lapwai&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13432</file_name>
      <mp3>13433.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13433.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Walking to school. Bathing and washing with a tub</title>
            <synopsis>Walking to school. Bathing and washing with a tub</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>240</time>
            <title>She had a protective family; Dances in Genesee</title>
            <synopsis>Nothing had was ever said about neighbors in
               country, so she thought everyone was perfect.
               No punishments from family. Being short upset
               her. Older brother always accompanied her on
               dates, protecting her without her realizing
               it; he refused to let her go out with one boy.
               Dances in Genesee. Brother protected her from
               dancing with a good dancer who'd been drinking.
               Dancing with everyone there. No lack of
               obedience then and now.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Visiting Mrs. Wahl and description of her home</title>
            <synopsis>Visiting Mrs. Wahl was a great pleasure for
               her. Mrs. Wahl kept an immaculate home, and
               taught her to play the piano. Caring for
               her crippled child. She fed the hired men on
               the porch She had a dressmaker come to make
               clothes. Grandmother used a horn to hear.
               Friendship with Mrs. Wahl.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Socializing in the Genesee neighborhood with dances and card games</title>
            <synopsis>Socializing in the neighborhood - dances at
               her family home. Youngsters didn't go to
               dances in town. Dances were a weekly affair.
               Genesee social groups were for card playing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Father homesteaded on Indian reservation; was well liked</title>
            <synopsis>Father homesteaded on the reservation. Indians
               liked him, calling him "Chief Robert"; for a
               while he kept a horse saddled.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2580</time>
            <title>Indian-White family; description of people and the household in Genesee; her friends
               drank and had little ambition
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>An Indian-white family. The Indian mother sat
               like an Indian on the porch and never learned
               housekeeping. Daughter became a skilled
               homemaker and married a white man. She almost
               sent her daughter away to high school, but a
               friend in Genesee offered to keep her.
               Acceptance of the family. The daughter probably
               didn't go to country dances. Women were addressed
               formally. Indian presence around Genesee Her
               attitudes towards Indians - she saw the
               daughter as a white. Her Indian friends from
               Lapwai drank. One complained that Indians
               couldn't save their money, having little
               ambition. Surprise at meeting her friend's
               mother, a traditional Indian; her reluctance
               to visit her friend in Lapwai.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Grandfather run out of harness shop in Salt Lake City by Mormons; homesteaders came
               to Genesee
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Grandfather run out of harness shop in Salt
               Lake City by Mormons. Father and his brother
               came to Genesee from Walla Walla and homesteaded
               Mother's family from Nebraska.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3900</time>
            <title>Self-sufficiency on the farm; father wasn't a good farmer, mother worked entirely
               in the home
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Self sufficiency on the farm. Pits for storing
               food. Father started farming as homesteader
               and never worked out. His successful farming.
               Building a home on his newer land. Mother's
               work was entirely taking care of the home;
               she never worked outside. People hung their
               clothes behind the door, and had no closet.
               Her family kept clean. Father worked in the
               garden and the older boys did much farm work.
               Mother had no leisure time. She didn't have
               a lot of work at home - milking cows. A
               horse that was supposed to be dangerous.
               Parents seemed to get along well.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Pvosenstein family mixed somewhat, less than most</title>
            <synopsis>Pvosenstein family - they seemed to mix somewhat
               less than most.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5340</time>
            <title>Family moved into Genesee to put children in school</title>
            <synopsis>Family moved into Genesee to put children in
               school. (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Son took over farmhouse when father retired and moved into town and daughter married</title>
            <synopsis>Son took over farm house when they moved into
               town, and father was mostly retired. When
               they moved into town most people still had
               hand pumps for water. Town gossip. No more
               spending in town than country. Usefulness of
               conveniences. She didn't work, but got married
               right after high school. Her parents wouldn't
               believe society today. People didn't expect
               much and got along with what they had. Honesty
               of people then.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Family and neighbors in childhood. An Indian-white family. Dances Life on the farm
         and in Genesee. 11-3-76 1.7 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         Sam Schrager: Well, in those days when you were a kid there, did you get into
         town much?
         
         Mary Edwards: No. You didn't go any place. If you went any place you went a
         horseback—you walked and if the family, that is, if, well,
         say my mother and dad, some of the kids were going, you had a surrey,
         you filled your surrey; they had a fringe on top.
         
         SS:  They did?
         
         ME:  Sure they did. And about the only time I can remember..—I was in
         it more than that—but I can remember going to my grandmother's
         funeral, 'cause we had this surrey full and we came to Genesee—
         the cemetery, and I knew the neighbors, because you thought nothing
         of walking. Of course, we were, oh, about two and a half or three
         miles from school and I walked a great deal of the time, sometimes
         we went on horseback, but—it just depended, you know. But we
         thought nothing of walking to school. I was pretty,small and we
         had a pretty steep hill, and sometimes my brother would carry me
         part way up that hill, my older brother. Of course, when we moved
         to town when I was still pretty young, J was, oh, I suppose, twelve,
         thirteen, somewhere in there—I really don't know, and I know someone
         was saying the other day, they were talking about bathtubs, and
         said they couldn't remember ever not having a bathtub. I said,
         "I remember when they didn't have a bathtub." You pumped the
         water - there was no other way of getting it. You carried it up,
         heated it in a boiler, and put it in a tub and had your bath.
         I said, "In my day there wasn't such a thing as a bathtub."
         
         SS:  Would each kid use - do that whole thing over again or did a
         bunch of kids use the same water?
         
         ME:  No, I don't think - I think I suppose when I was small enough my
         brothers probably pumped it for me, but I was still pretty young
         when I used to do that myself, because it didn't take too much
         because your tubs were only about so big. If you have to you can
         take a bath in not too much water.
         
         SS:  What was that tub shaped like?
         
         ME:  Perfectly round and it was about like that...they used the washing
         board. machine - you, well you washed some on a A but as far back as
         I can remember they had a washing machine that you went this way -
         you did it by hand...
         
         SS:  Back and forth.
         
         ME:  And it went through a wringer and then you used this tub to rinse
         them and you - they had two of them, you'd rinse it into one and
         then you'd rinse it into the next one to get the soap out. Oh,
         and they - you know, one thing I think of - you know as a kid I
         never heard an unkind word about a neighbor or anyone criticize
         anybody and that never dawned on to me until recently when now
         people are always just talking so much, you know, and saying some
         thing about somebody - maybe it's true, maybe it isn't. But when
         I was a kid I thought everybody was, I guess, perfect, 'cause there
         wasn't anyone, and I knew them for a few miles around because we
         went to school, they called it the Grey Eagle District, and there
         were programs and had church services now and then, in another
         area that was east and well, we usually went on horseback or maybe
         we'd go in a buggy or someway. I knew we'd go down there to that,
         and there was always good turn-out.
         
         SS:  To go there - you would go to church services there too, you say?
         
         ME:  Yes. They had church services sometimes - not very often, but I
         guess they were kind of special, but, ah...
         
         SS:  But never an unkind word - does that mean that you think your
         parents never, even among themselves, between themselves, would talk
         about other people.
         
         ME:  I don't think so. I don't think they did because I never heard
         anything until after we moved into town and I got to know people
         in town, and of course, I was getting older then. Once in a while
         you'd hear a little something, but not very much. It seemed like
         the older I got, is when you begin to hear people talk about some
         body - there was something wrong with this one or that one, and
         maybe they weren't as bad as the one that was doing the talking.
         But as a child I absolutely didn't think there was anything wrong
         with anybody because people that I knew never said anything unkind
         that I ever heard or ever would hear anyone bawl anybody out and
         as I remember I don't remember the teacher having any trouble with
         the kids. I can remember one thing, the only punishment I ever
         remember of was maybe when they was supposed to be quiet, was taking
         an exam or something and somebody would whisper, would go up and
         stand in the front of the room with your back to the class* That's
         the only punishment I ever saw in school when I was a kid. I never
         saw anything - I don't know.
         
         SS:  Do you think the kids always behaved their parents?
         
         ME:  Well I would say they did. I can't remember my folks ever saying
         'no' about anything because it - well, we weren't tempted to do any
         thing that wasn't right. There wasn't any reason as I look back
         at it, and I just wonder sometimes about it, because I never heard
         of anything about any of the neighbors out there ever doing anything
         that wasn't right - or saying anything mean about anybody. I always
         just thought everybody was fine.
         Do you think everybody was?
         I do - I really do.
         You think they really were almost perfect?
         Well, yes, I do - because there was no occasion - there was nothing
         to, well I don't know why. I can remember one time my sister
         corrected me for something - she was going to give me a spankin'.
         She went out and got a switch; she came in and of course, she was
         a lot older than I, and I looked up at her and of course, I was
         really pretty active for such a youngster, and I grabbed that thing
         and broke it in two and threw it out in the yard. She walked off,
         she never said another word*, it was dropped right there. And I,
         I can't - I can look back and think of some of the things they said
         and done, now I appreciate it. Cause I was so small and I didn't
         like it because my brothers, mostly, of course, some of them, there
         was one short one, but they were fairly good sized and my two
         sisters were larger than I, so I thought it was - I felt real bad
         about it - I was just awfully upset about it.
         
         SS:  About, ah...
         
         ME:  Being so small. And I remember one day my dad was sitting in a
         rocking chair and I don't remember what he was doing, and he picked
         me up on his lap, he says "You know, good things are done up in
         small packages." Well I remember things like that more? I don't
         remember him ever getting after me. I wasn't any angel either
         'cause I was active and climbed up on top of the house, I was told
         to get down, but... (Laughter). You didn't, it just seemed to
         me, I don't think there was any temptations - there wasn't any
         that I know of.
         
         SS:  Did your brothers and sisters that were bigger and older than you
         have any interest.in bossing you around at all - did they do that?
         
         ME:  Well this story I've told many times - it's a brother that's, he
         was five years older than I and this was when I got older and was
         in town, we lived in town and I had - they learned the dance quite
         young, that was the recreation they had and I learned to dance aw
         fully young 'cause we had family dances, not family dances but
         neighborhood, would come into your home and they'd dance and there'd
         be maybe a banjo and a violin and a piano or whatever. Well,
         when I got into town I, of course, wasn't going to miss a dance. I
         had one-this brother and - was smarter than I was and he knew a
         lot more than I did, and I don't care who I was going to date, he
         dated my girlfriend and it was the four of us together. I was never
         out of his sight, and yet he never got after me for anything or
         did It ever get in the way - well, I just thought he was a wonderful
         brother. He was such a wonderful dancer that I was tickled to
         death to have him in there to dance with. Only once did he get
         after me and I was going to something and he said,"Who are you
         going with.", and I told him, he said, "No you're not." I said,
         "Well, I sure am.", and so when this fellow arrived at the front
         door he went to the door and said, "She's not going.", and I
         didn't go and I never said anything 'cause it wouldn't do any
         good and Ididn't know what to say 'cause I'd never quarreled with
         any of them, but Ididn't speak to him for aweek. (Laughter)
         That ended that. Well, would you see anything like that today?
         Indeed you don't. But of course, now everything - if you don't
         know it, you can see it on T.V. So I - it was different.
         
         SS:  He was really looking out to protect you? He was trying to protect
         you?
         
         ME:  Sure he was - he was going to be right where I was and see that
         I was taken care of and he wasn't going to let me go with some
         one that he thought I shouldn't, and he saw that I did it, but the
         way he did it, it worked out. I think of him an awful lot and I
         think now I could've thanked him for taking care of me, but I
         didn't then, I didn't think he was taking care of me, but he was.
         
         SS:  You thought you was just going on double dates?
         
         ME:  Yes, that's what it was to me, and I don't think a brother and a
         sister double date any more. If they do, I haven't seen it or
         heard of it in recent years. But he was everyplace that I went
         to.
         
         SS:  What would be the kinds of things that you would go to - just be
         mainly dances and dating in those days?
         
         ME:  They were public dances in town. There was a hall they had the
         public dances inland everybody was there -nearly everybody danced
         then,' there wasn't any other recreation, really. They weren't out
         running around on the streets, not that I know of, I never knew
         of it,
         
         SS:  Well I heard that in some communities that some of the people were
         opposed to dancing - didn't want people dancing at all. Have you
         heard about that?
         
         ME:  Well they did around Genesee I don't think there was anyone in
         Genesee that objected to dancing. Of course, the dancing was a
         lot different then than it is now. What it is now, I don't know,
         but there was, as far as I know., if you go to a dance now, there's
         more or less drinking, and they all do. But I don't believe that
         they ever did then. I remember as I got older, that once in a
         while there would be someone up there that had had a little too
         much to drink, and I know one night this man, had always been very
         nice to me and he was a beautiful dancer., and he started over there
         and he came over to ask me for a dance and my brother knew he was
         coming to get a dance and he walked right around him and in front
         real quick, and he said, "Gome on, this is our dance." He didn't
         think I should be dancing with him, so I didn't. But he just did
         it so quickly, and there wasn't a word said, he never said a word
         to me. He didn't say, "Well, he's been drinking, you can't dance
         with him." He never said anything about it. I knew, I was old
         enough then, and I knew that fellow had been drinking, but. 
         
         SS:  But you would have danced with him if he'd have asked you'anyway,
         probably?
         
         ME:  I don't know what I would've doneJ I really don't know whether
         I would have got up and danced with him or not. I have no idea
         'cause there was so little of it, that you just - you just didn't
         see anything like that.
         
         SS:  In those dances, did a person usually dance with almost everybody
         else that was there during an evening? Is that how they went?
         
         ME:  Uh-huh. You didn't dance with one person all evening, which I
         understand they do a great deal now.
         
         SS:  Yes, they do.
         
         ME:  Then you didn't - you danced with your friends, all of them. They
         were all friends, and, it was just so different.
         
         SS:  Would they ask you right before the dance?
         
         ME:  Well, when the music would start, well, then the men would start
         over where the women were sitting down and come up and ask for a
         dance. Once in a while, before the music started, if you happened
         to be standing around somewhere, or close to one that wanted to
         dance, you'd "May I have the next dance?", but that was all.
         You wouldn't ask, only just the next dance. I don't know when this
         other started, really. 'Cause it seems like it kind of came on so
         gradually that—it was just different. I never said, I was no
         angel, I was in to things and done things that I shouldn't, I know
         that. Like when I climbed up on the house... I knew I shouldn't -
         I had no business up there, but I did.
         
         SS:  Did you get punished for doing it?
         
         ME:  No, they just saw me and told me to get down off of the house.
         I got down. There -was no fuss made about it or nothing more
         said; that was it. Now, why there's correction between the parents
         all the time. You tell a child he can't have it; they're going
         to do it anyway, and they'd look up out of the corner of their
         eye and keep going and starting to do it. I don't remember ever
         seeing anything like that when I was a child, never.
         
         SS:  I wonder why the kids were so obedient then?
         
         ME:  I don't know, whether it had anything to do with us living on
         the ranch 'cause we did have, we went back and forth. You spoke of
         Tom Wahl, of course, Tom, I knew his mother, his mother was a
         wonderful woman and.I came from a large family and I loved to
         go over there because she was a real fussy person and she was the
         only person I knew that was always dressed up - she never wore
         a house dress like other women around there and she had a little
         white apron that she wore only when she was getting the meals -
         and the meals were served why, I was in my seventh heaven when
         I could go over there and she asked me to stay a day or two and
         I did. I'd go over and stay. She gave me piano lessons, she
         had some beautiful paintings and things. I told Tom, I said, "I
         know more about your mother than you do.", because he didn't know
         her until later, and she had a family and they - I don't know whether
         you know or not, the one child was crippled and, of course, I
         think he passed away when he was about 20 years old; he was fairly
         young, anyway. She spent all of her time with him instead of on
         her house - she took care of him. He couldn't take care of himself,
         and so he, Tom, doesn't know his mother being so immaculate as I
         do.
         
         SS:  When you knew her was that before she had this baby that was crippled?
         
         ME:  Yes, yes,that's before they had any children that I used to go over
         there a lot. Then after she had her family and Cal, of course,
         was crippled; he was born that way, and I guess it was a, I really
         don't know the particulars, but anyway, she had her hands full.
         
         SS:  Could the child walk at all - could he...
         
         ME:  Well, he got so where he got around some, but, he couldn't - well?
         she had to put him to bed and he wanted to turn over, she had to
         turn him over in bed.
         
         SS:  Did she have to feed him too?
         
         ME:  Well, I can't remember that she fed him or if she didn't. But I
         know that she had to turn him over in bed and that she, well her
         time was spent with Cal,and I imagine I would say that he might
         of, as he got older, could feed himself but I kinda question that -
         I just can't remember that.
         
         SS:  So that would have been really having her hands full.
         
         ME:  Oh, it was terrible, it really was. He wasn't exactly deformed,
         but he was in a way,too5and held his head funny, you know. Well
         you would think at a glance that he just didn't have a brain and
         he really had - he was very smart^but he couldn't pass it on.
         He couldn't express himself, but those that really knew-of
         course, I was so young that I didn't think - you know, it didn't
         impress me too much. Well-it did, cause I felt sorry for him,
         but I can't remember of him ever doing anything on his own, that
         he was helped. But in later years they got a car for him and he
         did drive^and I know people were kinda shocked, they didn't think
         he should be on the road. He might have had better control of his
         arms than he did of his legs, but on the other hand, how could he
         have too good of control of his arms or why couldn't he have turned
         over in bed? I don't know, because...
         
         SS:  But he was smart?
         
         ME:  Well they said he was brilliant really, but, if you didn't really
         know him you wouldn't know, because it was hard for him to talk;
         he couldn't express himself. It didn't come out the way he wanted
         it to.
         
         SS:  Well, I wanted to ask you about Mrs. Wahl being immaculate. Wouldn't
         that be kinda rough to do in the country farms in those days?
         
         ME:  She's the only one I know of.
         
         SS:  I thought living was pretty rough then anyway.
         
         ME:  No, not for her. They had a porch and they had a long dining
         table in there and at that time the farmers had hired help,
         'cause of the machinery and everything was so different they had
         to have quite a bit of help, and when she had hired men she fed
         them out there because their house—in the kitchen and the living
         room she didn't want their dirty clothes in there. I can remember
         that very well. And I know that - Tom took me down to show me his
         son's new home and I said, "You remember your mother had this
         room built off of the kitchen to feed the hired help?" He laughed,
         because he didn't.
         
         SS:  Do you think she could be so immaculate because she had help in
         the home?
         
         ME:  No.
         
         SS:  She did that all herself? All the housework?
         
         ME:  She did it all herself. About the only help that I ever remember
         at that time you couldn't go buy clothes like you do now, and she
         Lewiston ...
         had a dressmaker come up from, I think it was but she was
         from out of Genesee anyway, it wasn't in Genesee, and she had
         this woman come up and sew and she'd be there for a week or two
         and she'd make these fancy aprons and things for her. And that's
         the only help I ever remember. In later years I wasn't around them
         so much,, and Cal got worse and she'd taken him to the doctors and
         different places and so forth, I wasn't around her as much, but
         she got so she wasn't like that. She was more like ordinary person,
         For instance, she came by one day, so many people rode a-horseback
         well she had been some place and she came by, she tied her horse
         up front, and came up and was sitting on the porch and when she
         got off, the horse had rubbed his head against her, she said "I
         should have gone on home and changed my shirty" and we were, you
         know, said why, "Well there's no excuse for dirt." Even if that
         horse had just did it, she should have gone on home and changed
         it. She said, "There's no excuse for dirt.".
         
         SS:  But you found her home to be a very special place to you., too.
         
         ME:  It was very special to me. It certainly was and she, I just
         thought the world of her, and you didn't go to your neighbors like
         you could now, because you didn't have the transportation. It
         was said you had to either get a horse or walk quite a distance.
         Tom's grandmother was hard of hearing,and she had one of those
         horns - I bet you've never seen them.
         
         SS:  I've seen pictures.
         
         ME:  She held that up to her ear, and you talked in that and I always
         wanted to take a hold of it; I was curious to get ahold of it,
         but I wouldn't. Now show me a kid today that wouldn't. If
         they were curious they'd go up and they'd ask her questions and
         they'd want to touch it but for some reason., I didn't have the
         nerve and I always wanted to take ahold of that horn and"take a
         look at it 'cause I just wondered how she could hear through that
         and what it was. I didn't know what it was all about. I knew
         what she was using it for, but that's all, but I never touched
         it.
         
         SS:  I like to tease my wife sometimes, she can't hear in one ear and
         sometimes I tell her she should have one of those horns.
         
         ME:  There's an awful lot of that in here, hard of hearing.
         
         SS:  Well, it's been that way for her ever since she was a child.
         
         ME:  Oh,for goodness sakes, well that's too bad. Bad enough when it
         comes on when you get older.
         
         SS:  But you know what made that place, her house, so special to
         you, what was it that made her placed I mean it was clean
         and it was cultured, too, from what you said...
         
         ME:  She was a marvelous person and they were such kind people, her
         husband too, he was a, oh, I don't know, they just seemed like
         such wonderful people to me. They were so good to me^ and I
         was always welcome and, well, I don't know.
         
         SS:  How far away was it from your house?
         
         ME:  Oh, I don't know, I suppose a mile and a half or close to two
         miles.
         
         SS:  So you just walked?
         
         ME:  Uh-huh. Up over through the fields. Over and around the road
         you go a little farther. They were just wonderful people and I
         think all the rest of the neighbors were. I never heard, and
         even after I was older and you began—we'd moved into town and
         I'd heard things about people in town, I never heard of any of
         those people out- there ever doing things, that they shouldn't.
         Or they never, well, they just didn't I don't think. I donlt
         think they did.
         
         SS:  Maybe she had time to spend with you because she didn't have
         any kids at that time. I wonder if that was...
         
         ME:  Well, she spent a lot of time on her house, but, I think one
         thing she knew that I thought the world of her? and I loved music.
         I started going over there, I just don't know J I haven't
         any idea because, well, time meant nothing. I never thought
         of age, I guess.
         
         SS:  Well, how close was your family to the other families around,
         to the other neighbors...
         
         ME:  Well as far as I know they were all good friends. Of course,
         we had cousins that lived on out farther east? it was about three
         or four miles, and that was a large family, too, and we'd go over
         there, but not real often, because we both, they were two big
         families and they couldn't all go. So maybe just a few would
         go at a time, but you just didn't go very often and yet, I never
         heard them say an unkind word. I never heard that one wasgirls
         or boys would ever say anything about their sister or
         brother or give them heck for anything they done. Never, ever.
         
         SS:  Well,when they socialized, your family, how did they do ifi
         Did they visit with other families or did they get together
         after school or what did they do?
         
         ME:  They - I guess considering socializing they wasn't very
         much of that. We went to things, like I said when they had the
         program in Pine Grove, we'd go down there, but really there wasn't
         much talent 'cause no one, well, there wasn't any way, you couldn'tthere
         was no teachers to teach any talent, anything unusual.
         At school why, the only thing that I can remember taught that was
         any fun was when they taught the spelling bee every Friday. Well,
         what would that mean to a kid today. They'd be bored. No, you
         didn't seem to - somehow you got along and you were happy with
         what you had, and if you had a house or had a horse and quite
         often each one would have their own horse, or maybe like the three
         of us that were younger, we all got on one horse, or maybe there'd
         be just one on the horse at a time, but we'd ride that horse around.
         I don't - and they did have these country dances.
         
         SS:  At person's homes?
         
         ME:  In their homes 'cause I know we had them in our home and we had -
         there wasn't any piano then,I think, there wasn't any piano. We
         had an organ, and my oldest brother played the violin, or fiddle
         they called it then because they never had a lesson, he just picked
         it upland my sister played the organ and another fellow played,
         I think it was a banjo, but I'm not even sure of that, one of
         the neighbors. And the whole family would come. There wouldn't
         be too many, the houses were built - the kitchens were always large,
         and the living rooms, seems to me most of them were pretty good
         sized. They'd dance and thought they had a good time. And how
         they'd get together - I don't know, I don't understand it. I
         know Tom and I had talked about it there for a time.
         
         SS:  How long would they stay - would it be a long evening, dancing
         until the early hours of the morning?
         
         ME:  I don't think so. I really don't.. They possibly be between
         12:00 and 1:00 o'clock, maybe 1:00 o'clock, but I doubt if it'd
         be anything after that.
         
         SS:  Would there be eats?
         
         ME:  Don't remember being - like at our house mother had a large
         family, well, she couldn't serve to all these people. I don't
         think that any of them did, I can't remember that. I don't
         think they did. I don't remember ever eating at a dance until
         after we moved into Genesee and then they'd go - there was a
         restaurant there and the kids would go up there and eat and so
         forth, but in the country I don't think they did.
         
         SS:  Did all ages come to Genesee dances, just like country dances,
         or was it more the same age in town?
         
         ME:  No, I think they were all there. Kids not quite as young as
         they did in the country. Because in the country they didn't leave
         them at home? I don't think they did. No, it was different, it
         was altogether different, because I know that - I don't remember
         seeing any small youngsters at a dance in town,and Idon't believe
         that women took small youngsters and went to things like that.
         When we first moved to town they kind of more stayed home with
         their kids. You didn't leave them with babysitters.
         
         SS:  And you didn't bring them with you, either, like in the country?
         
         ME:  No, they didn't. No, Idon't remember -it doesn't run in my mind
         of ever seeing a youngster there. In later years, I did, yes,
         but when I was young and I think they averaged almost a dance a
         week 'cause that was about the only amusement they had.
         
         SS:  In town?
         
         ME:  Uh-huh. And then maybe they'd be in the country, if somebody
         would build a new barn, they'd have a barn dance.
         
         SS:  Were there other things like clubs that you took part of in town
         in Genesee besides the dances when you were young?
         
         ME:  Well, eventually, you did, of course. I didn't - I knew there
         were clubs, but actually I was never interested in playing cards
         or anything like that until after Iwas married and of course, I
         went along with the group and went to the card clubs.
         
         SS:  Is that what the clubs were mostly - card clubs?
         
         ME:  Yes, they were card clubs. There were quite a few in Genesee
         that played cards and pretty good card players there,too.
         
         SS:  Were they women's clubs or for...
         
         ME:  Well, sometimes there'd be a group that would form where there'd
         maybe three or four couples, four or five or so, you know, had
         so many tables, but, it's more women's clubs. Now when I was
         younger, I was with a group and we had four or five tables? we
         played cards and men were there. But., in recent years I don't
         believe they do that anymore. There maybe a couple get together
         and go play cards with each other, but, not as a group.
         
         SS:  Were those clubs affiliated with - you know, like national women's
         clubs or were they just a local? .
         
         ME:  Just local.
         
         SS:  Did your folks have a 160-acre farm out there or what was the
         farm?
         
         ME:  They had - I don't know, my dad homesteaded out at the
         reservation^.and my brother owns that farm now. Now I don't know
         and I've been always going to ask my brother - I want to see the
         deed to it. Cause it's supposed to be a little different. It
         was signed by the President at that time, and I don't think the
         President signs deeds anymore. And I always think, "Why didn't
         I ask Bob to see that?" In fact, I never even thought of it
         until later years and one time it was mentioned. No, I never
         have seen it. But he homesteaded this and the Indians rode
         horseback - they came up over the hills from, they was more from
         around Lapwai and they had a trail came up there and it came right
         close to my dad's place, where they were living then, and while
         he - I don't know how long after he homesteaded that, he bought
         some more land, that was a couple or three miles from there where
         they built a home. But the Indians used to come through and for
         some reason they took a liking to my dad, and they called him
         Chief Robert. No one ever called him Bob when he was young, they
         called him Robert. And they called him Chief Robert. But he kept
         a horse saddled, they said, and I don't remember that 'cause, but
         I was told later that they did keep a horse saddled. But that
         wouldn't do them any good 'cause the Indians, if there was more
         than one there was nothing they could do anyway.
         
         SS:  What did he keep a horse saddled for - to get away if he needed to?
         
         ME:  I guess so. But they never bothered us at all or - they'd come
         and maybe ask for something - you gave it to them. But I really
         didn't see much of them.
         
         SS:  They wouldn't abuse that, they would just ask once in a while for
         something?
         
         ME:  I don't think it happened very often.
         
         SS:  You gave it to them to keep on their good side?
         
         ME:  Yes, you did. If anybody asked you just did, if you had it; if
         you didn't, why you'd tell them you didn't have it. But I don't
         think that people ever misreprepresented to other people; I think
         they just told them Lhe truth. I don't think it ever occurred to
         them to try and lie out of anything, or maybe I wasn't around enough
         that I heard it. I don't know.
         
         SS:  Well do you think that your father would treat the Indians just the
         same as he would treat white people, or would he treat them different?
         
         ME:  He was friendly with them as much as he could be, but they didn't
         mix much, and I know that they didn't have any trouble - my dad
         didn't have any trouble whatever at any time with the Indians. And
         in later years when I was a little older and could go a little
         farther, there was a family lived oh, about a mile from there, and
         his wife was a full-blooded Indian, and I don't know how - I'd heard
         different stories how she learned to cook, 'cause she didn't know
         how to cook, Indians didn't know. And anyway, they had two girls
         and a boy, and we were good friends and I used to go down there -
         I'd walk down, and this Mrs. Williams would be sitting out on the
         front porch with her feet straight out, just like the Indians
         sit - there she was. And how she could sit there and why, when
         they had chairs, but there's where she was. "Hello,Mary - how
         are you?. Becky, he in the house." That was about all she'd
         say. She was friendly; she was not the least bit unfriendly and
         I'm sure she was glad that we came whenever we did, or anything,
         and the daughter was an immaculate housekeeper and very well res
         pected and well, all three of them were, the two girls and the man,
         the boy in the family, all of them were very well respected. And
         when she had a family and her girl got old enough.in her high school,
         of course, she had gone to the country school, her mother was a
         little leery of sending her into Genesee into school 'cause there
         wasn't any Indians in there, even though this daughter was only
         a half-breed9 So they had decided, I don't remember now just where
         it was, but they were going to send her to some school what was
         Indian. They thought maybe that she might be embarrassed or they'd
         say something to her that they shouldn't. Well there was a good
         friend of there's that liked them, and was glad to have her, and
         so this women told Mrs. Williams, or her name was Cameron then,
         Mrs. Cameron, she said "I'd be glad to have her to stay with us and
         go to school." And she went through high school, and she was treated
         just like any other white person^ and her sister did,too. They
         both graduated from high school. And the oldest one, you wouldn't
         know she had any Indian blood, but the younger girl looked more
         like an Indian.
         Genesee accepted her completely 
         she was Indian, two take her daughter. - No, cause the family respected ith her and
         attended church
         her, as one of the
         and she was accepted. And she came back and years later, I'd s'een
         belng part Indian. you just
         her mother because of that h0„ that -because she was full-blooded Indian
         and married to a white?
         there ever said or done anything.
         
         SS:  Did she come and take Part in tne dances like other people?
         
         ME:  No, her mother didn't.
         
         SS:  Her mother is the one Imean.
         with them,and I don't thaink, of course, they don't live there any thank
         of anything different.
         
         SS: Weren't there afair number or at or at least some, well there were some
         people that were just liu. woman, that were Indians and married
         whites and...
         
         ME:  Well that was more around through, maybe, Lapwai, I think it hap
         pened down there. But up in our country it wasn't. There was
         only this one family, that I knew of, that married an Indian.
         
         SS:  But they didn't mix really then, that family didn't mix with the
         other families on a social basis?
         
         ME:  Well,there wasn't such a thing as a social basis in those times,
         really. But Mrs. Williams didn't go and call on her neighbors.
         All I can remember of her is sitting out on that front porch, and
         she never learned to really do housework and to cook like she
         should have. Maybe, I don't know how they did before they had
         this daughter that was old enough to do the work, 'cause I wasn't
         in their house then. I was younger, so much younger, and I got
         older, they were accepted, and I never even thought to ask my
         mother. My mother probably could have told me more about it,
         but it never occurred to me.
         
         SS:  Did they seem to have a happy marriage?
         
         ME:  I think so. I really do. Because they all seemed to be so kind
         of easy going,and I was there quite a bit and I never, ever heard
         any of them say an unkind word to each other. The sisters, or
         the brother or the mother or the father, and of course, I didn't
         talk to the mother very much; she was a little hard to talk to.
         And he was just like any other white man; I didn't think anything
         about it. I thought it was perfectly all right, because people
         didn't talk about those things. In this day and age, everybody
         would be talking about it and you'd think about it and you'd
         probably ask some questions. Well they were accepted, and that
         was it, and when Rebecca, of course, as I said, she was a half-breed,
         started in the country school they were all white people, and she
         was the only one that wasn't. Well she was, as far as I was con
         cerned, she was white, and I knew she wasn't. I knew her mother
         was an Indian, but it never - there wasn't any difference between
         her and any of the others. She was just a real, nice person.
         But I don't remember of her ever being to any of those country
         dances.
         
         SS:  Rebecca?
         
         ME:  Uh-huh. Now whether she was or not, I don't know, but I don't
         remember of ever seeing her at a dance.
         
         SS:  Do you think maybe the family would feel hesitant about it?
         
         ME:  She herself may have, 'cause she was a little hesitant about
         sending her to school in Genesee because they were all white
         people. So my idea would be, that Rebecca herself might have
         felt - I don't know. There was never, ever anything said.
         
         SS:  Now Rebecca is the one that went to school in the city?
         
         ME:  Yes^ No - she was the half-breed.
         
         SS:  Oh, it was her daughter?
         
         ME:  It's her daughter that went to school in Genesee,.
         
         SS:  But it was Rebecca's mother that sat on the porch?
         
         ME:  Yes. I don't know what her name was. I haven't any idea; to
         me she was Mrs. Williams, and when I was a kid you didn't callany
         married woman by her first name. It was Mrs. I didn't
         know their names.
         
         SS:  Well, Rebecca, she married and lived and just stayed right there?
         
         ME:  Well, she married a Genesee man and they bought a farm, and were
         good farmers, made a good living, retired where the retirement
         place - oh, I don't know just where it is, I've never been over
         there. But between here and Seattle, and it's quite a nice home.
         I've heard people speak about it and they thought it was a real
         nice place. It had a good, very good reputation. And I don't
         know, as I understand it you had your own apartment and you could,
         if you wanted to, fix your meal there or you could go and eat in
         the dining room? you had a choice.
         
         SS:  So Rebecca, she went to school in the country. Did she go on to
         high school?
         
         ME:  Yes.
         
         SS:  In Genessee?
         
         ME:  Yes.
         
         SS:  But she - it wasn't her that they were going to send away to
         school, it was her daughter?
         
         ME:  It was her daughter. And she was afraid that she wouldn't be
         accepted.
         
         SS:  But she married a white man, -Rebecca did?
         
         ME:  They all did, yeah. Yes, she did, she married a white man. And
         I know at the time it seemed kind of strange to me, I thought,
         gee, he's marrying her,and she isn't a white woman and he's a
         white man, but I really hadn't been around Indians at all, because
         they were mostly in Lapwai and I don't remember when they used
         to come up through there - to ride up through there and do this
         war whooping like they do. And they did a lot of it out there,
         but I don't remember much about it. I think I was too young to
         remember.
         
         SS:  Did you grow up being afraid at all of Indians?
         
         ME:  No, not at all. No, no, not one bit. To me they was just like
         anyone else. I think that if - when I was young, if an Indian
         had asked me for a date I would have been embarrassed. I think
         it would have bothered me because I wouldn't want to be disres
         pectful to him, and I would hate to admit that I wouldn't go out
         with him, but I don't believe I would of. Because I never was
         really around an Indian, 'cause to me Rebecca was a half-breed,
         but she was a white woman. As far as I was concerned she was
         just like any other white person.
         
         SS:  Well did you and she - where you two friends?
         
         ME:  Yeah. Yes, we were good friends, and I never even thought of
         her as being an Indian, 'cause she was treated just like any
         other white person and everybody, well, everyone respected
         her.
         
         SS:  She went to school in Genesee herself?
         
         ME:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS:  Well, you know when you say that she wondered about her daughter
         going to school there, it makes me think that maybe she didn't
         have the easiest time herself.
         
         ME:  Well, it could've been things that I wouldn't have known about.
         Maybe a few things came up and she kept it to herself, I wouldn't
         know. I just don't know.
         
         SS:  She probably didn't - as you knew her, probably, she didn't have -
         her whole life was with white people, not with Indians, probably.
         
         ME:  She was never around Indians, hardly at all, I don't think. They
         might have come up from Lapwai and come up, some now and then,
         but I rather doubt it.
         
         SS:  And she must have dated this white man that she married, I mean,
         they must have gone together some?
         
         ME:  Well I suppose they did, I really don't know.. Because it was
         never discussed or ever heard anything about it. Whether he
         just - the way laws were and so forth, whether he just married
         her, saw her and married her and that was it, I don't imagine
         that he really kept company with her any length of time. I
         should't say that I don't think so, 'cause I don't know. I
         have no idea, 'cause I never saw much of him.
         
         SS:  Well do you think that people had the idea then that Indians
         were kind of inferior at the time, 'cause of the way they lived
         and the way they acted?
         
         ME:  Well, I don't know. I never really had any prejudice against
         them in any way, and in later years I knew of a couple of
         girls from Lapwai that were full-blooded Indians, and were lovely
         girls, only they had a drinking habit.. And, of course, that's
         one thing that Indians.do like their liquor. They have a little
         trouble there. One of the girls that I knew was, I think, see
         Chief Joseph was her grandfather, and her father's name was Joseph
         too. And he tried to talk to the Indians when they'd get a sum
         of money, just buy land, you know, and try to get ahead, and she
         told me herself that you couldn't do anything with, 'it didn't
         mean anything to them. Said they got this money and they just
         drank it and that was it and they just lived on anything that -
         well, I haven't been in Lapwai for several years, but they didn't
         used to be hardly, well there was just old shacks mostly, you
         might say. And I think they just didn't care. But I think, and now
         they've spread out more and they're around through the country, they're
         probably a lot different. But I know, Josephine, used to tell me quite
         a bit about them and that, well, she just didn't think they had any
         ambition and they just thought the government should keep 'em.
         
         SS:  But she had ambition herself?
         
         ME:  She wasn't that type and neither was her father., and her father was
         a full-blooded Indian. So, but she didn't go along with it at all.
         
         SS:  This is Joseph's daughter, Josephine?
         
         ME:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Was her mother a white?
         
         ME:  I never - no, her mother was an Indian, I saw her once, and she was a
         full-blooded Indian. And, of course now, Josephine dressed like anyone
         else, but one day I saw her mother and she introduced me to her and I
         remember she had one of those scarves tied around her like the Indians
         do,and I was very much surprised 'cause I expected her mother to be more
         like a white person, 'cause Josephine was a nice looking girl, and very
         neatly dressed and everything, and I know this surprised me, when I
         saw this scarf tied around her mother's head. But I had always thought
         that I would go to Lapwai while Josephine was there and see where they
         lived, 'cause she had asked me out, but I never did. I guess maybe I
         was a little reluctant, because they were full-blooded Indian family
         and, well, I didn't think, I don't think I'd have the courage to walk
         in, if there were more Indians there I wouldn't feel at home.
         He had a half-brother; his mother had been married before and
         evidently lost her husband in Scotland and then she married Grey, and
         then she had two sons and a daughter, that were Grey's, and they came,
         well.I can't tell you, I'd have to look, I'd have to look it up. I
         have it written down when they... But they came out to Salt Lake
         City, I don't know, you may be a Mormon for all I know...
         
         SS:  No, I'm not.
         
         ME:  Well^ at that time the Mormons didn't like the other people and my
         grandfather went to Salt Lake City, and.I don't, it must have been
         just kind of a little shack that he had, and he worked with harnesses
         and things like that, kind of a harness shop, and the Mormons run him
         out of Salt Lake City, they didn't want anyone else in there. So
         he went to Carson City from Salt Lake City, and then my dad and my
         uncle came up to Walla Walla and they stayed there for awhile, and they
         came on over to Genesee and they both homesteaded.farms out there
         and their farms were, oh, a few miles apart. They both homesteaded.
         
         SS:  And they got that land just when the Indian reservation opened up for
         settlement?
         
         ME:  I don't know whether you paid anything for land then. Didn't you just
         have to... I don't know...
         
         SS:  Had to live on it for five years I think and do so many improvements
         and then it was yours - it was a filing fee, but I don't know if there
         was anything else.
         
         ME:  Well i never heard that mentioned and I never even thought to ask. If
         they did, they didn't pay much, 'cause he didn't have any money.
         
         SS:  Well do you think he was there waiting - I know a lot of people were
         waiting at Genesee for the land to open up and then they just, you
         know, took what they could.
         
         ME:  Well, I don't know, really; they were homesteading it when he and my
         uncle came, and when they opened up, I don't know.
         
         SS:  But they actually homesteaded the land, didn't they?
         
         ME:  But he actually homesteaded this 200 acres so a little over, or a little
         under, it's alittle over 'cause some of it has alittle canyon right
         in it, in the farm land, and he homesteaded that, and as Isaid the thing
         that I've always been curious about is the deed to this. I think that
         that should be framed. And I suppose my uncle's was the same thing,
         was probably signed by the President 'cause it was about the same time,
         and of course, they bought more land.
         
         SS:  When did he meet your mother? Did he know her before he came there?
         
         ME:  No, my mother came from Nebraska, and her father and mother came out,
         and they homesteaded a place down towards the Pine Grove District, down
         there, but I really don't know what her folks, what nationality they
         are, even. But, Ijust don't know where the Folletts came from, buto
         
         SS:  Related to Mahlon Follett?
         
         ME:  Distant relative, we don't claim any relation, but in, oh, at one time
         the parents, I guess, kind of got together and found out there was a
         distant relation in the Folletts and just where Mafalcma mother and father
         came from, I've never talked to Mahlonabout it, because we've never
         really said much - ever discussed it. I never thought of him as being
         related, 'cause I didn't know it for so long, when they came up in
         later years, it didn't make any difference to me.
         
         SS:  Was it rough going, you say he had no money when he started. Was
         it difficult in the early years for him on the farm?
         
         ME:  'I don't think there's a difference from what it is now, because people
         now have to have so much and demand so much and their children demand
         so much, nobody needed it, nobody had it. And, of course, I think
         it'd, well, he lived on a farm, you raised everything you ate, you
         had pigs, you had cattle, you had chickens, so you had your bread,
         baked your bread, you didn't buy it, that's for sure, and you
         raised your garden^and I remember there was an orchard back of
         the house, and they, my dad had a big pit—he dug this pit, one
         was for potatoes and vegetables that you could keep were put in
         different pits. Well these pits were lined with straw for the
         vegetables so -they wouldn't be in the dirt, then you'd put straw
         over them and then dirt over that. We'd go out there and dig
         out enough of whatever you wanted and you'd - well, I don't think
         you ever bought groceries to speak of.
         
         SS:  How deep were those pits, I don't mean exact, but I mean, would
         they be deep enough you could stand in them.
         
         ME:  No, they weren't too deep, 'cause he had, of course, more than
         one.
         
         SS:  Oh, he had two.
         
         ME:  And there would be one for potatoes and carrots and, oh, you see
         there was many vegetables you couldn't put in a pit. And I don't
         know whether they canned vegetables then or not, that don't register
         with me. I can't remember, 'cause I don't remember seeing any
         fruit jars.
         
         SS:  I think in those earlier days they weren't.
         
         ME:  I don't think so. No, to me, there wasn't. And I remember they
         had the back of the house was a - he dug a - quite into a bank
         and then they lined that with something - I don't know what, so
         that the dirt wouldn't come down into it. And in the summertime
         you had to put your milk out there in pans, 'cause you couldn't
         keep it in the house. You had to have milk, 'cause everybody ate
         bread and milk, or drank milk. But, I don't know, there was never
         any lack of anything 'cause we had plenty of meat, 'cause we had
         our own beef, and there was, we had the pigs and everything, and
         they did their own butchering.. I can remember seeing the meat
         hung up; it was frozen. I think the winter's - to me, the winter's
         were more severe, they were colder. You could keep meat for quite
         a long time. But maybe, that's just I don't remember.
         
         SS:  I've heard other people say that, that the winter's were colder.
         
         ME:  Well I would say so. And we always had, and of course, we had all
         of this fruity but there was no way— I think, maybe, I would say,
         but I'm not sure that either they probably had a pit of apples too,
         because there were quite a few apples, of different kinds, so I
         think there would be - 'cause I know there was quite a few pits
         back there.
         
         SS:  Well, could he make his entire living by farming? Did he do any
         thing else for a living besides the farm?
         
         ME:  Huh-uh.
         
         SS:  Do you know if he farmed before he came here? It doesn't sound
         like it...
         
         ME:  No, I'm sure they didn't. I think he was pretty young and as I
         said, he and mom both came to Walla Walla and then came on up
         here and I think they were fairly young and just went out there
         and homesteaded and now whether they got a little work then, but
         I don't think there was any work. I don't know where they'd work.
         No one else had any money around there that they could pay them
         for anything.
         
         SS:  Well, you know, the reputation of the country around there is so
         good that I wonder whether he just couldn't get a pretty good crop
         off that land right from the start?
         
         ME:  Oh, I think they did. I really do, I think they did. I think
         they did right at the beginning, I don't know how they bought
         machinery, that never even entered my mind, to start out with,
         because they'd have to have a plow, but they didn't have machinery
         like they do now, but, they had to have a mower and they had to
         have a plow and a few things. I know dad had quite a few horses,
         but, before that, I don't know.
         
         SS:  Well he must have been able to do well enough from his farming
         to get the horses and the equipment that he — when you were young
         he had pretty good equipment, did he? Did he have what he needed
         to farm right?
         
         ME:  He had all he needed, and of course, for that time, when I remember,
         he'd bought more land and built this home. Because when they'd
         first moved on this reservation, it was just kind of a little shack,
         little two-room shack out there and just when, or how long it was
         that they bought this land and built a home, I don't know. Because
         the home was built when I was a baby, so that's the only home that
         I was ever in till we moved into Genesee.
         
         SS:  Well, did they live in a true shack until they built that home?
         
         ME:  Just a kind of a shack.
         
         SS:  Was that right near the other place, did you say?
         
         ME:  No, they were about two or three miles a part.
         
         SS:  Is that on the reservation too?
         
         ME:  No, it isn't. No, it isn't on the reservation. Well, it's near
         out there where Tom Wahl, that farm is. I really just don't know
         how they managed, of course, machinery didn't cost very much then,
         but I know they paid for it somehow, and there was not, you
         couldn't go out anndo ageett an I'm sure of that. So Idon't
         know how they maniiadgyeeda, iT,know how
         
         SS:  What about your mother, did shue huave to do alot of work on the
         place -alot of responsibility?
         Just her housework. She never went out in the field or anything
         downstairs, besides the bedrooms upstairs So it it wasn't a small
         know What before, but, when I was that time they'd probably started comino out with
         Jars not too
         long after that.
         
         SS:  Can you remember if there wat!
         
         SS: CaSh ln your family? If you had money
         
         ME:  Nobody wanted anything.
         
         SS:  Well, clothes closet. There was aboart about so wide, nailed on the wall
         never saw acoat hanoer or anythino like that when 1was achild.
         After we moved to town, we had clothes closets
         up, is that it?
         
         ME:  People didn't have any clothes. I suppose, I probably had, I
         might have had two or three dresses, and you'd wash them. You
         didn't have a lot, that's for sure, 'cause they'd only have behind
         the doors where they hung the clothes. I know I was talking to
         someone not too long ago, I said "Do you remember when we used to
         hang our clothes behind the door, we didn't even have a clothes'
         closet?", said "Well, I sure do." (Laughter) What would you do
         without a clothes closet now?
         aren't
         
         SS:  I don't know. Clothes closets big enough now for all the
         clothes people have got.
         
         ME:  Well buddy, they didn't demand it, nobody seemed to care, 'cause
         no one else had it. They weren't trying to outdo the other one
         and I think that's one reason they got along so well, no one was
         jealous of anyone or had - I don't think there was any ill feelings.
         
         SS:  But not having clothes, say, you know, I've heard them say how
         the town kids used to make fun of the country kids, say, "Well,
         those kids don't change their clothes; they're smelly, they're
         not clean like around town."
         
         ME:  Well I think maybe that was in later years, because I don't think
         that happened; well, it wasn't in our family, 'cause I know they
         took their baths and I think that anyone in our family came in
         from the field and needed a bath, they got it^and they took it.
         But, again on the other hand, it could have been some older—and
         maybe I was kind of accustomed to it and expected and never thought
         of it. But I can't hardly believe that I'd be accustomed to it;
         I just can't, because I know they all did the same thing, as I
         said, they had these washtubs, as they called them, and they had
         their baths.
         
         SS:  You probably had to wash every week if you had only so little clothes,
         just a few dresses, it was probably pretty often that they washed.
         
         ME:  Well, I'm sure that they washed more than once a week.
         
         SS:  Oh, boy.
         
         ME:  Well, I'm sure they did.
         
         SS:  Well, do you think that your folks were taking the money that he
         made farming and putting it into more land - do you think that's
         what they did?
         
         ME:  Oh, they bought more land, yes. He bought, oh, I don't know, I
         think it's close to 120 in one field and 80 in another, something
         like this, where they built the home, later, where they lived, not
         where they homesteaded. And now they are going to tear down that
         house and the man that bought this, of course, this land has been
         sold, and he's built a new home out there. And I said to Tom WahJ:,
         went by there, I said, "You know I've always wanted to go back
         there and go inside that house again,"r—he said, "I'll take you
         over sometime." I said, "Oh, no." 'cause they've built a new
         home now out - a great big one, out in front.
         
         SS:  Well did that mean that your mother had only the house work to
         do or did she have leisure things she had time to sit...
         
         ME:  There was no leisure time. I think she was busy all the time with
         house work and, I don't remember of ever seeing her in the garden.
         She might have gone down and got some once in a while. But I can
         remember going down, she told me to go down and get some carrots,
         or this or that, and I can see Dad down there hoeing the garden.
         He spent a lot of time hoeing the garden, 'cause the older boys
         were doing quite a bit of the farm work. And I don't remember
         mother doing anything like that at all.
         
         SS:  But leisure though, she didn't have time to sit down and just
         relax and read or...
         
         ME:  I never remember ever seeing her sit down and relaxing. I just
         don't remember ever seeing her do that.
         
         SS:  It doesn't surprise mes 'cause I've heard other people say the
         same.
         
         ME:  I don't remember ever seeing her sit down and relaxing. And
         of course she didn't have magazines; I don't think we had a daily
         paper. I'm not sure they even had a mailman come out there, but
         there must have been, but I just don't recall anything about any
         mailman or anything. They did later years, but as a child, I
         don't remember, 'cause I just don't think there was a great deal
         of mail. I think we'd go to town, not very often, but they did
         go in now and then and probably picked up what mail there was, if
         there was any. But I know we didn't have magazines or paper when
         I was real small and on the ranch; of course, in later years we
         did.
         
         SS:  Was there, a lot that you were expected to do - a lot of chores
         that you were expected to do, or did your older brothers and sisters
         take care of that stuff.
         
         ME:  Oh, no, I helped with the dishes. Always dusted, that was one of
         my jobs, and I milked the cow, but not because I was told to*, but
         see, I have several brothers older, and my sister was quite a bit
         older, so we weren't very close. I mean, we weren't together a lot
         'cause she was so much older than I am. The boys did the milking
         and so there was a cow that I wanted to milk," I thought that cow
         should be my cow, and I could milk her, and they let me. I'd
         take my pail and go down and milk her, maybe they'd milk part -
         maybe if I didn't do a good job, they'd finish it, I don't know,
         'cause then I didn't pay any attention. But I milked a cow for
         quite awhile. We always had cats and we'd squirt the milk in
         the cat'and... (Laughter), feed the cat while you was milking.
         But I did quit milking, I didn't keep that up too long, I'm sure
         of that.
         
         SS:  Well did you have as much time as you wanted to play, and do
         what you wanted to that way?
         
         ME:  Sure. There was horses more than anything else, get on a horse
         and ride to the neighbors or maybe ride them up and down a bank
         somewhere. I know there was a bank, they told me not to go up
         that bank, I shouldn't, and I thought well I bet I do, and I did.
         (Laughter) But whether they knew it, they did, they never bawled
         me out.
         
         SS:  Sounds like they treated you pretty good, then, really.
         
         ME:  But, the only one thing I ever pulled over on them, and then I
         never told them. Dad had—there'd be two horses that would go
         together, they were in pairs, this pair of grey horses. One was
         a real gentle horse, and the other one wasn't, and no one could
         get on his back; hebucked them off right now. And that didn't
         make sense to me. And of course, the barns were built with a
         stall and a wall up between, and I wondered why I couldn't climb
         up that wall and slip over on this horse, and he wouldn't even
         know I was there, and I did. He never moved. I sat there, if
         I'd of kicked him, you know, or done anything, he probably would
         of thrown me off, but I sat there quite a while, and I thought,
         "Nothing wrong with this horse, he's just as gentle as the other
         one," then pretty soon I slid off, got down, went out of the barn.
         I never told them what I did, 'cause I was afraid then I would get
         into trouble, so I didn't tell them.
         
         SS:  You know it sounds like you were really treated well by your parents,
         I mean, you weren't really afraid of them hurting you or hitting
         you or, it seems like you felt free to be somewhat independent -
         it sounds good to me.
         
         ME:  Well, I think they all were. And the people that I knew were all
         the same way. They were different families where I used to get
         on a horse, you know, and go over, and as far as I know if was all
         the same. I don't think there was any disputes to speak. There
         might of been once in awhile, but I just can't hardly believe
         they did.
         
         SS:  How do you think the husbands and wives got along in those days,
         like.
         
         ME:  Well I never heard one of them ever say anything back to the other
         one. Now, why, they just say it, that's all. But I never heard
         it, and I know I was in different families, like going over to
         my uncle's place, well, I never heard them ever say anything to
         each other, I mean, to contradict one another or anything. I've
         never heard them And there was different families where I used
         to go, and I would be there, maybe, all day, but I didn't pay too
         much attention to the parents 'cause I was there to play with the
         kids, but I never heard anything. Never. Never was a word of
         disagreement. We must have, at times, had disagreements, I don't
         know. But...
         
         SS:  Do you think, well, in other words, you figure that they kept it
         to themselves or they just would talk to each other in private?
         
         ME:  If they did, they kept it to themselves. They sure did, 'causeand
         they don't anymore.
         
         SS:  No, that's true.
         
         ME:  No, and I never - and as I said, even with all the brothers that
         I had and everything, I never was really, they never really got
         after me or was strict with me in any way. Except this brother
         was taking care of me in a round-about way that I just didn't even
         know what he was doing. He was just being nice to me, as far as
         I was concerned.
         
         SS:  I have understood that in some families,,that, say, the women weren't
         treated as well as in others, like some families, the wife would
         wind up having to cut her own wood, orr even have to work in the
         field, and that sort of thing. Was that looked down upon...
         
         ME:  There wasn't anyone around there that did that, that I know of.
         Of course, I had these brothers to do things like that and my dad,
         and I didn't think women split wood, and a few neighbors that I
         went to, I don't think that any of the women that I knew*-they may
         have, but I don't believe they ever did. But I may not have known
         what was going on.
         
         SS:  I was going to ask you a little bit, too, about the - well, the
         merchants in Genesee. Now I understand that the Rosensteins
         were a big store there - did you deal with them at all, did you
         trade with them?
         
         ME:  Yes, I remember them very well.
         
         SS:  What did you think of that family?
         
         ME:  Well, they was just - the only difference that I could see, they
         were someone that told me they were Jews, and I didn't know what
         a Jew was. I don't know whether that's true or not.
         
         SS:  No, they were. That's what I understand.
         
         ME:  That's what I was told, and I wondered why it would make any
         difference. I didn't see what the difference was whether they
         were Jews or not, and I'd been in their home and we'd traded
         at their store, but of course, they left there! was still pretty
         young when they left;* I think they went to California. But
         I don't know if they mixed very much with the other people,
         or whether they didn't want to or whether they were afraid they
         wouldn't be accepted or not, I don't know; I haven't any idea,
         'cause to me they were just another family.
         
         SS:  You don't know whether they did or didn't mix? In Genesee?
         
         ME:  Well, they were a little older than I, and I wasn't with their
         girls -I can't remember how many there were in the family or
         anything, now - about the age of my older sister, and my older
         sister was a friend of one of them, but they didn't go back and
         forth a lot, but I know they were good friends. But I really
         just don't - I thought there was something different about it,
         and I didn't know why or what it was.
         
         SS:  About them as a family?
         
         ME:  Well, I just thought that it was strange and there seemed to be
         a feeling, and I don't know whether it was that they were Jews
         and were a little reluctant to mix with the other people, or whether
         the other people - I think the other people would have accepted
         them, if they were raised like I was; and I wouldn't have made
         any different to me whether they were Jews or not. But I think
         maybe they kept to themselves a little more.. That's the feeling
         that I had, and I never saw Mrs. Rosenstein out very much, very
         few times. She seemed to kind of stay at home by herself, I
         thought, a great deal. Of course, the girls went to school and
         so forth, but— and they supposed to have a nice house for that
         time, you know.
         
         SS:  Why was it that the family moved in to Genesee? What was the
         thinking?
         
         ME:  To put the kids in school. (Laughter)
         Oh no, dad bought a place. He bought a home in town, and
         we just moved in and my brother farmed the ranch, so we lived
         in town then the rest of our lives. Lived in the same house until,
         well,:we got married and went and so forth, and that was it.
         
         SS:  Well did your father then retire at that time...
         
         ME:  Oh yes, he retired when...
         
         SS:  When you moved in?
         
         ME:  He might of gone out a little in the summertime, but I don't remember
         even going out or thinking much about it again.
         
         SS:  Well was he older than...
         
         ME:  He was ten years older than my mother.
         
         SS:  But he probably, still, when he moved into town - what would he
         have been, about 50?
         
         ME:  No, I think my brothers did most of the work by the time we moved
         to town. He might of done a few things around, but not very much.
         He kind of retired - he did retire. And when we first moved into
         town there was hardly any running water - nearly everybody had a
         pump. There was a pump almost on - well ours was on the back porch;
         that's where most of them were. But it wasn't very long that
         I remember we had coils put in the stove and a tank in back of
         the stove so we had a hot water tank., and had bathtub and so forth,
         but I don't know what year that was or a thing about it.
         
         SS:  What did you think of living in the town as compared to living
         in the country?
         
         ME:  Oh, times began to change by the time we came to town, and as I
         said, when we lived in the country I never heard anyone say
         anything about anybody, and that was kind of a pleasure. And then
         after you got into town, you began to hear things, and they'd,
         well, people talked more. And I guess they got to talking more
         all the time, and that was really about the only difference, as
         far as I know, because you had your own pleasure. You didn't have
         any money to spend, or you couldn't buy a lot of toys and things,
         you didn't have - you might get a doll for Christmas.
         
         SS:  Was there much different in the - it sounds like you had more con
         veniences in town, at least...
         
         ME:  Oh, yes, we did because shortly after we got to town, as I said,
         it wasn't- I think that he started working on that probably right
         after we moved in and put the water in the house so we-had running
         water and could have a bath without taking it in the washtub.
         
         SS:  Do you think that meant very much to, like your mother, to have
         the conveniences?
         
         ME:  Oh, land, yes. Sure it would mean quite a lot. The work was less,
         but then she didn't - well, we did: have a cow in town,, too, for
         quite a while; they had, my dad had a barn, and quite a few people
         had a cow and milked the cow for years, and sometimes we had two
         cows in there. But we had our own milk and he still raised the
         animals on the ranch, did the butchering and so forth. But
         things have changed considerably. I don't know what a young person
         would do, today, if they were put back in that situation; they'd
         be lost, and we were perfectly happy. We didn't know any better.
         
         SS:  You would have lost the connection with knowing how to do things
         and knowing how to cope with it, because when you grew up that's
         the way it all was, and now we're so far away.
         
         ME:  Yeah, that's right. Yes, it is. No, you had to do what had to be
         done, and you couldn't hire things done. We did have a hired girl
         a time or two, but not for very long.
         
         SS:  What year were you born in?
         
         ME:  You're asking my age.
         
         SS:  Well, I thought I was being a little more delicate than that.
         (Laughter) Just-think of it as for the historical record, really.
         
         ME:  I was born in '97.
         
         SS:  I was just trying to think of how old you would have been when you
         were getting through high school. Did you work at all at that time
         when you were in high school finishing?
         
         ME:  Huh-uh. No, very few people did. My sister, after she went to
         college and was teaching, she was gone a lot and she'd come home
         in the summertime she used to clerk in one of the stores usually
         through the summer, but I never did. I helped more in the house
         with the housework.
         
         SS:  After you finished high school what did you do?
         
         ME:  Got married.
         
         SS:  Right away?
         
         ME:  (Laughter) It was foolish to get married, young like that, but
         sometimes they do. They still do.
         
         SS:  Uh-huh. Do you think it's better to have some experience with
         living first before you get married, to grow up a little more?
         
         ME:  No, I don't. No, I think that people, times have just changed is
         all. It's different. I've thought so many times that if my
         mother and dad would see what was going on today, I wonder what
         they'd think.
         
         SS:  I wonder, what do you think they'd think?
         
         ME:  They wouldn't believe it. I don't believe they could believe that -
         it took so little to satisfy a person, you really - you didn't
         demand anything of people. I don't think they did, as far as
         I know. You got along with what you had, you knew that was it.
         
         SS:  I think I should get going. I've stayed quite a while. I
         really enjoyed talking with you. In fact, I'd like to, if it
         would be okay, maybe...
         
         ME:  I said I don't remember those things, because it didn't mean anything
         to me. I thought, you know, everybody was the same, and I thought
         everybody told the truthfand I thought everybody was honest. I
         didn't think that anybody would take anything that didn't belong
         to them. We weren't raised that way, and I don't think any of
         them were then. I just don't know.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13432</xmlfilename>
      <previous>East</previous>
      <next>Eikum1</next>
      <disp_name>Edwards</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
