<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">12/16/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Dora Otter Fleener, 1974-12-16, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:27:50</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Fleener, Dora Otter</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife; housekeeper; author of Coming West from South Dakota</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894</birthyear>
      <residence>Rural Moscow</residence>
      <origin>Family moved from South Dakota in 1902</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#vigilantes"&gt;vigilantes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#authors"&gt;authors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#harvesting"&gt;harvesting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#writing"&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Colfax"&gt;Colfax&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13431</file_name>
      <mp3>13432.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13432.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Dave Fleener; father-in-law built shelter near Moscow; Fourth of July in Colfax</title>
            <synopsis>Her father-in-law, Dave Fleener, built a
               shelter when he homesteaded near Moscow.
               Horses often lost in "round-up" drives to
               Montana; rumor of vigilantes. Lard oil
               lights. Riding was cross-country. Fourth
               of July in Colfax.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Dance at Steptoe; helped people by trading for wood; turns down offer for free Moscow
               property
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Coming back from dance at Steptoe, his partner
               thinks they're lost, but Dave lets his horse
               find the way. Mr. Boles, the Viola storekeeper,
               helped people by trading for wood instead of
               money. Dave's first plowing with a breaking
               plow. He turns down offer from Lieuallen for
               free Moscow property, if he built a shack on it.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Hauled grain to Walla Walla; working harvest in Touchet; thrashing machine</title>
            <synopsis>Two days to haul grain to Walla Walla. Their
               first market. High cost of freight for
               needles. Working harvest in Touchet. feeding
               bundled grain in the thrashing machine.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Injuries to men breaking horses; crossing Siskiyou Summit; Pit River Native Americans;
               tuberculosis; diphtheria
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Injuries to men breaking horses. Crossing
               Siskiyou Summit on foot in deep snow. Pit
               River Indians unable to leave reservation to
               forage for food, causing their rebellion.
               An Indian with no clothes in the cold. Blowing
               on a trumpet to cure tuberculosis. Burnt alum
               and slippery elm bark cure for diphtheria.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Wild Davey and Will Drannan; women afraid of Wild Davey</title>
            <synopsis>Wild Davy and Will Drannan (author of 31 Years
               on the Plains and in the Mountains) were not
               the same man. Fleener family knew them both.
               Wild Davey hunted with a dog pack. Women
               were afraid of him; one threw a pan of dishwater
               on his head.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1680</time>
            <title>Drunk who tipped over his buggy</title>
            <synopsis>A drunk who used to holler at people; he
               tipped over his buggy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Music in saloons; Republican kids called Democrat kids names</title>
            <synopsis>She was attracted by sound of music in saloons.
               During T. Roosevelt's campaign, Republican kids
               called Democrat kids "damn rats. Lowery revival
               meetings (1912). The Methodist preacher was loud.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Threshing; working in the cookhouse; men harvested</title>
            <synopsis>Early threshing. Working in the cookhouse was
               a long, hard job. Men enjoyed harvest, though
               it was dirty work. Sucking eggs for entertainment
               Women might do a big project at home while the
               men were away in harvest.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2940</time>
            <title>Problems over order of threshing farms; spectator and engineer jobs</title>
            <synopsis>How problems over the order of threshing farms
               could arise. Combine owner could disagree
               Separator and engineer were top jobs. Hauling
               on bundle wagons.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3360</time>
            <title>First car; poor road conditions; cars were an impractical fad</title>
            <synopsis>The first car she remembers, a Hudson about
               1912. They weren't too useful because road
               conditions were poor, but roads improved as
               cars increased. Changing tires was difficult.
               Many thought cars were an impractical fad.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>Henry Fleener wrote for Drannan's book; events in the Modoc country</title>
            <synopsis>Henry Fleener (Dave's half-brother) and his wife did much of the writing for Drannan's
               book. Henry's kids enjoyed reading what had
               been written that day. Dave was asked to
               provide verification for events in the Modoc
               country, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Drannan's book</title>
            <synopsis>More about Drannan's book writing; he wasn't married in Moscow.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Steptoe Butte; first hot rods</title>
            <synopsis>The road to Steptoe Butte. First hot rods
               were "mud slingers."
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Working to own a piano; bedbugs; working in a Methodist parsonage</title>
            <synopsis>Her experience working out. Working to own
               a piano. Putting up with bedbugs cooking for
               a harvest crew. Unpleasant work in a Methodist
               parsonage; difficult washing; helping a
               dressmaker.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>Father's cures; cures for sore throat, diphtheria, fevers, earache; predicted weather;
               ghosts; believed in airplanes 
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sons to carry on the Fleener family name.
               Father's cures: turpentine or kerosene for sore
               throat; coal tar for horses; blowing sulphur
               down the throat to prevent diphtheria; aconite
               and belladonna for fevers; blowing tobacco
               smoke in the ear for earache. He predicted
               weather from the sky. A board on the grass
               will kill it during certain phases to the moon. David Fleener's father went with his
               wife to the spring because of ghosts; a
               report from heaven. Ansel Fleener, David's
               father, believed in airplanes.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5220</time>
            <title>Wild Davey and Will Drannan</title>
            <synopsis>More about Davey and Drannan.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Working out before marriage. Life during threshing season. Father-in-law's
         homesteading near Moscow (1870's). Controversy over identities of Wild Davey and William
         Drannan. Home rememdies. 12-16-74 1.5 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: The shelter that he built when he first cane here.
         
         DORA FLEENER: He must have brought some of the stuff with him. Like big
         baards and things like that when he come. He brought his wagon and team
         up from Walla Walla country. And he built his first house,put a
         canvas over the top, his tarp that he used for freighting.He built
         kind of a two board high for it. That winter it wasnft cold or
         anything. They didn!t get much snow and his horses could, he staked
         one out early days was the people were driving horses in the country
         to Montana. They picked up everything that was loose. And sometimes
         a horse that was running on the range, they'd let 'em out.They let
         by themselves. Colts and stuff. And they'd come and see
         hprses coming, they'd come into a band, them horses. They'd
         a bunch. They wouldn't try.to separate 'em out and he
         lost several that way. And two year olds or something like that.
         Sometimes they'd round 'em up on purpose 4
         Montana needed, the: some reason, I don't know That was
         a year or two after he came there of course.
         
         SS:  Did he ever mention vigillante days?
         
         DF:  He did. Coi rse, he wasn't in it but he heard about it.He said he
         knew a woman that.husband didn't come back and she suppposed that
         the vigillantes caught him. String him up. It was going on in other
         parts of Idaho around here. Cows, horse thieves. Horse thieving and
         cow thieving at that time. He didn't have anything personally to do
         with it himself though.
         
         SS:  He'd heard this where he'd lived?
         
         DF:  Oh yes. Another thing I didn't include in my part of it there was
         the first lights they had. Lard oil they'd use in a can, they' crimped
         the can. a cloth in there and light it like that.
         
         SS:  That was a pretty basic way to get your light.
         
         DF:  It wouldn't give much light. Smokey too, I think.
         
         SS:  What about early day social life?
         
         DF:  They had dances. Mostly dances. And parties.Viola was the first town close
         by. Viola and Palouse.And people would congregate in there and dance. They
         had saloons in those days too. They had a high old time, I guess. They
         used to go horseback riding too. He'd go in the wintertime or anytime
         they ride horseback. It was the only way that the go. Go to a
         celebration, they took awagon and the whole family went. On 
         seats, they'd put a board across it, wagon box you knoo.Drive twenty miles
         that way..Across the country. Talked about going to Colfax to the
         the fourth of july celebration one time, hey had somebody stay home and look
         after their stock while they, if they couldn't get back tten.They wouldn't
         come back the same day, they'd stay overnight probably. Celebrate.
         and bunting. It was trimmed up gay. I can
         remember in my day, the horses and flags in their bridles, you know.
         They had flags on 'em.Speaker's stand was all draped with bunting, red
         white and blue bunting.
         
         SS:  The roads were almost not any.
         
         DF:  No they weren't.
         
         SS:  It was cross country?
         
         DF:  We'd do as much as we could. Course they had to widen some oT the hills.
         They had some way of going, some trail of some kind.Nothing very direct.
         They could of course, but then, some people couldn't, go straight through
         because too hilly . Then after that, after they get so dusty that they
         couldn't hardly stand it, the automobile came to the country anyway,A
         dust, they couldn't see where they were going. Course, that was
         later.
         
         SS:  What about the night that he and his friend thought they were lost coming
         down from a dance?
         
         DF:  I think they went to Steptoe that night, a long ways off and^came back in
         the middle of the night. And it was kind of foggy and snow on the ground.
         Couldn't hardly tell with the ice* and everything, where they were.No
         fences and no buildings they could see. To tell where, any marks that
         they recognize. But they, Huoes thought that they should have taken
         the wrong direction all the time, but Dave, he knew what to do. He gave
         his horse free reign and let it go home by itsfclf.And he kept telling
         Hughes how they would find dome kind of a shack. Somebody'd stay over the
         rest of the night, they'd get their bearings later. He kept going and
         kept going, pretty soon they came to a barn building. He turned his horse
         and went right in the barn. He recognized thetld place. The horse had
         taken 'em back.
         
         SS:  Did he ever talk to you about any of the old characters that he knew?
         
         DF:  I don't think he did. Hughes was the only one that was with him. Course
         it was, Mr. Boles, he was the store keeper at, and postmaster at Viola.
         He was quite a character but people.liked him . well because he
         was on the side of people that didn't have much to eat. He'd take wood
         in place of, trade wood for provisions for wood, rather. And that way they
         got along pretty well. He had as many as two hundred cords. in his back
         yard one time. He traded for people.
         
         SS:  Is that where Dave Fleener did his trading, Viola?
         
         DF:  He did for a while, I guess. And Moscow, Viola was only three miles from
         there. Moscow is farther. About eight miles from there. Or something like
         that.
         
         SS:  What about the first plowing that he did?
         
         DF:  Yes, he did the first plowing that first year he was there. It was such
         an open winter. Two horses and a breaking plow. He brought a breaking plow
         with him. Few utensils, few things like that. He knew he'd need. He got
         his lumber to build his next house next year.Wide board, they call it
         board and batten, don't they? They built that the next year. An abetter
         house. Had the lumber from Viola, I think, or some sawmill around. They
         were getting up sawmills by that time. Those first boards were immense,
         wide things..Wide boards, there's a few of *em around the countryrnoo in
         old houses. Big timber, you know.
         
         SS:  Did he ever tell you why he turned down Liueallen's offer to start up in
         the town there?
         
         DF:  In the first place, he didn't want to have any town property. Liueallen
         asked him twice to trade with him. He told him he'd just build a shack
         there in town..Have it. He didn't care anything about town. He had all he
         could do with keeping up his own homestead. And then he asked him again
         to trade his team. Well he needed a team so he Couldn't do that. He
         wasn't interested.
         
         SS:  he talk about seeing how the country got built up with people?
         
         DF:  Well yes. One party that came across that settled there, he came to take
         up the land right across the road from him, would be the road now on the
         west side. But the woman was, she didn't think there would be any, just
         be isolated country, always like it was then. She didn't like it so they
         never even unpacked their stuff. Long before Mr. Collins came in with his
         family and they settled. Didn't take long for the country to settle up.
         Railroad commenced to come in about the '80's. Things commenced to be
         quite normal then after that. Took so long to get the grain to Walla
         Walla. Took two days, I think, to get all that grain to Walla Walla. The
         first market. Take the grain down there and then they'd get some provisions
         that would last them a year..I guess I told you about the woman that
         wanted to buy a package of needles. She finally went to Walla Walla and
         that was the only thing she could find. She said,"How come so much? Why
         does it have such a big price on it?" "Freight." he told her. For needles,
         she didnH think; that was very much. I guess some of the stuff was freighted
         to Walula River and then the river took it out to Portland, out that way.
         
         SS:  Did he tafck about going to Walla Walla himself?
         
         DF:  I don't think aa did. He tried freighting one time but that was before
         he took up the claim, I think. He didn't like freighting because he
         couldn't use his team. Wasn't cut out for freighting anyway. He didn't*.
         
         SS:  What was it that he told you about the early harvests that he worked in?
         
         DF:  Worked down the Touchet, go down in the summertime, he'd leave his place
         in the summertime. Harvest. Heading
         outfits. Threshing outfits.And I guess after he got to finally,he
         the bundles for the threshing machines. He'd feed it, he'd have a bundle
         cutter on each side of him. He'd take the bundle and put »em into the
         machine,And course, it worked pretty fast. And he'd reach
         out for the bundles and if a fellow was cutting the string at the same
         time, it might get jammed. It was pretty risky to do it really. Told about
         that,I guess up and down there, two of them at the bundle. Threshing
         bundled grain. It was a job. He was the feeder in the threshing team. He
         couldn't feed too fast. Too slow, they wanted to keep it up. Steady bunch
         all the time. Take somebody who was an expert to know just how much to put
         in. Not to put in.
         
         SS:  You mentioned that the bronc busting, the guys that were doing that were
         getting hurt.
         
         DF:  The wild horses, the broncs, bring 'em to ride, get on 'em, just ride 'em.
         Not like they do in the rodeo now. They wouldn't ride 'em for eight minutes
         or three minutes. They stayed with 'em and they broke 'era in. And he
         never tried it because he'd see what it did to the fella that rode em.
         He said they'd bleed from the ears, the nooe. 'Cause of the jarring. Stick
         with 'em though.That was in the earlier days, in California, I imagine.
         
         SS:  And the long trek that he took into Oregon over Siskiy ou Summit? His
         partner didn't think they were going to make it?
         
         DF:  He was a kid. He was sixteen, I think, at the time. I think they went from
         the end of thefstage line and they had, the stage didn't run over the,
         was a bad road and high parts of the mountain, snow, so they took that.
         It didn't take 'em very long to walk it. a day and a night or some
         thing like that. I think most of it was on top of snow. The snow's crust
         was hard. It wasn't too hard to go. But he way. To get
         there. So he was lost on the way. I guess he'd been across it before so
         he knew about where. He had a hatchet and an axe and he chopped places
         in the trees as he went along I guess, and when they come through there,
         why, he could see how deep the snow was. Way up in the trees.
         
         SS:  This friend of his thought they weren't going to make it?
         
         DF: Yeah. It was a long one for the kid. He couldn't see
         
         SS:  It seems like he had a lot to do with the Hood River Indians.
         
         DF:  Yes. A lot of the time f think in every other time just kind of
         camped out. Like cowboys do sometimes. They come in. Run those provisions.
         Probably made their ^ camped there, in those badlands, well they're
         not badlands exactly there. Z-M* beds with their grass. That's
         where the cattle grazed. The Indian country there. He was in Indians in
         the north end of California, his own claim. He took a claim there first.
         Built a shack there, and the Indians used to come, knock on his door, and
         they didn't knock on his door, they walked in. Hungry as could be and couldn't
         feed all of 'em. So he had to put a stop to that. The dog got so he wouldn't
         let an Indian come close to the house after awhile. It was pitiful. They
         didn't have any clothes on or anything. Shawl over their back. The 
         United States wouldn't provide them anything to eat or anything to wear and they couldn't
         leave
         the reservation to hunt.Fish like they should have been able to.The.
         state, they would go in, big camas and get provisions for the winter here
         and there. They'd be in their own part of the country but on the reservation,
         dasn't leave it. Reason it made the trouble I guess. Someone bound
         to go off. And that's the trouble, the Army trying to make 'em stay on it.
         They were so hungry that if they found anything dead, if a cow died or
         anything, they'd eat it anyway. No matter how long it'd been dead, they
         were so hungry.
         
         SS:  What were a couple amusing incidents that he told you took place between
         him and the Indians?
         
         DF:  The one I remember now was about the Indian in cold weather and he didn't
         have much on him. the bottom and he said,"Aren't you cold there?" And he said,"No,
         face no
         cold." Used to it. fit He didn't think that the Indians they hung, that they hung
         there were
         that Scar faced Charlie and I can't remember the other name now.
         
         SS:  Is that Captain 3ack?
         
         DF:  Captain Dack.He didn't think they were anything that bad.They were supposed
         to have shot 'em, a soldier, an officer in the army or something.
         
         SS: What did he say about, he wasn't down there at the time, was he?
         
         DF:  No, but he heard about it. He was right there at the time. And of course
         he knew 'em probably at the time. Probably on the reservation at that time
         or that part of the country, but he wasn't there to see the actual trouble.
         
         SS:  As I remember, they chased the Indians pretty hard.
         
         DF:  Yeah, they did.
         
         SS:  You mentioned that when he was younger his brother had T.B. They had a
         pretty unusual kind of cure?
         
         DF:  They had a trumpet that he could blow on, that would straighten his
         lungs.
         
         SS:  Made me think they probably didn't know anything what to do.
         
         DF:  There wasn't anything they could do hardly. anything you know.
         
         SS:  This diptheria epidemic, Dave's father had his own home cure?
         
         DF:  Yeah, burnt elm and slippery elm bark.
         
         SS:  I wonder where he picked that up from.
         
         DF:  I read something the other day about early rememdies and something.I guess
         maybe done by Whitnan county Quarterly. This historian that elm tea was
         good for diptheria. Didn't say slippery elm, didn't say anything about
         burnt elm either, but(pause in tapp)
         
         SS:  You know about Wild Davey?
         
         DF:  Well, there was a supposition^ if he was the same as Will Drannan or not.
         Will Drannan wrote a book, or he didn't write it, but he told the story
         of 31 Years on the Plains and in the Mountains maybe you've heard it.
         And Wild Davey, many people think he's the same man. We knew ^different
         because the Fleeners knew both of 'em. Because one of the Fleeners helped
         Drannan write it up. He was a newspaper man anyway and Drannan told him
         the story and he wrote it, see. And Wild Davey was a fella up in the
         mountains, wore long hair about the same as Drannan and I guess that's
         reason they got confused. But Wild Davey lived in the mountains and he
         had dogs. He was a hunter. He'd hunt coyotes, cougars, that was his
         business.He had so many dogs, they claim he used to eat them too. There's
         a story, tell about living in the time, these kids told about the time
         she met Wild Davey, he lived up in the mountains here, Moscow Mountain
         out of Troy there somewhere. And the womenfolks, they used to be afraid
         of him.Men were out harvesting, afraid of him, and they would ride their
         kids on horseback and go stay with each other, neighbors. One day Mrs.
         Kissing Wild Davey would be coming up to the house, she was just finishing
         washing the dishes. She met him out the corner of the house and threw
         the dishwater over him as he came around the corner of the house.(laughs)
         One way of fixing him. Never bothered her anymore I guess. He wasn't going
         to bother her anyway probably. But he used to come, the Fleeners tell
         about how he came one time to horses, the horses got away and
         he went into the country, try to find them. So they went in there and got
         acquainted with him. They knew them well, they were two different people.
         Now I've run across people that knew they were different here. But not
         very many of the people knew it.
         
         SS:  I heard that Wild Davey used to tell some wild stories. That had something
         to do with why people thought he was Drannan. I heard him called the Wind
         jammer.
         
         DF:  I don't know about that, but he was, I wouldn't be a bit surprised if he
         they did. This Mr. Gamble, Lola Clyde's brother, he said he used to work
         in the harvest with him, that Wild Davey, he didn't have much sense. He
         couldn't write a book he said, or anything. His name was O.C.
         he said. Right name was. He was, on my side anyway, I try to prove these
         things if I can, I go around, try to find his, somebody said he was buried
         in Troy cemetery and went down to Troy one day and I asked the post*
         if he knew where the cemetery is and she said,"Which one?" She said,"There's
         seven of 'am around here." I wasn't about to hunt 'em all up and find out.
         
         SS:  Do you think he really did bother the ladies?
         
         DF:  No, I don't think so.Anyway, he had long hair and he looked like he was
         wild you know, and he had so many dogs and he lived by himself. They were
         afraid of anybody that didn't look right, I suppose. New country,
         of.most anything that didn't look quite right I suppose.
         
         SS: Are there any other characters that you heard about?
         
         DF:  Can't recall any right now. We knsw a man that used to get drunk a lot
         and he used to stop at the schoolhouse and wave to us and the teacher.
         And if we were out playing in the yard and one time he came by my home,
         my mother was out hanging out clothes and he stopped and yelled to her.
         She didn't pay any attention to him, I was scared to death. I was about
         seven, eight years old then. But since we moved to Whitman county, be
         moved over there too and he used to come home drunk at night. And one
         night he and his wife stayed all night in the straw stack 'cause they
         couldn't get home. Another time he run off the road and tipped over the
         buggy and it didnH hurt him, but he lost his hat. That him worse
         than anything else 'cause he lost his hat.
         
         (End of side A)
         
         DF:  Steffens shotf. nire in Moscow, that happened just before we came. Read
         about it and heard about it, but....
         
         SS:  What about the drive for prohibition in this county? Was there strong
         feeling?
         
         DF:  I think there was. In town there was. I oWt know whether they had any
         big fights or anything about it, but then, they had lots of saloons in
         here when they first came. I used to hear the music and I wanted to go
         in so bad,'cause I loved music and they had music. That old saloon piano
         would just, tantilizing to me. It wasn't very many years that they had the
         saloons after we came. And parades and a lot of things like that to get
         up support against the saloons. And they went out and they'd booze anyway.
         In our neighborhood there was a family that moved away and a new family
         came in and they didn't seem to have much to do with anybody. People didn't
         go to visit 'em they always noticed applesauce cooking on the stove.EVery
         time they mentioned that, there was people coming and going more or less
         at night, they noticed. After a while the authorities caught on to it
         and they had a still in their house, a trap door in the pantry^and they,
         that was the nearest we ever came to it.
         
         SS:  Do you think it cut down the drinking, to have prohibition?
         
         DF:  I don't know. They say it didn't. I don't know, I couldn't tell.
         
         SS: What about the women's right to vote?
         
         DF:  I don't remember anything about that. I don't think it affected us much.
         At least I don't remember my folks ever saying anything. Course they
         weren't people to say much about anything any way.They didn't discuss
         anything in front of us kids, seems like. ^they'd done more of it I think
         I'd been a little bit better informed, at the early age, than I was. They
         never spoke anything bad about anybody or anything, why or wherefore. I
         know we were going to school when they had, I guess,.when Teddy Roosevelt
         was coming into, up for election. Part of the kids were from Republican
         parents, and part were Democrats. We.called them "damn rats"
         Not to their face.(laughs) The Munson girls were democrats, or fepublicans.
         Their father was in the legislature in. Idaho at that time. So, pretty
         strong Republicans. But that's about as much as I rmember about being
         involved in politics at all.
         
         SS:  What about the revivals that came to Moscow? Did you have anything to do
         with them?
         
         DF:  Only one of 'em I think. The Lowery meetings, that was the only one I
         rmember anything about. That was a preacher and Moody was the choir leader.
         I liked to sing so I was in the choir. Anybody that wanted to sing, they
         could sing. The funny part of it was, he had a chair at the, on the
         platform, and Ican't rememberin the back, you
         know how it is. You know what the spindles are, don't you?
         
         SS:  Explain it to me.
         
         DF:  The thing that go up and down the back And he wanted
         to get the attention of the audience or the congregation he 'd rip that
         baton across that and make that .noise. Everybody was startled and they
         quit talking and pay attention. That was in a tent, I guess that was in a
         tent.So about it, I  Took about a Fourth of a block there
         betwen Jefferson and Third. The sawdust on the floor and I don't know whether
         they had benches or what, backs to 'em anyway. Kind of a crude outfit.
         We had lots of fun in it. That winter there was an awful lot of snow too.
         out any It was deepv they didn't plow snow. People didn't shovel off their
         walks or anything either. Tramp the snow down on top of the drift and
         pack the snow and kept on the trail, that's all they did. Course, farmers
         liked snow in town because they had to use sleds in the country and
         they'd come clear down to town in sleds. They couldn't run, didn't have
         any snowplows anyway.
         
         SS:  Do you remember when this was?
         
         DF:  1912. February 1912.
         
         SS:  You performed for the adults? The choir?
         
         DF:  Well they gave the altar call they were supposed to leave the platform
         and go down among, mingle with the people and ask tiiem if they were
         Christians and if they wouldn't want to be. I wasn't very good at it, I
         just kind of bluffed it.(laughs)Never was very good with words anyway.
         a point. That part of it I didn't do too well.
         
         SS:  Was it a quiet or noisy meeting? Did peopoe get excited?
         
         DF:  It wasn't that kind. I remember it was quite tame. It was quite successful
         as far as I remember. I was used to really a laud preacher anyway. The
         Methodist preacher they had at that time was really a stomper rounder.
         Pace up and down the platform, up and down the pulpit. Pound his podium
         or whatever you call it. And So I don't know, I was used to being pretty
         loud preacher anyway, so maybe it was ordinaryHe must nave
         been there about two weeks I think.It was my second year of high school,
         I think, that year.Tihe choir was made up of young people, mostly
         school kids, I think. 
         
         SS:  I would like to know about the early threshing operations. What are the
         earliest ones you know about?
         
         DF:  Well, I saw a few that were very feeble. The engine wasn't powerful enough
         to propel itself.They hitched horses on to it to pull it out. And, from
         one place to another. I heard about, somebody telling about a story, I
         guess they were about that day, they were telling about early day
         threshing. The horses were pulling this machine through this, one thing
         to another. It dropped into a ditch, the front end of it, they drove it
         into a ditch and the horses couldn't pull it out. He was talking about
         it while they were eating dinner one day. The kind of worried
         about it. She said,"It didn't knock the water closet off. Laughs don't know
         And the tank was in front of the engine room, I smokestack, come
         pretty close to the ground. But it made all them people laugh because
         the water closet was the toilet in those days. But wasn't long before they
         got so.the engine would pull the separator. 'Bout '90, whatever * Just
         very few of 'em that couldn't pull, propel themselves around. Got bigger
         and bigger and bigger, you know, til they couldn't accomodate all the
         men in the homes so somebody had the. idea to build a cookhouse. That was
         with the machine always you know. I guess as many as thirty or thirty
         men in the crew then, at that time.Big outfits. The money then was real
         cash, they knew begining of the way very easy. Busy man had a team
         he'd take out and team the wagon with it, paid pretty good
         
         SS:  What was the cooking situation like?
         
         DF:  It was pretty awful I'd think. They had to get up pretty early in the
         morning.They had pretty long days because the farmers wanted the work done
         before the rain came, and for the right season. Got up about three thirty
         in the morning and went to the cookhouse, the kerosene lamps, started
         the fire and get breakfast. The men slept in the straw stack and the
         fireman, I guess he was the one that woke 'em up in the morning. He was
         the one that had to get up.steam to get up fire. He's ready to go right
         after breakfast. Men had to get up and feed and harness their horses
         too. .to be done before breakfast. Had to get up early too. The
         cooks,Ima Platz, he tells about the experience, she worked for seven
         years for the same man. And she was saying that, well they had to be
         real economical with their , they had to their meals on
         time. She said they had to fry a whole milk pan full of steaks for break
         fast. Had everything, warm biscuits you know. Baking powder biscuits and
         everything that goes along, eggs andAeverything. Moving day^. they were
         libel to pick up and move 'em any time, it didn't matter whether they
         were baking or what they were doing. She said they never lost any cakes
         or anything like that from falling or anything. Had to hold oQto the door^
         lot of times though when they rough around, leave the oven door
         open in the cookhouse. Be hotter in the dickens in there and you can
         imagine what it would be like in the summer. Wtta^ Had a side that
         they could raise and throgh.
         
         SS:  The sides raised?
         
         DF:  Kind of like awning. They had a water barrel outside where they set it
         outside with a little platform, it was by the cookhouse too. Fhe flunky
         kept that full of water for the cooks. And kept the wood split for 'em
         in ahandy place. Went to town and got the provisions for 'em and all.
         Got their milk from the country. If they had cows they might want to
         he'd go and get milk for 'em. The only refrigeration they had was just
         a tub of water to milk in. How they got along.
         
         SS:  Did she talk about how hard the work was?they got the Uork done at night. They
         practically met
         themselves getting up in the morning, she said.Didn't come to eat until
         they couldn't thresh any more. Had to go up to work, the men had to do
         all their work.
         
         SS:  What about the work of the crewsi Seems like the work was dusty.
         
         DF:  Sure it was, it was terrible. didn't have any
         blower and they had to keep mowing that straw back from, put it out on
         the straw stack with a draper, and the draper'd drop down. They'd keep
         em out of that back, and that was terrible hard, dusty work. That chaff.
         They'd hang handkerchief over their face to keep inbreathing it so much.
         
         SS:  Did they have a hard time holding the crews?
         
         DF:  No, they loved it. People just, the men liked to get together for one thing.
         They had a big time.And they'd all try to outdo each other in the working.
         Course, they didn't know any better to do that in those days, there
         wasn't any clean way to do anything. Sleeping in the straw stack wasn't
         very good either. Idon't think. They'd be pretty dirty and chaffy. Menfd
         be full of chaff.
         
         SS:  Did they take much time to socialize when they weren't working? Story telling?
         DF- They didn't have time, they didn't have time at all. Sometimes they'd have
         time to go and suck eggs. a tell about how they use to, when the
         young fellas used to rob the chicken houses of some farmers they knew
         raal well and knew they wouldn't care and they'd see if they couldn't suck
         the eggs. They'd try to get one of them fellas to suck eggs and he
         wouldn't, it just come right back up again, he just couldn't stand it.
         Some would like it.
         
         SS:  Dust put a hole in the egg and suck it?
         
         DF:  Yeah.I muldn't like that very well either, would you?
         
         SS:  I hear that old saying, "They sure broke him from sucking eggs."
         
         DF:  Here, they don*t know any better to suck eggs, too, they'd make that
         remark.
         
         SS:  Were most of the guys in the crew local?
         
         DF:  Yeah. Usually family men. Leave their wives at home an^go out and make
         money. That wasAthe only money they made the year, real cash. Iknow
         my sister, she used to, her husband'd go out to work, why she'd always
         get up and do something important like papering or some big job. She
         couldn't do very well when she had to get meals together. Either she'd
         change her furniture around one time,Ashc*h'a*nge her bedroom or her living
         room. Change the bedroom to the living room and the living room to the
         bedroom. Came back from working Saturday night, couldn't find the bed(laughs)
         But they always worked a full week and they came home, nobody work
         on Sundays, those days.And the stores didn't open, they couldn't buy anything.
         And the blue law at one time, it was against the law to have anything open.
         But they'd come home, get a change of clothes, take a sort of a bath, I
         suppose. Jump in the creek or something. They didn't have any bathing
         facilities at all. Shower or bath.(pause in tape)
         
         SS:  That sounds like it was a celebration.
         
         DF:  It was, yes. Men looked forward to it every year. Get together for men.
         And have a high old time. I guess they played more or less pranks on
         each other while they worked. But then, they didn't stop work to do it.
         In the combine days, I know they used to play a prank on each other.
         They'd with grease when they were greasing the combine and
         stuff like that.They didn't have much time, and they were older men
         usually.
         
         SS:  How. would the threshing operation be owned by one guy?
         
         DF:  Yes.Partner sometime,but usually just one man ride the machine and
         he'd get around to everyone that he could. He'd ikoX* out in the country
         probably.They liked to have the best operating machine, one that didn't
         break down so much and the farmers would speak for him ahead of time.
         Supposed to come after so and so got his done, well then, they'd have
         theirs. Sometime he had a break doan and he couldn't get there and it
         looked rainy, why a farmer might get somebody els'e who was handy. That'd
         make the threshing machine man mad that was going to do his. Cheat him out
         of that much money. Work the other way too, sometimes.Somebody begged him
         and paid him a little bit, a bonus or something, he might,one fella,take
         somebody else's Wontf* or something, work both ways. And so, some
         hard feelings?started that way. So then when they got the combines, that
         didn't happen ajy more. Each man had his own, go into partnership, go into
         the combine business to sometimes. That wasn't too good either because
         one farmer wanted to do all the say so about it and the other one was
         pretty meek why he got left out, and if he wasn't meek why they had harsh
         words at each other. Now that we got the old combine, it cost an awful lot
         of money but then, they're in debt up to their ears. And they have more
         fun with it days if they want to and as long as they want to,
         nobody bothered 'em.
         
         SS:  The old threshing machines, they gave a lot of trouble?
         
         DF:  Well yes, it was like any machinery. If they didn't have it up good. It
         was a kind of rattletrap thing to start with anyway. Kind of older. Fix
         "em up with haywire, they didn't last. Then just like they did after, with
         their combine, now they have to get 'em probably in perfect shape before
         they even start or they end up having trouble during the season.
         
         SS: Were there jobs that were top jobs on the operation?
         
         DF:  Engineer and the separator man of course. The separator man was the owner
         because he, the separator was the biggest responsibility of the whole thing.
         Keep it going and and when it was about to break down or it was
         plugged up sometimes, watch it pretty careful And the fireman
         he had to know his business, had to keep up the steam all the time. Work
         straw, he had to keep stuffing in there pretty fast. They felt a little
         above everybody else. Easier than fireman and the sack sewer too, he was
         pretty important. Cook. Two women were cooking together. Hardly ever one
         could hardly manage to work alone.
         
         SS:  They usually, were they hired like the men were?
         
         DF:  Yeah. Well, yes they were. But if they wanted the job and they were the
         best one, why they'd take it. Weren't very many people that wanted the
         job of cooking because it was hard work and they had usually girls eighteen
         or so, single girls or else, young married women. They didn't have any
         she children, no responsibilities at home.Ima Platz young
         married women at that time. And the husband worked on the machine too.
         Dora Hill that was a partner with her, she was a married girl of eighteen
         I think at that time.
         
         SS:  Was the pay pretty good compared with the men's?
         
         DF:  I don't really know what the pay was. I imagine it was pretty good for the
         cook. I asked Ima if she was the head cook and she said no, they both
         shared alike. And said they, either one of 'em plans all the meals and
         the other one helps out. She said they just worked together. They got
         both the same pay I think. Eight ddllars a day was pretty good pay at that
         time. I know men carpenters oot three dollars a day. My dad had somebody
         build him a chicken house and he only paid him eight dollars a day, for
         carpenter work. The man, he had a team of horses and wagon, he'd get more
         for them. Wasn't much more, but...
         
         SS:  If he had that, then he'd haul the grain??
         
         DF:  Haul the bundles in, he was the bundle hauler. Go out in the field and
         pick up the shocks..Quite a number of them, six or eight or ten I guess,
         bundle wagona. Racks onto aw outfit and running gives along with the men.
         Team would be with the wagon. But they had to go all over the field and
         pick up the shocks. One man was armed with a gun and the other the bundle
         wagon, man that was on the ground, he'd take a bundle and throw it up to
         the fella on the wagon, and the fella on the wagon would catch it on his
         fork and put it in place. And they always put it so that when they handed
         it up so that when they took it down they wouldn't break the heads off.
         That's what, they load their wagon.
         
         SS:  What you remember, were they still using headers?
         
         DF:  No, they didn't use headers in my country at all. That was down the river
         from the Touchet country. All along Waitsburg and down that way. Seen
         pictures of 'em, but I never seen it, work at all.
         
         SS:  What do you remember about the first cars coming into the country?
         
         DF:  The first one I remember anything about was our neighbors had a car.^Had
         that about 1912, I imagine. I remember it didn't have any top on it and
         tne steerisDgu,heeonwSRe other side of what they have now . On the right
         hand side instead of the left. And all the gears on the side where the door
         would be on that running board. They all had running boards then too. Gears,
         brake and the honker. Squeeze on a bulb and it honked. I guess about that
         time we got a few doctors around town got cars, but the Lincoln country
         people couldn't use 'em. People in town couldn't get out in the country
         either, in the wintertime, becauseAmud and things.And they didn't clear
         the roads and there wasn't any road service or anything at that time.
         You could get a cax for about a thousand dollars. Got our first car in
         1917 I guess it was. Maxwell. The tires were so expensive and so hard to
         keep from cracking a nd deteriorating from the amount of sun, the ^would
         crack you know, and they had cotton fabric and if the rubber cracked then
         the water would get in there and cause a blowout and they had a lot of
         tire trouble in those days. If you had tire trouble, you had to fix your
         own, too. They had rims instead of wheels. Rims, the tire was on a rim
         and you'd unbolt it from the wheel and take it off and try to get the
         tire off the rim then. Some job to do that. Didn't have any hydraulic jack.
         You had to get under the car and put it under the axel. These lumberjacks,
         you've probably seen 'em, haven't you? Didn't have to go very high cinder 
         car in those days. The Model T was kind of car because they were
         higher off the ground and could,^didn't get hung up in deep ruts. And in
         the mountains where there were rocks and stumps still in the road, they
         used to be. They got more and more cars, then the roads were so dusty that
         they couldn't see where they were going, why they had to do something about
         the roads then, you see. One thing followed another that way. 'Bout 1917-18
         I think it was, a lot ofAcars come into the country.
         
         SS:  What did your folks think about cars when they first came in?
         
         DF:  I don't know what my folks thought. Used to hear a lot of talk about they'd
         never amount to anything because it wasn't practical to have and they
         scared too many horses and caused to many runaways and everything. They
         wouldn't last, they were a passing fad, they thought it was.(pause in tape)
         
         SS:  Is that where Drannan met the Fleeners?
         
         DF:  Yeah. They lived in Moscow. He came there to write, or every day the kids
         would go to read what they had written during the day, and had a great
         time reading because it was always interesting. And I know that they say
         that they called father, that's my husband's father, once in awhile
         to verify some of the facts, because he'd been in the Modoc war down there
         in California. So he helped out with that some. I know.
         
         SS:  That's where they helped him?
         
         DF:  Henry Fleener was the one that did most of the helping. He did most of the
         writing, he and his wife. He did the actual writing of it. I understand.
         They called him Dave Fleener, that's my husband's half-brother Henry.
         Being as how he'd been in the same part of the country they wrote about
         he wanted to verify some of the facts in the writing, that part of the
         country only. You've read that book, Jiaven't you?
         
         SS:  I've read the book by a man name Bate about that book called Frontier
         Legend. It was written to show that Drannan's was a bunoh of lies.
         
         DF:  Personally I've never read it, but I've heard that there is such a book.
         
         (End of Side B)
         
         SS:  Drannan's wife...
         
         DF:  He never had any wife.
         
         SS:  He was married later, after he was in Moscow. He didn't have a wife when
         he was here?
         
         DF:  No, I don't think so.I don't think he lived very long after that, did hej?
         
         SS:  I think he died in 1913. In the southwest.
         
         DF:  It was Seattle where he died.
         
         SS:  He was in Seattle for a while. The story that Bate tells is that he died
         in the Southwest.
         
         DF:  There might have been some of that story was not made up, but I know some
         of it wasn't either.I'm sure it wasn't all fiction.
         
         SS:  He was working on the book here in Moscow?
         
         DF:  Oh yes.That's a story about him one way or another, I don't know. All I
         know is what I know, that's all.
         
         SS:  I was wondering what you knew. When Dave's half brother was helping him,
         was he writing the stuff about Kit Carson?
         
         DF:  I guess so. Drannan told him the story and he wrote it down. He told me
         if'-r Drannan couldn't even write. I don't know about that, but he was^ able to
         put down what he wanted to say in good order, anyway. Been said that he
         went to the university and got it written. But I don't know if there's any
         truth in that. He might have got it rewritten or something, I don't know.
         They ended up there something. I know that Henry's kids, they were just
         youngsters, they liked to read his, what his folks had written day,
         every day. Because it was interesting. Theymust have written the whole
         thing I think from begining to end.As it was told to them.
         
         SS:  Did they think it was true?
         
         DF:  I suppose they did. I don't know. Never heard. One vja\j or 4he oAhey~.
         
         SS:  Bate's story is that it wasn't true.
         
         DF:  I know. I've heard that. They were telling something about that book.
         
         SS:  I've heard that they use to have dances up there. Yeah. It was quite a place.
         It was isolated one thing, and it was hard to
         get to it. Up there in that butte.
         
         SS:  How did the people get up there?
         
         DF:  They went horseback mostly, I guess. Must have been some kind of a road
         up there. It was quite a feat to get the road cut out like it is now.
         You've been up there, haven't you?
         
         SS:  I haven't been up the top of the butte.
         
         DF:  A winding Doad and it wasn't very wide either.Kind of scary to look down
         the ledge. I don't like, I was born in the prairie country I guess, don't
         like these roads way up on the aide of the hills.(pause in tape)
         
         SS:  What do you remember about it burning down?
         
         DF:  We lived of the university, out in the country. About, it was sort
         of high. You see it burning in the middle of the night. We were looking
         out of our window upstairs window, see it. That's all I remember about
         it. People mourned about the fact that it burned up so many df their
         records and so many of their trophies and everything too.
         
         SS:  What was the kind of car you were describing that was a mud slinger?
         
         DF:  Boys,^all them mechanical minded and they'd see if they could find an
         old motor to fix up. And the chassis, they had to have a body to put
         it on. They'd build a wooden seat and bed for it, kind of a pick up thing
         out of it. Board across it'for a seat and a back. No fenders. Wasn't any
         fenders. Sling the mud if they went through mud. Be called mud slingers.
         
         SS:  Did you do much working out?
         
         DF:  Yeah, I did^a lot of it. My sister's older than I am and she wasn't very
         well, so she taught school but she didn't work out. She had an^
         that she'd teach. In those to teach you passed an examination. She taught
         school when she was eighteen. And she stayed home summers and I worked
         out then. Different places around the neighborhood. I was good at sewing,
         to sew and so I had me sewing and doing housework .
         Five dollars aaeek. Igot paid. Pretty good pay,days. Bought a piano
         and Ihad an awful time paying for it, Inever did get it entirely paid
         for. Ipaid a hundred dollars for it. My dad paid for it. He didn't think
         Ineeded it. But my mother spoke up for me and so I., got it. But I worked
         there for the people that had the piano, they wanted to get rid of it
         and so Iworked for them. Took the job before Iknew anything about the
         piano really, but Ifound out they wanted to get rid of the piano and
         Iwanted apiano so bad. Got achange to have it that way by turning my
         wages over to my dad, all that I made for that year I worked out. Worked
         out for one family while they were baling, balers, Idon't know how many
         men, awhole table full and they had so many flies. 0ne plaee- Iworked,
         the bedbugs ate me up at night. Terrible place to work. I worked for
         these other people that had the piano, Iworked there cooking, helping
         cook for the warehouse men and the sacks that came in, sacked all the
         grain at that time. They had men that piled the sacks in the warehouse.
         Whitman county in Pullman and Palouse.
         
         SS:  Theee people with the bedbugs, what were ou doing for them?
         
         DF:  Ifollowed the main cook. They had baler crew or two. Idon't know whether
         it was one or two crews, but Iknow that there was alot of men baling
         hay.
         
         SS:  Did you stick with the job?
         
         Week. That was all Ineeded. I didn't tell'em about the bedbugs because I
         knew, Ididn't want to complain or something Iguess. Idon't know why I
         didn't. Iguess Isuppose if Idid I'd need another room that wasJ, e£ bad
         Iwould have. Itold her when Isettled up Ithought Ideserved more than
         five dollars aweek. Adollar aday, Isuppose Iwas supposed to get a
         dollar a day there because Iwas alone.J. know the first night Iwent to
         bed, took alamp upstairs, we had coal, we didn't have electricity or any
         thing of course. And Iwas dead tired, got to bed awful late because I
         worked until dark and had to feed 'em after that and work afterwards.
         But Iwas tired and Iwent to sleep right away. So Icommenced to feel some
         thing crawling all over me and biting me. I had an idea what it was though
         I never experienced it before. I'd heard about 'em. So I got up and I
         thought I'll light the lampand they won't bother se then. Bedbugs never
         bothered anybody in the daytime. Bother you at night. I'd heard, I don't
         know whether that was true or not, but that's the way they bother mostly.
         But that didn't stop 'em. So I thought I'd let 'em have the bed and I'd
         qet down on the floor on the rug. They beat me to the rug I think. Couldn't
         i told her I didn't like the bedbugs and I
         thought I wought to have more pay,'cause I worked hard and put up with
         so much. She said,"Why didn't you tell me, I'd given you another room?"
         But I still figured the other room would be as bad as one. I was
         the kind to never complain, I always took things as they come.So.
         
         SS:  Did you get more pay?
         
         DF:  I got ten dollars.
         
         SS:  How did you feel about the piano after you got it? Had you played piano
         before?
         
         DF:  We had before and I loved it so much. But it didn't have a keyboard
         that I liked. I wanted a little more keys on it. Organ has so many octaves.
         Piano has more. I got an awful lot of good out of it though. I got
         married before I got it paid for. My husband paid the rest of it. Like
         35 dollars a hundred. I worked for a dressmaker too, in Pullman.
         Quite a long time, worked for my board while I was working over there
         so I wouldn't have to pay for my board. I don't remember what I got there
         but I got more there than I got for working for Dr. Rounds in Pullman
         too. Day work. We lived so far away I couldn't work for my board. I
         worked downtown too. So I got another p3a ce with a preacher and his wife,
         Methodist preacher. That was a terrible place, the parsonage. Oust a
         ramshackle of a place and I didn't like him either, so I quit there
         pretty soon. I don't know whether he left the country or why the family
         left. He got transferred or whether I just quite, but I got another
         job. I stay, room and board with another couple I had lots of fun with.
         They wanted me to play 500 I made an extra hand to play cards. I use
         to entertain 'em by kicking up in my bunny suit at night and try to take
         a light up to the ceiling. They had light on a string, hanging from the
         ceiling. Drop cord I guess they called it. It didnH have any shade on it
         or anything. But I had to do the washing there and oh my, I had to do it
         in the basement and everything was coal. Burn coal in the stove. Coal
         smoke in the mist and the air from that washing. Couldn't see anything)
         couldn't tell you were washing anything clean or anything.
         I didn't stay very long there either. Mrs. was the person I was
         working for there in She got ailing and couldn't keep up with her
         work so she called me. I was gonna go on and do dressmaking by myself, I
         had plenty of work that people had come and give me their work. But I was
         just tired out and I couldn't. Couldn't sleep nights for worrying about the
         work. So I quit that and got married. That's the end of that. I tried going
         to school too. Before I worked and before I started working in these places.
         After I worked at Cassidy, that was the place that found WSC, at that time.
         It's WSU now. One semester and I thought I'd - ' some credits there and
         I'd teach. But I got sick of that because I couldn't ge^t the subjects
         I wanted to andso I quit that and got married. Go out
         and took this other job, rather. Other jobs. And then I got married after
         that. 1916 I was married.
         
         SS:  What's a buny suit?
         
         DF:  All over night clothes. Feet And all.
         
         SS:  Did you know your husband long before you got married?
         
         DF:  Was quite a long time because he was in the same neighborhood with us.
         Bachelor, I don't think he would have ever got married if I hadn't picked
         him up. There was something queer about it. This Fleener that crossed the
         plains in '52 that got about here. My husband's father was the only male
         left from that family. See the one boy died across the plains. The other
         one died of T.B. That left only Dave, in that family, that was a male
         He had one son that was Ansel and my husband. And although this
         Samuel that crossed the plain in '52, he was married again. He had four
         sons that time and none of these sons ever had a manchild that carried
         on the name. So I'm the sole person that propigated the Fleener name.
         That strain. So I feel pretty good about marrying him, after all.(laughs)
         And it looked for a while as though my sons wouldn't have any manchild either.
         The oldest one didn't have any children at all, they had to adopt one.
         They managed to adopt a boy, when they was quite along in years. But
         another son, his first one was a girl. Youngest son , he didn't have any
         for a while because he aas younger. He finally came up with three. We
         got six boys out of the 29 grandchildren named Fleener. It's up to them
         now to carry it on. That one strain of the country,now.
         Escept for that one. Samuel.
         
         SS:  From looking at these cures, are there any you remember from your younger
         days, any home remedies you heard about or tried?
         
         DF:  I can't remember any around here. But my folks were great people to give
         us turpentine and sugar, and kerosene and sugar for sore throats.
         of sugar with a few drops of kerosene on it. Or turpentine or something
         like that. I remember.
         
         SS:  Did they work?
         
         DF: I don't know. Something to do I guess. I don't know. It didn't cure us
         right off, I know that.
         
         SS: What about when you were working with animals? Were there any tricks that
         you used for treating them?
         
         DF: Well, my dad used to use coal tar for everything. His time. I know, I didn't
         do that so much. He never had any horses have any wire cuts, but he'd use
         coal tar if they had 'em I know. Had one mare that bruised her hoof above
         the hair line, you know, the hoof. Thought sure she'd lose her hoof, but
         I don't know what he did, but she didn't lose her hoof after all.He was a
         great doctor, he was. He'd doctor those kids with home remedies. had
         a sore throat, he was awful worried about dintheria, It was that age when
         there was so much of that around.Looked down our throat and if he saw any
         white patches down our throat why he'd blow sulpher in our throat. Make
         a funnel out of a paper and put the small end and then he'd blow it down
         the throat. We breathed in ia lot of it go in our lungs. If any of 'em
         were drawing in their breatfcat that time, why, wasn't very comfortable.
         His remedy a kid. All through my life
         really. He used to, for fever, he'd give aconite and belladonna. In a few
         drops of water.We were supposed to take that every little bit. Teaspoonful
         or two. Earache, he'd blow tobacco smoke in our ear. He wasn't any hand to
         smoke a pipe or anything. He'd just have a corncob pipe. Mother would ask
         him to blow smoke in our ear, warm smoke. That was supposed to relieve the
         ache somewhat. I never 5-iock I usually treat 'em like I did
         wdath people. Stomachache, I'd give 'em a drop of peppermint or something
         like that.
         
         SS:  Did he have any beliefs about weather prediction?
         
         DF:  Oh yeah. Ansel's dad was a great hand to predict all the time about the
         circle around the sun mean so and so. He was a great one to believe in...
         
         SS:  Circle around the sun would mean what?
         
         DF:  Mean a storm. If the circle got bigger it meant the storm wasn't going to
         come, I guess. I think that's the way it went I might be wrong. But the
         sunrise and the sunset, the different colors meant so and so too. A
         colored sunrise meant a storm. And he was a great believer in planting
         in the dark of the moon and the light of the moon, too. Heard about that
         I guess. I don't know which is which. I suppose, plant things in the
         ground that have the roots in the ground certain dark or light of the
         moon. I don't know which it is.
         
         SS:  I think you plant things that grow in the ground with roots in the dark
         the ground.
         
         DF:  My dad never went for it at all, but he always had good crops. I don't
         know much of it myself. There's something in it, I guess, alright. If you
         put something like a board or something on the grass,it'll die out if it's
         in a certain time of the moon. Then a certain dark or light, it'll kill
         out.
         
         SS:  You mean the grass underneath the board?
         
         DF:  Yeah. It won't if it's the other. I don't know which is which, though.
         I've seen things die out laying on the ground that way.
         Some of it sticks down close to the ground and can't get it.
         
         SS:  Was he much of a believer in good and bad luck?
         
         DF:  I don't think so.No I don't think of that. I don't think they were
         superstitious. anything like that. Like cats or a ladder or anything
         like that. He never mentioned it.Talked about his grandfather, though.
         Grandpa Fleener telling about his grandpa. Ansel's father's father. He'd
         could see a ghost, seems like his wife had to go after water down in the
         spring. They were back east in Indiana or Missouri or someplace. And he
         was afraid of this ghoat and he'd go with his wife to get water and let
         her bring the water back. Go with her keep this ghost from bothering her.
         Story they used to tell.
         
         SS:  Did he know where the ghoat came from?
         
         DF:  No. there at the spring. That's all he. It might molest his wife
         and so he went with her to keep the ghost away from her.
         
         SS:  And let her carry the water?
         
         DF:  Yeah. I don't know why he didn't go alone then. I could never figure out,
         but that's the way the story went.
         
         SS:  Did you ever hear that out here? People coming back after death?
         
         DF:  Well let's see. He used to tell us stories about such things. He said
         there was a girl one time that died and then she came back to life and
         they asked her what she saw. She said while she was gone there were a lot
         of little kids there and everything was so beautiful, she said. I remember
         him telling that story, he'd tell that story too. He'd tell some pretty
         weird ones sometimes,about bears getting after people and tearing 'em
         up.  remember more details about what he used to say, but I don't
         good enough remember it.
         
         SS:  I thought the story about this friend's mother, wouldn't let the boy go
         swimming? I thought that was a funny story.
         
         DF:  He did too, that was very funny.
         
         SS:  That's how he told it, he wouldn't let her go swimming til he learned how?
         
         DF:  Couldn't go near the water til he learned how to swim. How do you learn
         how to swim any other way I wonder?
         
         SS:  He really believed that there were going to be airplanes?
         
         DF:  I guess so. I ob n't think he believed that, he had the idea that he could
         build one. rHis dad thought he was crazy, thought he was getting off the
         beaten path. When he got in his mind something, he ought to be more, he
         ought to have his mind on something else that was more necessary then such
         crazy things as airplanes. Are there any other questions you wanted to ask?
         
         SS:  That's mostly it. Is there anything else that comes to your mind?
         
         DF:  Not now, anyway. Probably will be after while. That happens, you know.
         (pause in tape)
         
         DF:  ... couldn't prove my point. Even Mr. David, when he wrote the history,
         why he said they were the same one, but...Before Ansel's dad died, why we
         he said to me he knew they were different persons.
         
         SS:  I never could figure out why Davey wouldn't call himself Drannan if that's
         who he was.
         
         DF:  I don't either. There's Bill Drannan and Wild Davey. Where they got that,
         I don't know where they got the connection Davey, and Bill Drannan.
         I don't know how Davey got the name Davey either really
         because his mane was no Davey about it.
         
         SS:  Did Davey live here for quite a while?
         
         DF:  I guess so. He was here in the country when we came in here. I don't know
         how long before that.
         
         SS:  Drannan didn't stay for very long?
         
         DF:  No he didn't. As soon as he got it written, I think he left. Far as I know.
         I think the Fleeners^got some pay for helping him, but he never paid 'em
         anything. There was some hard feeling about it somehow anyway Kind of
         skipped out, you know. Took his manuscript and left.
         
         SS:  Did the Fleeners know much about history? Were they very interested in it?
         
         DF:  I don't know. I don't have any idea. I don't know how they could tell if
         it was authentic or not or anything about that. I suppose they took it that
         he was telling the truth. Put down as they were told.
         
         (End of tape)
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13431</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Fleener1</previous>
      <next>Flodin1</next>
      <disp_name>Fleener2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
