<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/25/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Elmer Flodin, 1974-06-25, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:02:37</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Flodin, Elmer</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer; logger</occupation>
      <birthyear>1899</birthyear>
      <residence>Dry Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Swedish homesteaders (early 1880's)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fishing"&gt;fishing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#unions"&gt;unions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#working conditions"&gt;working conditions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moonshine"&gt;moonshine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Prohibition"&gt;Prohibition&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Dry Ridge"&gt;Dry Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Big Bear Ridge"&gt;Big Bear Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Helmer"&gt;Helmer&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13430</file_name>
      <mp3>13431.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13431.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Father came from Sweden and worked in Idaho hewing timber for the railroad; left homestead
               cabin to work on Plummer railroad; homesteaders burnt land; Indians took better care
               of land
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father comes to America from Sweden and worked out to
               Idaho in the early 1880's hewing timber for bridges on
               the railroad for the Northern Pacific. He left his
               homestead cabin in spring and walked out to Plummer to
               work on the railroad. He knew Henry and August Anderson,
               two of the earliest homesteaders in the area, in Minnesota;
               many of the early homesteaders in Dry Ridge country worked
               their way out together on the railroad. They cleared a
               plot around their cabins in spring so that they would be
               protected when the Indians burnt off the land in summer.
               The Indians took better care of the land than whites,
               because burning kept the brush down. Big yellow pine
               with four foot stumps.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Men walked to Moscow and back for groceries; in winter he cut timber and burnt land;
               early sawmills
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Early sheep grazing and corrals in the area. The men
               walked to Moscow and back for groceries with a pack
               on their backs. In winter he cut his timber and burned
               it to clear land. Early sawmills.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Kids growing up on the Ridge; fishing and hunting, Troy's Midsummer Picnic</title>
            <synopsis>Kids had a better time growing up then than now, with
               get togethers on the ridge. The fishing and hunting
               was great; blue grouse. Troy's Midsummer Picnic. Dry
               Ridge School. He followed a footburner plow; clearing
               the place.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Horses hauling to Troy; hauling cream; storekeepers gave kids candy; dance and entertainment
               in Troy
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Hard on horses hauling to Troy. The neighbors took
               turns hauling cream to Troy, and father went once a week.
               Storekeepers gave kids free candy. Troy was not a tough
               town. Dance entertainment in Troy, on Big Bear Ridge
               and in Helmer.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Elmer started working in woods; fires in Genesee fields; farmers didn't join the union</title>
            <synopsis>IWW. Elmer started working in the woods at Camp 6 in
               1918, in early springs and late falls. The IWW's came
               in and got clean camps. He joined up after a representative explained how they wanted
               to improve conditions.
               Fires in Genesee fields, caused by red smut, were blamed
               on the IWW to turn farmers against them, so they wouldn't
               join the union. If they had, farmers would have more say
               now. Ole Bohman made a speech against the IWW outside
               of the bank in Troy. Elmer's father came home believing
               it, so Elmer threw his membership card on the table to
               show him. Many local men carved their initials and
               "IWW" on the old bridge across Dry Creek.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Conditions of old railroad camps</title>
            <synopsis>Conditions in old railroad camps. Getting rid of
               bedbugs and greybacks; carrying a little bottle of
               quicksilver worked well for his father. Using horses
               on the farm.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Description of how strong local men were</title>
            <synopsis>Chuck Wells was the strongest man Elmer remembers in the
               woods; he used to break peavey handles rolling logs
               onto decks. Local strong men. Big Anderson: his
               strength and frightening appearance, his perpetual
               motion machine, his cancerous leg. Big told how he
               threw a camel over backwards when he was being bothered
               about smuggling Turkish cigars on ship. He regularly
               threw four foot long chunks of wood over his shoulder
               and hiked up to his cabin with them.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Cougar Jack got his name by breaking the back of a
               threatening cougar with a fence post.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Cougar Jack got his name by breaking the back of a
               threatening cougar with a fence post.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Lots of local moonshiners. Where people went for
               moonshine as Prohibition grew.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Lots of local moonshiners. Where people went for
               moonshine as Prohibition grew.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>Old Pat Malone sat in his chair and slept; never made arrests, good for Bovill</title>
            <synopsis>Old Pat Malone sat in his chair and slept. He never
               made arrests. If you gave him a bottle, you better not
               have too much whiskey in it. He was good for Bovill,
               well liked, and always talked to people he knew.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Survival of frontier homesteaders. Support of IWW despite opponents Local strong
         men. 6-25-74 1 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         ELMER FLODIN: When he come here, a fellow by the name of Nastrum, there in Minn
         esota, he knew him. And he wrote to this old couple and he got
         finish up his military training there in Sweden. And then he wrote
         to them and then they told about the United States, so he went to
         Minnesota to them. And then he started working on the railroad.
         That's what he was in Sweden. There was working in timber and he
         was a great with a broadaxe and so then he got a job hing
         timber for the bridges on the railroad.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: Was that Northern Pacific?
         
         EF: Un huh.Yeoh, he went to Northern Pacific Rock Minnesota to
         Moscow. You see, awhile there, at one ways you go the Canadian Pacific.
         That's North Pacific that goes into Canada and called Canadian Pacific
         in there.
         
         SS:  So he wound up coming to Moscow because he was working on the railroad.
         
         EF:  Yeah, well before they got there, it was way up north there. Because
         they'd walk. He had his log cabin here. He'd spend the winter when
         they wasn't working at home. Then they had walk all the way from
         Plummer. That's where they were, they catch a train to Plummer.
         Take their pack on their back and to Plummer.
         
         SS:  Do you know how he wound up coming to Dry Ridge country?
         
         EF:  That I don't know. I think one reason was Henry and Ao^tft&gt;T Anderson,
         they wereKhere.And he got acquainted with them, , back
         east.See, Henry Anderson, he homesteaded this place up here.
         And Anderson, he homestead on a big farm down there
         below what is now Dan McKenzie's place.
         
         SS:  So...
         
         EF:  Anderson, he, that's the place that Ted Kreyi got.That
         was Limos. There were three brothers here. At the time.
         
         SS:  he probably came out here and found this land open. Had it been
         surveyed?
         
         EF:  They surveyed it. Hammond, they used to live on the west 80
         right across the creek. Ynu know, coming down from Little Bear Ridge,
         you know, when you come, you see that little place on the flat down there.
         Well that used to be the old Hammond place. He wgs the surveryor.
         Him and Ed surveyed through this country.Ed Sandberg up here,
         Dan Tallson, the place just across the road,
         a hundred sixty east and west.And Sandberg and Alffced Johnson, he's the
         one, you know, where they tore down this house. Well, that was my
         dad's first brother in law. His wife passed away. In '96. And all
         them come together. They all worked the railroad.
         
         SS:  So they all took up the land here about the same time.
         
         EF: They all took up land here together. Homestead in here. And
         then Olsons, they come in. Emil wasn't certain, they would talk a
         lot. Carl, did he ever tell you what time...?
         
         SS:  I think he said it was the late '80's, but it was close to '90,
         maybe '88.
         
         EF:  I know they come in late to that.
         
         SS:  What's this about he worked out on the railroad when he was first
         homesteading. He had built a cabin and he would leave it?
         
         EF:  Built the cabin so he'd have a home. You see, you had to build on
         it. YOu had to make an improvement and you had to spend so many
         months out of the year you had to spen^on the land. To file your,
         to put your claim in.
         
         SS:  So when would he leave to go work on the railroad?
         
         EF:  Well that would been in the spring of the year when they broke
         up so they could go to work again. See, that was all abne like grading,
         all done with horses. And they had to have it when it was tall ground,
         not too wet.
         
         SS:  He just left the place here?
         
         I guess so. When they left in fh„ xn the sprxng of the year, they'd work
         a plot around the cabin. Get all grass and that away. Safe for fire.
         Come home the fall, why the Indians had all 
         So they kept, took better care of their land then the white men
         doing. There was no brush, all found was just a big yellow
         pines. No little timber in between.Dad had trees out there that
         was better than four foot on the stump but he sawed down and burnt
         for to make field. And he could stand on the top of the hill over
         there and the line back the field there,he could
         look right through the trees,see the whole farm. That's little
         better than half a mile.Just open pine country. And then there was
         some sheep men come in here too, and late I think, come in here
         with their sheep. Down on the creek bottom-down here in the ty
         that used to be a big sheep corral. And there used to be a sheep
         corral up on Olson's place.I heard they come up from Washington
         with their sheep.
         
         SS:  Yeah, I know there were some guys I know, from around the big Bend
         country that were grazers. They just came through here and used
         it as they wanted to. Was there any trouble with the sheep eating
         up the land.
         
         EF:  Well, you see, there was no population. It was just grass. It was
         free, open range. All over. They could go up to Elk River, they
         could go any place they wanted to, you see. That's what they did.
         They went back in there and all back of Helmer. You see you come
         where that shop is there east of Helmer. Well you go straight
         there to Potlatch and there used to be a corral. That I remember
         not so far back when we used to go fishing, you could still see
         that sheep corcal there. And old cabin.
         
         SS:  Did your father actually have to walk out to get to Plummer?
         
         EF:  They didn't have no horses. N0 transportation, no railroad. They
         just had to walk. that bunch that went together like Dan
         Tallson,Sandberg, they all figured when they were ready to go to
         work, why, they'd all hit out for Plummer." And uhen they wanted groceries
         they would walk. Walk out. After Moscow got started, why then they
         just take a pack on their back and pack it home.He said he packed more
         thao one sack of flaur from Moscow out.
         
         SS:  Must have taken him a day or two to get any where walking.
         
         EF:  It took him a couple of days. A good day to come in and back. They said
         they had to put the packs, they had a sack of flour and they
         had some coffee and stuff. needed to pack out. Then after a few,
         I forget what year he said it was, he said he was working for Tomer there
         in Moscow and he bought him a little saddle horse..He had a saddle horse
         to ride.
         
         SS:  And there was no Troy then.
         
         EF:  No Moscow. At first..Lewiston, I see the picture of Lewiston, it just oas
         a square front like the old building. That's the picture of Lewiston.
         That picture there told where the&gt;| file on the land. Land Office. That's
         where they all had to go to file on their land was Lewiston.
         
         SS:  Do you know when he stopped going out to work and just stayed here? Was
         it a long time?
         
         EF:  Yes, he worked out for quite a few years. While he was clearing land.
         Now, like in the wintertime when he was home, then he fall timber and -for
         
         SS:  Did that timber get to the sawmills or ©as that before there were mills?
         
         EF:  Burnt it. Burnt all them big wood. No sawmills. I forget what year that
         there Bohman mill started. Johanson, he smarted the first mill
         right there where Bendel's Meat Market meats is? On the creek bottom.That's
         where they hauled their first logs. And that Bohman, he started a sawmill
         right, you know where they took out that big cut down there that house
         is Bendel's, they fixed up on that new road there? On the left if you
         it still kind of shows where the millpondiwas.Bohman started that.
         That was Bohman's mill.
         
         SS:  Did these other's come in about the same time too? 
         
         EF:  Oh, that come way later.Yeah, that come in later than that. That did, it
         was after 1900 when O.k' got in here, I guess.Little after in 1900.
         
         SS:  What about right around here? Where were mills in this area around Dry Creek?
         
         EF:  Well, Troy Lumber Company, they had one mill right fiere where you made
         the turn. That was Standard Mill. Then they had the White Pine mill and
         the Old White Pine. And then Ole Bohman had one mill on 
         
         SS:  Was there a mill called the Dry Creek or the Dry Ridge mill?
         
         EF:  Dry Uh huh. That was up there, right back up there where the stock pile is, rock.
         That was the Dry Creek mill.
         
         SS:  Did it take him a long time to clear up the land?
         
         EF:  Oh yes.
         
         SS:  Real slow?
         
         EF:  Yeah. Yeah, they didn't have much feed for quite a while. You see, they
         had to get work up so they'd have enough so they could afford to feed
         a team of horses. And there wasn't much, very big horses.Hundred pound
         cayuses to break up the land with. I remember the first team he had. That
         was 22, 24 years old. I remember them.
         
         SS:  What was it like for you as a kid growing up out here?
         
         EF:  Great. Better than, we had more fun and better times then. they  now.
         You can talk jso any like Carl Olson. They'll tell you that the
         kids today, they don't have the enjoyment we did. We'd all get together
         and always have ridge parties. Schoolhouse dances. So we didn't have like
         they have nowadays, wherever they go. Take the car and take off.
         No, we had,I'11 say, me had a lot of fun as kids. And one thing you don't
         have, what we had thenNis good hunting and fishing I know. All I had to
         go down here to patrfure and in an^ Come back with 18-20 fish.
         Nice trout. And if we went down to Bear Creek, we jis t down to the
         old mine up here and go down Bear Creek,Ncome home with over a hundred
         fish. No limit, those days and blue grouse, by the hundred.
         Great, big bunches of 'em. I never knew how, the mountain grouse get up
         like that. You catch them up to 6-8 pounders. I 'mem ber, after dad got
         me the first .22, we had alot of birds, My brother bought
         a 16 guage shotgun and after that we had to get bird meat to eat all
         through the summer. So.
         
         SS:  Now you got to hunt for anything.
         
         EF:  You can't find blue grouse.No.
         
         SS:  Was a lot of the food that you ate wild?
         
         EF:  Oh yeah. I'll tell you, that blue grouse, that's good meat, like
         the Chinese pheasant.(Pause in tape) And then they always had a stand
         set up, a was right over here. Had the choir singing, had a piano
         always took the church organ there.Had the minister and sermons. Yah.
         
         SS:  Was that a custom from Sweden to have a minister?
         
         EF:  It was a custom. Sweden, they never, they wouldn't think about working
         on Midsummer day.
         
         SS:  You couldn't have been more than 9 or 10 in that picture.
         
         EF:  No, I wasn't too old there.
         
         SS:  What was the school like in that schoolhouse?
         
         EF:  Well, it was gust about^the same you go to ride.,you
         had one teacher for all grades. From the first through eight. But, I believe
         we learned just as much, if not more in them old schools than they do
         nowadays. You take my eight grade. Arithmetic. 
         Mrs. Flodinfe. Here's a picture of the school up there.
         
         EF:  See, we had algebra in the eighth grade. You don't find that now. We had
         a good there. Yeah, that's old schoolhouse. That's sitting up there by
         Kenneth's house now. Ken Hawkins.He had it right there where he got his
         grain bins. And he pulled it up there. Use for a shop. I remember when
         we had 32 children going to that school. That schoolhouse was crowded.
         Ellen Gourd was our teacher. Our teacher there, that's Christie Robinson.
         
         SS:  you start working around the house when you were pretty young?
         
         EF:  When I was fourteen I, following a foot burner. You know what a foot-
         burner is? Walking plow? Three houses,
         
         SS:  Ts that right after you quit school?
         
         Before. You see, the all had school certain times of the year. And
         you had spring break so you'd be able to help. I followed on
         walked this way.
         
         SS:  What do you mean
         
         EF:  I was short, you see.
         
         SS:  You were short.
         
         EF:  I got it sitting down there beside the old house. The old plow.
         
         SS:  By then, was your father just making a living farming?
         
         EF:  cattle. That's what we did. In those days 
         a lot of cows and sold cream. Now here, 8 to 12 cows to milk,
         Lot of cattle. This barn here was about 24 feet. In them days without
         helped. about that many.
         
         SS:  When you wese a kid, what did it look like around here? Was it cleared
         up by then? Did it still have timber mostly around the place?
         
         EF:  Yes. You could see all that, that white fence,. the timber .
         Well I broke up a strip over there. You take a look at that that's the
         field over there. That back end, I broke that. And then, you take over
         here, east,30 acres up there, I broke.
         
         SS:  With the walking plow?
         
         EF:  Three horses. The last, the last 15 acresjprobably, then I had a cat and
         big breaking. But the biggest part was done with three horses. Now here,
         I tell you about that first year.
         
         SS:  Yeah. That's them?
         
         EF:  Here's them and this one here.That's his first team horses.He was old
         when this picture was taken. That's, this was cold.And that's when dad
         marked this.
         
         SS:  He had that same team for 20 years?
         
         EF:  Tbis one here,he was 20, I think this one was 23 years old when he killed
         her.
         
         SS:  It's something that they could work so many years. That's tough work.
         
         EF:  Well, he used them on the wagon. He used them to haul grain into town.
         
         SS:  Would he take his grain to Troy?
         
         EF:  All that was rough on horses, 'cause 4 him rocks  have to pull
         over rocks. Hit a rock and back and forth and hih^ horses.
         
         SS:  How often would you go into Troy? When you had the wagon?
         
         EF:  Oh, twice a week. Now, like when we was selling cream, Sandberg would
         take 'em one day, take one day, dad take it one day. Well, it
         was every other day. So once a week. Always once a week. 
         
         SS:  id you get to go into Troy much when you were a kid?
         
         EF:  Yeah, you bet. I always went in, when he went to town, I always went
         when he went to town. In those days kid come into
         town, why it was, go find a big paper sack and fill her up with candy.
         You come home with a great big paper sack full.
         
         SS:  he storekeepers would give you the candy?
         
         EF:  Any little kid come in, why aid ohanson or
         
         SS:  Sounds like a pretty good deal.
         
         EF:  Yeah. Of course, for ten cents, you got more candy than you can buy for
         four bits now.And cookies, they had it in 30 to 50 gallon drums. Wooden
         Weigh barrels. He's going to take it, add it up when you want and he it
         out for ya. Package like you get now. You know a grocery sack that big.
         That would be two bits for the ginger snaps, old time ginger snaps. Buy
         just two package is what you buy now.
         
         SS:  Did you have kids that you got to be friends with in Troy that you'd play
         with? When you were in town?
         
         EF:  A few kids. They used to come out, go over here to church, their
         folks did, and they used to come ove'r here after church for dinner. So
         So I had the Petersons. And different kids that way. Those days you got
         acquainted with people, than you do nowadays. If they wanted to They're friendly,
         friendly people.
         
         SS:  You think that Troy was a pretty tough town? Back in the early days?
         
         EF:  Troy really was not a tough town. Newer. I think you'll find nowadays,
         like Moscow , there , they're tougher towns today than Troy was when I
         was a kid. Never seen much trouble around town. I tell you,people,
         more of getting together in those days than.they do nowadays. Now like
         you have a dance at fl hall there in Troy or out at the Bowery out on
         Randle, peaceful, never seen a punch. Good music, and then up there,
         as you come in from Moscow up here
         
         SS:  Used to be what?
         
         EF:  Round hall. There they had dancing and roller skating.
         
         SS:  sounds like there were a lot of different places to go for entefctainment.
         More than nowadays.
         
         EF:  Yes,and then you had community hall on Big Bear Ridge. And then you had 
         round hall and pavillion for skating and dancing in Helmer.
         
         SS:  Could you go from one place to another and pot feel like an outsider?
         
         EF:  Pret'near the same bunch. You all running in the same bunch.
         
         SS:  Up around Princeton and Harvard people have told me there used to be a
         fair amount of fighting. At dances. And the group from Harvard might go
         down to Potlatch and mix it up some. It doesn't sound like, it was different
         around here.
         
         EF:  Out at Big Bear Ridge, I always had a nice time out there. Just kids fights.
         Get it out or something, but it wasn't much fighting up at Helmer. And
         outsat Byers floury on Randle Flat. That was always peaceful. And Byers,
         they really kept order.
         
         SS:  Did you have much time for this stuff? What it just be on the weekends?
         
         EF:  We would go to Big Bear Ridge, Friday night. Saturday night we would go
         out fchere to Byers. And then there'd be schoolhouse dances in between.
         Like after school, around ChristmaB and New Year. School closed and
         they always had the school parties.
         
         SS:  About how old were you at this time? Teenager?
         
         EF:  Teenager, yeah.Like you seen the picture here, used to^ get together on
         Sunday. Tfeen when I was older, about 10,12 years old, we had our church...
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         EF:  Well as you go out to the highway, you just go past Eddy's, where he's
         got the fence, and then make a little turn, it's that road. And that is
         now the Lion's Club in Troy.
         
         SS:  Was that the church for everybody around Dry Ridge? church
         
         EF:  Uhhuh. Bear Creek,.They had quite a
         Sunday School. That church used to on Sunday.
         five and six classes in the church.
         
         SS:  Did you like Sunday School pretty well?
         
         EF:  Sure. It was a custom to go to Sunday School. Folks all went to church
         Sunday. We kids to Sunday School.
         
         SS:  When did you start working in the woods?
         
         EF:  Eighteen. 1918.
         
         SS:  That's when the World War started. Where did you start in at?
         
         EF:  Up at Camp Six. That was my first. And then from there on went
         to different camps. Over atKfburteen, I worked at Camp Five and I worked
         at Camp 8 at Elk River. I work early in the spring of the year and then
         after they through the fall, working the fall, why then, I'd go to the
         woods to work.
         
         SS:  What was the camps like? What was the living like?
         
         EF:  Well, that's when the IWW's come^and change it so the clean camps,railroad
         cars and some wasK jacks. It was clean. You had your bath and nice
         accommodations, good kitchen, nice, clean kitchen.
         
         SS:  When you first started it was like that?
         
         EF:  Well that's the way it was more or less here. You got up into the 
         and them other camps up north, that was different. You had to carry your
         bedroll. But then, after the IUW's got in, why then, you got rid of the
         bedroll.
         
         SS:  What do you know about the IWW's coming in? You told me that you and some
         other guys joined up because you thought it was a good bunch.
         
         EF:  Well, wanted to get rid of the bedrolls and get clean accommodations
         in the camp. That's what they went for. 
         
         SS:  How did they organize?
         
         EF:  Well, something like the CIO and AFofL is today. They had men come
         around organizing the men. Sign up for . That's the way it
         was when I joined up with them down at, when I was at camp.
         
         SS:  What happened when a guy came in? Did he explain?
         
         EF:  He explained to you what this was, what they wanted. If he asked for clean
         bedrooms, no bedrolls. Wanted sheets on the beds. Course, that we didn't
         get,clean blankets.
         
         SS:  What about all this stuff they spread against the IWW? Have you heard
         that?
         
         EF:  No. That was just propaganda I guess^IWW. That was just trying to break
         it up. 'Cause they wanted tne working class,
         because they were nothing but working class themselves. And then, politicians
         talked against it.
         
         SS:  You told me about Ole Bohman gave a speech against it. Would you tell
         me about that one?
         
         EF:  Well, that one figured that the IWW was putting matches in the wheat straw,
         in the grain shocks out in Genesee and burning thrashing machines. But
         there was no IWW had anything like that. I never heard any of the IW
         speak about that. What it was^that there red smut. Was set lots of fires
         even after IWW went out. Was the talk.
         
         SS:  Ole Bohman gave a speech in town saying that they were no good?
         
         EF:  Yeah, that they were doing this and that ^ against the farmer and what
         are we doing setting them fires? Because he knew, he was a banker, he
         knew that the IWW tried to organize the farmers in with the labor party.
         Which was the biggest mistake the farmers ever&gt;done. VJhe,n ^e1 d'*n JO"
         
         SS:  When they didn't join up with the IWW?
         
         EF:  Yes.
         
         SS:  Why do you think that's so?
         
         EF:  Well, I tell you, if it had been that, he would have had more to say for
         himself. It would have been one thing, you wouldn't have to go to town
         and just be asked what you give me for this and what you want for that.
         They heve more to say. It'd been better for the market.
         
         SS:  you think the IWW wanted the farmers to join?
         
         EF:  Yes.NBecause, the feller come aroundKto us, what he said about it. I
         even brought that to my brother and dad. What, thatAbe for their better.
         It would have been a big union. Been the labor and the farmer.
         
         SS:  It would have been strong.
         
         EF:  It would have been a strong union, yes.
         
         SS:  You told me that your father believed what Ole Bohman said?
         
         EF:  Yes he did, because he didn't know that, what it was. What they was doing.
         He knew that there was thrashing machinee burning. But he didn't know
         the truth of it.
         
         SS:  What was it you told me about, you said he came home and he was telling
         you how bad they were?
         
         EF:  He'd been to town on Saturday and that's the day that Bohman made that
         speech there^a^ the bank. And then I come home from camp on Saturday^ and
         he's telling me about. And he got to talkigg about how bad they were.
         I disagreed with him on this and that, I didn't think that the working
         classes that bad a people or anything. And then also that you couldn't
         trust IWW's, but they might attack you around your home. So then after
         he got through with his speech and I had to talk to him. I my
         him on the table and asked him what he think now. I said,IWW in
         your house. Well, there used to be an old bridge down here, across Dry
         Creek. 0ur old road just go right straight up across. And there was their
         names, carved their names, IWW's carved all over that whole bridge.
         
         SS:  You mean the guys that were in it?
         
         EF:  Uh huh. men working in Troy, walking home or driving home
         from camp on Saturday evenings. Stopped there and carved their name on
         that." Carve your initials and IWW. Tnat bridge had a lot of carvings on
         it.
         
         SS:  You say that most of the guys that worked in the woods ..around here got
         in it?
         
         EF:  Yeah. They did.i Quite a few from Troy. They were IWW's.
         
         SS:  What did your father think then? Did you persuade him?
         
         EF:  Well sure, that persuaded him that was nothing like it. Because
         there was, you might say, they were not strangers out the country,
         most of them lived around in Troy and surrounding, Deary, around the
         country. That belonged to the union.
         
         SS:  do you think they kept it quiet or they didn't care who knew? That
         they were for the union. Seems like so many were against the IWW.
         
         EF:  That's what you hear. But it's one thing. Now, my dad was telling me
         about how dirty the camps were,^ railroad camps. Lousy and dirty
         and you had to carry your own blanket roll. Didn't have no bathe or anything
         in the camps.Thai's one thing that IWW got out. Now when Marble Creek
         was running, they had them old log buildings and you had to carry
         your blankets.
         
         SS:  What did the guys do about bedbegs in the camps? Was there anything that
         they did?
         
         EF:  There was powders they used. They were using that, ut still you couldn't
         get rid of them. Them old log buildings with cracks in logs are full of
         em. And not only that, there are greybacks in camps. You had to watch
         out for them,
         
         SS:  What are greybacks?
         
         EF:  human louse. That's what they were.And dad said in the railroad
         salve camps, them camps were full of There's a , they oeed to call it
         grey salve, I don't know what's in it. Smear that on your body, that would
         drive them off.
         
         SS:  Did you tell me that your dad believed in quicksilver?
         
         EF:  We had a little bottle of it, about that big.About that square. 3ust a
         little bottle. And there was quicksilver in that. And that's what he was
         told to carry on him when he crossed the ocean, because them boats that
         theef come on, they were buggy. And so he carried that and then when my
         brother come here, he had him carry too.
         
         SS:  uid it work?
         
         EF:  Well, that's what dad claimed. worked. Dad carried that in his bedrollj
         in his bed in the railroad camps.He carried that bottle with him. And
         dad said that he never had any trouble, keeping clean.
         
         SS:  Did you work for a long time in the camps?
         
         EF:  Off and on in the springs and falls. I did that probably/along, five years.
         And then me and my brother, we rented a farm from dad, went to farming
         together. Course, then too, when we got through, first few years, I'd
         go out to the camp in the fall every year when there wasn't nothing
         to do.
         
         SS:  What was your farming operation like? Whan you started what did you use?
         
         EF:  horses. Til 1928, when dad bought a tractor. First tractor. Course
         we had horses then too. We always kept five, six set of horses after we
         had our tractor.
         
         SS:  Would you just use it for riding or farmwork.
         
         EF:  They were big horses. I had one team there weighed sifcteen hundred a piece.
         My brother had a team that weighed over seventeen hundred a piece. They
         were all big draft horses. Tu^c&gt;xCon and Belgian horses. -No, we used
         them, like I'd do the plowing with the tractor and heavy, like the discing
         went to, and then my brother, he used them for like the mass cultivation
         and the seeding with horses. He followed up behind me. With the horses.
         
         SS:  Were there any guys in the camps when you were working that were really
         strong men? I hear that there were some big drinkers or heavy workers in
         the camps.
         
         EF:  There was some pretty husky men. The strongest man that I know of was
         Ooe Wells. Negro. Up at, he lived just east of Deary. Because they always
         him roll down, skid 'em with horses and roll into decks on
         the landing. And he'd break peavy handle after peavy handle. That man
         was strong. And he wasn't too big a man. He had strength. And there was
         lots of big lumberjacks, I tell you, there was lots of them up there.
         Over two hundred pounders. We was working back of Avon once here for
         Charley and then there was one steep side hill that they couldn't
         log with horses. So he wanted someone to roll them down. There was a big
         fella by the name of Bill Greenwood. So he took the job and he asked
         me if I wanted to go with him and we log that side hill. So him and I hand
         logged that with peavys. I was about 19 years old then.
         
         SS:  And he did the heavy work?
         
         EF:  We both had to work on a log, roll together, something to get'going.
         That man had power. There was strength in old Bill.
         
         SS:  What about, what do you remember about Big Anderson? Did you know him?
         
         EF:  Yeah, he was an old sailor. Retired down there. His legs bad. He had
         varicose veins.It must have turned cancer, because he had big sores on
         his legs. But that was a big man.There was quite a few big ones around.
         You take Gus Sandberf up here. That was a big man. Strong man. And young
         Carl Olson up here. Big Carl they called him. That was a strong man.And
         there was quite afew up north in Pleasant Hill area. Some pretty
         husky men up in there.Like old man.
         strong man.
         
         SS:  What was this about Big Anderson's invention?
         
         EF:  NHe was working on, he said a machine that was supposed to run forever on
         He had all kinds of gadgets on that thing. I really couldn't
         explain just how he had it built, but I seen it. It was a round rig. Made
         something like a barrel. Had all kinds of propellers and different things
         on that.
         
         SS:  It was supposed to be perpetual motion?
         
         EF:  Yes, it was supposed to be perpetual motion. But he never got it going,
         til he passed away.
         
         SS:  I'd heard he was a pretty frightening looking gyy for some of the kids.
         He looked something like a eonster, with his big beard and his caftes.
         
         EF:  Yes, he was a monster. And he had bad legs and he had two, long canes
         when he walked to ten. He walked to Troy. Once in awhile. Had two long
         sticks there. He was better than six feet. I figure him six three. And
         he was broad shouldered, big man. Not fat, but just big boned man.
         
         SS:  His legs never healed up?
         
         EF:  No. Arid they smelled. They had a bad odor to them sores. Always had to
         have 'em erapped. And when he'd take that off, why you'd see the pus on
         his bandages. We down there visiting, see, Andersons, they
         lived just across creek from them, wasn't too far to go. We'd go
         down there on Sundays and we'd go and visit him. My dad always went over
         and us kids would go with him.
         
         SS:  he used to talk about his sailing days?
         
         EF:  Not too much. He didn't say too much. Only thing he was telling about,
         when he was a sailor he always used to smuggle Turkish cigars around the
         different places. And I know it was Turkey, he would come to Arab country
         and raised camels and then they were going to arrest him there for smuggling
         cigars and they had acamel there that was loaded, ready to go and he
         grabbed it by the front legs and tipped it over backwards and after
         that scared them and they left him alone.That's the only thing he ever
         told about his strength. How he kicked that camel over.
         
         SS:  But he was a real strong man.
         
         EF:  Oh he was strong, you bet. No doubt. That man was strongA in his old age.
         He'd make his own wood down there, around the trees. Take wood, say,
         20 inches through, four footer and he just take that up and throw it on
         his shoulder and walk to his cabin with it. So he had strength.
         
         SS:  He could walk without the canes when he was working?
         
         EF:  He could. But when he went off to walking, carried to rest
         himself on, his canes. His legs were bad.
         
         SS:  There were a couple other guys, I think you mentioned one of 'em,I can't
         remember. There was one guy out by Deary that you mentioned.,He was an
         old character. Did you know Wild Bill?
         
         EF:  Cougar Stremmen. That was a big, strong man.
         
         SS:  Do you know why Cougar
         
         EF:  It was one cold, bad winter, about four feet of snow, and he's walking
         Texas Ridge there. And he met a cougar, and the cougar faced him,
         in the fence right next to, and he broke a fence post there, hit the cougar
         across the back and broke his back and he got the name Cougar Dack. Cougar
         wasn't going to get away from him. Nice friendly man, Cougar was. I knew
         him when I started working in the woods.
         
         SS:  What about the moonshining that went on around here? Was there a lot of it?
         
         EF:  Yes, there was a lot of it.Here, there and all over.
         
         SS:  Was there any guys that were big operators?
         
         EF:  Sam McKin, he was a big operator. He had a big setup up in White Pine
         country. And there was, you take, lots of 'em up in north there, Pleasant
         Hill and Spring Valley country up in there.There was lots of moonshining
         going on. Lots of it around Deary. Helmer. Bovill
         
         SS:  bias there alot of difference in the stuff, some of it good and some of
         not?
         
         EF:  Different. Different how they kept the]rcoils and that clean.Used to be
         siome out Little Bear Ridge. the done quite a bit of it. Cecil Emmett.
         
         SS:  Did guys have to be pretty careful not to get caught ?
         
         EF:  Yeah. They had to be careful. Oh, Sam McKin, he operated for many years
         and he never got caught, he was careful.
         
         SS:  That's one law that seemed crazy.
         
         EF:  No.
         
         SS:  What's a point of having a law that no one listens to?
         
         EF:  Well you see, there was prohibition at that time and for a long time they
         could go into Washington and get it and then Washington went dry and
         then they'd go to Montana or ship it out from Montana. And after Montana
         went dry, why.then they were getting it out of Canada.
         
         SS:  There was always a place to get it.
         
         EF:  the same time there was a lot of moonshinflt going on
         
         SS:  Did you know about any guys getting caught?
         EF: quite a few. Quite a few that were caught.
         
         SS:  Did you know Pat Malone at all? From Bovill?
         
         EF:  Sure did. Old Pat. He'd sit in his chair in the hotel un there in the
         lobby and sleep.And the only thing is, Pat, he liked his whiskey as well
         as anyk else. He never made no arrests. He'd find somebody with a bottle,
         why, he'd just ask,"Have you got a drink?" But if you handed Pat a bottle
         with a pint of whiskey, you might make sure you'd take your drink first,
         otherwise you wouldn't get any. I seen that happen more than once at a
         Fourth of July celebration. He'd see somebody with a bottle and he*«l sneak
         up behind 'em. Oh Pat would get drunk, go to his room and sleep it off.
         
         SS:  He soueds like quite a guy to have for sheriff.
         
         EF:  Well, you take the Moscow , they had to have a deputy up there.
         And Pat was one that he kept good order, people listened. They liked him.
         And he got along well with the people, whenever there was anything
         at the Pat got the job.
         
         SS:  Whenever there was what?
         
         EF:  Change in the offices. New sheriff coming in, they'd elect, didn't
         make no difference if he was Deunocret or Republican party come in, why
         Pat Malone always got that job, you know.
         
         SS:  I hear that people really liked him.
         
         EF:  He was liked, yes, he was liked. All,not only in Bovill, but surrounding
         community, Pat was liked.
         
         SS:  Did you ever hear any stories about him going after people?
         
         EF:  No.
         
         SS:  Theye seems to be a lot of stories about him around.
         
         EF:  There could be lots, people that know quite a bit about him. As far as
         me, I didn't know, I knew Pat. Working in the camps up there, I would
         see around talking.
         
         SS:  From the camps you'd see him.
         When I'd come in, to Bovill, you'd catch Pat, he'd always stop and talk
         to you if he knew you, he'd always stop and talk.
         You hadn't been farming many years yourself when that depression came
         along.
         Istarted farming in '21,'22. When Istarted farming. We bought the
         stock and outfit, Ibought dad out and went to farming.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13430</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Fleener2</previous>
      <next>Flodin2</next>
      <disp_name>Flodin1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
