<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">12/18/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Gus Gamble, 1974-12-18, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:05:16</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Gamble, Gus</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1890</birthyear>
      <residence>Genesee, Paradise Ridge</residence>
      <origin>Daniel Gamble's brother</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#police officers"&gt;police officers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lynching"&gt;lynching&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moonshine"&gt;moonshine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Colfax"&gt;Colfax&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13437</file_name>
      <mp3>13438.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13438.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Shorty Hill shooting with bandits will driving a stagecoach with Felix Warren; Felix
               Warren knew how to drive a stagecoach well
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Driving a stagecoach loaded with gold for Felix
               Warren, Shorty Hill shot it out with some bandits and
               got away from them. Gus saw Felix Warren changing horses
               in Genesee while racing from Spokane to Walla Walla;
               Felix was quite a man to use the whip.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Shorty gets a twenty dollar bill for breaking a horse.</title>
            <synopsis>Shorty gets a twenty dollar bill for breaking a horse.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>840</time>
            <title>Ed Hill swimming the Columbia river to get away from a cop; Shorty gets arrested,
               sent to Colfax, then escapes; Angry farmers decide to lynch another man who killed
               another farmer
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Ed Hill, Shorty's brother, took off and swam the Columbia
               River after a cop got stabbed trying to break up a fight
               he was in. Eventually he wrote his mother from Montana
               asking if the cop had been killed, and her answer is
               intercepted by a sheriff. Shorty gets arrested and sent
               back to Colfax on a train, tied to a Black man, but the officer
               falls asleep and he escapes in the darkness. Later he
               turns himself in because he says he's innocent, and gets
               six months for escaping. Angry farmers decide to lynch
               another man, who killed a farmer, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>What Ed Hill did to be lynched; Where they lynched him</title>
            <synopsis>Ed Hill swings at the farmers with his cup in a floursack,
               so they lynched him along with the other. They left them
               hanging out two windows on the second floor of the
               courthouse at Colfax. A dent stayed in the tin windowsills
               where the rope was hung.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>How Shorty avoids having his moonshine operation raided by agents.</title>
            <synopsis>Shorty overhears some agents planning to raid his moon
               shine operation in the Salmon River country. So he caches
               the moonshine, then turns the shoes around on his horse,
               so it appears he's going out to his camp, while he's
               actually going into Lewiston.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Gus's first job at the age of 12, the price he was paid; the eating routine of the
               harvest crew
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Gus' first paying job was carrying water for a thrashing
               crew at the age of twelve for 75C a day; while he had
               been promised a job cutting bands for $2.00 a day.
               Carrying water was twice as hard, the pay terrible, and
               he didn't have a cayuse. Eating routine of the harvest
               crew.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3420</time>
            <title>Driving a bundle wagon during harvest; working with different plows</title>
            <synopsis>Driving a bundle wagon in harvest. As a boy he used a
               walking plow, then graduated to a gang plow.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>Logging in the early days near Elk River.</title>
            <synopsis>Logging in the early days near Elk River.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Living and working in the logging camps; working with different people in the logging
               camps; accidents, deaths, and fighting in logging camps
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Railroad bunk cars in logging camps. Ten hour days,
               plus walking to and from the job. Greeks and other
               nationalities came to the woods before he left.
               Accidents and deaths were common and fighting when
               drunk too.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>More about Shorty Hill. Harvest work as a boy. 12-18-74 1.1 hr</description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13233_lcoh_13233.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13437</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Gamble_Gus1</previous>
      <next>Gamble_WJ1</next>
      <disp_name>Gamble_Gus2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
