<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/28/1978</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Glen &amp; Agnes Gilder, 1978-06-28, Interview #6 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>3:03:04</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Gilder, Glen &amp; Agnes</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #6</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Harvard, Spring Valley</residence>
      <origin>Came with family from Seattle, Washington (1919)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gambling"&gt;gambling&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#grange halls"&gt;grange halls&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crops"&gt;crops&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sheep"&gt;sheep&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bears"&gt;bears&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sewing"&gt;sewing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#land clearing"&gt;land clearing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#construction"&gt;construction&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#woodworking"&gt;woodworking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#log cabins"&gt;log cabins&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dairies"&gt;dairies&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#working conditions"&gt;working conditions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teamsters"&gt;teamsters&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#skilled workers"&gt;skilled workers&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Harvard"&gt;Harvard&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Pullman"&gt;Pullman&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13450</file_name>
      <mp3>13451.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13451.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Fourth of July Celebrations; Ball games against locals and outsiders; Native American
               Horse Races
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Early Fourth of July celebrations in local neighborhoods. Other occasions for getting
               together. Ball games:shifting sides to play against outsiders; feuds could be put
               aside, Horse races with Indians and locals: betting, kinds of horses.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Driving to Spokane; The Difficulties of building a Farmers Union; Advantages of Grange</title>
            <synopsis>Driving back to Spokane. Farmers Union an organization of farmers to better their
               conditions. Effort to attract new members. They brought attention to the farmers'
               plight but were not effective. Different kinds of farmers made it difficult to find
               common purpose. Advantage of Grange over the other organizations. The Grange stores.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Joined Grange at thirteen; Travelled in hard weather for meetings; Dances after meetings</title>
            <synopsis>Commonness of Grange halls. He joined at thirteen; Grange needed more attendance.
               The younger members didn't mind the hard weather to get to Grange. Dances after meetings.
               The schoolhouse was the center for all meetings.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Family discussions with Kathy Jacobs</title>
            <synopsis>Family discussion with daughter,Kathy Jacobs,(not transcribed)
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>People cooperated together; Barn raisings</title>
            <synopsis>People cooperated with each other as far as they were able. Barn raisings.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Neighbors helped when needed; Haying for a man with rheumatism</title>
            <synopsis>Help from neighbors: They knew when you needed it, you didn't ask for it. Community
               haying for a man with rheumatism.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Gambling on the Harvard farm; Continuing depressions; starting over and the reluctance
               to invest in land
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His gamble on the Harvard farm, Desperation of banks; continuing depressions. Successful
               alfalfa crop. The effects of having to start over again. His reluctance to take chances
               by investing in land.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4920</time>
            <title>Raising sheep and dealing with bears</title>
            <synopsis>His sheep raising, which was easy money for him. Partnership with a sheepherder. Dealing
               with bears. Moving the herder, gently,
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Moving to a new neighborhood in Palouse River; School board meetings; Wartime wages</title>
            <synopsis>When he moved to the new neighborhood, some long-time residents weren't outgoing,
               but there were other newcomers as well, School board meetings. Palouse River was friendlier
               because there was more turnover there.Wartime wages.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Sack sewing and labor during the war</title>
            <synopsis>Sack sewing during the war for $17.00 a day. No exchange labor during war.His injury
               sack sewing,
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6420</time>
            <title>Conditions of a new farm and clearing land in free time</title>
            <synopsis>Conditions of the farm when he bought it. Clearing the land with horses. Need to make
               a living meant that clearing was done in spare time. Cleared land called "tamarack
               soil."
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Wheat crop failure at Harvard; feeding cows ruined crop</title>
            <synopsis>Loss of wheat crops at Harvard. Hay was always his crop. Feeding ruined wheat crop
               for cattle around '48.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Building early houses and using available space</title>
            <synopsis>Use of space in small house on the new place. Building early houses. Layering wallpaper,
               using cheap wallpaper. Two children to a bed.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7860</time>
            <title>Building a log house in 1950; Construction took 10 years</title>
            <synopsis>Building the log house they live in now(starting 1950), Cutting logs and trying to
               get them by the miller. Use of logs. Course of house constructing was ten years, Wiring
               by himself because the contractor wanted the whole job. His experience helping others
               build their own houses. Learning woodworking in high school. The instructor said "if
               you could build a perfect box you could build anything.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8760</time>
            <title>High school and college in Pullman; Living in Pullman and working at a dairy</title>
            <synopsis>Going to high school in Pullman, connected with WSC, which taught four years in three.
               It was a hard course of study. Living in Pullman with others in a one-room shack.
               He worked four hours a day at the dairy. Entertainment in Pullman.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9000</time>
            <title>Working while attending school; Studying animal husbandry</title>
            <synopsis>His earnings while in school. School was set up for district without schools. He went
               to study animal husbandry. The decision to go was the young people's.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9420</time>
            <title>School in Potlatch; Boarders took advantage of Glen's sisters</title>
            <synopsis>Distance to school in Potlatch. His sisters lived and worked there, and were taken
               advantage of by the people they boarded with; her sisters had the same experience.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9660</time>
            <title>Bad housing conditions at Camp 11; IWW improved conditions; Potlatch punished pro-union
               employees
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Description of bughouse in Camp 11. 75 men in the room drying their clothes every
               night. Lousy bunkhouses. Farmers took better care of hogs than Potlatch their men,The
               cook shack had good food, IWW success in improving conditions within, one year. Potlatch
               punished employees who sympathised with union by denying them retirement benefits,
               Potlatch opposed union because it cut into profits. Firing employees.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10560</time>
            <title>Working as a teamster from 1918 to 1926</title>
            <synopsis>His work in woods from 1918 to 1926 as teamster: he could always get a team. He preferred
               skilled work that paid more,
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Agnes Glenn (wife) Farm self-sufficiency; farming equipment. Juliaetta and
         Kendrick Dr. Ruffle. School and dances. Tramway. 9-28-75 1.8 hr KP
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This conversation with Glen Gilder and Agnes Clark Gilder took place at their
         home in Spring Valley not far from Troy, Idaho on June 28, 1978. The interviewer was
         Sam Schrager. Please see the PDF transcript for labels of who is speaking.
         
         GLEN GILDER: — clear across the United States.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: Agnes was telling me she wasn't too sure that there'd be a plane
         back East. Now that they've landed, there'd sure better be.
         I was going to ask you guys about the-Fourth of July, since you
         were telling me about a picnic and I can remember you saying
         once that you used to have picnics pretty regularly on the
         Fourth. Is that a tradition?
         
         Used to be, used to be.
         
         Used to be fifty years ago. Now they've kind of quit it, but
         they're talking about having some kind of a picnic at the CC
         dam, from around Troy, I don't know who's in on it or whether-
         Everybody's supposed to come.
         What about it fifty years ago? I mean, was it an annual- every
         year there was a picnic?
         Well, where I came from, I don't know about around here, but
         thev didn't so much around here, but over on the coast they used
         to have a neighborhood picnic and we all went. Of course, I
         was achild then,-fmore than fifty years ago. I, like everybody
         else thought had to have something, some sort of doings on
         did. And every little town that^couldn't go to the next town
         conveniently, they had a picnic and generally had a ball game.
         The,one that I remember around here was in Moscow and everybody.
         and that was in 1919, I think.
         
         Well, that was just a big Fourth of July celebration.
         It was a pretty big one alright. And then there was one at
         Pullman about the next year.
         
         But the same year they had a big blowout at Kennedy Ford and
         most neighborhoods had aGrange picnic, aSunday School picnic
         or a town picnic, they had something. Or just a bunch of fa
         milies get together. If there wasn't anything else going on
         my folks and adozen or so neighbors would all go up to Laird
         Park and have their own picnic. And they'd get up there there'd
         be people from here and everywhere and there was horseshoe games
         and baseball games, there was always a lot going on.
         After we were married a couple of years, we went,to Park.
         Yeah, we went up there and into Deke Johnson's and the Butterfields
         and Nelsons and who went with us? - Yes, just
         congregate that way. Two or three families or twenty-five fa
         milies or whole neighborhood, it didn't matter.
         So, it just depended on the year, what people did on the Fourth?
         
         You're still talking about the Fourth?
         
         Well, the Fourth, as a general thing. But it was customary.
         We'd celebrate the Fourth of July in some way. Harvard- it'd
         be in town or else Laird Park, one or the other. And everybody
         in the neighborhood was there, there just was no exceptions.
         You were talking about how the neighborhood would - people would
         get together for different occasions, but the store was the
         place people would meet.
         
         Yeah, the store- every day at mailtime, that was for sure. Es
         pecially in the wintertime.
         
         And church was a place- no, it was the school.
         
         Oh, for parties and literary and such as that, why, the school
         was the social point and then later on they got, I don't know
         that it was later on, but they got thefcrange Hall and then that
         was, of course, we congregated. And then in the summertime, why,
         anyplace that happened to strike your fancy.
         Ball games was one way.
         
         Huh?
         
         I said ball games sometimes were-
         Yeah, that was important.
         Was this Princeton versus Harvard?
         
         Yes.
         Well, they had one at Kennedy Ford- around Kennedy Ford and up
         there around
         Yeah.
         They had pretty good-
         Yeah, and on up Deep Creek, Potlatch had a very good team. They
         hardly ever played the country boys, they played the larger towns,
         Genesee and Colton and Colfax and such. But used to be a ball
         game at Kennedy Ford four years out of five on the Fourth.
         Was it town against town usually?
         Neighborhood against neighborhood, as a rule, but they did- Ken
         nedy Ford against Viola or Kennedy Ford against rCty or
         the Indians up at Tensed. And hard tell who it would be, but al
         ways something going on.
         
         What would the boundaries be of your neighborhood?
         
         None. It'd depend on-
         Well, yeah, in a way, but there wasn't any. Post office distributation
         or school district or something like that might draw
         a line, but actually there wasn't any. If Princeton had a real
         tough game coming up, they're just as apt as not to come up to
         Harvard and ge1^ their best players and go play someplace else,
         maybe Tensed, Deep Creek, Mountain Home.
         So Princeton could be your enemy one time and you could be on
         their side when they played against Tensed?
         Yeah. (Chuckles) Yeah.
         
         Have you ever heard of this one up here at"Eary and Troy?
         Well, yes, still goes pretty strong. (Laughter)
         Won't even look at each other yet, some of 'em.
         Did they ever get on the same side to play Bovill? I don't know
         about that.
         
         Might, Potlatch or something like that.
         They might if they were going to get a game with some real tough
         team like Potlatch or Genesee, theyA double up.
         With the high school they had- Well, the high school, I guess
         you got Deary and Bovill going together against Troy.
         That's only recent, though. Well, I tell you, there was some
         awful feuds went on in those days over this baseball.
         and basketball
         Wasn't just baseball, it was footballAand everything else.
         Well, it's basketball now, but in early days
         ^didn'tfconsider basketball, didn't even have 'em. Didn't have
         it till the schools organized their teams.
         Do you remember afeud in between- was it Princeton and Harvard?
         The feeling?
         The feuding.
         
         Oh, in the baseball game, yeah, yeah. Used to get some pretty
         mad people and on the other side'd be some pretty happy people.
         Not very often.
         
         There was some real unfriendly talk between them, but I wasn't
         there so li
         lt's funny, they go to a baseball game and have a row-in the
         baseball game they'd play the tightest game that they possibly
         could and have several arguments during the game; next Satur
         day night go to Princeton or Harvard and they'd have a dance
         and they'd just mingle in thereAlike they was all brothers and
         sisters! (Chuckles)
         
         Oh, they had to make their own amusement and they made
         it. Horse races used to be quite common. Princeton, you know
         that coop store there that the lane runs right up towards the
         hill there? I've seen a lot of horse races on that. Good ones,
         some of 'em. Kennedy Ford had a round track up there and horse
         racing and rodeos and so on was quite common there and would
         be on the Fourth of July but they'd probably have two or three
         or four during the summer. The Indians would come from Lapwai,
         Tensed and anybody that had a good horse anyplace in the coun
         try, he'd try to be there and try to get some of that money.
         I think it cost about 5 to enter a horse in the^races and then
         they'd split that among the winners. And they generally took up
         a collection, pass a hat before the race and^thejt kinda split
         that. Give some little incentive. Wasn't very likely to get
         over2 or 3 or 5 at the very best, but they had their fun.
         
         Was there sidebetting going on, too?
         
         Pardon?
         
         Was there much sidebetting, too?
         
         Oh, absolutely, yes. Yeah. Didn't matter whether there was a
         law against it or not, they bet all they could stand. Some of
         'em bet all they had, you know, cash in their pockets. There
         was just lots of excitement, rivalry and such over those horse
         races.
         
         Were you under much incentive to support your neighbor's horse,
         your friend's horse? Bet on him.
         
         I didn't know enough about it to think I was a bettor. I'd
         probably spent all the money I had before it got to that point.
         Oh, sometimes bet a dollar or two, if I had it. But it was the
         older guys, sportier guys went in for that. The younger guys
         kind of got a kick out of watching it and that was the extent
         of it.
         
         Were those Indian horses really hard to beat?
         That's right. That's right, , however there was some damn
         good horses around Palouse and Potlatch and Kennedy Ford, too.
         Some darn good ones, but they never went out of their own county,
         they never tried to go to Spokane or Pendleton or Colfax
         or any of those places, they stayed little.
         
         The horses they'd race, would they be horses that had been
         raised for riding horses instead of work horses?
         Yeah. Yeah, there was riding and driving. There was some
         pretty good French coaches in the country at that time, some
         German coaches. Quite a few Hamiltonians and an occasional
         thoroughbred. But there were lots of- these were only breds,
         they weren't halfbloods that we had. But every now and then
         some of these little knotheaded broncos caught wild would clean
         house. They would. Some of 'em were terribly fast.
         There is something I've kind of wondered about, is how much peo
         ple did just straight horseback riding in those days as compared
         to going by wagon.
         
         Well, if I was going to town I'd go horseback, if she was going
         to town better take the hack or buggy. And the kids, of course,
         would have to have a place to ride, so they'd require a wagon,
         hack, buggy, whatever had.
         
         You've driven from Colfax- You know I showed you where
         my granddad lived out there, showed you the road that went out
         to his place. They used to start from there about five or six
         o'clock in the morning and sometime get into Spokane and have
         their horses taken care of and probably had supper eaten by seven
         thirty. Approximately seventy-five miles, approximately ten
         hours, an average of about seven and a half miles an hour. And
         some of rem could make an average of ten miles an hour and hold
         it all day, and drive a hundred miles with abuggy; nothin' to
         it. They'd leave that place right there and in about seven hours
         they'd be in Spokane. Had an old team, Dan and Lou, half Hamiltonian
         and Ifpect half was cayuse, Idon't know. They were
         only about seventeen or eighteen hands high and about two hands wide
         but they could travel.
         How far is it to—?
         Palouse to Spokane? 
         
         Well, no, from, well, Kennedy Ford to Spokane? 
         Somewheres in the neighborhood of seventy-five miles, I don't
         know.
         
         It's just 100 here, or used to be.
         tfeah. Well, with those kinks and such, about twenty-five miles
         down there and you'd have to go through Moscow and then come down
         here, this coming down here wouldn't count. But seventy-five
         or eighty miles. If they had to go to Spokane, they'd just
         simply go. I don't know of any time but once that they ever
         drove in the wintertime with a sleigh, but they'd go in the
         summertime when it was warm.
         
         In those days had to-get^ through on the train, no trouble
         at all. But they've taken all those off and want to take all
         the rest off, I guess.
         
         I know that's true and I can't see why they did it. They could
         have gone down to Kennedy Ford, a mile from the house, caught
         the train to Palouse and then caught the train from Palouse to
         Spokane. I don't know.
         
         Did they haul any stuff back with 'em?
         No, not as a rule.
         Did they stay overmight when they got to Spokane?
         Oh, they'd have to. Maybe stay a week.
         Where would they stay, I wonder?
         
         Oh, I'll tell you, they had friends all over town, but if they
         didn't want to go there, they always went to the Ridpath. But
         they had friends all over town- good ones.
         Sort of seems to me like you're saying they're taking a vacation.
         (Chuckles)
         
         There was always some definite reason for 'em to go. Maybe it
         was a meeting of this or that, Farmers Union, Grange or what have
         you, but there was always something definite to go tor.
         You know, you mentioned the Farmers Union. That's something else
         that I'd like to find out— something about. What was that?
         I never even heard of it until the last fifteen or twenty years.
         Oh, it's been longer than that, they've had it for years. It
         was an organization of farmers to try and better their conditions.
         Markets and such. It never accomplished very mnch. It couldn't
         get big enough. Then here about twenty years ago, they reorganized
         and made adefinite effort to get in all the new members they
         could and they created some fuss alright. And about that time
         they got that National Farmers Organization, and
         they did quite abit of good and on the other hand, they didn't
         accomplish near what they thought they were going to.
         oh  this farmers strike, just recently. Does that have
         its roots in the kind of movement of the Farmers Union.was?
         Iimagine it did. Ithink it was acombination of Farmers Union
         and NFO; Ireally don't know about it for sure, but Ithink it
         was. And, out of all the three of 'em they accomplished about
         the same thing that the national strike did last winter. They
         brought some attention to the farmer from higher up government.
         But, it was more or less ineffective. Idon't know, they didn't
         any of 'em accomplish what they had thought they would.
         Was the Farmers Union back in the old days, was it something
         that everybody supported,or was the opinion about it amongst the
         people, the local people, divided?
         
         Oh, about half, maybe, of the farmers in an area would sign up
         and take out amembership in it and then about half of them would
         go to ameeting or two and then they'd all go dormant and there'd
         be two or three, maybe five or six would keep it enough alive to
         keep it going and then^me up some other little surge and they'd
         go ahead again; up and down. But farmers are aclass of people
         that you can't organize. There's wheat farmers, there's cotton
         farmers, there's corn farmers and there's pig farmers and dairy
         farmers and wheat farmers, and what'11 apply to one won't touch
         the other one, even in the small neighborhood. Used to find dairy
         men and wheat, poultry, this and that and all of 'em had a dif
         ferent slant on what they wanted. And if the program that was
         shown to them didn't suit 'em, they just left it alone. Grange
         has come the closest to organizing neighborhoods and keeping them
         together and serving a purpose, better, I think, than any of the
         others, but maybe I'm wrong. I don't think so, I don't know.
         
         SS:  What makes the Grange, say, better than the Farmers union as an
         organization?
         
         GLEN:  They didn't cater or try to go to any specific point in the bus
         iness, but they wanted to include everybody, and they did. They
         had one in just about every other town. You know, they used to
         have one at Troy, one at Joel, one at Moscow and one at Palouse,
         Kennedy Ford, Princeton and for a time they had one at Harvard.
         And they would work together very well. And they'd have some
         arguments here and there but they'd say, "Will we support this
         or will we not support it?" And then they'd just hold kind of
         a- you've seen 'em on those little elections on points. And
         then whatever they decided, that's the way they'd go and the
         whole dang bunch'd push it. And they'd go from Grange to Grange
         and just push something through. They had a store in Moscow and
         Palouse and Garfield where you could buy just about anything that
         you wanted, and that was all owned by individual grain growers.
         And indivivual grangers- we each could put in 10 and they used
         that 10 to get a building and stock it '. as much as they
         could. They bought cooperatively gasolme-
         
         SS:  What was the first thing?
         
         GLEN:  Landplaster. Gypsum. And then they put in tools, machinery parts
         and things like gloves and overalls and things like that. I
         don't know they worked that, but the Latah County Grain Growers
         evidently taken that over. And the Grange is out of it.
         
         SS:  Well to the store, then they've got the Grange
         Co-op and all. Is that one of the- those stores?
         
         GLEN:  That's one of 'em. All of these were organized about, oh, in
         the '30's.
         
         END SIDE A
         
         GLEN:  I really don't know. They must have organized that before even
         1900, but I really don't know.
         
         SS:  I know it's a long time ago.
         
         GLEN:  Perhaps they would be more active during hard times, but- I
         just don't know enough about it to tell you.
         
         SS:  Did your father- did he believe in the Grange much?
         
         GLEN:  To some extent, yes. But my granddad, oh, I think he belongedhe
         was in the Grange though and he thought that the Grange could
         do it and would do it and supported the Grange more than he would
         the Farmers Union. But, on the other hand, I think he'd support
         'em both equally if they had it coming- in his estimation. He
         was Master of the Washington State Grange, oh, twenty-five or
         thirty years,I guess, I don't know. I don't know when he first
         went in, I know when he went out was in November, 1917. That's
         when he died.
         
         SS:  Was there a Grange Hall in the area where you lived back that
         early?
         
         GLEN:  Grange Hall?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         GLEN:  Damn right. (Chuckles) You bet. They used the schools and the
         churches and the public halls like the Odd Fellows hall or some
         thing like that, but they almost always got around to building
         their own hall. Took some time, but that big one at Kennedy Ford
         is still in use and I believe it was built in 1906,/(I m not sure.
         What does it say on the end of that building? I think it's f06.
         Was the Grange as open to nonfarmers back then as it is today,
         or was it mostly farm families?
         I think it was. I think it was open to just about everyone. The
         merchants in Palouse, he was involved in farming almost as much
         as the man that was-
         Well, that came later.
         
         Huh?
         That must have come later, because-
         It probably did, I don't know.
         
         When my folks were on the coast
         You know, I joined the Grange in 1914. I was supposed to be four
         teen years old but I was only thirteen, but they needed more mem
         bers and they needed 'em badly and they held a meeting and decided
         to take I and Carl Lancaster and Mau4e Canfield, and there wasn't
         any of us quite old enough, but they needed the more members and
         all of our belonged, so we just got elected to be members,
         almost a year before we were old enough.
         We did the same thing over on the Coast with me, put me in before
         I was fourteen or whatever it was supposed to be. They had to to
         get a quorum.
         
         That's the reason they had it that way at ours, because-
         They had the members, but they wouldn't come.
         
         Well, that's right, there's always something, seemed like, that
         would keep them from coming. And so, they did that. And it
         worked alright. And then, we kids never would open our heads,
         we didn't have any opinions to express or anything of the sort.
         And then on farther than that, our dues, membership, was just as
         good as somebody that was seventy-five years old. That's really
         the main object, was to get a little bit more financial
         stability.
         
         You were junior grange members or full Grange members?
         No, there was no junior; that didn't come for a long time.
         They might have had it back East, but they didn't have it on the
         Coast.
         
         No, nor here. No, that didn't come until in the 30's sometime
         My folks were very enthusiastic Grange members over there^.
         What you're saying that the attendance of meetings was a problem
         then like it is today.
         
         Well, it was. ^Transportation was pretty good if you were young
         enough, you didn't give a darn whether it was raining or blowing
         or snowing, you'd get on a saddle horse or get in a sled and go,
         but as got a little older, it was awful nice to stay home
         and let that Grange meeting worry about it's own problems, and
         not go out in the cold after you'd been out in it all day! But
         the younger people, they didn't care about whether it was storming
         or not. They couldn't get a saddle horse that night- couldn't
         get a team to take their girl, they didn't take her.
         Well, we walked.
         
         Would you say that this was social mostly back then, or was it
         more political, more decision- you know, making decisions?
         
         Was it really just to socialize and get together or was it forto
         organize the farmers' interests?
         
         Oh, the farmers' interests were really primary, and I think there
         hardly ever was a meeting that there didn't something come up in
         serious business; probably two or three ., but at the same
         time, they never drew the line on that social part. If you didn't
         have Grange this week, they'd arrange for their dance the next
         week or the^ice cream social or something.
         Well, over there on the Coast there wasn't any social business
         about it, it was strictly business if .We never danced
         or anything.
         
         Would the dancing be after the meeting?
         Would be after the meeting, quite often. Quite often.
         Was the dancing at Grange any different as a get-together than
         dancing for a community dance?
         Just the same thing. Had the same music, the same people, no
         difference.
         Well, they could charge and other people came in on the regular
         dance.
         
         Yeah. Saturday just as a dance, then they used
         charge the men as much as fifty cents, more than likeL it was only
         twenty-five cents. Gosh, it got to be way long in pretty good
         times- wartimes- when they got up to a dollar for a couple.
         The Grange was a big benefit socially and economically. In bus
         iness, it didn't hurt anything, never.
         What was the school program like? Was that at the schoolhouse
         and a fairly regular affair?
         
         You mean other meetings in the school?
         Well, you said the school programs that you had. That would be
         evening get-togathers.
         Well, at first, Thanksgiving, Christmas or Easter or the last
         day of school. But the schoolhouse, that was generally the
         place until they got better, for everything. Hell, the first
         Grange meetings at Harvard were held in the schoolhouse for years.
         And church, and elections. The schoolhouse was the center of
         that neighborhood, and then they built the church, then they
         built a Grange Hall. Come slow, but it all came. But that old
         schoolhouse was busy day and night.(It's ringing all the time
         here) (telephone)
         We're even on the Smokehouse - same phone number as the Smoke
         house downtown, and we get their phone numbers- their phone calls.
         Calling for Richard Spencer all time] (Chuckles)
         
         made a mistake, but it's sure a convenience. You can go
         over there and answer the phone and all they want's the beer par
         a little more serious matter.
         
         There are^ have been, occasions out here when make a mistake like
         that the telephone company had to correct it, right now! Regard
         less of what it cost 'em. That's really infringing on your rights
         when the phone rings for somebody else constantly. It isn't as
         bad here as it could have been.
         
         Some of 'em can't get it through their head that they re getting
         the wrong number.
         Do they use the same number?
         Yes, it's in the- it's alright in the Troy book, but this is a
         book that was published someplace in Utah.
         Talking about the Unions.
         
         You don't need to worry that secretary of the union'd be right
         around; they give you a certain number of days that you don't
         have to sign up and then he'll be around after his 5 bill.
         Is that such a bad thing?
         It isn't too bad. I used to get quite a lot of work with 'em.
         Used to sign up with 'em in the fall and generally was good for
         as long as I wanted to work. Weather got too damn bad I didn't
         want to work. But they'd lay us off day or two, then call us
         back, then lay us off and then call us back. Well, what do you
         expect? We're not members and the members of course, naturally
         just entitled to that first chance at a job as soon as anybody
         wanted it.
         
         Say, how much were those pictures? Do you remember?
         Something that really has puzzled me for a long time that I'm
         trying to figure out and that is; there on the one hand it seems
         like the community, the neighborhood, not just where you lived
         was really strong. And it supported people, a lot of support,
         you know, help. And then on the other hand it seems like still
         a guy had to make it on his own. I mean, he had to pull hard
         to make it. And I'm not too sure where you'd draw the line, where
         you'd say that's as much help as you could get around here and
         where you had to pull out on your own. You know what I mean?
         
         Yes. Well, there wan't any line there. People would cooperate
         as far as they were able for time and money and such, but there
         wasn't any line. Maybe they'd start to build somebody a house
         and four or five of 'em would go aways, four, five of 'em take
         over and go from there on and different ones'd drop back in and
         out, but they'd finish the job in some way. Roberts' house, they
         started that the day or two after the fire and George Nichols
         barn, he decided he had to have a barn and so they started it,
         it took a while but 'got it and Burgers' house and barn. Just
         went on all over the country. The place where Ashes live, there
         was a fellow by the name of Trottmeyer owned that and he was sick
         and they put that barn up from start to finish and it was a big
         barn; 52x60 I believe.
         
         Everybody work on it at once there or was it a barnraising in
         the old style?
         
         Yes, that's right. And then they got it up to point where
         they didn't need all this crowd, why then, whatever was necessary
         would take over. Maybe one crew would work a few days and then
         they had to go home and another crew'd take over.
         His barn, did it burn down or was it just being built from scratch?
         It was from scratch. No Tottmeyer's barn didn't burn down, he
         didn't have a barn, but he had to have one and so they put it up
         for him. Shortly after that he died and they even finished it
         after he died. My dad was administrator of that estate and they
         sold it to Hamberg and by golly, they still went ahead after that
         and kind of made a neighborhood projectNof it, finished it up
         anyway.KThey claimed that Albert Bailey done that, supervised
         it. Then they had a barnraising and they all pitched in, went
         to the mill and got lumber for siding and another crew went to
         the woods and got shake timber and my God, they made the shakes
         and everything, when they raised the barn on . place. I fra
         med it. And I think I was seventeen years old; seventeen or eigh
         teen, the neighbors come in and set it up and Dad
         traded a calf to ^^ for lumber and I and one of the neighbors
         went and got that on two wagons. And then my brother and I went
         to the Hoodoos and got some cedar for shakes. And two or three
         days, there must have been a dozen neighbors around there making
         shakes and they figured they had enough ahead, and then four, five
         neighbors started in and put those shakes on the barn. And,
         you know, thtf^old barn's still standing over there; still in use.
         Put up there in 1917 or '18.
         
         It sounds like, Glen, the kind of cooperation you're talking about
         is when somebody needed something, a big project, where it was
         really more than a person could spare time by just themselvesit
         would take a long time to do it by himself, and that's when
         the community moved in and helped.
         
         That's the way it worked. They would take over and all work to
         gether, have a big old time while they're doing it. And they'd
         get acquainted with newcomers that way and they'd visit. They
         would take over. If somebody was sick, this'n would sit up with
         'em all night tonight and somebody else sit up for tomorrow night
         and if necessary they did it time after time. They thought noth
         ing of it whatever, just the thing to do and they did it.
         When you put up your barn, did your folks, did your mother feed
         the people over there working?
         
         No, if I went she'd go and take a potluck dinner, and they just
         made kind of a picnic out of it. Then if there was only one or
         two or three, why, then the folks would feed 'em and think no
         thing of it. Just whatever the conditions called for, why, that's
         the way they done it.
         
         SS:  What about the other side of the coin? Say like when people were
         having hard- really pretty hard luck- hard times struggling to
         make it? Say like in the Depression or just when you had a lit
         tle, then you still wouldn't feel that- a person wouldn't just
         call on his neighbor for help, would he? Seems like when you
         had a rough time you just struggled through it pretty much by
         yourself.
         
         GLEN:  No, you didn't call on your neighbors for help. The neighbors
         knew you needed help and they volunteered it. No, you didnt call
         on 'em; you didn't have to. One or two cases where in harvest ih
         somebody would be hurt or sick, hell, we'd just all get together
         and1.crop and forget it. Let their own go. Go and
         take care of this one, get it out of the way so he would have his
         money to pay the bills, if there were any. But, no, they didn't
         ask for help, no, they didn't have to. there at Potlatch
         was crippled up with rheumatism and, gee, he had a big haying job
         probably about 100 ton and those farmers from all over the country^
         they pulled in there and mowed it, raked it, shocked it, and hauled
         it in his barn and baled it. And Pete didn't- I don't think he IV45
         a penny and I don't think that they had to furnish a meal.
         We'd go to the house because that's where the water was but, God,
         the women was all there and they had dinner ready for us and sup
         per if we wanted to stay. Herb and Louie Kegley and I, there was
         three of us in the crowd went over there, four or five miles away,
         took our horses, each had a team or^whatever was necessary and
         that big bunch of hay was taken care of in four or five days.
         One man couldn't have taken care of it in a month. And he never
         called for help. The old lady and the kids was out there trying
         to help him; neighbors seen it and just took over. Hodge was
         there; Fay was there, Hibberds were there, Kegleys, Wallaces,
         Pete Clyde, everybody was there. So darn many of 'em, they
         got in the way sometimes. But they did the job. And Pete never
         did get over that, he never did completely get over that, but he
         finally did get so he could work, do chores and things like that.
         They called it rheumatism, didn't they?
         
         Yeah, it was rheumatism, but I don't know what type.
         Probably arthritis, we'd call it now.
         I know that he ended up a cripple for the rest of his life.
         About when did this happen?
         About '48 or '19.
         
         When you were in danger of losing your place at Harvard in the
         '30's and you were really working hard to catch up with the Land
         Bank people, you couldn't really get much help, or you didn't
         try to get much help from the neighbors.
         No, although, they were awful good about coming in and help
         during harvest and I'd go over and help them during harvest. That
         was just an ordinary thing. You know, there wasn't any way they
         could help me.
         Wasn't very many of 'em had much themselves.
         
         No they didn't, not as a rule. Having their own troubles. There
         ain't no use trying to help me; I got myself into a helpless condition
         there. We knew before we went up -^ chance of not making
         it. If we hadda got a break and wheat had got up about 1 we'd
         a made it good, but to stay down under seventy-five cents a bushel
         why, just wouldn't. We just went up there on a gamble and we knew
         it. But, on the other hand, I had it whipped, had it wh ipped,
         but they decided I wasn't entitled to any more time.
         That's part of the story we talked about, about back in the '30's
         before, I mean, that's what made you wind up coming over here and
         it seems to me like that happened to a number of people.
         Oh, yeah, I wasn't alone on it. By no means!
         
         No, the banks were desperate; they'd had their holiday but
         they still had money out they couldn't collect it, and it was
         just conditions. They had it in 1893 and they had it again in
         '97; they had it again in 1922 and then they got it again in 1930
         and it lasted till 1940. That was a long time. That was rough.
         Do you think it would have made a big difference if you hadn't
         a grown wheat? If you'd done something else with the money? At
         that time?
         
         That's right! And ^had done it. They said you couldn't saise
         alfalfa in that area and I had an idea that you could. So I
         put in a crop of peas, there was twenty-seven acres on that field,
         and I innoculated it and then I landplastered it and the next year
         went out there and landplastered and I disced it twice and har
         rowed it down and put in that alfalfa, and at the first of June
         when it should have been a foot high it was only about two inches
         high. I don't know what got into it or what held it back, but
         anyway, it started to grow and I got off that twenty-seven acres
         I filled that barn, 52x60, and I'll bet you that it had 100 ton
         in it. Best alfalfa I ever seen. It was just simply a matter ofand
         that is the answer to your question. I had done it. I had
         alfalfa and I had the cattle to eat it and sheep. If they'd
         left me alone I had it whipped. I had a nice bunch of sheep,
         about 100 ewes and I had about twenty head of pretty good yearling
         and three year old heifers to eat that hay and I was on my way.
         But I was back payments and back interest and I did manage to keep
         the taxes up. Sometimes I was late with them, but I kept 'em
         up. That was just something that happened and I don't think it
         hurt us. We'd been well fixed by now if we coulda stayed there.
         We come over here. We had to struggle a little harder, we had
         to sell this stuff because we didn't have hay land here, we had
         to sell the stock in order to get in here, so it put us right
         down to bedrock again then we just hung tough and struggled along
         and finally we're alright. We don't need for anything.
         So, it's alright, wasn't hurt. Probably a good lesson, I don't
         know. (Chuckles) But I know I didn't have the incentive to strike
         out and get bigger and get rich. I was afraid to stick my neck
         out for a 500 investment. I was scared to do it on account of
         the experience we'd had over there. So we just struggled along
         a dollar at a time. There was never a dull moment. (Chuckles)
         Not any single moment. It was a hard battle and interesting
         battle and the tougher it'd get, the harder I'd fight, I
         think the more I enjoyed it.
         
         SS:  It sounds like there was a purpose in it, because being hard
         made it all the more challenging.
         
         GLEN:  Well, it sure as hell wasn't easy, but it worked out. Give a
         person back in those days . had the guts and the money or
         any way to get ahold of a big piece of land when they almost
         give it to you, why ' should adone it, but who knows, that the
         was gonna come, as it is now. I didn't.
         
         SS:  When you first- when you say 500 bucks, what kind of investment
         are you talking about, that would have taken 500 bucks?
         
         GLEN:  I coulda bought the 160 that lays right there, that the lake is
         on for 500. And Joe Mc Collum walked out here^ two or three times
         and said, "Glen, you don't have to have any money to take that,"
         he says, "you just take that and pay the taxes,"which were about
         15 a year, "and pay me when you get the money." But it was still
         a debt of 500, and my debts had to have always been paid in some
         way and I was afraid to stick my neck out. I had little kids.
         I figured I could protect them here; if I did that, maybe I
         couldn't. And, there was opportunities like that scattered clear
         around me. These places were all for sale. They were busted,
         they were discouraged. Some of 'em hung on, some of 'em didn't.
         But that's a matter of foresight and hindsight.
         
         SS:  Yes, I think that those kinds of things- everybody has in their
         past, (outside noises)
         
         When you got into that place at Harvard, you to lay 500
         down on it?
         
         GLEN:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Then what was your mortgage?
         
         GLEN:  2,500 left. There was 280 acres, I think. There was a lot of
         farm ground on it. But not any timber- merchantable timber- lots
         of brushland left. There were 125 acres cleared and the balance
         was brush. Pasture. But, it was a^good prospect if we coulda
         iust got another two bits a bushel for wheat, but we couldn t
         get it.
         
         SS:  Were there very many other people that were running sheep in the
         area at the time?
         
         Oh, there was quite a few little ten and fifteen head bands,
         yes, but there weren't any bands around me anywhere. There was
         too, Bob Thompson had 100. Well, there were one or two bands
         around of 100 or better. Most people didn't like sheep, most
         of 'em didn't. I figured that made it good for the sheepherder.
         Kept up competition, left you more room to pasture and left you
         this and that. But I was lucky on those sheep, I bought some for
         1.50 a head and I had about a lamb and a half to sell the next
         fall from each ewe, and I got- I think I got about 5 a lamb or
         was that a little heavy? I think, I got around six cents a
         pound, somewheres close, and sold the damn ewes for 3.50 after
         selling the lamb crop. Sheep always did treat me that way.
         Easiest money a man could make.
         
         SS: Did you run 'em outside of your place? Back in the countryside
         tnere?
         
         Oh, yeah, yeah. Lee Butcher came up and said to me that if I
         would tend camp for him that he would take these sheep of mine
         and put 'em with his, he had 500 and I had 100 ewes or a little
         better, and we took 'em to the range and we started 'em up Ruby
         Creek and fed that all out and then we crossed over into the head
         of Bear Creek and come in there behind Dwight Corey's and
         finished up there at Dwight Corey's in the fall. And what I did,
         I'd take him his groceries and his mail and salt and everything
         he needed and move his camp twice a week. He did the herding,
         and it worked very good for both of us. We had a little bear
         trouble, we lost a few lambs, but not too many, between us, pro
         bably fifteen or twenty. Bear get into 'em, but we got about half
         as many bears as they got - the bears got lambs. We trapped
         'em. And get the dogs started on 'em. I had a bunch of pretty
         good dogs, they'd chase 'em and tree 'em and we'd get 'em that
         way. Had some fun; some excitement, and a scare or two.
         
         Those bears?
         
         Yeah. Yeah, one time there was a great big old yellow pine tree
         snag laying up a steep hillside and there was a bear that we
         were after stepped up on the top of that and stood there broad-
         side and shot him and he kicked, he went on this side, he
         went on this side, he went on this side and he come right at us.
         We were standing there at the stump. Lee said, "We probably bet
         ter get get the hell outta here." We took off and pretty soon
         that bear kicked clear down into the creek deader'n a doornail.
         That reaction after- after he was shot it was just funny, he just
         crossed back and forth over that log and acted just like he was
         alive, but he was coming right towards us. So, we got outta
         there.
         That sounds like a pretty good- 
         It looked that way to us, yes.
         
         In the arrangement you had with this guy, he did the herding and
         you the supplying, that sounds like a good deal.
         It was. It was a good deal for both of us, because he didn't
         have horses or equipment to get his stuff and further than that
         he couldn't leave the sheep long enough to go and get it. Didn't
         take me very long.a couple of times a week to go and supply him
         and move his camp and set him up. I made him kinda peeved one day,
         I didn't get into camp to move him quick enough, he thought it
         wasn't quick enough. It was almost dark, or it was dark by the
         time I got through and he had packed everything, but he got his
         supper and then he figured it was too late that I wouldn't be
         there. I know he had a can of tomatoes and he only ate half of
         'em, so he had 'em in a dish in this box and he had a lot of stuff
         that shouldn't a been packed, wouldn't have ordinarily, but I
         put that on that horse, a box on each side and led him over quite
         a steep hill and down into another draw; unpacked it and about
         the time I got the tent set up and his bedroll packed into the
         tent and stove set up, why, here come Lee and he was kinda
         peeved, little more than peeved; madder.'n hell. Says, "You moved
         that stuff and I didn't figure on you comin'," he says, "I didn't
         get ready move," he says, "tomatoes in there and a jar of
         sourdough and there's no lid on it." And, he says, "That box of
         stuff is- I'll bet you that everything in it's ruined." Well, I
         felt pretty bad. He took the lid off, took the tomatoes out,
         and I don't think they spilled a dropJ And he went on down and
         the sourdough I don't think it spilled a drop. He was happy and
         I felt better. But I did carry the mail to him earlier after that.
         
         Don't know what held me up that day, but something. Something
         held me back.
         Was he a bachelor?
         Yeah. Well, no, let's see- no, his wife lived in Lewiston and he
         owned a place in Lewiston but they none of 'em ever come up there.
         He was just a starting, he wasn't out of the woods yet.
         Did he have grazing rights in the area there?
         Yeah. He had the whole Ruby Creek, Flat Creek, Bear Creek. We
         had grazing rights on 4,000 acres there i expect.
         So you got grazing rights just by going in with him then?
         Yeah.
         
         Did you keep the partnership up very long?
         
         No, just the one year. He- I had to sell out- I had to get out
         because we were coming here. So I sold the sheep. I sold every
         one of 'em.
         You kept some.
         
         No, of that bunch I think I sold every one of 'em, didn't I?
         You kept that big old long that high and long hair on
         her about so.
         
         Didn't I go- Yes, I musta kept them ewes that I got at WSC. I
         got thirteen head of ewes from WSC and I guess we kept them.
         But I sold everything else.
         
         You know, it seemed to me like your roots in a way are over on
         the other side of the mountain more than here. I've had the
         feeling that your oldest friends are over there and those are
         people you grew up with as compare d to people over here, where
         you're more of a newcomer. I kind of wondered how the difference
         was between the neighborhood over there and the neighborhood
         over here. It seemed like that's a little more solid, old-time
         neighborhood than what you came to when you moved over here.
         It was overall, but down here on Allen's place Pelfrey was a
         newcomer. Up here on Boughten's place, Boughtens were newcomers.
         And over on Davises- the next place over- no the second place
         over, was another newcomer. And we just worked right together,
         because we were newcomers. There was some of the older people
         accepted us, Stostems and Osmond and Mc Leans over here. But
         as a rule it's pretty hard to break into them- it was hard to
         get acquainted with 'em, but on account of having all these new
         comers made it a lot easier. We exchanged work, we exchanged
         visits, we helped one another just like friends would. Some
         times we ' together, sometimes harvested together or butchered
         or things like that. And just got by pretty good. But I'm sure
         glad they were there because the old-time neighborhood people
         didn't care whether they accepted us or not, they were kind of
         hard to break into.
         
         Not all of 'em.
         Not all of 'em, but as a rule that was true. One new business
         man in Troy said, "it took me five years to get these people in
         this neighborhood to even trade with me. All of 'em." He says,
         "There would always be a few," but he says, "it took five years
         to get started, acquainted, or whatever you call it."
         Was he Swedish or Norwegian? Was he Scandinavian?
         
         Yeah, he was. He was Swedish, but the neighborhood he was a
         stranger and they had their habits. They traded in the store
         where they'd been trading there for fifty years and they wouldn't
         change. He was new. And the same thing kind of applied to us.
         I don't understand it, but it's hard to break in to one group and
         on the other hand, they elected me on the school board the first
         year I was here. The neighborhood was trying. And, oh, we got
         by. We learned to like these people and they finally learned to
         like us, but they weren't real anxious to cross that barrier be
         tween ' stranger and somebody they knew. But they finally
         did.
         
         Which school district was the one here?
         
         This district here, although there was a school right down here
         we belonged to this district that's over here
         at Big Meadow.
         
         Where was the school?
         
         The school was over at Big Meadow where the church is. That
         church is the old original schoolhouse.
         Big Meadow, now where are we talking about exactly? Which church
         is that?
         
         It's on Walt Littler's place. I think you've seen that Advent
         Church over there.
         
         Sure.
         
         Well, that's it. That's where the school was. But these kids
         never had to go over there. They had consolidated and our kids
         - a bus right here in front of the house.
         
         How did it come that there was a school?
         
         There was a school some other place. It wasn't there. They
         brought that over when they bought that church. They brought
         that church over there from some place up here on the hill. I
         don't know for sure where, -
         Which board were you on then?
         
         Big Meadow over there. Why was that?
         Oh, they wanted something done- put you on the board, you mean?
         Yeah.
         
         They wanted something done and they were afraid somebody else
         wouldn't do it. (Chuckles)
         I don't know, but they were consolidated and yet they had their
         individual school board out here and we had to go to town to
         school board meetings that were represented from White Pine over
         here, Big Meadow and down here at Nelson's and the school board
         meeting at that time would involve twenty-five, thirty people.
         And arguments! Oh, boy!
         
         Still having them.
         What was the argument over then?
         Oh,-salaries, insurance, bus drivers, repair on the school buil
         dings in Troy. Some people'd go right along with it and other
         people said, "Let 'em fix their own damn school!" But, we finally
         wound up going in and helping 'em; donatlag labor to finish those
         buildings up. And, finally, they just eliminated all these out
         here and a three-man school board, same as- instead of having a
         dozen schools around the country represented in there, just had
         a three-man school board, and that took two, three years to get
         that.
         
         You know, when you talk about hard to break into this community;
         when we've talked about what it was like for newcomers around
         Harvard, you said that it was easy for them that they were pretty
         well accepted.
         
         They were.
         
         So there was a difference between there and here?
         There was every nationality under the sun over there, but there
         were no Japanese up there. And when we firt went in there and
         until we left even, there was a constant change in the population
         for different reasons and when we came over here, these people
         were all born here, and there hadn't been any newcomers come into
         the area until about the time we started- we came. At the last
         of that depression these people around here were, oh, they wanted
         to get out of here and go someplace else.
         
         The war started soon after we came here and anybody that could
         get away went to the Coast to the shipyards and war effort, what
         ever it happened to be.
         
         Pulled out. Wanted to get out. They could get out and make big
         money working, but it was almost impossible to make a living at
         farming. You could make enough to eat and that waa about all.
         But, conditions changed with the war andAa few of us worked and
         done our farm work and still went out and got a job sawmilling
         or logging or going to Moscow on construction or anything.
         I can remember when my brother was working in the shipyards in
         Bremerton and made a dollar an hour. Boy, I thought that was
         magnificent to what we had been making. It for a while
         until prices started going up.
         
         When you worked for like Steelsmiths- what kind of pay did you
         get for that kind of work?
         Oh, by that time the war was going great guns, I got 17 a day
         down there.
         
         Where you talking about? Down at the mill?
         No, was out at iteelsmith.
         Oh, really? Just working for them?
         
         When I went up to the mill, then I got an hour, didn't I?
         Yeah, I think so.
         What were you doing for Steelsmiths?
         
         Oh, sewing sacks, on the combine. Yeah, that was big money. And
         I worked for Bert Walner down there after Steelsmiths were
         done- I was getting 17 a day, but then that was wartimes.
         Did you do the same thing for Walner, sack sewing?
         Um-huh. Sewed sacks.
         Had you done that before?
         
         Oh, you betl Lots of 'em. When I was just a young kid I used to
         do that, go out with those stationaries and sew sacks for thirtyGLEN
         five, forty days at a time. They were not new to me, the combine
         was. That was my first experience on a combine, but it didn't
         make any difference. Sewing a sack was the same, you sat
         and sewed it on that moving machine it bothered for a couple of
         hours and then after that you didn't pay any attention to it.
         You mean it took a while to get used to the position?
         The jiggle.
         
         That was a pretty skilled job on those crews, wasn't it?
         Oh-
         Pretty tough job to get.
         
         Semiskilled. Any farmer pretty near could do it. But the far
         mer had to take care of his own business. He couldn't go and
         help somebody else. The days of changing labor were out. Help
         was too damn scarce. The guy ahead of me out there at Steelsmiths
         didn't know how to sew sacks, and if he got behind he just throw
         the sack off the side, didn't sew it, dump it off!(Chuckles)
         He dumped off about four or five and Frank says, "No more of that."
         He just shut the machine down and sent Kelly to town to get a
         man andshe happened to run into me and I went out there and I
         worked for him several years and got along just fine. But finally
         one day the combine wheel dropped into a sharp ditch just as I
         pulled^150 pound sack of peas up over my knee and it tore the mus
         cle loose in my back some way, and from the 17th of August till
         the 1st of March I didn't dp ^a thin. I was in terrible pain.
         Took a long time to get over that. But they were insured and
         had enough to eat, that's about all we needed.
         
         Were you working in the mills at the same time? Back then? That
         was later.
         
         No. I had worked in mills, yeah, all my life-
         For Potlatch.
         
         I had worked in mills all my life off an on but during that time
         I had enough here to almost keep me busy and almost do the job
         and then I'd get my harvest done here earlier, why, I'd go out
         and hire out to somebody else for a few day that were remaining.
         Was this place pretty much ready to work and farm when you got
         here, or did you wind up having a lot to do to be able to operate?
         This place had 25 acres cleared on it. No fences, no buildings,
         excepting that little house out there. I don't know how we did
         it but we did it. And now there's 125 acres on it and somebody
         else is farming it. And all but twenty-two acres of that were
         cleared up with the horses. Cleared up and and broke and
         farmed with horses. Walt cleared up twenty-two acres,
         one strip up there and one over on the other side of the place.
         Then we got our own cat and cleared up some more up there,, come
         later. But right nowAthere's 125 acres of it in crops.
         When you cleared with the horses was it much the way that your
         father cleared his place, or was there must difference?
         Yeah. Just the same, no change there. The change come when we
         got bulldozers and cats and big plows. Horse days- as long as
         there was horses, it couldn't change, just one way to do it.
         Stumppuller?
         
         Oh, we had a stumppuller over there but I never here, no. Powder,
         crack 'em with some powder, pull 'em with block and lines. Block
         and tackle you'd call it probably. Cable..Then we didn't take
         all the stumps out the first time around, not by any means. Vie
         went around 'em, over 'em. We left 'em there to break our riggin' up in the future
         years, and it sure as hell did it! We do
         the best we could, get by with it. If you could clear up two acres
         a year, you were doing awful good. And they come in with
         a bulldozer in later years and clean up two acres in an hour.
         
         An hour?
         Yeah.
         Really?
         Yeah.
         Well, it wasn't always done neatly.
         Well- we had-
         
         Had a lot of work to level it off and get it ready to-
         Well, we had chopped the big timber down and cut it into wood
         and pastured sheep on it till they kill all the brush. And that
         final shot that Walt made here, the twenty-two acres, heck, he
         done that in about ten hours with a dozer; small dozer at that.
         Well, didn't Hunts do some, too?
         did Littler come in here?
         
         In the '50's.
         About '55 or '56,
         So when you started you were only raising crop on about twentyfive
         acres?
         That's right.
         
         And enlarging that every year by a couple of acres.
         Right. Yeah, you couldn't work at enlarging your place steady,
         you had to take a day here and an hour there and then two days
         someplace else. You had to make a living, whether you made it
         making cedar poles or whether you made it cutting wood or
         working for a sawmill or some other farmer, any way you could
         make a dollar. And then work at that clearing up little bit;
         just spare time.
         
         went back here to look at the place, you know, look
         it over, I think we went in about that deep of dust.
         A foot deep, huh?
         
         Just about. Had a big wind over there someplace- come to think
         of it, we did have a lot of wind blowing dust.
         See, the next three years- Well, when this land came out of the
         timber it was fluffy, loose, red colored and you had to farm it
         three or four years before it settled down to be what it is now.
         It was chuck full of tree roots and grass roots and they used to
         call it tamarack soil. It was different than anything we'd ever
         seen, but it produced pretty good crops.
         Right away or after it had been settled down?
         Yes it did, it didn't do too bad especially if you put it in hay,
         which we did. Grass, clover, alfalfa. Anything to get hay. I
         didn't like wheat, never liked wheat and I never will. I didn't
         like it.
         
         One reason why we objected to wheat over there at Harvard; two
         times at least it froze out.
         Well, one time it froze and one time we got that stripe rust. I
         had a crop there that looked like it was going to make fifty bu
         shel and the frost hit it in July when it was right in bloom and
         it made fifteen bushel of damn poor hog feed! And another yearit
         was the next year, the following year-had about forty or fortyfive
         acres of pretty good looking fall wheat and that stripe rustno,
         that was spring wheat- the stripe rust hit it. And it made
         about fifteen bushels of hog feed. Not good hog feed either.
         Didn't get any kind of a price on it at all. But we'd get some
         pretty fair crops on part of it.
         
         SS:  So you went for raising hay and keeping your own stock here from
         the beginning?
         
         GLEN:  That's right, we didn't want any wheat. We just put wheat enough
         on it to condition the ground and get it so it would raise a
         crop of hay. Get it level enough so that thought could mow
         it. But I never left it grain over a year then I'd put it in hay.
         Hay was what I wanted. It's always been my crop, I don't know,
         I had good luck with it. And the stock was better for me than
         grain. They were good to me. Always made a little bit of headway.
         We never did have a bum crop on this place by frost or rust or
         parasites or anything of the sort. We were just lucky here, we
         never had a thing to hurt us that way. Always had a good crop
         of hay and fairly good crop of grain. About 1948 it rained and
         rained and rained, we had the wheat bound and shocked and it
         just kept a raining. Every day I'd go out and look at it and
         that wheat was just on top of those shocks was just as green as
         could be. Beautiful. Every kernel on top was sprouted! And
         the wheat got up that high on top of the shocks. Fortunately, I
         had it insured and this Harry Botser come out from Moscow and
         appraised it and give me about 75 loss on it. And as he was
         leaving I said, "Henry what'11 I do with that stuff?" He said,
         "Do whatever you want to. It's yours. You can burn it. You
         can plow it under." And he suggested things that I could do with
         it! But he didn't say anything about hauling it in the barn and
         feeding it, and I didn't either. So, I'd bring in a load and
         I'd spread it all over the barn, it was wet and green. And then
         the next day I'd get another load and bring it in. And you know,
         those pigs and chickens and cows had more fun threshing that crop
         than I ever had running it through a sfcjftarator! And it made me
         a little money! (Chuckles) I don't know whether I was supposed
         to do that or not, but I did it. Then the neighbor down here, he
         didn't have any stock, when they got through with mine, he says,
         "Do you want some more?" And I said, "Sure." So I hauled his
         wheat crop up here and put it away. Had to stack most of that
         outside, but they ate it and they loved it and they got fat on
         it, although it was absolutely worthless. You couldn't sell it.
         Just was worthless to anybody else. I went to Lewiston and bought
         just a few more sheep and I think I bought an extra pig or two
         and didn'-t have money enough to do me any good, but I got a few
         and they sure had a time around here.
         
         The extra stock that you bought ate it?
         Yeah.
         When you were first over here, you know, it seems like with that
         little house, sometimes when you^had company some had to stand
         against the door to hold it shut] (Chuckles)
         Well, it sure used to get full, but we made it.
         Boy, look at the picture of all the kids, in that one picture.
         You had a big family.
         
         Yeah.
         Course we-
         Well, we built onto it.
         The oldest girl was married when the last one came. Yeah, we
         built onto- two rooms. One whole room and boarded up a porch.
         Well, they didn't use 'em both at the same time, when the other
         was ready to fill, they moved off the porch.
         
         Art described it pretty good, he says we were a little bit crowded
         but he says we made do. He had the same situation.
         
         Art?
         Sundberg. Yeah that must have been a crowded situation with the
         older houses, having a big family.
         
         These homesteaders out here on the prairie all had the same situa
         tion.
         
         Well, some of 'em had big houses to start with.
         
         To start with? No, very few of 'em. They got 'em pretty sud
         denly but they had to get a crop or two before they had the money
         to do it.
         
         That house was standing when you came here?
         
         Yeah.
         
         Yeah, there were three rooms and the back porch and I guess the
         back porch was boarded in but there had to be some work done be-
         cause it was^0collid. We put on felt paper.
         Well, as they got bigger and couldn't sleep three in a bed, why,
         we'd finally struggle around and get another room added on so
         they could have at least two in a bed; at the most two in a bed,
         however it works.
         
         What did you do about a house when you were first there for space?
         Did you have one room to yourselves?
         
         Yeah. There was a very small bedroom- well, there were two bed
         rooms, one the girls and the boys weren't as big. You see, the
         two oldest girls- were the oldest and Lloyd and Richard wereand
         flllen. So they were small enough to-
         
         Oh, yes, they crowded, but we made do. We got that porch fixed
         up for 'em pretty early and it made a nice room for the boys.
         The girls had one. And then we built a back on, and then the boys
         had lots of room, and a nice situation out of that. Then we started
         this. That's another beauty of being ignorant- if I had a known
         what it was going to take in work and hours and dollars I never
         woulda started this house- wouldn't had the nerve.(Chuckles)
         Well, the other one was just kinda on the way down. There wasn't
         any foundation under it and it was just kind of a patch-up deal.
         
         Yeah.
         
         Course, I suppose he could have put a foundation under it but-
         You wouldn't a had anything when you got done. That house was
         built there in the '70's, original part of it.
         
         It was put up without any studs between the walls, just, I don't
         know how they did it.
         Box.
         
         The top and bottom must have been nailed.
         
         Well, in these pamphlets from Whitney County, there were lots of
         those old cabins built that way. They'd make a foundation, or
         a start and put a 2x4 at the bottom and a 2x4 at the top and then
         they'd nail these 1x12 boards just like that up. And there'J be
         a two inch airspace in there so they battened the outside with
         1x4s and then they put in their inn^Hf wall and put wallpaper over (f
         and then the lumber'd shrink and the wallpaper'd crack and the
         wind'd blow through and the snow'd blow through and they'd patch
         that up and paper it again. I don t know which one it was that
         was telling about papering it the first time with newspapers.
         Then they got prosperous and got a roll or two of felt paper and
         they papered it with that. Then they got some fancy wallpaper
         and papered it with that. That's three layers. And every year
         they'd paper it again and clean the walls up till they had about
         fifteen or twenty layers of paper on there and it began to get
         pretty warm!
         
         What about your family's place when you grew up?
         
         We did about the same thing over at Harvard. But here- Oh, we'd
         only papered that over there about three or four times, I guess.
         Probably not that many.
         
         It was comfortable. It was pretty good. Pretty good.
         
         The first time we tried to paper- it was pretty good paper on
         there when we came and then it and torn a little here
         and there and somebody gave us some paper and it wasn't very good
         paper. First thing, we started out bright and shining one morning
         and he got it all glued and everything ready to put up, put it
         over his head and his head went right through it! (Laughter) I
         started to |ugh and I couldn't stop laughing. But after that it
         seemed to go pretty good. It's a wonder he didn't kill me! I
         guess he saw how funny it was himself. (More laughter)
         
         The kids nowdays, it seems like that each kid or person requires
         is so much more than it was- not that long ago. I can't imagine
         two kids in bed; two or three beds in a bedroom.
         
         Yeah, nowdays,Aeach supposed to have a bed of their own in a bed
         room.
         
         Yup. Well, we finally got it. Let's see, it had to get down to
         grandkidsAbefore we got it that way! Oh, well, it was not
         too bad; two of 'em in a bed, they were comfortable and if they
         didn't start out any other way, why, they liked it alright.
         What did you envision when you started to think about building
         this house? If not the house in its present form, what were
         you thinking of? I mean, it's a beautiful house and I always^
         imagined that from the beginning you were going to build it
         up like this.
         
         Well, we had wanted- up there at Harvard, if we had built, we was
         going to build a log house, I think.
         Yeah.
         
         We wanted it, anyway. We thought when we started this house that
         it was going to be so big, so much bigger than the other one,
         Well, it is, it's about twice as big or more, but still
         when any of the kids come home, why, we're- we kind of divide
         'em up with the rest of the family to make room for them because
         I guess you get another family in here or two, well, it's going
         to fill it up okay, and it does. So when the bunch came home
         for the reunion, why, we didn't think of anything else, we just
         let 'em go to Edgar's and well, I guess, that was all.
         Whenever we had room- there was two up, , three up and
         two up there and two here; oh, they got i-^Tnaybe it was a little
         crowded, but they made do.
         
         Were you thinking the house- about this scale, about the way it
         turned out when you started building?
         
         Oh, never woulda had any idea it would take so much room to hold
         a family^ ^second generationin there- third. But, we had this
         plan, we planned it for years even to where the windows and doors
         were going to be. When we started in on it we had a pretty good
         idea what it was going to end up. But it took quite a while about
         ten years, but Ididn't see where there was any rush. Every
         body says, "Why don't you get a loan? And get a contractor?"
         Heck Idon't want a loan because you gotta pay them back. Sooner
         have my own work in it. Maybe take a little longer but it was
         mine.
         
         What year did you start building?
         
         We started this in r50, didn't we?
         
         Yes. Cutting the logs.
         
         Is that the way you proceeded, you started by -
         
         Well, first we cut the logs and got them all ready and then a
         gyppo mill come in up :here on the next place and I give him a
         share of the logs to mill them and he took his share and as
         much of mine as he could get, but it wasn't too bad, I kept getgrr
         ting a little gain on it all the time. I'd put a log on the car-
         riage and think, "Well, that's a good cabin log." And the first
         thing I knew he had it sawed up into inch lumber, so I had to
         go to Lewiston. But we kept at it and finally got enough. And
         I had a big load of selects pulled out like those over there with
         no knots, no strings, no nothin'. I went to Moscow for something
         well, when I come back that was gone and I had to start almost
         all over again, but the next time I held onto thflffselect stuff,
         when I got it I brought it home. And finally got through.
         This guy's what we call rip off.
         
         Yeah, well, - dammit he had to eat, he had a big family, he had
         to eat. I don't blame him. And they were big kids, they were
         grade school and high school.
         
         What you were doing, you were getting your logs sawed in half
         and getting- try to get the best paneling you can?
         I wanted my fair share of the better grade, yes, I thought I
         was entitled to that. And I wound up with- I'm satisfied.
         Well, these exterior- the logs; are they cut in half or are they
         whole logs?
         
         Oh, these logs?
         
         They're squared on three sides. And made eight inch square with
         the round side to go out. And then we didn't have to -. any
         corners, we just cribbed it. . Like that. And another log went in
         here and then another log went over the top and caught this cor
         ner again. Made a substantial corner. And then we put, oh a wall
         like this one- there'd be about five sixty penny spikes. We
         bored a hole half way through the log and drove that nail in
         there til the head hit the hole we'd bored and that put it half
         way through the next log. They were eight inch nails and they
         went four inches in each log. And it don't seem to be giving any
         place, it's in there. Be a long time if nothin' happens to it.
         So, how did the work progress? S? first year you got the logs
         cut.
         
         Yes, and then the next year we got 'em sawed, and then during that
         summer the kids dug the basement with a team of horses. They had
         a time of it but they did her. I was working at the mill then
         up at Moscow. And we put up the- on Saturdays and Sundays or any
         time we could get, we put up these walls, and got them up where
         they were gonna be and then, I don't know, we got that roof up
         there some way next and closed ., but we had the roof on
         it and then that made it so we could work- when the mill shut
         down, then we could work all winter in here, and we did. And all
         that lumber was piled here in the middle of the floor. There was
         no division there. And we had a stove here to try and get it dry,
         and we thought we had it dry, but that would shrink, not too bad,
         but it shrunk. And I always thought that I'd like to take it down
         and put it tight, but I never will.
         
         You did, this part here.
         But, it took ten years, so what? From start to finish.
         It was ten years before you moved in?
         No, no, we-
         We moved in in '56.
         
         It was '60 before we moved in.
         So what remained to be done at that point, when you moved in?
         Oh, these walls needed to be finished. The bedrooms needed to
         lined
         be and cabinets built and fireplace built. And we didn't
         get the fireplace built until '62. But, we just kept a peckin'.
         I got money enough to get the wire and I asked a contractor to
         come in and put that wire up while the building was^ pretty much
         of a skeleton, and he wanted to contract to do the whole thing,
         furnish the wire and put it in, but I couldn't do it. These
         walls weren't done, they couldn't put their lamps in and I don't
         know, the ceiling was floored up there, but it wasn't floored
         underneath. The ceiling wasn't there. But, anyway, he didn't
         want any part of it because I wouldn't contract to do the whole
         thing, so he just passed it up. And then I didn't know anything
         about electricity, but I asked everybody I could see what to do
         about the wiring, and they all advised(me) to get the heaviest
         wire you could possibly get for that purpose and I did. And be
         fore this wall went up I put the wire in there. Comes in over
         here and under the basement and comes up the wall and into there
         and over here. Oh, got by with it. But he wanted me to borrow
         the money, give him contract and go ahead. I couldn't see it
         He couldn't see it; he couldn't see it my way, I couldn't see it
         his. Just as well, we got by.
         
         Had you ever built a house before this one?
         
         Oh, not alone. I'si helped Nance on his. I helped Dean High on
         his, I helped Burgers on theirs. Even as a kid I used to get in
         on those house raisings and things like that. Oh, yeah, I had
         a little, enough to know what to do, how to do it, but I wouldn't
         be as fast as an expert or a carpenter. But I had a pretty fair
         idea. The biggest help I got, when I going to Prep high
         school.I took a couple or three semesters in cabinet making.
         Where it was just woodwork. But I learned how to use the tools
         and what they were made for and why they were made and so on, and
         that give me an idea that I could do it.
         
         It did.
         
         Well, the old instructor down there, C. Roberts- said, "if
         you can built a perfect box, four sides of it, and make it per
         fect," he says, "you can build anything there is out of wood."
         I didn't quite get that box perfect, but I got it by enough to
         get a grade. And then took the knowledge to work in here.
         What prep school was this? Where was it?
         
         Pullman. That college used to have what they called^ prep school
         there for places that didn't have high school, we could go in
         there and take high school courses, and get about anything you
         wanted to, basics. It was high school, that's all it amounted
         to.
         The only thing is that high school never was as hard as that.
         
         No, they crowded us.
         I took high school about the same time he took
         and we didn't
         have the assignments nor the kinds of books that they had in
         as freshmen
         there, or anytime during high school.
         
         They crowded us harder. We was supposed to get what's ordinary
         high school in four years, but we had to get that in three. They
         didn't give us four years. So assignments were pretty big and
         the load was heavy and believe me, they pushed us.
         Was that good or bad to have to work like that?
         A kid with ordinary intelligence, it was probably good, but I
         was so goddam dumb it was all I could do to get by.
         Well, I don't think that because, as I say, I took high school
         about the same time you did that and I've seen your books and we
         never had anything like it in high school. And the courses then
         were probably a lot harder then than they are now, so there's
         no comparison.
         
         I know they pushed us.
         Did you live at Pullman?
         Yeah.
         
         When you were going? Where did you live?
         I don't know - If the Conservatory of Music is where it used to
         be or not, but we lived just across the street from it down over
         a bank.
         
         Student housing? Did you live with other students?
         There was four of us bached.
         In a regular house.
         
         In a little one-room shack. It was about 14 or 16 feet wide and
         about 20 feet long; kitchen in one end, dinind area in the middle
         and beds were double bunks in the back. We did our own cooking.
         And I worked all the time, let's see, pretty near four hours a
         day. And set up half the night-
         Studying, I hope.
         
         END OF SIDE E
         
         Oh, well, I got by.
         
         Where did you work?
         
         Huh?
         
         Where did you work?
         
         Oh, I milked cows out at the dairy and one year I was the barn
         boss out there. Used to have oh, about twenty-five, thrity head
         of horses and I took care of those horses night and morning. Had
         to get over there about three o'clock in the morning and feed 'em
         and curry 'em and harness what they were going to use that day.
         And then somebody else come along and cleaned the barn out. I
         didn't have to do that but it took all the time I had, then I had
         to go back over in the evening and unharness 'em, curry 'em, feed
         'em and water 'em and take care of 'em. I loved it, that part of
         it.
         
         I think I would have stayed over there.
         
         Over in Pullman?
         
         No, in the horse barn! (Chuckles)
         
         Sounds better than the one-room shack?
         
         Well ,at least he woulda had more time to study.
         
         We worked at that studying pretty conscientiously. We knew that
         it was just up to us, there was no foolin'. We might go to a
         dance once a week, very rarely ever went to a show unless it was
         something up on the campus there. We used to go to the occasional
         ball games, not too many. There just wasn't time for it. We did
         try to get to a dance about once a week. All of us liked to dance,
         And there was always girls around there that were glad to get a
         date.
         
         But to go to Pullman in the first place, to go to high school,
         that in itself sounds to me like
         
         Small number went on to do that.
         
         There was quite a large bunch of these boys- Now, see, at that
         time, Spangle didn't have a high school, and there was Boyd Lambert
         and Dolly and two^ three others from Spangle. So the dis
         trict up there paid the tuition. We didn't have to pay any
         tuition.KHad to buy our books and our board and room and clothes;
         that was about it. But, you know, with the few hours that I worked
         every day, and that was seven days a week, I could make and save
         during the summer about 300, 400 and one year 500. And
         a lot of that w earned at a dollar a day. In harvest I could
         get three. But^I could make- I think I got about fifty cents an
         hour over there so I made about two dollars a day. Financially,
         got by fine. Good. Nothin' to it. But, I never was any great
         deal ahead in my studies.
         
         They shouldn't have charged you one cent for books.
         Well, they did, though.
         
         Washington paid all the books, paper, pencils at that time.
         Where was your family living at the time?
         
         Oh, Harvard. No school- just grade school there. There was a
         high school in Potlatch, but we wanted to go down here.
         Why? Did you figure it was better? Better school?
         
         Well, yes, we thought that.
         AWouldn't have had a chance to work, probably.
         No. They had more to chose from. I was agriculture; I wanted ani
         mal husbandry and things like that, and I couldn't get it unless
         I went there. That was my main influence, that I could get
         a broader choice of things. However, they crowded us with algebra,
         and all
         and history and geometry, , English and history
         they made us take that when you get one or two
         classes in each semester of something like botany or horticul
         ture.
         
         But got that in high school.
         
         I know, but, animal hus- I always got a semester of that in
         there. Every semester.
         
         Was it your decision to go, Glen, or did - or was it your par
         ents' decision?
         
         It was mine, strictly mine, as far as I was concerned. And then
         the neighbor kids, it was their's too. Their parents encouraged
         it. But the one of them wanted to take- to be a teacher,
         antoher one wanted to study more or less languages, Spanish and
         things like that and you couldn't specialize in the high school,
         but all of us did alright after we got out of there, we went in-
         t if
         to our line of work and did tright
         Well, I think if he'd taken high school at Potlatch you probably
         would have had the same thing except you wouldn't had a chance
         to work.
         Well, I couldn't have got animal husbandry or feed and seeds or
         crops and seeds.
         Well, I know, but-
         But, yeah, that's right. But it was about six of one, half a
         dozen of the other. I think we'd been just as well off either
         place.
         
         Those days,Harvard, or two miles beyond Harvard, and Potlatch
         were a long way apart. There wasn't any cars. I guess there
         were cars, but who had 'em?
         Very few cars then.
         
         And it's too far for a horse to make the trip every day.
         Yeah. Oh,
         
         His sisters stayed in town and worked their heads off.
         Where?
         At Potlatch.
         Worked on Nob Hill or where?
         No. They worked on the other hill.
         But they worked.
         
         Yes. Yes, they worked, darn right they worked!
         What did they do?
         
         Housework. Take care of the kids. The old heifers, they'd leave
         the dinner dishes and the floor sweeping and everything else for
         those kids to do after they got home from school. They took a
         hell of an advantage of 'em.
         
         Sounds like Anna Utt talking about- she did the same thing.
         Yes, she did.
         
         My sister did the same thing in Seattle. Carol did the same thing
         at Moscow when she went to the university, .Jt was Just a
         common thing. Sluff onto to those-
         
         Those women wouldn't do a hand's turn that they could possibly
         leave for those kids to do after they got home.
         It's always been that way and always will be, I guess. Now, it's
         TV to look at sit and look at.
         
         To put up with it the kids must have wanted to a certain amount
         of education.
         
         Well, they did. They did, figured they benefitted enough to make
         it worthwhile to do it. But, I'd do it again if I was to do it
         over again, I'd still do it the same way, but I wouldn't try to
         go through in three years. I would make them lower that load
         so that if I wanted to" take five years. You could do it now
         but you couldn't do it then. They just piled it onto you, you
         had so many hours when you registered and that was it.
         So it was really a struggle, a struggle to keep up with all that
         stuff?
         
         I just had a awful time. Just a continual round of pleasure!!
         (Chuckles)
         
         Now, you probably read more history than anybody I know, so it
         didn't destroy your love of learning.
         No.
         
         I think a person the more you study or read9 the more they want
         to. Most of the people that I've known can't get enough degrees.
         I know one woman you see over here, Church, has studied
         and gone to school for imagine fifteen years at least, maybe
         more. If I had kept at it, I would have been a lot more apt to
         Camp 11
         
         Your exposure to that. You once described what that
         was like. Would you describe that to me again? Camp 11 was like
         when you saw it.
         
         Well, the living conditions?
         
         Yes. When they were pretty bad.
         
         Well, the bunkhouse was 30x- I imagine 75 feet- and there was a
         row of double bunks there on the wall, and each bunk, one above
         the other, and they put about, oh, must have been 75 men in
         that one great big room. Had a stove in each end. And we'd all
         come in sopping wet night after night after night. Well, the
         only place you could get those clothes dry was to hang 'em up
         the ceiling; with seventy-five coats, seventy-five pair of
         socks, seventy-five suits of underwear and seventy-five suits of
         overalls or pants, and there is people,that d swear that d
         stink! AThey'd get it cleaned up maybe once every two or three
         years and then somebody'd come in with a batch of lice and go
         through the whole damn bunkhouse! Bedbugs. Oh, hell! They lived
         a little bit- hell, farmers used to take better care of the hogs
         than Potlatch took care of their men! The cookshack was the same
         size building and great, long tables right down the middle of it,
         two rows of 'em. And there was one place where they did a good
         job. Anything that you could imagine: they had steak for break
         fast, they had bacon for breakfast, hotcakes for breakfast, fruit,
         fresh milk, and pastry, baked goods, ummmm! Man they was just
         tremendous. But, after you'd been there about a month, the cake
         tasted just like the potatoes and the steak. I'll swear it did.
         
         They said the reason for that was that you d got the wrinkps out
         of your belly, and so by that time you were getting particular.
         But, the cooks were good. They were tre mendous! And the Potlatch
         furnished them anything they wanted to cook, it just didn't
         matter what it was. Fresh meat used to come in there every day,
         as far as I know. However, earlier than that, when they didn't
         have the transportation why, it used to get pretty rank.
         When was it that you were in there at Camp 11?
         Well, it'dl to be 1918, I think.
         
         So the cooking was good and the living conditions were atrocious?
         As tnear as they could make 'em clean.
         
         I think you're not getting- did you hear what he said?
         I said, the cooking was good, the food was good, but the living
         conditions were terrible.
         
         Oh, that's right. Yes.
         It's funny that they had both good cooking and bad living, but
         I've heard it before.
         
         Well, that's the way it was. That bunkhouse was terrible. How
         ever, right at that time these IWWs come in and then it was seven
         men to a marion shack. And we had a room as big as this one,
         thirty feet long. And I believe there were ten or twelve feet
         wide, and there'd be two bunks across from each other in the end,
         that's four men and
         two bunks about half way up, six, and
         then one bunk would be in one corner or the other. And there was
         always an empty bunk, they never let 'em
         fill it, but it was just for company or camp inspection or such
         and such. But then, by that time, we had electric lights, bath
         room, showers- there was no tubs, but showers- and we could wash
         our clothes nights if we wanted to. And even had a special car
         where you could go and play cards or set and talk or read. Gen
         erally read in your bunk, -because it was quiet. But it just
         changed from terrible to pretty darn good^ just in one year.
         Was that year 1918?
         
         In '18 and '19, yes, seems
         And you attribute it to the IWWs?
         
         right in there, I don't remem-
         
         The labor trouble forced it. They fought it, the company fought it
         in every way that they could, but it just seems like they couldn't
         put it over. God, they used to fight that! I got a kick out of
         Art- and I didn't mention any names but I knew that the guy that
         got so white in the face was Jim 0'Connel. But they finally worked
         in. And instead of-
         
         There's something wrong there because the IWWs in 1918 and Jim
         0'Connel came about '34-
         
         He didn't come till 30 or in there-
         
         There was more organizing that went on later that Art was talking
         about,^he CIO, which was during the '30's.
         Well, you see they had kind of a- well, first they had the 4 L's,
         that was the company's union.
         
         Did they try to make you join that one?
         
         Oh, yeah, you had to join it if you wanted to work there. After
         you joined it all you did was pay your dues, they got no benefit
         from it, but it kept the unions out. And then there was a long
         period in there didn t have anything. And then, finally,
         the time that Art's talking about, was after the Depression, why
         then, they did form a union and guys like him that put it over.
         I admiredhim for putting it over and helping 'em, although after
         they got in there, he couldn't belong to it because they had him
         in a supervisor^ job. But for them to beat him out of his retire
         ment money over that deal was typically Potlatch. That's just
         the way they worked. He wasn't alone on that. Malcolm Grier
         and numerous ones got the same thing.
         
         For union activity? Or for other reasons?
         
         Oh, punishment for even sympathizing with them. Potlatch and
         all other companies did not want this union. They knew that they
         were going to have to pay wage and they didn't want to.
         That s breaking into profits. But they finally had to.
         Did you ever come- You were working there in '18- and didyou have
         any contact with the IWWs or with the company propaganda against
         No, not particularly, no, I just had a job to do and I did it.
         I thought IWWs was working before our time.
         
         They were, and that's a fact.
         
         I mean they- trying to make it work.
         
         "The IWWs came and then they kind quieted them down and then
         at the same time they got the eight hour day pretty well through
         and they did get clean bunkhouses. And then they kinda died down.
         The mines were organized and they stayed organized, but the mills
         didn't. And then they had this, which was just a farce, took
         a couple of dollars out of every check. And then there wasn't
         anything and then the unions came back in and organized and put
         it over and they've had a pretty good deal ever since. But it
         was a long-time struggle. Potlatch used to can these people over
         sympathy or making remarks or things like that, they'd can 'em.
         They might hire 'em back in a couple of weeks, but they'd can
         'em and sometimes when they conned 'em they'd leave and go down
         to Bend or down to Lewiston or down to Long View. There's a lot
         of places they could go, if they had money enough to get out of
         town. (Laughter)
         
         Most of 'em didn't have money enough to get out, unless they went
         out by night.
         
         Well, Wynmeyer took his wife and each of 'em took a kid by the
         fist and they walked out. They had to, they couldn't get a job.
         I knew they came back to town walking, but I didn't know they'd
         walked out.
         They left, but came back, did they?
         Uh-huh.
         
         That was about 1930 or somewhere along that time.
         You ran into Wynmeyer, is that the second time he was in or the first?
         No, that was the first time. I never seen him the second time
         he was in there. No him and had a little disagreement,
         but ^got away with it.
         But he didn't. Did you work in the woods very much, Glen?
         Oh, yeah, I did. Up until- from 1918/t about 1926 or '27, why I
         did.
         
         '26 he was-
         
         I say, up until 1926 or '25, along in there, why, I did I put in
         a lot of time in the woods, and then in 1935, I think it was, we
         were up at Harvard and I went back into the woods then, summers
         and spare time and still did my farming. And.by that time I fi
         gured I had almost had enough of the woods, I was going to work
         inside if I was going to work in the winters, so I startedAthese
         sawmills. However, I worked 1927 and '28 in that boiler room
         over there in Potlatch?
         
         Yeah. And I worked down along the dock in '29. Then in October
         I quit andjjbought the dairy outfit.
         The mill shut down in 
         When you were working in the woods, what kind of work did you
         usually do?
         
         Drove a pair of horses if it was humanly possible.
         I knew that was what you were going to say.
         
         But, however, sometimes I'd have to- I worked on a landing up in
         Camp 2 at Collins. A season. And away back before— while I was
         still in grade school I used to saw for Jess Hutley and can't
         even remember the other fellow's name. They was logging on that
         Lenhart place over there, we used to saw there in the summertime
         there. That's all the sawing I ever did to amount to anything.
         
         GLEN:  If I could get behind an old team of horses, that's what I wanted
         and that's what I did. And believe me, I was just good enough
         that if I wanted a job all I had to do, was to go into camp and
         ask for it. They might turn a dozen away, but I never did get
         turned away. I'd go into the main office up there in Bovill and
         tell Nogle I'd like to get a team some place and he'd say go up
         here or go up there and I'd have the team.
         
         SS:  So what you knew from handling a team on the farm held you in
         good stead when you wanted to handle a team in the woods?
         
         GLEN:  That's right, I'd just grown up with 'em. Worked one year for Shadduck.
         He coulda hired fifty other guys if he'd a wanted 'em, but
         he wanted me and one year I worked with Corey; same deal, he could
         a had any amount of emj[ he wanted me. And Queener, after I star
         velus
         ted- I worked for him at Neva, that s I worked for Shadduck,
         and as long as Queener was logging if I wanted a job with
         him I had it- a team of horses to drive. I liked that. I still
         like a horse.
         
         All the time in the sawmills until they made that against the law
         I worked with steam in^Potlatch, the boiler room. And then later
         went over to run tne engine over there for a while.
         And then everything went electricity, there just wasn't any
         steam and so I went to edging then. Never to work for the
         lowest man on the totem pole, I want to work up there they were
         making pretty good money. Took just a little bit of skill. I
         tried to get it some way.
         
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13450</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Gilder5</previous>
      <next>Gilder7</next>
      <disp_name>Gilder6</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
