<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/21/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Edward &amp; Dixie Groseclose, 1976-07-21, Interview #3 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>3:43:32</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Groseclose, Edward &amp; Dixie</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #3</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1900</birthyear>
      <residence>Potlatch River, Juliaetta</residence>
      <origin>Came with family from Bland County, Virginia in 1907</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#croqueting"&gt;croqueting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#poor"&gt;poor&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#trapping"&gt;trapping&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#suicide"&gt;suicide&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#doctors"&gt;doctors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bootlegging"&gt;bootlegging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#superstitions"&gt;superstitions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#ghosts"&gt;ghosts&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#parties"&gt;parties&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#literary"&gt;literary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crops"&gt;crops&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#smoking"&gt;smoking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch River"&gt;Potlatch River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Juliaetta"&gt;Juliaetta&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Teakean"&gt;Teakean&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Virginia"&gt;Virginia&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Agatha"&gt;Agatha&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13459</file_name>
      <mp3>13460.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13460.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Where Susan Groseclose lived; dealing with homeless men; actives that Susan Groseclose
               did and dealings with her other family
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Aunt Susan Groseclose. Her garden was by the railroad tracks.
               Finding a dead hobo. A hobo with lice who didn't want to leave
               their home, when only Ed and his mother were there; he acted
               as though he was a family friend. Aunt Susan was always busy;
               after she broke her hip, she crocheted all the time. She sat with
               Dixie's mother at night after working all day. She jumped over a
               horse by mistake. Susan's daughter made round button holes on
               her gown. Everyone called her "Aunt Susan."
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Boys not knowing how to do any work in the home; Mr. Groseclose learning how to took;
               divisions of labor between men and women; Dixie's enjoyment of working outside
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The boys in Ed's and Aunt Susan's families grew up without
               learning how to do any work in the home. He found himself
               ill-prepared to batch when he grew up: having to look after
               himself and the cattle when his sister got a toothache. His
               sister-in-law cooked her best to show him. The traditional
               division of labor between men and women. Dixie's great
               enjoyment of outside work and dislike of housework; her help
               with farming. She had trouble using a plow: "cat-and-covering".
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1620</time>
            <title>Having to do housework and not liking it; missing school to help out at home; family
               illness
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The work she had to do for the family as she was growing. Her
               preference for non-domestic work. She missed a great deal of
               school because of work at home; but she enjoyed school and
               always passed. She felt she was needed at home. Accepting what
               you have in life. Mother's illnesses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Helping at home as a youngster. Putting up hay together for a
               farmer.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Helping at home as a youngster. Putting up hay together for a
               farmer.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2100</time>
            <title>Having tonsillitis and other health problems; growing up with adversity and making
               do with what they had
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Her tonsillitis and other health problems after marriage. Growing
               from adversity: the children shared with each other. Most
               families had little. The "make-do" family.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>No traveling to cities during the Depression; having produce was an advantage; cheap
               cost of cloth in the South
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>No point in going to cities during Depression; having produce was
               an advantage. Collecting from the railroad for killing their two
               cows. Cheap cost of cloth in the south; worked for seventy
               cents a week there.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Hand-me-downs and gifts of clothing for family; how her father made a living</title>
            <synopsis>Hand-me-downs and gifts of clothing for family. How her father
               made a living. Trapping - markets for skunk oil and gall.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Getting lice and having their horse and saddle stolen; Discussion of whites' relationship
               with Native Americans
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A man who gave his brothers lice and stole their horse and saddle. John Smith robbed
               the Indians of corn, which set pattern
               of whites' forcing of Indians. Sorry record of whites' dealings
               with Indians. High Indian morals.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>A Southerner who committed suicide after killing a black.</title>
            <synopsis>A Southerner who committed suicide after killing a black.
               Conscience catches up with murderers.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>A cousin who was protected by God from killing a man with a
               gun, which misfired.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A cousin who was protected by God from killing a man with a
               gun, which misfired.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3660</time>
            <title>Survey dispute between his sister and Indians. Kimberling's land
               boundaries were set by himself, not a survey.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Survey dispute between his sister and Indians. Kimberling's land
               boundaries were set by himself, not a survey.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4020</time>
            <title>Native American friends teaching relatives English; Differences between Native Americans
               living on the land and whites
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His Indian friend went to school and didn't like to speak Nez Perce,
               but taught his relatives English. A burial site for eight Nez Perces
               south of the river. 4n Indian family that was prone to
               tuberculosis because of their damp homesite. Indians could
               divide up land but whites couldn't. Indians might lie but
               wouldn't steal.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>Dixie's poor treatment from Dr. Foster in Lewiston; Dr. Foster supposedly curing breast
               cancer
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>She got poor treatments in Lewiston from Dr. Foster, who was
               drinking heavily. A bootlegger who sold cold tea for liquor.
               Foster cured cancerous breast lumps by applying a burner,
               which was painful. A niece who died from breast cancer by
               dallying after it was discovered, in hope of getting Foster's cure.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5160</time>
            <title>Dr. Foster's house was haunted; Southern Superstitions; Jim Deevers' reputation as
               a wizard
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Story that Foster's house was haunted by a figure of a nurse.
               Southern superstitions: throwing a sickle in milk that wouldn't
               churn; cure for breaking a spider web; killing an ox in an effort
               to cure it. Jim Deevers' reputation for being a wizard led to
               fun at others' expense, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Suspicion of the Deevers' family; religious beliefs about devil-worshippers</title>
            <synopsis>Suspicion of Jim Deevers; his wife Liz Deevers was called a witch.
               Ed's brother pretended to be a ghost on a roof. Devil-worshippers,
               a recent phenomenon, should be run down if they try to stop a
               person driving a car.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>A superstitious Norwegian girl who helped the family out during ,
               her sickness upset her.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A superstitious Norwegian girl who helped the family out during ,
               her sickness upset her.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Dixie and Ed's courtship; what they did for fun; Dixie being prepared for married;
               and stepfather disapproval of Ed
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Their courtship: when it started he was 20, she 13. His injury
               in an accident hauling poles led to his getting to know her better.
               As a little kid she once told Ed not to get married. Stepfather
               liked to talk about the wild times he had had, but disliked Dixie's
               going out. House parties: kissing games. She was prepared for
               marriage from work at home. Stepfather's disapproval of her
               beaus, including Ed. (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Going to a dance and causing opposition for father; Dixie had no trouble getting dates;
               Going to Literaries
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Taking Dixie to a dance raises opposition from father, although
               she got home by midnight with a chaperone. Stepfather had no
               legal right to stop her from marrying. Young men who were
               rounders became suspicious of their daughters. She had no
               trouble getting dates; some boys were too old to go out with.
               Going to literary with an overloaded buggy. Debate topics and
               other literary activities; mock trials, and the oath to lie.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8280</time>
            <title>1918 Flu epidemic; home remedies for a variety of illnesses</title>
            <synopsis>Flu epidemic (1918) ended local gatherings. Treating flu; syrup
               of figs a good laxative. Powdered alum cured a mortal case of
               nosebleed.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8640</time>
            <title>Fire burned down their rented house at Teakean: trying to fight it.</title>
            <synopsis>Fire burned down their rented house at Teakean: trying to fight it.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9000</time>
            <title>Loss of belongings from fire except for saved produce in cellar; illnesses contracted
               from donated clothing; irresponsible doctor and regulations for ending quarantine
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Loss of belongings in the fire; stored produce was saved in the
               cellar. Donations from neighbors - contracting the seven year
               itch from clothes they had been given. The children contracted
               scarlet fever. The doctor failed to come until they were on their
               way to Agatha, and then tried to stop them from moving. She
               protested so strongly that he let them go on. They had to be
               quarantined at Agatha; the store gave them credit but they
               couldn't sell their cream. Unreasonable regulations for ending
               quarantine; doctor's irresponsible conduct.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10080</time>
            <title>Loss of crops in 1928 due to bad weather and trying to farm at Teakean</title>
            <synopsis>Loss of crops that year because of bad weather (c. 1928). Effort
               to farm land at Teakean.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10380</time>
            <title>Brother was an English Lutheran minister; division in Ed's family about religion</title>
            <synopsis>Brother was an English Lutheran minister, strongly opposed to
               drinking and smoking. Division of Ed's family about religion.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10620</time>
            <title>Ed converting to religion; discussion of people in Russia</title>
            <synopsis>Hard luck in living. Ed has been converted to religion, which he
               didn't used to like. Under the czars, Russia had fine churches but
               the people were illiterate; improvement under communism.
               Dunkard practice of Lord's Supper.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10800</time>
            <title>Different interpretations of the Bible; first phonograph</title>
            <synopsis>Differing interpretations are made of Bible. Moral law originated
               in the Bible. The first phonograph he saw - the original invention
               was the important one.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11160</time>
            <title>Importance of religion to them as young people</title>
            <synopsis>Importance of religion to them as young people. Effects of
               "sanctification" may not show in the way a person conducts
               himself.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11340</time>
            <title>Adventists didn't work Saturdays but did on Sundays; Religious denominations are confusing
               to non-believers
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Adventists at Arrow wouldn't help a man whose team got stuck
               on their Sabbath. An Adventist who hauled timber as the
               church got out on Sunday. Religious denominations are confusing
               to non-believers. An Adventist jailed for disturbing the peace.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11760</time>
            <title>Where Adams got his wheat and what he sold it for; Adams stopped shipping because
               his wheat was Egyptian; smuggling wheat to Kansas
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Adams got his Alaska wheat from Lee Hall, who pawned it off on
               him as a yarn. Adams sold his wheat for $26 a bushel. Why
               Hall was miffed at Adams. Adams stopped from shipping his
               wheat once the government discovered it was Egyptian;
               smuggling his wheat to Kansas.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12180</time>
            <title>Man running for road boss which united Virginians; differences between North and South
               causes Methodist church split
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A man ran for road boss to "beat the Southerners", causing the
               Virginians to unite. Leland's two Methodist churches, because
               of differences between North and South.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12360</time>
            <title>Getting drunk; writing poetry; acceptance of others</title>
            <synopsis>Getting drunk from booze and cigarettes. His writing of poetry.
               His acceptance of the needs of others; he didn't want to deprive
               others of work. Hoover gave money to the wealthy to hire
               people, but they didn't.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12600</time>
            <title>Roosevelt's program and the misuse of it in Lenore</title>
            <synopsis>Roosevelt's program. Misuse of program at Lenore - the man
               in charge hired his son as timekeeper and assistant foreman,
               but he didn't know how to do the job. A man who could do the
               work wouldn't.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12840</time>
            <title>Living in a section house.</title>
            <synopsis>Living in a section house.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Adversity: house fire, quarantine, making do. Courtship. Her work. Foster and Adams
         as promoters. Aunt Susan. Hoboes. Southern witches. Religious differences. 7-21-76
         3.6 hr
         96p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: You know I was going to ask you a rifle about a couple of your
         kin down there at Arrow, who you had mentioned to me and I'd also
         heard were pretty interesting people, and one of them was Aunt Susie.
         
         EDWARD GROSECLOSE: Aunt Susan?
         
         SS:  Yeah. I was wondering what you remember about her. What she was like.
         What do you .mean? What she was like?
         
         Well, I had an idea she was quite a lady, is what I heard.
         Yeah, she was quite an old lady to get around and do and go places
         and take care of people when they was sick. Oh, I don't know, she
         was just a general old lady of them times.
         
         SS:  Do you remember her when you were first here? She was still around
         wasn't she?
         
         DIXIE GROSECLOSE: Oh, yeah, she, oh, I don't know. Can't remember what year
         that she died. But I can remember sometime about a year or less
         after we came to Idaho 1907, 1908. 1908. And she was a neighbor what
         was it? Four miles from us?
         
         EG:  About four miles away.
         
         DG:  From our folks, and they had a big family and lived on a homestead
         ranch up there^below the George Johnson place down the canyon.
         
         EG:  Well, that steep hill out this side of George Johnson's there where
         them blackberries are up on the hill and across- that was their home
         stead there.
         
         DG:  Out from their homestead just below the track, they had a kind of a
         garden out there and she'd plant lots of ground cherries instead of
         blackberries. The later years that she put ground cherries in. She
         was a big worker. She done lots of sewing and crocheting and had her
         a garden. General all-around person.
         
         EG:  Yeah, they had their garden out there below the railroad tracks where
         all them blackberries is, and they had to pack their stuff to the
         house from there. About a quarter of a mile.
         
         DG:  Yeah, one time she was out there gathering ground cherries, wasn't it
         when she found a dead man?
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah, found a man dead out there.
         
         DG:  I guess he was kind of a, what they call a hobo, or somebody, you know.
         out there. So she found a—
         
         Early days them people used to- hobos they called 'em- they'd go along
         you know, and anywhere they got tired or anything, they'd stop. I
         guess this fellow was sick and laid down there by the river and died.
         
         SS:  Did you see many hobos?
         
         EG:  Oh, yes, in the early days they was a lot of 'em went along. And they
         had to bum for something to eat at different places. They was one,
         especially- Back in the East when anybody'd come to your place, you
         took 'em in the house. Rainy country back there, they never expect a
         fella to stay outside, but this country here, why you had all the out
         side to sleep in and that's where you stayed. They was a hobo come
         to ttoebKcountry here and bummed around for quite a while and my mother
         and my brother, Grover, was stayin' at my brother Will's place in 1904
         when he went—
         
         You told that before, didn't you?
         
         Not to me.
         
         Did the tell about the bum that had the lice?
         
         Huh-uh.
         
         So he come up there and they fed him but they — but he went away
         and then at Christmastime my brother he come up to the rest of my
         brothers' up in the Potlatch and I went down there and stayed with
         Mother. So he come back then when there was nobody but me and my
         mother there and I was just— oh, I was ten years old, I guess, he
         come in and sit down there, and until after, oh, along ten
         o'clock or so she asked him if he'd rather go— "Well, maybe he would."
         So she showed him upstairs where to go to bed, and he went up there
         and the next day he got up and stayed around again. I went out and
         cut wood and great big two hundred pound fella, he stayed there and
         watched me cut wood, never offered to cut any. She got to watchin'
         out the door to see what was going on. While I was cuttin1 wood he
         was standing there with his shirt open— doing like that— she seen
         then he was lousy. She knowed what she was up for. So he stayed
         there til she sant me with a note up to a neighbor, Hickman, up there
         to have him come down and tell him to leave. She wrote in the note
         that Lazarus was there and she thought he'd been dead three days and
         wanted Eli to come down and take care of him, bury him or something!
         But while I was gone up there, why, Grover and my other brother Hughes
         they come down, and so they was ahavin' quite an argument when I got
         back down there. So they gave him the dinner- he was getting kind a
         fcranky with Hughes but he never would argue with Grover. And Grover'd
         get kinda fcranky with him. He said','1 was at your place a while back
         and you and I was pretty good friends." But he went away and he never
         come back. We had to clean up them lice! (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  How long did he stay?
         
         EG:  Oh, he come there sometime along about toward noon sometime one day
         and stayed til afternoon the next before he left. They had to invite
         him to leave before he went.
         
         SS:  Your mother didnjt feel she could just tell him to get out?
         
         EG:  No. I don^t know what a little, old woman thought in them days if a
         a big, husky guy come along and stopped thataway.
         
         DG:  Back to Aunt Susan, why, she always was busy as long as she lived and
         I could remember, she'd work all day and then of an even
         ing, why, she'd sit down and she always had her mending basket or
         piecing quilts or crocheting, fixing, sewing, making something for
         some child or something that way. And so, I don't know, she finally
         broke her hip and was in a wheelchair for a while. And so, you'd go
         m, why, she was never idle ft minute, no matter what. She'd have three
         or four crochet things workin* 01?. She'd get kind of tired of one
         pattern and fool with another one. And I used to always tell her that
         if I ever got to heaven that I'd sure glance around and if I saw some
         body over in the corner with their hands aflyin' I'd go to the corner
         because I'd know it was her,K busy all the time. And this one
         time my mother was quite ill— remember she had pneumonia? But any
         way they was settin' up with her at night, and she'd work all day and
         get on a horse and ride down and set up with my mother all night and
         then in the morning get on her horse and go home and see about her
         family. And one time my dad brought the horse out of the barn, you
         know, for her to get on to go home and he was aholdin' the horse, and
         it was on a kind of a sidehill like, and it wasn't too big of a horse,
         and she was pretty active lady at that time, so she grabbed ahold of
         the saddle horn, you know-, and give a jump and jump up into the saddle
         and she^went clear over the horse hanging onto the saddlehorn and she
         jumped and she went clear on the other side instead of landing in the
         saddle.
         
         SS:  She get hurt at all?
         
         DG:  No hurt her it: kinda twisted her arm a little hangin' on
         but she just laughed. She was always quite jolly and jokey about
         everything. She had a daughter and everything and oh, we kids would go
         there quite a lot when we were along about twelve-fourteen in there
         and her daughter fcjia.. Mae was beginning to learn to sew a little bit.
         And so she was making a nightgown and her mother offered to help her but
         g-fftfcMae decided that she didn't want any help, she wanted to do it all
         by herself and she did just fine until it come to making fes^ buttonholes
         and so she put her buttons on and made her buttonholes, and so, her
         mothere laughed so about it that she got the gown out and showed us when
         we went to visit, and instead of folding the cloth and just cuttin' a
         little lit, you know to make the buttonholes, why, cut them
         in round circles for her buttonholes and she worked little round
         circles and her mother just laughed and laughed over that, showed every
         body that come  buttonholes.
         
         SS:  Was  embarrassed by that, do you think? The girl would be em
         barrassed by that.
         
         DG:  Well, it didn't bother ^KMae too much, you know, but her mother just
         got such a bang out of it all.
         
         SS:  Was Aunt Susan called aunt by everybody or just by her nephews? She
         didn't go by that name?
         
         DG:  Well, everybody called her Aunt Susan. There was so many Grosecloses
         around, you know. It was Aunt Susan and Uncle Jim and Aunt Lizy and
         Big Jim and Little Jim, and all of that. But my brothers and all, when
         they were little, why they liked to go and visit Aunt Susan and
         Uncle Jim, and when they were small they'd say, "Let's go to Susan-Jim's."
         And they made the folks to go up to Jim's and stay all day- Susan-Jim's.
         "Want to go to Susan-Jim's." But Aunt Susan was just aunt to the. neices
         and to their nephews and everybody that come along;\Aunt Susan, yo u
         know.
         
         Why would they want to spend the day at her place?
         
         Well, they had kids that were smallt you know, and just jolly friends.
         And everything, you know. 
         
         SS:  But she worked harder than the average woman?
         
         DG:  Well, I don't know that she actually did. They all had a lot of families,
         but I don t think she was a harder worker than any of.the other that did
         that.
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know, she was husky along about that time than the others
         around. She had that family of nine to look after. Well, I don't know,
         after I growed up I said that Aunt Susan and my mother was two of the
         meanest women that ever lived. They raised a whole bunch of boys that
         dddk ?t know anything. We didn't know anything about housework, we nev
         er had to wash fchhe dishes, we never cleaned up the house. We didn't
         know nothin' about that. No. Our mothers done that. Had some cousins
         that come down here from Spokane and they had nine kids, too, but the
         help little boys, when they got to be eight-nine years old, they to
         do the dishes. The older boys- well,the oldest one he was a bellhop
         from Spokane, the folks was away and the first thing he done before he
         got dinner was to go and take his broom and clean the whole house, clean
         it all up good, and then he could make a good dinner. I seen. ... there-
         Three girls. them people learnt their boys something, mother and Aunt Susan they
         just waited on on us boys like, I don't know what they did like.
         
         SS:  What about the girls? Did the girls work?
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah, the girls, they worked, they done housework.
         
         DG:  He only had one sister himself.
         
         EG:  I only had one.
         
         DG:  But Aunt Susan had four girls, I think.
         
         EG:  Three.
         
         SS:  Now, you must have enjoyed that when you were growing up, not fo have
         to do any of that stuff.
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah. But when we got a little older and had to get out on our own
         a little bit, it wasn't so good.
         
         SS:  You didn't know how to bach?
         
         EG:  Yeah. I went out, well, when I was seventeen, my sister, was'sixteen,
         we went up in the hills and milked cows. Sent all the cattle up here in
         the hills from Tftkean, seventeen Iwent up there and my sis
         ter got a toothache. It was a filled tooth, ulcerated, and there was
         nothing that would ease it but cold water in her mouth. You know how
         long that would ease it. That was all she could find. Well, she started
         out the next day with my brother, a preacher, he had to
         come out to preach, so they thought they could get a tooth pulled at
         Southwick; there was nobody there and *he -had to go clear to Kendrick.
         Then she was down in this country and when she got down here then she
         stayed down here two weeks. I was up there alone, and see I had eleven
         cows to milk and ten calves to feed and a separator to clean up and do
         my own cookin'; carry^water that I drunk and washed stuff up three
         quarters of a mile in a bucket for two weeks, and bring in my cows. Oh,
         I knowed how to stir up bread, but one batch, the last batch I made, I
         forgot to put any salt in it. And I would get up of a morning and go
         and milk, take the cows and get them out; tend to the calves and then
         I'd get my breakfast over about ten o'clock. Get things cleaned up
         about ten and then lay down and sleep til about three. Get up and go
         and out after the cows. There was no fences, you pointed the cows north
         and you'd expect to go north to find 'em and if they cirlced and went
         south, maybe you didn't find 'em for a day or two. So this other even
         ing I come in and my oldest brother and his wife and my sister come in
         with a four horse team. My brother got sick and my sister had to drive
         the team in; she hadn't been used to drivin' four horses; she was good
         with two. She come in with that outfit. I got in and I had nothin' to
         eat, they'd eaten everything up. My sister-in-law she said that was the
         best bread she'd ever eat. Well, she'd been out all day with^nothin'
         to eat. And I Laughed at her, I told her that I could beat her cookin'!
         She stayed there for a couple of weeks, and boy, if she didn't do her
         best. She put cream in her biscuits. She had biscuits you could hard
         ly pick up, they'd pretty near fall to pieces. But I never would brag
         on her, only, "That was pretty good."
         
         SS:  She was doing that because you had been doing all the cookin' by your
         self?
         
         EG:  I had been doing thgiycookin' and she wanted me to brag on her cookin'.
         She could cook, alright, but then she could slop it up, too, if she
         wanted to. Didn t try all the time, but that time she was doin' her
         best.
         
         SS:  What do you think the idea was that your mother and pur aunt didn't
         teach the boys?
         
         EG:  Oh, I don't know, I guess back up to their time that was the way it was
         done, and they was a little older than this other family. And this
         other family was raised in town. I guess that's the way all old-timers
         done, the men done work outside the house and the women done the
         a that
         inside. If they didn't have enough to do,, they'd get a hired girl to
         help. Men didn't do much, I guess, only when they had to go out in the
         hills huntin1, or somewhere like that.
         
         DG:  Women didn'tjgo out and help in the fields, you know, like they did in
         later years. You know, they'd maybe spin and weave and sew and cook
         
         Yeah, they did£ My mother used to go out in the fields and beans.
         
         SS:  When she was young?
         
         EG:  Yeah, well, she was young, yes, it was after I could remember though-
         I was the youngest one, she wasn't very young.
         
         SS:  What you're sayin'—
         
         DG:  Well, my folks, I can't remember my aunts and all of them, you know
         and Granddad's family doing very much outside work, but they would
         help to gather in the fruit or something, and then when they got big
         enough they'd go and do housework for somebody else, you know, to earn
         money, but I can't remember of them just going out in the fields and
         takin part in everything.
         
         Then you figure then that the ouMe work was more later for women?
         Seems to me like it is. More and more women's lib!
         
         Well, what about you? Were you raised to do just the inside woto(, for
         the most part?
         
         No, not entirely. My main chores at home though was really bringing
         in the cows and milking and things like that. And I didn't do an awful
         lot of work,
         
         EG:  Didn't do much field and garden work.
         
         DG:  I married pretty young, and then after I was married, why, I loved to
         work outdoors. I still don't like housework. I don't like any part of
         it. I used to like to go out and shock hay and mow the hay back in
         the barn when they hauled it in. And I never did do much mowing, but
         I did quite a lot of raking and shocking and hauling and all like that.
         I guess I didn't understand enough,. I'd run into something
         with the mower blade, but I tried it a little bit. Even tried plowing
         a little, but I didn't get very far with that because cut and cover,
         But I just thought it was fun.
         
         SS:  Because what?
         
         DG:  Plowed- cut and cover, you know, just get in and out,' ' keep
         the furrow like he did and Id get real aggravated. When oldest
         daughter was a baby I went out, it was so lonesome, you know, went
         out in the field where he was aplowin'. followin along after him,
         watchin' him plow, and I asked him to let me plow and he could carry
         the baby, and so, he let me try, you know. And I would get pretty ag
         gravated because I couldn't do it as good as he could! (Chuckles)
         
         EG:  Well, that's a funny thing about them old footburner plows. A man
         that was used to runnin' 'em, you see, he knows that every move that
         plow makes, and it's just adjusted like that, you know, but the first
         time you start to plow, if that plow starts to go too far, take too
         much land, well, you don't notice it until it's got over there four
         or five inches then you throw it back and when you throw it bac, most
         likely you'll throw it too far, and it'11 be going this waywhen
         it goes this far it won't cut it all out and just throw it over
         and that's what they call cuttin' and covering when you don't do it,
         and then you press down the handle a little too much, it'll come up and
         make dog beds and-
         
         SS:  Dog beds?
         
         EG:  Yeah, dog beds in there- the plow don't run level, why, it'll go up and
         down you know, and make a deep place and a shallow one. It's quite a
         thing to that.
         
         SS:  That's what was happening to you?
         
         DG:  Cuttin and coverin'. I didn't plow a very long strip, but walk
         along and seeing him  easy and smooth, you know.
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know, you never seemed to think after you got used to
         tunnin' that plow, if it started to go too far thataway, why you just
         back, you know. Well, it was all done within an inch, if that tipped
         an inch, why you throwed it back an inch and you held it right there^
         And if you had a plow sharpened right, you could set it in the ground
         and turn it loose and it would run, but if it wasn't, why then, you
         had to keep fightin' it.
         
         SS:  Well listen, if you didn't like to do the housework and that kind of
         stuff and the cookin' so much, you still must have had to do an awful
         lot of it in those days, didn't you?
         and
         
         DG:  Well, I- when I was home havin' the younger brothers, you know the one
         sister,^1 was eight years older than the rest of 'em, and I had to do a
         lot of work, and a lot of babysittin' and a lot of water carryin' and
         quite a bit of washing and dishwashing and cooking.^Unless Mama was sick
         I didn't do such a lot of the cookin', but he was pretty good to help
         with the cookin'. And she cooked because we never had a lot on hand
         and couldn't afford to waste anything or fix thing nobody could eat.
         (Chuckles) But I had to do a lot of preparing and getting things in.
         
         SS:  You think that that's why you didn't like it so much, 'cause you had to
         do so much of that when you were young? When you were a kid?
         I don t know, but I just naturally— Now, my youngest— my only sis
         ter- my mother could knit and crochet and sew and all that, but I never
         cared for any of that. My sis is like that. She can do all kinds of
         fancy work and Icould sew alittle bit, a quilt,  Idon't to
         be very particular or anything. I think it was beautiful to see it,
         but I'd rather have amagazine or a book or out playin' along the river,
         or something that way, you know. I'd rather have a fishin' pole than
         I would to have a needle in my hand, or a crochet hook. (Chuckles)
         Did you say to me before that you had to miss a lot of school because
         
         SS: of your mother being sick?
         
         Yes, I missed a lot. I don't know if I've done away with my report cards
         but I used to have 'em; quite a few of 'em, and oh, out of a seven or
         eight month term, I probably wouldn't average attendance of what would
         figure four months out of a term in the schoolroom. I'd be missing so
         much through sickness in the family.
         
         It wasn't your being sick so much as your mother? Right?
         
         No, I didn't miss a lot on my being so sick, just mostly some of the
         rest of the family, you know, helping with the little ones and with my
         mother.
         
         SS:  Do you feel that that retarded your learning?
         
         DG:  What?
         
         Do you think that held back your learning a lot to miss too much school?
         Could you catch up and that kind of thing easy?
         
         Well, I could do pretty good. I got along good with school. I liked
         school, and even some of the teachers tried to encourage me to go on
         with school, but financial wise and the folks would have had to let me
         stay away from home and all, and they didn't agree to it, but I did
         manage to make my grade each year. I made a grade^a year in spite of
         it all, you know.
         
         SS:  Do you remember how you felt about that then? I mean, did you feel that
         you were really missing out to not be able to go to school all the time?
         
         DG:  Well, I did feel bad that I couldn't go. I don't remember that I really
         felt that I was being held back. Someway I could understand that I was
         needed, but I liked to go, -ift it made me feel real bad not to be able to
         go more. To be in school. But, I don't know, I I more or less
         accepted it as something that had to be. always kind of felt that I
         did. And when I look back on the things that I did, why, I learned an
         awful lot of lessons, and quite a bit that helped me after I was married
         and.life went on. And being poor people, when I look back on it,
         why, I think.I learned something from all of it, that was — been helpful
         in my years later.
         
         SS:  When you say you learned something, then you think of it like you learned
         how to care for people?
         
         DG:  Well, yeah more understanding of people and how to be content— to get
         along with what you have and things like that, you know. And just kinda
         accept what comes and not expect to be a millionaire when you had only(Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Was your mother sick chronically?
         
         DG:  Well, no, not so much. The babies come pretty fast and then she had at
         times off and on, there was kidney problems and pneumonia, and just
         things that would happen along. But she finally had a stroke, oh,
         that was, of course, several years after I was married. She passed away
         when she was only sixty-four. And there must have been It hit her in
         the morning and she was never conscious til night.
         
         SS:  But when you were helping and you were staying out of school, was it
         mostly when she was just actually sick or when you were needed to help
         raise the kids?
         
         DG:  Well, whenever- just whenever I was needed to help with the youngsters,
         and little things that I could do, you know. The neighbors would come
         in and help what they could with the work, but it was just somebody to
         be in the house all the time.help look after the smaller ones when
         the dad happened to be outside, you know. It was just that I was—
         Well, back then, an eight year old kid can do quite a bit, you know,
         looking after little ones from babies on up to three and four and five
         years old. And you knew enough to kind of keep 'em out of too much
         trouble.
         
         SS:  Was she in bed for much of this time when you were home helping instead
         of at school?
         
         DG:  I was never out so much when she was able to be out of bed. She wasn't I
         bed— well, maybe two or three weeks at a time, and maybe in another two
         three weeks why there'd be— if she wasn't ill some of the children would
         be and there would be a need, you know. Maybe I'd get to school one
         week out of some months and then some months maybe I'd be there all b^£
         maybe only six or seven days out of the month. All in all, if I had my
         record through all the years that I went, I don't think I was in school
         more than what would you say? More than half of the time?
         
         EG:  Something like that.
         
         DG:  You can remember looking at the cards. talkin' about it.
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Then after you two got married, you had to do all that work over again
         at home. I mean, there was all that work you had to do just the same.
         
         DG:  After I got married, why, I was workin' for us and started having my
         own kids. And then when I got a chance to go out in the fields some
         because I liked to go out your know when he'd be mowin' and he'd let
         me drive the team and rake. I went not because he ordered me to, or
         anything but just simply that I liked to, that I wanted to be out. And
         then up at Tekean, when we lived there, there was one summer that, oh,
         there was a neighbor had a job and he had quite a bit of hay to put up,
         and he kept trying to find somebody to put it up, you know, so he
         could stay on the job and so Ed didn't have anybody to help him and
         our kids were small, and so he took the job of hauling the hay— with
         the wagon and a team, and I went with him and would help him pitch it
         on, you know haul it out of the shock. You mowed it? Did you mow it?
         Or just haul it?
         
         EG:  I think I just hauled it.
         
         DG:  Hauled it and put it in? But, anyway, why, it took us three or four
         days.to put the hay in, and we d get our chores done and take the lit
         tle kids and drive out. What was it, about three miles to this place
         and then we'd haul hay all day. And I can remember we needed the money
         so bad, and I think it was thirty dollars we got for putting that hay
         in. I'd help pitch on the wagon and then mow it back in the barn, and
         like that. And so I was his hayhand through that job. And we 
         the money and very glad to get it. And I didn't think, really, too
         much about it. It was something that I enjoyed doing.
         
         SS:  Sounds like you really had rough times, where you just really needed
         the money that you could get.
         
         DG:  Well, we never, had very much wealth. (Chuckles) I had quite a little
         sickness after I was married. Oh, I had lots of tonsilitis and we let
         it go too long, really, before we had the tonsils taken out, and it
         kinda ruined my health. And after our second child was born, I was a
         whole year before I was gettin' straightened out where I could do very
         much work, and that made it pretty rough on him, and he had to help with
         with us the house and sometimes we could have somebody that— part of the time.
         Oh, to look back on it, it seemed kind of rough at the time, and now,
         it seemed that you kind of grew from it more than you would from having
         just everything handy and just at your finger tips, like our three older
         children had it kind of rough and had to walk quite a ways to school,
         and we didn't used to have much. And while the other two didn't have
         much, well, they had much better opportunities and much better chance
         than the older ones did, you know, finances. And things got a little
         bit better. But the older ones feel that they really, when they look
         around at their own kids and their grandkids and all, and they talk
         about it, and they feel that they really, you know, didn't miss any
         thing, because they felt that they learned alot about life, too, you
         know. How to consider others and all. Iknow that whenever they got
         a treat of any kind, especially the oldest one, why, she got a nickle
         or got acandy bar, or somebody give her one, she never eat it^anything
         til she got home and cut it up equally and divided it with the others.
         Nowadays, why, kids, I don't know, they're not all that way, Idon't
         mean that, but I can see it in the little younger ones, they're run
         ning into the store for something all the time, and maybe they're gonna
         give somebody a bite and once in a while they'll divvy up but it seems
         like it's just different somehow. Ican see it in our grandkids, they're
         different than other kids. And there was one thing, there wasn't too
         much trying to keep up with Jonses, because pretty near everybody were
         in the same boat. You know, the neighbors and the neighborhoods we
         lived in, there wasn't very many families that was enough ahead of you
         you know, or what you consider real well-to-do, that you need to feel
         too out of place. Most everybody was just about the same boat. Willing
         to share and so on.
         
         How much did the kids- did they really pull together as they were grow
         ing up? Imean, did the family operate as a unit? You know what Imean?
         Or were they kind of- I mean would they share in your concerns about
         having enough to make do?
         
         No.
         
         Yeah. Ididn't think we ever had any trouble. Did you?
         
         We got along really quite good. We've been pretty proud of the kids in
         that respect. And I know our oldest boy, one time Iwas talkin' to him
         and Isaid, "Well, the two younger ones, while they didn't have anything
         and everything," he was working pretty steady then, and they had bet
         ter opportunities and both of them went into good jobs right out of
         high school, and so I was talking to Virgil about how it was with them
         and how lucky they were, you know, if they had a treat, and the things
         that we did and had and didn't have, and, "Oh, well," he says, "Well,
         Ma we didn't miss it. Well, you just never missed it, you just don't
         know the difference, when you don't have everything now, you don't miss
         it, do you?" Well, I got to thinking about it, and you just knew you
         wasn't going to have it. And you didn't spend your time grievin1 over
         it, you just made-do. And I was laughin' about it; we're the make-do
         family, I said, "If we didn't have it, we could do without, or find
         something else to take it's place."
         
         SS:  Were there ever times, Ed, when you were worried about having enough to
         make-do?
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know as I worried much about it. I just made-do with
         what I had.
         
         DG:  There was times that he had it awful rough.
         I just had to take it as what I got, and make-do with that. Wasn't
         nothin' to worry about, because- in the '30's there, there wasn't nobody,
         nothin' to do, and there was five or six people in our neighborhood
         down there that needed work, but there was no use to go anywhere else
         because when you went over in the cities, why they was there by the
         hundreds- that was a lookin' for work! We had a little place we could
         grow garden and grow most of the stuff we eat, so we was that much bet
         ter off than most of the people. We had some chickens and generally a
         pig or two and a cow or so. I got down once I didn't have any cows.
         And then I got ahold of two and the train killed 'em both one day.
         They got on the track; train killed 'em both. And the company, they
         
         EG: was kinda slow about payin'. I got ninety dollars for the two of 'em
         at that time.
         
         DG:  That bought us another cow.
         
         EG: Yeah, everybody else wanted more for their cow than what the railroad
         paid me for that.
         
         DG:   least we got something back out of it.
         
         EG:  They was so slow that I told 'em if they didn't pay me I was gonna put
         a fifteen dollar a month milk bill on that— add it on, because that
         was all the milk cows I had. ThejY they paid me. When you got an ani
         mal killed by the railroad,you're generally about six months gettin'
         the pay, or longer. My folks places down there, the railroad
         run right through 'em, and they'd put the cattle one one side for a
         while and then the other and then they'd come and crawl through the
         fence. Well, there was always good feed on the railroad, and,stock
         would get to pushin' on that fence and some of 'em'd learn how to crawl
         through and others just naturally get through and then didn't know
         how to get back out. That was thejmes that got killed. Let's see, I
         think we got about five killed at one time. And then he got three
         horses killed and another'n crippled at one time on the track.
         
         SS:  Did you find that you could get by by bariermg and not using money?
         In the early days? Were there many chances for that?
         
         EG:  Well, yes. there was a lot of that you know. Like—
         
         DG:  Well, you could trade work.
         
         EG:  Well, you didn't know^a dozen eggs— you didn't know how much it cost
         you to produce them eggs, but then you could always take them to the
         store and trade 'em for something. Generally, eggs run from fifteen
         to twenty-five cents, here in this country. But back in the East, why,
         they used to go to five cents a dozen, back there.
         
         DG:  That was about 1904. 1901. We left the East in '02. Got out here, eggs were two
         bits, at
         that time.
         
         DG:  I can't remember exactly how much eggs was when I come out, you know,
         they in 1907. But I can remember bought, what ;caey call percale,.now they
         call it calico and made clothes, you could get it for five and ten cents
         a yard. And you could get the nicest lace about they had for five cents
         a yard, and all like that. And then my mother worked a lot for seventy
         cents a week and managed to do pretty well on it, then finally, I think,
         I believe the most she ever got was about two and a half a week when she
         worked for a doctor and his family.
         
         EG:  That was before she come West. She never worked for no wages after she
         come out here.
         
         DG:  No, not after she came out in 1908.
         
         SS:  Two and a half a week?
         
         Yeah, back in well, 1900, why, girls would go and work for fifty cents
         a week. And a young woman would go and do all the housework for a dol
         lar a week, back in them good old days!
         
         Instead of five and eight, ten dollars a day, why, they—! (Chuckles)
         But, of course, you could buy an awful lot with that amount of money
         then, too.
         
         Well, back at that time there, what they called that calico, was three
         cents a yard, so, you see, for about twelve cents they could buy enough
         of calico to make a big dress or two dresses.
         
         SS:  Did you always have enough clothes for the kids? Or did you find you
         had to mend 'em and patch 'em?
         
         DG:  When , or when I was growmup?
         
         SS:  Well, both.
         
         DG:  Well, there was a lot of makin' over and hand-me-downs. People'd give
         things— now, my mother, being good at sewing, why, she did an awful
         lot of making over out of older things. And Dad was well acquainted
         with a lot of railroad men, you know, like conductors on trains or
         engineers and all like that, and a lot of trains went through. And
         he was a cripple man, too, so instead of sending things to the Goodwill;
         never heard of the Goodwill then, you know, really, but they would
         sometimes throw off sacks, gunny sacks, of clothes. Older suits and
         dresses or whatnot and discards; they knew the family didn't have very
         much, and they'd throw that off. And Mother'd rip up the suits, and
         she made the boys suits. And I've got pictures of 'em where they're
         all dressed up in clothes she made and she made their trousers and
         shirts. And so, once in a while they was made out of new material, but
         we didn't get anything much all ready made, that was bought'. And then
         with us— well, I didn't like to sew very well, I have did quite a bit
         of it, and we used a lot of makin' over. Quite a lot of mending, and
         all like that, too.
         
         SS:  What did your stepfather do to make a living?
         
         DG: Well, he trapped a lot f$. the winter. And at one time, that's 'fore he
         was married, though, he had a little store.
         
         SS:  At Arrow?
         
         DG:  Uh-huh. And he raised, you know, corn and hay and had cows and
         chickens and raised hogs for meat.
         
         EG:  quite a little business at Arrow at one time.
         
         He worked out in the harvest fields some, during the harvest period.
         And then in the wintertime he'd make- he and Ed's brother, Will, worked
         together a lot and did reasonably good with trapping.
         
         Well, at that time, the skunks— they was a Doctor Foster here in Julia
         etta and he was a rubbin' doctor and he would take skunk oil and he'd
         give a dollar a pint for skunk oil, and he'd take that and rub his pa
         tients with it for arthritis or rhtMnatism, stuff like that. He used
         that skunk oil, so he'd handle all the skunk oil they could get. They
         wasn't too many people catchin' em and rendering that out. And then
         there was a Chinaman he run onto down there at Lewiston give twen
         ty-five cents for skunk gall. So the skunks he could get, he'd get
         twenty-five cents for the gall and a dollar a pint for the oil. Oh, I
         don't think possibly ajskunk'd make apint of oil, but then it took a
         lot of skunks to make—
         
         What about skins?
         
         Huh?
         
         What about the fur?
         
         Well, the fur, they got- I don't know just what they got for that, but
         they got something out of the fur, too. And that oil.
         
         Did they trap anything else, Ed?
         
         EG:  Oh, yes, they trapped- well, along at that time coons were just about
         gone outta the country, but coyotes, they picked up quite a few of them.
         You know, in them days, coyotes, they had a bounty on 'em of two and a
         half, and then they'd get the fur off of 'em in the wintertime. So a
         coyote made a fella quite a little money. But, nowdays they don't let
         you— they won't let ya kill a coyote hardly.
         
         You told me once that you figured that the Indians got lice off the whites
         if they got 'em from any place. Do you think that's true?
         Yeah. Well, yes. Well, now that hobo that I was tellin' ya about stay
         ed with us there, and before we come out here my brothers were stayin'—
         baching with a feller up the Little Potlatch there and a white man come
         and stayed with them. He come there with some Indians. And then these
         white fellers stayed there a day or two, and he give them lice. So
         chances are he give the Indians lice fore he come there. And then,
         stayed there and he borrowed my brother's horse. Well, one brother had
         a saddle and the other had a horse and they put the two together and
         this fella borrowed 'em to go somewhere and he never did come back!
         
         DG:  These are the four oldest brothers, and here they are when they're a
         they had on little older. But all the clothes were made these suits were made out
         of hand-me-downs, old suits and things, and then they're just barefooted,
         
         EG:  They said the man- oh he was burnin' the brush and the man was workin'
         on Sunday burning brush, and then the fella— oh, I don't know what,
         somebody told him that he'd send him where there wasn't no Sunday, so
         he sent him to the moon. And that's the way the man got in the moon;
         he was burning brush on Sunday. That's the old story.
         
         DG:  That's the old, old story about Solomon Grunday burning brush on Sunday.
         Kind of a, what you call it?
         
         EG:  That was an old story. That's the way the man got in the moon, was
         that he was burnin working on Sunday— he was burning
         some brush on Sunday!
         
         DG:  An old fable.
         
         SS:  Well, you say in here, Ed, too, what you said to me before. That you
         think the Indians were more civilized than the white man. I'm just
         curious about that. Do you really think it's true?
         
         EG:  Well-
         
         SS:  I'm not saying no; I'm not saying I disagree with you a bit.
         
         EG:  When the white man come here, the things that they done— Well, now the
         first ones that come here, the first settlement was a bunch of outlaws,
         you know, said they was a bunch of gamblers that had went broke and they
         come here to find money; find gold. That's what they come for.
         
         SS:  Come where?
         
         EG:  Come to America.
         
         SS:  Oh, here.
         
         EG:  And there was only one man in the bunch that knowed enough to govern
         'em, and that was John Smith. Well, he went to the Indians an they
         give him corn. The first time he got corn for a little- I don't knowmaybe
         a few beads; he went back again, and they was slow about givin'
         him corn, and he took a gun and went to the chief,ytold him that he'd
         fill up their ships with corn or he'd fill 'em with their dead bodies,
         and they took the corn away from 'em. Held 'em up. What would you
         think of that today if a man come to your place and- strangeryou
         treated him good and he went away and he come back a little while
         later and held ya up and took everything you had? That's the kind of
         fellows that the first settlers was in this country. Now then, the
         Indians-
         
         DG:  If they didn't take it all, they forced 'em to give 'em what they wanted,
         
         EG:  Yeah, they took what they wanted from 'em by force. And then they trade
         'em a little something and then the Frenchmen they come and went up the
         Mississippi and took that country there, everything in the Mississippi,
         that was their's. Well, then they sold that— the United States give
         'em $20,000,000 fer it, and then they told all over the world, come out
         to this free country, come in here. And they come; went to takin'
         Indian land. The Siouxs— some of the Indians, they might have been a
         few of 'em that worshipped idols, but the Siouxs and the Nez Perces,
         they wasn't that kind. The Siouxs they had a history— I read part of
         it of their's— that they believed in divine healing. They had great
         medicine. They called it great medicine. And they were very proud of
         their women. The women was the Mother to men, and anybody that wronged
         a woman - a Sioux woman - he was in trouble. If one of their own didn't
         take and take care of , they'd take him over the hill and kill
         him with rocks.
         
         SS:  You told me about that.
         
         EG:  Well, that was that. Well, then these three drunken cowboys come and
         caught these two squaws and kept 'em overnight, and then turned 'em out
         and the next night three of these white men was hung. Well, them men
         had no business going into that Sioux country. That was a nation of
         different people. But, of course, they wasn't as strong- they wasn't
         as well fixed militarily as the white man, so he just— well, that was
         the way in them days. If one bunch of people wasn't as well prepared
         with the armies as the other, why, the other one just run over 'em;
         that wasn't considered wrong in them days.
         
         DG:  The Indians was pretty civilized when we come though.We always got
         along pretty good in any of our dealings.
         
         EG:  Yes, they had awful good morals. Old Joseph's father, he says, "The world
         don't belong to anybody. You use the world as long as you're here, and
         then it goes to somebody else." That was his theory. He was one of
         Spalding's first converts.
         
         DG:  The world belongs to God, and we're just tenants.
         
         EG:  You are here and as long as you're here and as long as what you do with
         it. But then, the Indian was here and he had a good livin'. The animals
         and stuff that growed in this country here- he made a good livin'. Got
         along fine here. And he had no idea— that's another funny thing- the
         Indian had no idea of any other part of the world except where he was.
         Well, the other people over there, had no idea that there was any other
         Part of the world except what they had. They knowed of India, but
         they couldn't get there because the Truks blocked the trail. And Colum
         bus got the idea he's coming' around this way and get to India, and he
         come to America, well, America- the Indians didn't protect their country
         because they was no other part of the world to them but that. So the
         white man come and they treated him good and he got a foothold, and then
         he kept a kickin' the Indians around.
         
         DG:  Just takin' a little more.
         
         EG:  Takin' a little more and more all the time til he took the whole country
         over. Then the Nez Perce that didn't want booze on their reservation,
         but the white man come in here and bootleggers sold it to 'em. And they
         caused the death of an awful lot of good Indians by peddling booze to 'em,
         
         DG:  The young people ree so much, he's quite tolerant towards the
         Indians because they were here, you know, first. But these younger peo
         ple now, where the Indians are finally getting money back, you know,
         from all of this, why, they don't think the Indians got it comin'. I
         know—There's a lot of people that don't think they've got it comin' and thftf's
         a lot of 'em that do think they've got it acomin'. But then in the early
         days the people didn't think was nothing' just kick him out, shoot him,
         do anything with him. And a nigger the same way. I'll tell you a story
         about a policeman my brother knew back in Old Virginia 'long about 1903-
         '04, round there. This policeman shot a negra - well the nigger was
         two bits a dozen then, you know, and killing a negra you didn't ;
         ab nothing, but it got on this policeman's mind. And when he'd go to
         bed at nights, this nigger would be agittin' in bed with him. And when
         he'd be out, he'd see the nigger walking with him. He shot himself.
         But up to that time, you know, it wasn't considered nothing, but after
         he'd killed that one, why, he just got spooked by it and he went crazy.
         Killed himself. That's one thing, you know, it's not so- let's say you
         killed a man- that's something that's not so good after you've done
         it, why, most likely it'll git your mind. You might think- git mad at
         him- oh,"I'11 kill him." Well, then, if you're just turned loose and
         never git caught, why, it'll most likely show up on ya sometime. And
         then there's a funny thing about people— gunmen shootin' at a man.
         He's a great big thing, but awful good marksmen how they can shoot at a
         man and miss him, as big a thing as he is. I don't know, there's just
         something about your nerve and things that way.
         
         DG:  Maybe they don't always intend to hit ya.
         
         HG: Well-
         
         EG:  That gun never snapped. It was a good gun. He pulled it out and he
         shot at a stump and it fired every shot just as regular as they come.
         But when he pulled it on that man it snapped, every bullet around snapped,
         didn't fire when he pulled it on that man, but agoin' pulled it
         on a stump and fired every shot.
         
         SS:  Did he fire more than once at this man he got mad at?
         
         EG:  He never fired it; never fired the gun. He snapped it clear around
         at him.
         
         DG:  What do you mean, he snapped it clear around?
         
         EG:  Well, it was a six-shooter and he tried to shoot him six times, and
         the gun snapped every time.
         
         SS:  When you say snapped; what does that mean?
         
         EG:  It just snapped, it don't fire.
         
         SS:  Clicked, but didn't fire.
         
         EG:  Clicked, but didn't fire, but when he took it and cut into that stump
         it fired every time.
         
         SS:  He must have been pretty mad at that guy? He was ready to kill him,
         was he?
         
         EG:  Yup. He was drunk, and he was —
         
         DG:  It wasn't his fault at the time that he didn't kill him.
         
         EG:  No. It wasn't his fault. It was the Almighty had his arms around
         him that kept that gun from firing.
         
         SS:  Well, you know, you grew up around the Indians out here.
         
         EG:  Yeah, I growed up among 'em.
         
         SS:  What did you think of their way of dealing with people as compared to
         the white man's way?
         
         EG:  Well, they were honest.
         
         DG:  'They was honest ones and they was just—
         
         EG:  Well, they was some of 'em that would be crooked. They learnt most of
         the crookedness from the white man. They was honorable people. When
         they said they'd do something, they'd generally carry it out. Sometimes
         they pulled some funny tricks; like my sister's homestead downAhere,
         they'd had the line surveyed between her and the Indians. And they set
         some stakes there. One tall stake and some low ones. My sister ^line
         of fence had never been put through. The Indians fenced away down
         around on her place. So this morning my brother got up and went out on
         a porch and there this old lady Allen and a Indian neighbor, Jim Red
         Coyote was out there foolin' around the corner, and Jim had the stake,
         the big stake. Albert hollered at him to put it back and he took over
         towards the railroad track and my brother, Grover says, "Maybe he just
         around track site." And when he got over on the railroad, he
         didn't stop on there, there was a big fill and he got behind the rail
         road track and went up to the other Indian's place up there. Wall,
         they decided that'd be about as good a day as any to put the fence
         through. So my brother went up to his corner, forty rods away and
         come down and sited to look.where this corner was where they d had
         there on the flat, and when he looked at that, and then looked on
         over across the country, why, it wasn't very f£r til he was a quarter
         of a mile off. The line was supposed to have went this a way and
         from where they'd moved that corner there a rod or two in the field
         why, it was way off over this way time they got over the river. That
         wouldn't do. So they had to go up to the school section corner theft
         on the hill a quarter of a mile up there and come from there down 
         iron there to this established corner and then they'd get the line
         through. And they got a line through and put the main part of the fence
         in.
         
         SS:  So they put it back where it had been?
         
         EG:  Well, we got it back where it was by going up to the school section
         corner a quarter of a mile further and then looking down at my brother's
         corner where the fence was in, but his corner post leaned a little and
         after we got the fence in the Indians had Briggs, the surveyor to come
         and survey it and he moved the fence three feet out. We'd got up on
         the Indians three feet and they put in the fence then the whole way
         through, and tore our fence out and throwed it off of their place. So
         it was always the Indian fence the whole way along that line there. We
         never did put in any fence.
         
         SS:  I want to ask you more about the Indians, but that reminds me; that story
         you told me about Kimberling and his fence being off his line.
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS: How did he get his line off in the first place?
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know.
         
         SS:  Had it been surveyed before he was there, or what? Had the land been
         surveyed already or what?
         
         EG:  No, he'd never had it surveyed. He musta started at the Indian corner
         somewhere and then just went out and measured too far.
         
         DG:  Did he buy.?
         
         EG: He homesteaded. Him and Tom Hall homesteaded, both of 'em, in that draw
         there. Tom was his son-in-law. And Kimberling just got in and got a
         place located there and then just built a fence til he got tired of
         fencing . There was nobody around him so, he just stuck his fence way
         out. Took in twenty, thrity rods more than what he had comin'.
         
         SS:  Just didn't pay no attention to it?
         
         EG:  No, he didn't pay no attention to it, took what he wanted. Built
         his house on vacant land and put an orchard on vacant land. There was
         a little patch of good land there and up on his place in the draw it
         wasn't any good. So he put out his garden and orchard on vacant land.
         Built his house on vacant land. Built his barn on vacant land and
         proved up on it, thataway.
         
         SS:  What year was it when he left and your brother got his place?
         
         EG:  I don't know- let's see, I don't know what year he sold out to Fisher
         and left the country nere.
         
         SS:  Were you still a kid?
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Oh, it don't matter. 
         
         EG:  Oh, it was '07 or '08 that he got out of here.
         
         Among the Indians that lived around where you were raised; did you have
         any personal friends? Ones that you were close to?
         
         Yes, they was one boy; he was a little older than Iwas, but Joh^on Wil
         liams, he went off to school and he learned to talk English. And he
         come back and he wouldn't talk Indian any more, only to an old Indian
         that couldn't understand English. To one like that he'd talk a little,
         but very little. And I used to ask him what the Indians called some
         thing; he didn't know. He would never tell me what anything was in
         Indian. Now if he'd a been a boy that would told me what stuff was in
         Indian, I'd a learned to talk Indian. But no, he wouldn't do it. If
         I heerd an Indian word, and would tell him the word he would in terpret
         it; tell me what it was in English, but he wouldn't tell me.
         
         SS:  Why not, do you think? He just didn't want to speak it any more?
         
         EG:  Just didn't want to speak it. And then he learnt all his family; they
         all learned to speak. When his little sister went to school, why, they
         had learned to talk- speak English, you know, when they first start
         ed to school. That was a great help to them. Now there was some other
         girls went— well, this Sam Waters down here, when he started to school
         he couldn't talk a word of English. He had to learn it along with his
         school work. And then the Mc Catty (?) girls, Tillie and Jane, they
         had to learn English from readin' in their books and J:he teacher talk,
         But the Williamses they knowed how to talk when they went to
         school. They could talk good, because Johnson learnt 'em. He only
         lived to be about nineteen and he died. There's a tombstone down there
         across from— across the river from Albrights, then there's a locust
         tree up there; I planted the locust tree and this tombstone, there's
         eight Indians' epitaphs on that tombstone. The Williams family therewell
         Johnson-
         
         SS:  How did he die?
         
         EG:  Tuberculosis. And Tom- and I don't know what his wife's name was- she
         never could talk English, or never would, then Esther and Agnes and Tom
         and his wife and Johnson, and then there was three younger ones. Eight
         of 'em all on that there. And then there was a stranger buried; there
         was nine in that graveyard over there where that tombstone is
         and that one locust tree's standing up there by it. I plated the lo
         cust tree up there when I rented the place and used to farm it there
         a while. Well, I rented it because there was wood on it, I needed the
         wood. There was driftwood there, lots of driftwood on there and I
         rented the place for that. And then I did farm it a little. Well I
         rented it for the— I only paid twenty dollars a year for it.
         
         SS:  What did you use the wood for?
         
         EG:  For my house.
         
         SS:  Firewood?
         
         Yeah. I got the wood out of there for two, three years before I rented
         the place where Elliott Williams lives, I rented that and was there for
         better'n two years.
         
         Where did your friend go to school when he went away?
         
         He went to school down there at Arrow, down there where Joe Wing lives.
         That's where the schoolhouse was.
         
         SS:  That's where he learned his English?
         
         No, I don't know where he went to learn his English. Some Indian school
         somewhere. father and his family lived on that place, and their house
         was kinda under the hill over there on the far side of the river, down
         in there, and I guess that was a damp place in that flat. Must have
         been what caused 'em all to have TB and die young, possibly*living in
         there right close to the river. But Amos— An Indian could split up a
         piece of ground, but a white man couldn't. If you had forty acres that
         there was five acres of good land and the rest was all scab, you had to
         take the whole forty to get that. But an Indian could take ten acres
         or five or twenty or whatever it was. So Amos split two forties and
         took all that ground in there that's rock, over across the railroad.
         That was A-l farm land when the railroad went in there, but they cut
         that bluff off and turned the river down in there and it just kept eatin'
         that way til instead of going right down the railroad where it
         was supposed to, why, it's clear over against the other hill now. Washed
         all that flat away, there was about twenty-five acres there. But them
         Indians, they moved the corners, and there's nobody today knows but them
         Indians where them corners was supposed to be.
         
         SS:  They moved the corners?
         
         EG:  Yeah, destroyed the corners where Briggs had marked. We couldn't ever
         find 'em. Briggs could tell ya close to where they was, but exactly
         where the corners was nobody ever found 'em. They was supposed to be a
         rock mark at every quarter corner. They got rid of ' em.
         
         SS:  Did you trust when the Indians told you something? Did you trust them;
         what they said?
         
         EG:  Weeel, no, not too much. They would lie, but they wouldn't steal, the
         early day ones. They're different now.
         
         SS:  I want to ask you about Foster. You had mentioned to me just when I
         was leaving the last time, I wanted you to tell me when you went do wn
         there for treatment.
         
         DG:  Well, he had become such an alcoholic by that time, til you couldn't
         depend on him for treatments. And Ed had left me there- they had, they
         called it the Health Home right by where they had the offices, the dif
         ferent doctors, you know, for to do the osteopathic— I think that's
         what they were-. And so, he said I'd get two treatments a day and the
         food, the kind of diet I was supposed to be on. And so he thought, well,
         give me the best advantage, you know for the time I was down there, so
         he left me there at the Home. And, to begin with, oh, for a morning or
         two I got what I was supposed to have, then they got so they'd put things
         out, you know, that didn't agree with me, and that wasn't ordered by
         the doctor. And I had a little trouble there, you know, and he had to
         get after 'em to get 'em to fix the things I was supposed to have. And
         then it went along two, three days just fine. And then one^ I went
         over to take my treatment and he was in no condition to give me one, so
         I went on back over and waited til the time for the evening treatment
         and I went back and he was still, you know kind of under the weather,
         so I was kind of a little disturbed— and what was it? A Marshall, a
         Doctor Marshall? Dr. Marsh? I'm not sure about his name now, Marsh I
         think. And he told me, he said, "Well, rather than for you to miss a
         treatment," he said, "if you prefer, I will give you a treatment."
         Well, I thought that was better than missing, so he give me the treat
         ment that night. Well, the next morning I went over and didn't see
         nothin' of Dr. Foster at first, so Dr. Marsh come by and wanted to know
         if I wanted to take another treatment by him, and so I told him I did.
         So, he was givin' me a treatment when Dr. Foster walked in, and he still
         wasn't- he was drinking enough that he wasn't too good, but he got kind
         of mad. He said, "Oh, so you just took it on yourself to change doctors,
         have you?" And I said, "Well, the idea was," I said, "you weren't av
         ailable and so I didn't want to miss my treatments." And so, I don't
         know, I guess maybe Foster give me a treatment or two after that, but
         he was always kind of disgruntled, you know, about it some way. And
         then— what was it happened to the— cloudburst come and—
         
         EG:  Cloudburst come and tore the water system out and they had an awful time
         gettin' water around there.
         
         DG:  Had to haul it and put it on the street corners in barrels, you know, for
         the people. And they couldn't get good water, and so it ended up, he
         just took me home.
         
         SS:  Was this during the time you were sick after having your baby?
         
         DG:  Yes, it was the year after. The baby was our second child- and what
         was she? About five months old when I was down there at Fosters?
         
         EG:  Something like that. I don't know.
         
         SS:  Did Foster have a good reputation at that time?
         
         DG:  Well, outside of his drinking-
         
         EG:  He had had a good reputation up to that time. I don't know much about
         him after that. But I know he got to drinking a lot.
         
         SS:  Do you think that when he was up here in Juliaetta that he was highly
         regarded, while he was here?
         
         EG:  Yes, he was here. 
         
         DG:  Apparently, as far as we know. We had no personal contact^ with
         him at that time.
         
         EG:  Well, my folks did. My uncle and him was great friends here. And him
         and his wife finally quit, and I happened to see her. She come up to
         see my aunt up here one time, and she was tellin' a story about the fel
         la comin' and sellin' twelve— I believe it was twelve bottles of moon
         for thirty dollars. And he give the fella a sample and she'd quit the
         doctor then and she said, "I think the old doctor was in on that. Got
         caught on that." But he took a lot of people. Thirty dollars for twelve
         bottles of drinks, booze, supposed to be booze, and when they got it it
         was cold tea! And he was gone. They figured he'd come from North Carolina
         and he got money enough that ^way to go back. So I suppose he went
         back, nobody knows what become of him, but he didn't show up no more.
         
         DG:  I don't know maybe some of his sons might be alive and still know, but
         he was really supposed to have cured several cancers of the breast. I
         don't know that internally or anything like that that he could do any
         thing for 'em. But the lumps that came and all, and he put what
         called a burner on. But I've seen the people that had the treatment
         and when they had that on, why, they just out and walked, practically
         day and night, just out walking the street, you know, just
         and walk because of the pain. But there was several people that it seem
         ed- don't know of course, never followed 'em up for years afterwards,
         whether it ever come back on 'em.
         
         SS:  So the treatment itself was kind of painful?
         
         DG:  Yah, very much so. And then he had a niece, passed away with cancer of
         the breast, and she was expecting a little one, and she noticed just
         before it was born, she noticed this lump, but they didn't think too
         much about it, thought it was milk gland or something. So when the
         youngster was born- they didn't go to the hospital them days- the doc
         tor came to the home- and he- She said to her husband, she said, "Now
         I mustn't forget to ask the doctor about this lump." And so she said
         that everything was.taken care of and the doctor started to leave, he
         even got out to the car and she told her husband, "Call him back, I ne
         ver mentioned the lump." And so he called him and he came back in and
         he said to her, "Oh, so you're another one of these women that's got
         cancer, huh?" And just kind of laughed- "Or think they've got cancer."
         And then when he examined her, he said, "Well, you know, I am a little
         apprehensive about this." And he said, "Just as soon as you're able,"-
         they made you stay in bed about ten days those days, instead of gettin'
         up in an hour or two- he said, "Just as soon as you're up, come in to
         my office, 'cause I want to make further examination."
         
         SS:  This was Foster?
         
         DG:  No, this wasn't Foster.
         
         SS:  This wasn't Foster.
         
         DG:  No, no, this wasn't Foster.
         
         EG:  An M.D.
         
         DG:  It wasn't Foster, yet, at that time. But she didn't go right in. By
         that time— I just don't remember just what- she said something about
         and her husband told her she was kind of imaginative. She got kind of
         mad, and she though, oh, well, she'd had a life- she was the second or
         third wife- and he had buried one woman with cancer, so she said, "I
         just thought well, if he feels that way,she just got kinda mad and
         kinda stubborn. And so it went on and she didn't go in right away;
         went on for a few weeks.
         
         SS:  Was he mad at her because- he was mad at her for—?
         
         DG:  Well, I don't know as he was mad at her, but he just made some remark
         about maybe she was imagining more, or something, you know, and made her
         sore. So that when she finally did go to the doctor, why he said to her,
         he said, "Well, I can't be sure what this is til it's taken out and
         tested," but he said, "I'm very concerned," He said, "I would like to
         operate immediately." And she said, "Oh, I don't know that I want this
         operation." You know, just that quick, she said, "I would like to see
         if I could get in touch with Foster." She'd heard and knew him, you
         know, around this country. And she said, "Could I wait long enough, or
         could I go and see them?" He said, "You go see 'em, if you know where
         they are." And all like that, but he said, "Whatever you do, don't put
         it off. Do it immediately." Well by the time she wrote up here to know
         where they was, and time she got Foster- one of the boys, the old man
         was gone- she got him traced down, when she found one of 'em, and he
         was in Portland not far from Beaverton. Not far from where she was at,
         and when she got him traced down it was about six weeks later. So, when
         she got to him, why he said, "Well, I've got to make a bunch of tests
         before I can be sure." So then it was about three weeks more before he
         got all of his testt^done, and then he told her, "It's definitely.
         And he said, "I could put a burner on and take it off if it hadn't of
         gone into your glands." But he said, "It's gone in already. Gone into
         your glands, and you never in the world could stand the pain, that you'd
         have to endure." But he said, "Had you," You know, "if they'd gofin
         touch immediately, right at first," he thought he could have did some
         thing for her. She lasted a year, but she left what? Four? Five? kids.
         
         EG:  Five kids.
         
         DG:  And her baby was a year old.
         
         SS:  It was too late to have any operation by that time?
         
         DG:  Too late by time for^surgery to do any good. And then by the time she
         died, of course, it had gone all over her, you know. She was only forty
         years old.
         
         SS:  You know, speaking about Foster, there was a story that I heard that
         kids, oh, people around Juliaetta used to think that they would see,
         after Foster moved down to Clarkston from here; looking at the house
         they would see the figure of— What have you heard about that?
         
         DG:  We heard about that, that it was a haunted house, and it was a nurse,
         supposed to be, kind of a nurse that would come out, on the porch up
         there, that they would see.
         
         EG:  I don't know what it is- I think it's supposed to be seen from Maicie
         Nye's house up here, up to the house up there now where Miller lives,
         Floyd Miller.
         
         DG:  Yeah, but I haven't heard anything about it in later years.
         
         SS:  What I'm talking about was , what the story was back then. Now, I've
         heard a couple of different stories. I don't know which one might be
         the one that people told. But I heard one, there was a nurse that kil
         led a baby or something up there, and she was standing in the window.
         And the other story I heard was that it was Foster's wife, a figure of
         her standing in the window up there.
         
         DG:  I don't know, I only heard that there would be something that would come
         out kinda at the door or porch or something that looked kinda like a
         nurse would appear at different times. That's the only one that I have
         heard. I never took much stock in it anyway. (Chuckles) But, yet I've
         heard it, you know.
         
         EG:  I've heard that, but I don't know how that there ghost stuff like that-
         I wouldn't believe there was such a thing if I seen it!
         
         SS:  Did you ever hear ghost stories back in the South?
         
         EG:  (Laughs) Oh, yes, yes. 
         
         SS:  Would you tell me a little bit of what you heard from back there? I'm
         not saying you believe in it or not, I'm just wondering what you heard.
         
         EG:  Well, the things that— the remedies for being bewitched. Now, if you
         had your cream—if your cream wouldn't churn, it was bewitched. So,
         the thing to do to get that cream to churn was to take a sickle- one
         of these little hand sickles, take that and heat it red hot, and put
         that down in your milk and that would kill the ghost and your milk would
         churn. That was the way to get your milk to churn.
         
         DG:  I think people were kind of- quite a few of 'em were awful superstitious.
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah. was, back in them days lots of superstitious people.
         Then it was bad luck to sweep down a spiderweb, a cobweb they called 'em,
         big cobweb up in the house, you broke one of them to keep from havin'
         bad luck, you was supposed to take so many yards of yarn, that you'd
         wove, you know, yarn, and take that there and stand in front of the fire
         place and throw it over your left shoulder into the fire and burn that
         yarn, stop the bad luck from breaking that spiderweb. Yeah.
         
         DG:  Now I had some relatives—
         
         EG:  Oh, her- now then I remember the right one- that was a ghost story, it
         was her uncle. He believed in witches. So his ox was sick and he
         went to the witchdoctor, they had one back there, went to him to find
         out what to do for his ox. Well during the time the old man was gone
         the ox got sick and the boys put him in the barn— or he got in the
         corn, and the boys put him in the barn. The witch doctor told the old
         man to come home and draw the picture of an ugly man on the barn door,
         and then get up before sunup in the morning and not say anything to any
         body and shoot that picture with a silver bullet. That would break the
         spell on the ox. Well the boys had put the ox in there and he heerd the
         old man acomin' and he come with his head up to the door to be let out
         to pasture and the old man he shot the ugly picture on his door and he
         heard a racket in the barn and went in and went in and looked and he'd
         shot the old ox right between the eyes. Killed him dead! (Chuckles)
         
         DG:  And there was a woman back there that they thought was a witch. Old
         Liz Deever—
         
         EG:  Liz Deever, yeah, they always said she was a witch. Jim Deever's her
         husband. Her husband was a wizard, too. And there was one young feller
         wanted him to teach him how to be a wizard. Yeah, he teach him, but
         he says, "The first thing you go to be a wizard, you've gotta sell your
         self to the devil." Well, he didn't want to do that. So, Doc Young, he
         believed that Jim was a witch, or a wizard, and my dad and Old Jim Deevers
         they used to get together and make up stories to tell Young. My
         dad; they fixed it up, they told Old Doc Young that he was to go up Tot
         son's Branch, a creek, a little creek they had back there called Totson's
         Branch, he'd go up Totson's Branch and many a time with a gun and never
         see a thing to shoot at. Well, he thought Old Jim had bewitched him,
         that was the reason of it. Well, anybody that goes out ahuntin', you
         may go for a month and not see a thing.
         
         EG:  acomin' this way, and in a certain place would turn right back and
         go the other way. Well, it did. But that was the end of the ridge. It
         come down one side- the ridge was here, went right back up the other
         side of the ridge. It didn't keep agoin' straight. Then John he went
         out and shot a fox, shot at one, and Jim Deevers took crank colic
         that same day. And he'd shot at that fox with a silver bullet, he thought
         "I almost killed Old Jim." (Chuckles) He thought Old Jim was the fox,
         you know, and he thought he'd hit him and caused him to have that belly
         ache! (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Well, why did they think she was a witch? This was his wife?
         
         EG:  Yeah, she was his wife. Oh, I don't know.
         
         DG:  I guess a lot of things she told kind of half way happened or
         and then they'd be scared to death.
         
         SS:  They'd be scared to death by what she said?
         
         DG:  Yeah. Well, I can remember as a kid, and then even after we come out
         here where the Virginia folks was, that Liz Deevers, Liz Deevers, all
         Liz Deevers- and they always called her the witch. As for ghosts, I
         don't remember hearing talk so much about ghosts.
         
         EG:  My brother skeered some people one time with that ghost stuff. He
         sneaked up on top of their house, and took a rope and tied it around
         a brick and knocked it down their chimney, you know, and had it a bump
         ing and a scrapin' around in there, and they was scared and they all run
         outdoors, and theyxoutside before he got his rope out, he didn't get his
         rope off and get off of there, but they got out before he got offa the
         house!
         
         SS:  It's funny, I've never heard of a wizard before. I mean I've heard
         the word wizard; I've heard a lot about witches, but I didn't know that
         they had husbands that were wizards.
         
         DG:  Well, what I think; the witch and the wizard that would be the husband
         and the wife, huh?
         
         EG:  Well, they don't have to be a wife, but then he's a man witch.
         
         DG:  A wizard was a man witch.
         
         SS:  Do you think he thought he was? Or do you think he never thought he was?
         
         EG:  I don't think so. I don't know. They just got that— Well, you know
         they used to burn people— the English used to burn people; witches.
         That there, what was her name? That great general that led the French?
         
         SS:  Joan of Arc?
         
         EG:  Joan of Arc. You know they burnt her for a witch. And then over in
         the Colonies, I think they burnt some witches there. Now, that's some
         thing the Indians - they wftfe, terrible people, they burnt people at the
         stake; but there was our white men that burnt witches. Take somebody
         they didn't like and thought had done queer things and they'd burn 'em.
         They was just as bad as the Indians.
         
         DG:  Have you ever heard anything about these Devil-worshippers? There was a
         scare in here a while about them.
         
         SS:  Is this recent? Recently?
         
         DG:  Oh, a year or two ago.
         
         EG:  They got abutcherin' cattle, and taking some of the insides out of 'em.
         
         DG:  Well, wasn't it up toward Winchester or someplace they got something
         strung up across the road and Nto stop a car? Anyway, I know that
         there was scare enough about it that there was a lot of people said
         that Doug Johns, he got real disturbed about 'em, you know. And
         he told his mother, said, "If you're ever going like to Lewiston or
         drivin' somewhere and you see a bunch crossin' the road holdin' hands,
         you know, they just come up over a bank or just walk across the road
         and hold hands and just stand there for the car to come, why," he said,
         "just Pour on the gas and go right on." Said, "If you hit one, it's
         alright, you're still able to go. Then they'll leave. If you kill
         one of 'em, then they say, they'll skin that one out; person out, and
         they'll go on. But otherwise they might take you, you know, if they
         get you stopped or anything, because it's asacrifice or something that
         they do." They said if you kill one of their own, you know, just that
         way, then they'll go on some other place. Ayear or two ago there was
         quite abit said about it, and there was supposed to have been— it was
         up near Coeur d'Alene,^think it was, that Virgil told me that was sup
         posed to really been some of 'em there.
         
         I've heard that. Coeur d'Alene was a place where that was going on.
         And then we heard once that there was toward Winchester^one time.
         
         SS:  I was going to ask. you; were there things like signs for getting married
         Why you would know who you might marry? I've heard that sort of thing.
         
         DG:  in the house, why that meant somebody was going to die, if it flut
         tered in your window.
         
         EG:  Oh, yea h, that was a woman- a girl I had up there at Tekean that was
         superstitious. I had her come and work for me a few days, and a dog a
         howlin1 was a sign of bad luck or death or something thataway. And if
         a bird come and fluttered in your window. Well, I had an apple tree
         
         G: Bring a hoe in the house
         
         SS:  Bring a hoe in the house?
         
         DG:  Yeah, that's bad luck.
         
         EG:  Bad luck to bring a hoe in the house.
         
         SS:  You had an apple tree?
         Had an apple tree set out there a ways and a bluebird would get in
         that apple tree and it could see its reflection in the window, and boy,
         it would come right up there and it would just have a great time then
         there in that window til it would get tired and go back to the tree a
         while. Sit there a while and see that reflection again and it would
         come back. Why, that was a sign of death. She told my wife that stuff
         and if I'd a knowed she had them foolish ideas in the head I sure wouldn't
         a had her on the place. But they was superstitious.
         
         SS:  Where did she come from?
         
         EG:  They was Norwegians.
         
         DB: And they happened to live up there, and they was a fine family. She was
         a lovely girl. An awfully nice person but very superstitious. She had
         a crippled sister, something happened and the sister was crippled, I
         can't remember now just what-
         
         EG:  She jumped off— they turned the wagon over and the old man he was Nor
         wegian, he talked awful broken, too. He was a preacher. I don't know
         how he ever got anybody to understand him when he preached.. This girl's
         name was Ruth and he called her Rute. Said he turned the wagon over and
         he says, "I yumped and Rute yumped, but Rute didn't jump far enough."
         She got hurt bad when he turned the wagon over.
         
         DG:  I can't remember what they thought all this happened, but they had some
         superstition.
         
         Did they?
         
         Yeah, about why it happened. And so, Lillian— wasn't that her name?
         
         Yeah.
         
         Why, she would tell me about that, you know, that that was the cause, of Ruth,
         I can't just remember what, some superstition. And when that bird come
         why, she'd say— oh, she didn't like it. 'Course he'd be out
         working, he couldn't stay in the house all time, and the kids was little
         and there I was, sick. And so, of course I figured that my folks down
         here had smallpox pretty bad at the time, and every time after she'd get
         through with all her worries and our telephone would ring, why, I was scared for anybody
         to answer it,
         I figured it'd be some of my folks was gone or else I was gonna die or
         something because they had me in bed with a icepack on my heart there
         for three weeks. And I don't know whether it was necessary or not, and
         then the dog howlin'. They took me to the hospital, I wasn't doin' very
         good, and so the doctor decided they should take me to the hospital.
         They took me in the night, then the doctor up there. And we went by
         his brother's and left the oldest youngster, she was about three and
         we had the baby with us, Peggy, the second^ And when
         we was gettin' ready to leave why, of course everybody started out and
         the dog followed us a ways just ahowlin' and a howlin', and oh, I was
         scared, I thought, well, that's the last time I'd ever see that place.
         But now then I could see how silly it was, he was just upset because
         everybody was agoin' and he couldn't go along. And I don't suppose I'd
         believe in anything anymore if it was true, but there while I was sick
         and kind of upset anyway, you know, so many things kinda happenin', why
         I can almost be superstitious.
         
         EG:  She got down to weighing a hundred and fifteen pounds.
         
         DG:  And I^weigh a hundred and eighty now. But a hundred and fifteen was
         pretty thin.
         
         So you two didn't really put much stock in superstitions, yourselves?
         
         No.
         
         Did you court for very long before you got married?
         
         Huh?
         
         Did you court very l#ng before you got married?
         
         (Chuckles) I guess you'd call it that way. She was just-
         I was a kid and he was- (Chuckles)
         
         Well, I was twenty years old and I bought me a top buggy, and my cousin
         was agoin' to go away, she was fourteen and so was she, and so she went
         up there to my cousin's, and my cousin told me she wanted me to take her
         buggy ridin' before she went away, and she was goin' in just two or three
         days. So Sunday my brother's wife was down there and I had to take the
         top rig up to take the whole family up to Sunday School, and comin' back
         then, why, Ihad to get around to give my cousin a buggy ride, so my Cou
         sin Joe and his sister and Dixie, they come down in their rig to our place
         and I unhooked from the hack and hooked onto the buggy and the four of
         us come on down, brought her down home. And my cousin he was a- stutter
         ed and he says, "You-u-u adarn fool if you don't take Dixie up to Sun
         day School next Sunday." Well, Iwas twenty years old, a big bashful
         guy and then her a little kid- just practically a kid that way-
         He's seven years older than I am.
         Isaid, "Well, I've got my consent," Isays, "how is it with you?" 'oh,
         it'd be alright So the next Sunday Icome and got her; took her up—
         they had a picnic that Sunday and the next Sunday I took her and then I
         left the country, up in the hills for quite a while. And then somehow
         or other, why, something come up and we went together a few times again.
         He had another girl for a while.
         Kept fofclin' around that way, and I don't know, things just seemed to
         happen. Igot acquainted with aschool marm that Iwas gonna have abig
         time with that winter and I got all crippled up, and I couldn't do that.
         So, as fur as Icould get, when Igot too tired of stayin' home, was to
         walk amile over to Wilson's where she was* And everything just throwed
         us together that way til—
         
         SS:  How did you get crippled up?
         
         EG:  Turned a wagon over.
         
         DG:  Little poles on it, threThim and-
         
         EG:  Me and my cousin was comin' down the hill with a load of poles to build
         a corral on the place down there in Catholic Gulch, and we come on the
         top of a little grade up here between here and Kendrick, there was a
         fella met us there with a car: four horse team; and he had to back up to
         get out of the way and every time he'd try to back up he'd kill the aigine.
         That was better'n sixty years ago, you know. And finally, after
         about ten minutes there in the lights of that car, I took my lead team
         off and pulled him out of the way and then put 'em back on and we come
         down the grade, got just pretty near the foot of the grade and we
         went over the grade and just turned the wagon upsidedown. Caught my
         cousin under it, and I might have been knocked out for a while, I don't
         know, but when Icome to Iwas clear minded, so Iwent alookin' for my
         cousin and I found him under that load of poles. They was a big rock
         there, and he was squeezed til he couldn't holler, but there wasn't a
         bone broke in him.
         
         DG:  That rock held the load.
         Held the load up, you know, so it didn't break a bone in him. Didn't
         we hurt him any. Well, he was numb when^ got him out of there, so Igot
         on-my wheel team was layin' down, they was throwed out of the road and
         layin' down and the leaders was up in the road. Iwent up and got on
         one of 'em, and started out with the other and so I took the lines off
         and unhooked the one I was on and just turned the other'n loose in the
         road with the eveners, and went down the road ahollerin* for help. And
         there was a fella over there across the river where they've got that
         farm now; he answered me and I told him, so he phoned around and in a
         little while there was five men there to help. Well that load of poles
         was tightened with a springpole up over a pole, you know, right
         across there and ends with that pole and that there long pole had two
         them on there, and that was turned up and them was under the bottom
         
         EG: so you know them chains was tight. No way agettin' 'em loose. I had
         a knife with a plier on it but my thumb here was numb, I couldn't use it,
         and I give it to somebody else but they couldn't use it to cut a wire
         link that was in there, but the other chain was good. So finally I said,
         "Is there anybody around here got an axe?" I, with a tight chain
         you could chop it with an axe, and that was the only— Another fella
         says, "Old Man Leland's got an axe." The other one says, "I'll go get
         it." And he went up on the road and walked around three head of horses
         and walked down there three quarters of a mile— about three quarters
         down and back to Leland's- went afoot and got the axe. Another fella
         come and brought my other horse back, and one fella said that he seen
         him go by, that'd he steer the folks if he went on home when he passed
         him. " Another one come though and brought him back up. I says, "He's eleven miles
         from home." "Well," he says, "he'll be there pretty soon if he keeps
         going they way he passed me." He brought the horse back, and they got
         up there-
         
         DG:  And his Uncle Joe lived-
         
         EG:  And they got up there with that axe and just one lick apiece and them
         chains just flew. And so then, they got the doctor, he come up in his
         car and brought us down here to this place over here; my uncle was there.
         We stayed over night. Well, the fella rode down hill and my cousin up,
         comin' down here and we got down here, why he says, "I can walk." And
         me and this guy looked at each other, you know and grinned, and he just
         hopped out of the car and into the house he went. Well, I started to get
         out and I'd been^oin' up there and around just doin' as much as anybody,
         and perfectly clear of mind; I told 'em to get the axe to chop the chains,
         and practically everything that was done, I told 'em what to do. I was
         perfectly clear of mind, but I rode in that car down from up there to
         here, and when I started to get out of that car, and if somebody'd split
         me from my shoulder blade to the hip bone with an old dull knife, it
         wouldn't a hurt a bit worse. Then a fella he come and tried to help me,
         boy, that was worse yet. There was no way for me to get outta there
         only wiggle out on my own. I got out; got up to the house. Two weeks
         that I couldn't pick up a toothpick with this hand here. There wasn't
         nothin broke but ligaments just all busted up.
         
         SS:  Was it all in your hand and your arm?
         
         EG:  My hand here was thataway and then my back. I lost three months of that
         winter there.
         
         DG:  It throwed him out in a bunch of rocks. He sftt on a highchair when
         he could kinda walk, but he couldn't set and get up. And when he'd come
         to visit me, why, if there was the highest chair of the kids' highchair
         there, why, that's what he'd sit on. You know, he could just bend. But
         he was crippled up for quite a—
         
         You were really young at that point when you were going together.
         Yeah, you know, it seemed like an awful difference— don't seem bad now
         but when we were in school— see, when I was eight, why, he was fifteen.
         And there were some fifteen, sixteen year old girls and he was having
         a big time with them, you know, and here I was a little towhead with braids
         running around there.
         
         A lot of funny things like that happens and a fella don't know why, but
         they fall for them little girls.
         
         DG:  Then one time it was rainy and couldn't be outside, and the big kids,
         of course would get together and get 'em some books or be talkin' or
         something and the little kids would hang around, and they had a book of
         riddles and rhymes and they was agigglin' and areadin' and there was another
         grown boy or two and two or three girls and so on, and they was a
         readin', and I was pretty timid then, I didn't do much talkin' and
         kinda bashful, and I was standin' listenin' at 'em, and they read over
         "Needles and pins, needles and pins, when a man marries his troubles
         begins." And he's laughed about that so much, you know, and I didn't
         even remember it.
         
         EG:  Well, Bill Kinzer picked at the kids a lot more than what I did, the
         little kids there. And she come over there and she said, "You should
         never, get married, Edl, I told him,
         
         DG:  Said I just looked at him and "You should never get married!" k I guess
         I just wanted him to wait and that seems funny when you think about it.
         
         SS:  Wait a minute, you played needles and pins? How did that work?
         
         EG:  Little verse, see, that we had in the book, "Needles and pins, needles
         and pins-"
         
         SS:  How did you figure it meant you?
         
         EG:  Well, that was her, and she told me, "You'd better never get married, ED."
         
         DG:  Just a bunch of littlefkids hanging around there, and I was always back
         ward and never talked up much, and that's what they all noticed, but
         hwen they read that, said I just looked up, "Better never get married,
         Ed!" (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Did you feel that you were— now how old were you when you got married?
         
         DG:  I was almost seventeen! (Laughter)
         
         SS:  You were almost seventeen?
         
         DG:  (Laughter) I was married the 24th of December, and I was seventeen the 25th of
         February. So I married young.
         
         SS:  Did you feel at all at the time that you were really young to get married?
         Or did you feel like you were ready for it? Marriage?
         
         DG:  Well, I don't know, I suppose I was young. I think that if I could start
         out all over again, I'd marry the same guy. But at the same time, why,
         I might want to be a little bit older. Maybe I could have managed a
         little better or something, I don't know.
         
         EG:  Well, she was the oldest one of the family and she got to going out,
         you know to parties and around like that, and her stepdad he didn't
         think she should go so much. And him and her mother got to havin' quite
         a little trouble over her.
         
         SS:  Your mother stuck up for you?
         
         DG:  Mom always did, yeah. My stepdad, it was kinda funny- they never had
         told any reason to distrust me, I'd always git home when they me and anything,
         but let a bunch come in, young kids, and he'd set and tell about all the
         times he went to the parties, and how they had a bottle of whiskey and
         they'd get some old maids drunk and all these things, you know, and all
         the big times and then if I went out with the neighbors to a party in
         the neighborhood, why, then it was all wrong. But I was always pretty
         good. Mom always played ball with me, you know, andk I'd listen and
         she'd let me go, but I'd have to be home at least by twelve, or ten or
         eleven. I don't know there might been a time or two I didn't get to go,
         but most of the time I'd go. But a lot of the time, why,— I had a
         very good friend and she had an uncle that was quite a lot older than
         any of us, and he played the banjo. He'd take his banjo and go and play.
         And we'd just go around the neighborhood to the different houses, you
         know, and so he would come with Harriet and they'd get me a lot of times
         you know so I could go.
         
         SS:  Would it be dances? Is that what it would be?
         
         DG:  Well, once in a while some of 'em would two-step or waltz a little bit,
         and they'd have- what you call 'em? Where they call 'em. Square dances,.
         
         EG:  Quadrille? Square dance.
         
         DG:  They'd square dance some. And a lot of times just games or taffy pull.
         They make taffy. We had a lot of fun at taffy pulls. Pretty near every
         party they had a taffy pull.
         
         SS:  What kind of games?
         
         DG:  Oh they'd have -, you know and if you didn't answer why-
         
         EG:  Spin-the-Platter, and I don't know.
         
         DG:  you know. Playing Post Office and all them kissin' games.
         
         EG:  They was one family come in there one time, that they had a lot of fun
         the winter that they run the parties there. They had the most kissin'
         games. People don't think nothin' about it, but some girls- we went one
         to have one place. some of the girls wouldn't go and it made this fella mad.
         He said, "If they was out in the dark, they'd kiss." But just to play a
         game, they wouldn't do nothin' like that. They had some funny games;
         one of 'em was kiss both sides of the watch. Take a man's watch, you
         know, the chain, put a girl and a boy up there and they'd have to kiss
         both sides of that watch. Hang it right down over their mouths, and
         they was supposed to kiss both sides of that watch. Well just as they
         went to kiss the watch, why, (Chuckles) you'd jerk the watch up, you
         know, out of the way. And then they'd make a Dutch wagonwheel. That
         was quite a thing. Two would take a handkerchief, hold each end this
         way and then two more across it this way, and they'd get everybody in
         the crowd up there with a handkerchief across that there-
         
         DG:  They usually had men's handkerchiefs, big handkerchiefs, and they'd take
         'em—
         
         EG:  Then the top one, the top handkerchief, they had to go under there and
         cross- change places, and they was supposed to kiss as they passed under
         there, and then they had to come back over there. Well, if they went
         over on this side of the handkerchief, thisaway, if they come back on
         that side they was alright, but if they happend to come back, you know
         on this side, they twisted the handkerchief, then they had to go back agin
         and every time they twisted the handkerchief, they was supposed to kiss as
         they went under there. And then, of course, when they got the handker
         chief straight, why, then them two was done and the next two come down
         and tried their luck that way.(Both Dixie and Ed were talking, and Dixie's
         voice was largely lost)
         
         DG:  Then they'd look at the stars, sometimes, that was to redeem something
         that you had—
         
         Oh, yeah, they had things to redeem, and some would look at the stars-
         And'hold it up and you'd look through that and somebody'd pour water down
         
         DG: it, you know, into your face
         
         EG: Sometimes they'd have to bring somebody a bucket of water to play— a
         drink of water to pay for . One time I was at a party and I had
         to bring a young lady a drink of water to pay for a forfeit. I went
         and brought the bucket, and she drank out of it. When I held it up for
         her to drink, she says, "Don't pour this." I says, "I won't." I wouldn't
         a poured it on her, but she was afraid I would. I give her a drink out
         of the bucket.
         
         Used to have quite a lot of fun. And then back to the gettin' married;
         of course, like most everybody seventeen, sixteen, you think you're
         pretty smart anyway, well, I thought it was alright. But, there was a
         lot of things that if I'd been a little older, I could have did better.
         But then, there was a lot of things that I already had did, you know,
         with the housework and the experience with children and the washing and
         cookin' and a lot of things, why I was just learning, you know to
         manage on what we had to do with and so on. And we got along pretty good.
         
         SS:  You probably didn't mind getting out of the house where you'd been brought
         up?
         
         No. There was quite a bit of contention, as I began to grow up. My step
         dad in his own way, in some ways was quite good to me, but it seems like
         as I grew older, he had a lot of dreams or ideas that he would like for
         me to gone on to school. And then he began to get the idea, I think the
         part of it would be^that sooner or later I was gonna be gone, and he was
         going to miss me at home. And he beg^n to find pretty much fault with
         any boyfriends that I had. And, of course, that didn't help mat
         ters any. The first one that I had, that I went with, why, they didn't
         care much about him, but he treated me fine what little time I went with
         him, and my stepdad was gonna just put a stop to that right now, and Mom
         said, "Just leave her alone, I think she'll find it out for herself We'll
         get further by just lettin' her alone." Well, it wasn't too long til I
         didn't want anything more to do with him.
         What did he think of Ed at first?
         Well, Ed used to stay with him and bafch with him.
         Oh, he was just like a brother.
         Real pally until after Ed and I began to pay a lot of attention to each
         other-
         
         Well, I had a good buggy and team and when we went someplace, of course,
         that was the way she got to go, was because I had a team. Well the Ostells,
         they lived across the Potlatch, but they had a hack, and they
         couldn't get out with a team, but I could cake *buggy and go up to Arrow
         there and they'd bring the hack- bring it across the railroad bridge,
         pull it across by hand and hook my team onto it and we'd go anywhere we
         wanted to. One night Iwent up there with the buggy rain men
         come and eat there at Arrow at the store and Ihappened to stop my buggy
         right in their trail where they come from the train to go over there, so
         when I come back my buggy was turned over, laying down on the side. I
         didn t see why anybody d done that. I thought Old Chris maybe or some
         of 'em had done that and I asked him about it. "No," he says, "the train
         men done it," he says, "you left it in their trail that they come down—
         the way they come down to the store.and they just turned it over when
         they come it." So that was the reason it was turned over. We went
         from there on up to Deary in Ostell's hack and back that fur, and then
         took the buggy. But that's what made the old man mad was because I had
         the conveyance, you know, and she couldn't awent a lot of times if it
         hadn't abeen for the conveyances I furnished.
         
         SS:  And he didn't want her to go.
         
         EG:  He didn't want her to go. And then one big mistake I made there about
         him— They had a dance up at a place up the canyon there, there was no
         body living at the place at that time and a fella had it rented, and it
         was a pretty good house, but it was up there, and so ~ Jamison, he
         come home from school and told me about it, and wanted to go. I says,
         "I haven't got no girl," and didn't know nothin' about it in time to ask
         Dixie to go with me, so I said, "I don't think I'll go." Then I said,
         'I'll have some fun there watching the girls pull their rubbers off going
         up in that mud." But that night it wasn't muddy up there. But Gilbert
         and I started out together. He was going to get the Ostell girl, pick
         her up at Arrow, and as we went by why, Jim Ostell he'd come over there
         and got Delia Jamison in the canyon there and they was going up. I hadn't
         aimed to stop at Wilsons because I had no date. "Well," they said, "You'd
         better go up and ask Dixie to go." "Guess it won't do no harm to ask her.'
         Well, when I got up there, why, |arry Ervin and Harriet was there at
         Wilsons, that was the girl that Gilbert was going to meet, she was
         there at Wilsons and Dixie was all ready to go. So I hadn't asked her;
         she'd a went if I hadn't a  But the old man didn't know that
         I didn't have a date, so he told my brother, my preacher brother, about
         me atakin' her to aoldj house for adance, when Ididn't have any
         idea she was going, and I didn't have anything to do with the girls til
         me and Harry went together and we started up the hill. And then the
         girls, they got to teasing about what the school marm had said about me;
         If I'd just knew what she'd said. Then they wouldn't tell me. I don't
         think she'd said anything, they was making up something.
         
         DG:  Oh, she might of. Holly used to say quite a bit.
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         DG:  Holly used to say quite a bit.
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know whether you'd heard anything or whether you hadn't,
         or anything. But, anyway, you wouldn't tell me and there was a steep
         grade along there, and I told 'em, "If you don't tell me, I'll shove
         you over the grade!" And I'd grab the two of 'em and take 'em over the
         edge of the road and from there on up, why- went on up with the girls. I
         I didn't know she was to be home by ten o'clock.
         
         DG:  No, it's twelve.
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         DG:  I was to be home £v twelve.
         
         EG:  Oh, well, whatever it was, I didn't know anything about it, till Harry
         come around and got Harriet. He says, "You know, Dixie's supposed to be
         at a certain time."
         
         DG: Well, I asked Harriet to go because, them days and everything, pretty
         particular what people thought about your reputation, and I knew that if
         I was gonna get to go again, and if Mom told me to be home by twelve, I
         better be home by twelve. Well, there was married couples there, you know
         so, a lot of 'em was havin' a good time yet and I had to leave by eleven
         thirty to be home by twelve. And so, nobody said anything about break
         ing up or going and I knew I had to go. I wasn't much going to go by
         it myself or anything, and so I went and asked Harr I said, "I don't like
         to do this, but," I said, "I don't want to go alone." He said, "Well,
         go ask Ed." I said, "Well, the folks would have a fit if they kn^w^if
         the dance or the party was still going and Ed and I took off by oursel
         ves."
         
         EG:  Well, the first thing I knowed about it was Harriet said that-
         
         DG:  So, I asked her if she would mind coming and she was kind enough and good
         enough that her and her uncle come with Ed and I. And so, when I got
         home, why, my dad didn't happen to hear me come in, I went in very quiet
         ly. And so, he happened to wake up and he said something to Mom about
         Dixie hadn't got home and Mom said, "Well, she's here. She's been here
         in bed quite a while." And he lit the lamp and come to look to see if
         I was there, and I was. Not braggin' on myself or anything like that,
         but then, I always tried to get home and io, especially, what Mom told
         me to.
         
         SS:  Did he give you a hard time about that later?
         
         DG:  No, no, he didn't say anything. He proved to himself, of course, that
         I come home and gone to bed. And she told me I could go, you know
         and everything. It wasn't just every time that he'd have a spell about
         it, but^now and then that he would get real disturbed about my going and
         I think that the older I got— as I grew older and looked back on it, I
         think that the idea was that he hated the idea when I did leave. And
         then when he found out I was going to get married; well I had kinda of
         threatenedK somewhere and try to work. I didn't really
         want to stay at home. And he was going to see that I didn't get married
         til I was eighteen. But he had never adopted me and so, therefore, he
         didn't have any legal right as to what Idid or didn't do. And so ,he
         couldn't do much about It. And it wasn't that he disliked Ed-
         I've seen alot of young fellers in my time, you know, they wasn't so
         young, but, they was kinda rounders in their day. And when their famil
         ies growed up, especially their daughters, they was always suspicious of
         'em and awful particular. And that's the way it went. Like te was tel
         ling about getting the old maids drunk and getting out and having quite
         a time when he was young and all that, well, when his stepdaughter growed
         she was just as wild as the women he used to chase, and he
         didn't want that.
         
         Did you look up to Ed alot? He was so much older than you- six, seven
         years. Did you find yourself looking up to him like he was abig brother
         or something like that?
         
         I don't really know or think so much about it, Ijust began to like him
         real well. I had plenty of (both are talking at the same time)
         but I didn't have any trouble, as far as that a havin' boy
         friends. Two or three of his cousins had tried to go with me, Idon't
         know, there was Mil Kimberling and there was guys quite abit older even
         than was older than you, wasn't he?
         
         Oh, yeah. Well, Iused to take her when she was akid that way, because
         I had the outfit.
         
         And Fred Walter. But there were several even older ones that asked me,
         you know, to go with 'em. Well, Iknew that they were enough older, that
         either one of 'em, Iknew the guys and Iliked 'em alright, but I'd say,
         "Oh, gee, Ican't date you because the folks would just never stand for
         it." There was*too much difference in the age that way. But for no older
         than I was and marryin' youn I started out with the boys when I was
         thirteen, and there in about four years, I had lots of chances.
         
         SS:  Was that true for your girl friends as well? Were they going out about
         older
         the same age as you started? Were they going with the boys?
         
         DG:  Well, most of my real close girl friends was— Harriet wasn't too much
         older; a year, maybe.
         
         EG:  Delia was the one that was a couple of years older than you.
         
         DG:  The others wasn't too much, you know; Bert and Mae and them - wasn't
         too much difference in the ages. And the rest of 'em— When he was
         talking about taking us for a buggy ride, why, her and I were both born
         in 1900. She was born the second of February and me the twenty-fifth.
         And she was a fairly good looking girl and quite a sporty girl and she
         just had all kinds of boyfriends.
         
         EG:  There was one time we started up to literary with the buggy I and you
         that I was to take a couple of the Ostells along. So, I give Gilbert
         Jamison a saddle horse to ride up to literary so we wouldn't have so
         many- only four in the buggy. And we got up to Arrow, why they was a
         girl there, she must a weighed a hundred and eighty, there from Montana.
         She used to live here and she come up there, so we got up there, why,
         there she was; three girls and Jim Ostell and myself and Gilbert. There
         was that many of us in the top buggy and the saddle horse. (Chuckles)
         So, me and this big Montana girl we got in the seat and Delia set on her
         lap and Dixie set on mine and Harriet set on their two nees in the
         middle out in front and drove the team. And Jim and Gilbert both rode
         the saddlehorse. We had that buggy full that time! (Chuckles) And
         we got up there, there was one place on the road was cold and the road
         was froze over with ice, slick, too, but I had a sharpshod team, and they
         was some brush down below the road and as we went over that ice there
         them brush raked the side of that rig and I knowed that that was too fur
         down there, and I told the girl, I said, "Pull the upper line." (Chuckles)
         I got scared, but, boy I could just feel my head gratin' on the rocks
         down below there! I knowed when them ' was arakin' that buggy that-
         Well, there must have been ice there that held it up level, because they
         was way down below the road, and rakin' the side of that buggy.
         
         DG:  They had lots of literariesT and one time we walked— what was it? About
         five miles or so, we walked up to literary and back.
         
         EG:  Yeah, I wasn't along that night.
         
         DG:  Well, that's how far it was. Wasn't it?
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Where was it that you had literaries? School?
         
         EG:  Where this concrete schoolhouse is up here. Down here above Johnson's.
         
         DG:  Right down here above Johnson's place.
         
         SS:  Pilot Rock? Pilot Rock. That's where it was. That's where we had most of the
         lit
         eraries. Pilot Rock. We'd have debates. We'd have a lot of fun. And
         one time Iwas on the debate team, and Iforget whojelse it was, and it
         was as to whether concrete or wood would work the best for railroad ties.
         You know, which would be the better. Sometimes there'd be sensible things
         and sometimes just silly things that'd come up. And he had an older bro
         ther, Levi, and he was real good at debating and the things that he got
         in on. And a lot of times they'd have some real good—
         
         Well, they had Dan Harbock and Marion and Levi and Grover was awful good.
         I never was much good.
         
         Sometimes they'd have kinda little programs. Little skits or songs, you
         know.
         
         Sometimes they'd have somebody say speeches, or sometimes sing or some
         thing.
         
         SS:  Would they have party games, too?
         
         EG: Well, I don?.t believe they had so much party games.
         
         DG: 
         
         EG: 
         
         DG: 
         
         SS:  Mock trial?
         
         EG:  Yeah. One time we had—One time we had one up there; they had me arrested for
         beatin' up on a
         fella for stealing my sister-in-law's affection. They brought that fel
         la in there with aarm bandaged up and an eye black, and say, he was a
         badly crippled up fella. I'd beat him up for stealing my sister-inlaw's
         affection. And Ihad to have alawyer and then you had to be
         sworn in. Fred Albright, he was the clerk and he had to swear 'em in.
         And you had to hold up your right hand and solemnly swear that everything
         that you told was alie and nothing but alie, would ease your conscience!
         (Chuckles) That's the way you took the oath.
         
         SS: Would ease your conscience?
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  And then they put on a trial?
         
         Yeah. They'd have to tell, you know- Well, they accused me of beatin'
         this feller up and they had him up there, and Isaid, "No, it wasn't me
         at all. Ihadn't touched Mm." He says,"The Old Man, the Old Man Kim
         berling had beat him up. It wasn't me." (Chuckles) Yes, had quite a
         tlmel^Th" witness, you know, one would say he was there and another
         say he wasn't. Idon't know where Iwas that night, Iwasn't around
         there. Iwasn't supposed to be there, Iwas off somewhere else, as a
         witness, you know, telling Iwasn't around that place at all that night,
         Iwas somewhere else; regular horse thief story, you know.
         
         They had one at Arrow one time- They had one at Arrow; they had my brother arrested
         for stealing afella's
         
         EG: Not much party games. Sometimes they'd have amock trial.
         Plays, or just kind of a funny recitation
         
         DG:  The guy really had hogs any everything, you know. They made a pretty
         good trial out of that, though, it wasn't so much silliness. But it was
         a lot of fun, a lot of things that went on, you know.
         
         SS:  Levi studied law, eh? He was pretty good with the words?
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah.
         
         DG:  And good at writing. He wrote a beautiful hand. He was Al Groseclose's
         father, and Jean Groseclose's dad.
         
         EG:  After the flu scare in 1800 there never has been a literary since organized.
         
         DG:  1800?
         
         EG:  1918.
         
         DG:  1918-1919.
         
         EG:  When that big flue epidemic went through and killed so many people,
         why they stopped all gatherings. Church and everything, you know. They
         never— nobody could have any gathering of any kind for quite a while
         there to stomp out that flu.
         
         SS:  How bad did that hit around where you lived?
         
         EG:  Well, it hit pretty bad. I had it when my second child—
         
         DG:  Don't know too many that really died, but we know of some that come near
         dying.
         
         EG:  When I got it they'd found out what to do. They used to take aspirin to
         keep your fever down and take something to keep your bowels well open.
         
         DG:  And you had to stay absolutely in bed.
         You had to keep yourself cleaned out and keep temperature down. And
         we got to doing that, why they didn't lose many patients after that.
         But doctors didn't know what to do on the start and they lost a lot of
         people. We had a woman got sick across the river down there and the river
         
         EG: was high, and she had the flu and the doctors so busy he couldn't
         get one to come; she was awful sick. So her husband come over and5he
         says, "She can't take oil nor she can't take salts," he says, "I don't
         know what to give her." "Well," Isays, "get her some Syrup of Figs."
         So I went up to Kendrick to the drugstore- believe it was Kendrick I
         went to- Kendrick or Juliaetta anyway. I got her a bottle of Syrup of
         Figs and some aspirin; brought it back and he come across and got it;
         took it over there and she come out of it alright.
         
         SS:  Why did you figure that?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         Why did you figure Syrup of Figs?
         
         Well that was kind of a laxative.
         
         That was a laxative, and it was something good tasting; kids liked to
         take that. It was an awful good laxative. I used to keep it on hands
         all the time.
         
         Did many people at Arrow get the flu? In 1918?
         
         Well, they had it in— quite a few had it and I don't believe there was
         any deaths exactly from the flu, but they had an awful time to get along.
         The families would all get down and one couldn't hardly get up to put a
         stick of wood in the stove or wait on another and somebody else'd just
         have to go and carry the wood in and kinda help out, because it would
         really knock you for a loop, you know.
         
         You talk about flu now, but I had it that time down there, and I kept
         a sack of epsom salts sittin' by the bed, and I'd have such a terrible
         taste in my mouth, I'd reach over in that sack of salt and get in my fin
         ger, like that, you know, hold it in my mouth. Now them things tasted
         good, by the side of that nasty taste in my mouth. Idon't know how many
         times I filled my mouth up with salt 'fore I got so I could get around.
         
         DG:  And a lot of times, you know, they'd have the nosebleed so bad, you
         couldn't hardly stop it, you know, they'd die from that. And we had one
         friend up at Tekean, that he had it so bad they had the doctor up there
         several times, and his nose would bleed, you know til they couldn't hard
         ly stop it. And so the doctor was there one day and told 'em- his name
         was Ed, too won't be here in the morning." Told his wife, you know,
         "You can expect him to go sometime tonight." 'Cause he was so low, you
         know, and they was having trouble with his nosebleeds.
         
         EG:  Somebody during the meantime told 'em to take powdered alum and snuff it
         up your nose.
         
         DG:  Well, when they found out-
         
         EG:  They found about that and they give him some of that; he snuffed that up
         his nose and that stopped the bleeding and he come out of it all right.
         
         DG:  This neighbor or somebody had heard tell of it, you know, and they tried
         it and it did stop the bleeding.
         
         EG:  Well, that was one other thing that come along with the bleeding of the
         nose was-
         
         DG:  The next morning they called the doctor, and of course, he figured they'd
         called him, I guess, something about telling Ed was gone, but they called
         him and told him that he was still there, and he said, "I can't believe
         it." But he come out of it and lived to be what? Eighty-one years old,
         wasn't it?
         
         EG:  Well, he ain't been dead much over a year now, I guess. He was about a
         year older'n me.
         
         DG:  Well, anyway, after they got that bleeding stopped, he was so weak, you
         know, that the doctor. believe it was possible that he would live.
         
         EG:  We have what we call a sort of flu every year or so, I believe, about
         every year, you get sick you got the flu, it's not like that was.
         
         EG: Beside the taste in your mouth, what were the symptoms that you had?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Beside that awful taste in your mouth, what were the symptoms?
         Well, you'd ache witfc that flu. Ache and hurt all over, you know, and
         then you'd have your fever and sometimes chills and then you'd go into
         pneumonia or have all these—
         It's hard to tell what you would do if you hadn't a got right in on the
         start, and you got to holdin' that fever down with aspirin.
         
         SS:  Was this in 1918 that you got it? Or was that later?
         
         EG:  '18. No, it was in '20 that I had it.
         
         SS:  Later.
         
         DG:  He had it in '20, but it was in '18 Kthe epidemic, I think broke out
         and you know it was real bad.
         
         SS:  Did you live at Tekean for very long?
         
         DG:  About ten years.
         
         SS:  Did you finally sell out or what did you do? Why did you leave?
         
         EG:  Well-
         
         DG:  We burned out.
         
         EG:  Burned out, is the reason I left and went down on the river, down to
         And then I didn't no crop that year. Lost the crop up
         there, I didn't get it harvested the year before-
         
         DG:  Bad year. Nobody had much crop.
         
         EG:  Then burnt out.
         
         SS:  How did that happen? The house burned down?
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         DG:  Well, it was a rented house. We had a cabin; lived woods
         and we'd rented this house and moved out to the settlement.
         
         EG:  It was a quarter of a mile to school.
         
         DG:  "He  to school. And then the house didn't have a
         flue in it, it had just stovepipes that went up through, and it was a
         log house, and then there was a kitchen built across the side of it that
         was built on with lumber kinda like a leanto, you know just kinda like
         a shed, and a stovepipe went up through that and there was a. little attic
         up over it. And the people that had owned the house- there was lots of
         mail orders them days, you know, and parcel post- and they had this excel
         sior that's packed around things, and then they had little like these
         eighteen, twenty pound fruit boxes- and up in this little attic over the
         kitchen, they had that place just suffed full of those things. And Ed
         said one time, he said, "I'm going to clean all that out." And I said,
         "Well, you'd better not do it without asking." We were just renting one
         year at a time, you know. I said, "You'd better not without asking Mrs.
         Garrison about it." We'd lived there a year when we burned out. You see
         you'd had one good crop and you had another one in. We were in there two
         winters, see, and out in March the next spring. And the only thing
         that we can figure out— we had had breakfast and I had stacked up the
         dishes and then I got the girls ready to go to school; combing their hair
         and getting them ready, and we had the three children then, and Virgil
         was about three years old—
         
         EG:  Well, they had had the upper part of the attic in tRft top of the house,
         they'd had it full of stuff up there, but I went and took a lot of that
         stuff out .there, but still there were a lot of boxes up there. And this
         one first story of the house was logs and the next one was boards, second
         and they set a two-by-four on top of these logs and then boarded
         it up on three sides with lumber, and then built this lean-to kitchen
         come in thisaway, you know, and fastened onto them two-by-fours. Well,
         I'd heard it said that if you take horse manure and put formaldehyde on
         
         EG: it and roll it in agroundhog hole and stuff the hole shut, it would
         kill groundJiogi!" So Ihad some formaldehyde and an old gunnysack and
         lots of rat holes in the cellar. So, Icut some pieces of gunnysack;
         put formaldehyde on 'em and shoved 'em in them rat holes and stomped
         em shut in the cellar. But Inever had got up over the kitchen to take
         any of that old stuff out of there, and just afew days after that, why,
         we heered a roar-
         
         Well, there was a guy we took in, a crippled guy; the county was gonna
         pay us to take care of him and he- we'd moved his things, they were still
         stored on the front porch, and he and Ed were busy talking about something
         that had happened in the neighborhood, and I'd went in and got the girls
         ready and got 'em off to school and I'd stacked my dishes before Idid
         that, and then Ithought, "Wellness has talked to somebody and heard
         quite abit about it, I'll sit down and listen." 'Cause Ihadn't hap
         pened to hear about it, the two of 'em talkin' and they'd talked to some
         body. So Iwas alistenin', you know, to that. And, all at once I
         thought, "What is that?" I'd hear kind of aroar and the stove in the
         where we were wasn't any unusual fire. So I went in the kitchen
         and raised up the lid on the cookstove and the fire wa spractical
         ly out, you know, there was no big fire, the stove was pretty near cold.
         And, I thought, "Well what?" Then I could hear this roaring above my
         head. I couldn't see it, but all at once I realized, you know, so I
         screamed, you know, "The hous'e is afire!" So, of course, Jess was kinda
         crippled up and he just grabbed his coat and hat and got out of the way,
         and he took Virgil; held onto him to keep him back. Well, Ed went out
         and jumped up on the shed roof, told me to hand him the axe and Ihanded
         him the axe. Well, there was awell there, but it was
         I figured I'd chop a hole through the roof, you know and get water up
         there, but when I got up there I could hear this fire goin' up this
         way- you know, it was just like a stovepipe up there, and I heerd that
         I know there was no chance, I said, "Throw out the jumk, it's gone."
         
         DG:  You told me to get to the telephone and get-
         
         EG:  Call the neighbors.
         
         DG:  But there was a five-gallon can we always kept full of water, and that
         can that five gallon of water was what I could get to and he told me to
         hand him the water. Well, I picked that five-gallon can of water up in
         one hand and held it up higher than my head, like there was nothin' to
         it. He got it and that didn't do much, and he got the axe-
         I never chopped through because I he*rd that fire going up the wall, I 
         
         DG: knew that there was absolutely no chance to get that out. 
         He told me to get the water, so I ran to the telephone, party line,
         everybody rubberin' at you, and everything, and if there was an unusual
         ring, why, people knowed there was something wrong.
         
         EG:  Just one long ring-
         
         DG:  I just went and give a long ring- just a crazy ring, one short ring and
         a long ring and a lot of jingles, and then I began to hear the receivers
         coming down, why, I told who Iwas and the house was on fire. Of course,
         a lot of people could see that lived around in sight, could see— A lot
         of people got there pretty soon and we got quite a few things out of the
         house.
         
         SS:  You got a fair bit out of the house?
         
         EG:  Not very much. We didn't get either stove. We got some bedding out.
         We burnt all our clothes except what we had on. I had a good saddle, I
         burnt that up in there. Ihad^ in there so it wouldn't mold in the
         winter, you know.
         
         DG:  We got the bedding, and the clock, got the clock, and I got my sewing
         machine. Well, we lost things in there. But we lived— we had a won
         derful crop of apples and a cabbage patch and we'd had our meat- our meat
         burned, but lard; we had lard in the cellar and lots of canned fruit in
         the cellar and a big barrel of kraut. And so we lived out of that cellar
         because we didn't have any crop the next year, so we lived for a year
         out of what- and the cellar was just a little ways from the house and it
         was built- you know filled with sawdust and had a shake roof on it. And
         or something they got there
         it caught fire on the roof, but some of 'em took hoes,Ashovels-
         
         EG:  Snow, throwed snow on it.
         
         DG:  Well, they knocked some of the shingles off. And then the schoolhouse
         set up on top of the hill and they could see and they was kids about twelve
         fourteen, fifteen and in there, several boys come and they run in the
         cellar to bring out the fruit and it was in shelves and they'd just make
         a dash in there; just run their hands kinda- work their hands through
         the jars and just grab what they could, and then they'd run out, you know
         and just drop it in the snow. Well, he had a brother that took a sack
         and went in and he was asackin' up a big sackful to bring out, but by
         the time he got»what he could carry in the sack, why the boys, just in
         and out, you know, and dodging around him, had the cellar empty and they
         only broke two or three jars. But they wasn't takin' time, you know,
         for any sackin' and just dodging in and out and they really emptied that
         cellar.
         
         EG:  But the cellar didn't burn.
         
         SS:  Sounds like it still must have been a real setback for you.
         
         DG:  Well, the greatest blow was that— people were awful kind and good, and
         they give us things, you know, give us clothes and some money and then
         some new materials that they happened to have, and I happend to have a
         sewing machine and could sew and we managed. But we got the scarlet
         fever right after that. So, that when we moved we was in quarantine.
         And we had some cows, and then some cows of my uncle's, and so we couldn't
         ship cream because of this scarlet fever. So we fed cream to the— we
         had hogs, didn't we?
         
         EG:  We churned up a lot of butter. We lost about fifty dollars on top of
         everything else with the cream.
         
         DG:  The fifty dollars worth of cream, that's all we'd a had to live on, you
         know. And I had these stone crocks, and my uncles could use the butter,
         too, but I would churn and work it down and press it dam in these crocks
         and then when I'd get a crock full, why, I'd put a layer of salt about
         like that and you'd be surprised— we had a good cellar thereA place
         we moved to, and we'd put that in there and butter- we had butter for a
         long time. But there we were, we didn't have a dime of income and we
         wasn't allowed hardly to leave the place.
         
         EG:  Couldn't leave the place for a long time.
         
         DG:  Well, when the kids-
         
         EG:  We got the seven year itch; and, oh, boy!
         
         DG:  from some clothes was given to us, got the suit that he wore. And we
         really had it really rugged there for a year or two.
         
         SS:  They called that the seven year itch? Is that what it's called? Or is
         it just called the itch?
         
         DG:  It's so hard to get rid of, that they used to call it that.
         
         EG:  I believe they called it the septicemia, the man that give me the clothes.
         
         SS:  Did he know he had it?
         
         EG:  Well, they knowed they'd had it, but didn't realiaze it was in them clo
         thes, I guess. And I wore that suit and I got it and the rest of 'em
         got it from me.
         
         DG:  We really had a time.
         
         EG:  I was up there and couldn't get away and my nephew lived below, he come
         up to see and I talked to him and asked me what he could do for me. I
         Said, "Dell, for God's sake," I says, "send me some sulfur!" (Chuckles)
         So he got me a big batch of sulfur and sent it up to me.
         
         SS:  Did that do it?
         
         EG:  Cleaned it up with that.
         
         DG:  Then, with our scarlet fever, though shortly after we burned out, why,
         the kids got sick and, well, the girls wasn't so awful sick and they
         didn't break out much. Well, the minute that they broke out, why, we
         called up the health officer, Dr. Farley at Orofino; we called him up
         and told him we had something and we didn't know what. We were staying
         at my uncle's and they had a family of children in school, too. 
         they ought to come up and see about it. "Well," he said, — the
         weather was kind of bad and everything- he said, "I don't like to make
         a trip on the hill right now. I can't come for a few days. Just keep
         'em home." You know, and everything. Well, that made us all kind of
         sore and so Mrs. Chilt the lady at the switchboard, and all, and
         Dr. Horseful was coming to Cavendish; there was a child that was awfully
         sick there and he was coming to Cavendish just about every day, which
         was four or five miles away, but it was on top of the hill, you know,
         and so she told Dr. Farley why don't you authorize Dr. Horseful to come
         over and check 'em? Well, he wouldn't do that. So, then we waited and
         he'd tell us— and so finally I called and told him that we were the one
         that rented this place down the canyon and it was time to get down there
         for spring work and that we were going to go. And, well, he'd be up,
         he'd try to be up thet^ you know in two or three days. Well by that time
         the girls was pretty good, but Virgil, he wasn't so sick, but he did
         break out, he just broke out thick, and the rash was showing on him quite
         a lot. And so, when we moved down, of course, we had some cows and
         things that we'd gathered up, you know, andAhousehold stuff people d
         give us and so on, and my uncle took his cows down there and kind of
         went in with Ed rentin' the place. And so, he had taken the cattle and
         his oldest boy had went along—And, was Peggy with us or was and
         Peggy both on the wagon?
         
         EG:  They was both on the wagon.
         
         DG:  The girls was on the wagon, I guess with my uncle and some of the stuff
         had gone. And I had the hack— did you have a wagon, too?
         
         EG:  I had a wagon.
         
         DG:  And we were kinda comin' together, but I was adrivin' a hack, you know,
         a bunch of stuff on it. And I had Virgil all bundled up and everything.
         And we had to go from where my uncle lived down a lane- what? about a
         half a mile, wasn't it?
         
         EG:  Yeah, about a half a mile. 
         
         DG:  Down to hit the road; main road, to take off down to Agatha.A And, who
         did we meet, you know before we got out to the main road, here come Dr.
         Farley, and, of course, he stopped in the road, and he stopped and asked
         where we was goin', and I told him, "We told you we had to move." He
         says, "If you got anything contagious, you can't do that." And so, he
         asked questions, and I unbuttoned Virgil's coat- shirt- you know he
         in this wind and everything could see his chest, and he said, "Oh, my goodness, get
         him bundled up,
         get him bundled up. You can't go anywhere, you've got scarlet fever, and
         I can stop you. You can't go into another county and all with scarlet
         fever." And, I said, "Well, now, Dr. Farley, we've tried to get you to
         come up here or authorize another doctor, and you didn't do any of it.
         Now, part of our children are already gone down on down^the grade with
         my uncle." And, I says, "No doubt, legally, you might be able to stop us,
         if we got a contagious disease, but," I says, "I want to tell you some
         thing; we've been on the mercy of the people since we burned out here
         long enough. With my uncle keepin' us, and he isn't able to do that.
         Maybe you can stop us, but I want you to know one thing; whenever you
         stop us, you've got the full responsibility of us. You're gonna see that
         the county, or yourself or somebody takes care of us, because we tried
         every way to do what's right." And, I said, "You know it, and the people
         all on the hill know it, and they've tried, too, there's been other peo
         ple talk to you. Now, I don't say that you can't stop us, because maybe
         you can. But when you do, that's just fine, when you do, we're at your
         mercy. You're gonna take care of us, see that we're took care of."
         
         EG:  She s the one that done the talkin'. When he told me, I just laughed at
         him. Just laughed. Well, you could take it serious or you could laugh,
         because there you was right out in the road, and how's he gonna stop you
         when you was sittin' in the middle of the road? Well, then she tuckered
         up and^ doin' the talkin', and I didn't say nothin'.
         
         DG:  Afterward he told somebody that she'd a should never married Ed Groseclose,
         she should a been a lawyer!
         
         SS:  What did he do?
         
         DG:  Well, after I talked to him, you know, well, he said, "That woman shoulda
         never married Ed Groseclose—"
         
         SS:  No, I mean, what did he tell you to do?
         
         He said, "Well, here, I'll give you a quarantine card. And you go straight
         to the place where you're movin' and you put this card up and you call
         Dr. Lyle," - was the health officetat Nez Perce, "you call Dr. Lyle and
         report your case to him." And then, he'd take charge because we'd be in
         another county. So we did. We come on; put the sign up and called Dr.
         Lyle to come up and check us. And he asked about the questions and I
         
         DG: told him that we had this up, but that he figured that we had scarlet
         fever and I told him how long we'd been in; tha the girls was over it,
         but that Virgil stilly was having it. And he said, "Well, just stay in,
         but, you don't go anywhere, you don't sell any ".' , you don't let your
         kids go to school." So the people at Agatha- there was a fella
         Hoskins had a store- post office was there- and we had a phone.
         
         EG:  Had one put in, we didn't have it when we first moved there.
         
         EG:  Well, we could call up and he would put things out of the store; he
         credited us, you know, and he'd set the mail and stuff out on the porch
         and we could go down and get it and bring it home. We stayed out of
         people's houses, and so on. So, we let everybody know about it. Then,
         called up Lyle and I told him, I said, "I think that we are through
         this. That we would be able to go out." It had been so many weeks.
         "Oh," he said, "you can?.t go out if there is any kind of scalin', if
         there's anything-" Well, Virgil's hands and feet had peeled, you know,
         and they had scaled and I'd watched until that had quit and everybody
         else was all through with it alright. And so, I told him, flI think,
         we're all through," I said, "we can't stay in here much longer. We
         can't sell cream and nothin' to live on. Things is just to where we've
         got to get out." "Well,^you can't get out til I get up there, and I
         don't know when I can get up there." And so on. So, I waited two or
         three days and he didn't come up, so I got on the telephone and I called
         him up and I told him, I said, "If you're not up here," - I think that
         was on a Saturday- Friday night, or Saturday morning- I said, "if you're
         not up here to check us before Monday morning," I said, "I'm tellin' ya,
         Monday we're goin' out." I said, "Ed's got to get out and
         get stuff to put in the crop." And, I said, "We're not stayin' in any
         longer." "Oh, you can't do that." I said, "Well, we're just awaitin'
         til Monday and we're going." So, he didn't show up Saturday. Sunday,
         I thought, "Well, I guess he isn't goin' to come and I'll just go out
         if I get arrested." 
         
         So, Sunday evening, just about dark, we went with
         Ed after the cows, all just walkin' out on the place to get away from
         the house, and they had an old iron in a apricot tree back of the house
         where we lived, guess they'd used to call the men in out of the field
         or something, and we heard somebody apoundin' on that. We could look
         down, you could see there was a man down at the house. So, I thought,
         "Well, maybe that's him." So, I took the kids and went onback to the
         house and Ed was bringin' the cows. So, he talked to us a little bit,
         and he asked, you know, about the scalin', and I told him, well, that he
         had scaled but there wasn't anymore scales that hadn't shown up for a few
         days, and he says, "What about his feet and his hands?" I held out his
         hands. "What about his feet?" I just picked the kid up on my lap and
         just started jerking his shoes off, and he says, "That's alright, you
         don't need to do that." And so he said, "Well, you can go ahead. Fumi
         gate; clean up, and then you can take your sign down and go." I said,
         "Just how do I fumigate? What do you want me to do?" And he said, "Well,
         burn some formaldehyde candles in each room, " Spread
         our clothes out on chairs and things like that, you know, just put those
         formaldehyde candles, And I said, "Where do I get the candles?"
         And he said, "Well, you can buy 'em at the drugstore, buy 'em in Lewiston."
         And, I said, "How do we buy 'em," I says, "we've been in without
         money, and we can't go any place to git 'em. Maybe you'd better just
         get some and send to us." And, I said, "I'll do what you tell
         Well, I give him to understand that him or the county or somebody was
         gonna send the candles or whatever we were to do, well, he didn't^send
         as many- I didn't have to do near as much as he'd first told me to. But
         he did send 'em and I did do the fumigatin'. And years afterwards, why,
         we had a daughter that was born there in Agatha that had the scarlet
         fever and good heaven, they didn't have us to fumigate, we just had to
         wash the bedding and hang it out on the line and hang the clothes out
         in the sun and in the air. And they put her in a room; kept her in the
         room for a couple of weeks or so and they let Johnny- as long as we
         kept him out of the room- they let him go to school. And there was such
         a difference in the way they handledjthing, But we really went through
         it because we burnt out and a dry year and a crop failure.
         
         SS:  Was the crop.failure that year?
         
         DG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  What happened to the crop?
         
         DG:  It was so dry, the people couldn't get— it dried out. Just work up
         cloddy.
         
         EG:  One reason I didn't get some work done I was exposed to that scarlet fe
         ver, and it rained a lot. Well I worked, plowed in the rain a lot of
         times, but when you're exposed to scarlet fever you don't know whether
         to get wet or not; that might a put you under the ground. I lost qaite
         a little time stayin' in the house out of the rain when I'd abeen out a
         plowin' if I hadn't abeen exposed to scarlet fever.
         
         DG:  I don't think I had it.
         But, there wasn't a farmer in the whole country that year that got his
         farmin' done. It rained late and then it turned hot. And three days af
         ter it quit rainin' why the ground was baked hard. Even the tractor men
         give up, they didn't get all their work done.
         Well, that must have left you in terrible shape financially. No money
         at all.
         
         DG:  Now the people didn't know us too well and there wasn't any reason in
         the world for theiTman Hoskins to have carried us, he didn't know whether
         he'd ever get a dime. He just took a chance. I guess he felt sorry for
         us, you know. Of course, we had a few chickens. We had eggs. And, as
         
         DG: I say, we had our canned stuff, you know and° kraut and lard and all
         that, and we had the milk and the butter. It was the flour, you know
         and things like that we had to buy. But he was very good and when we
         got to where we could sell some cream, you know, where we could sell the
         cream, then we began to pay him. And then you finally got to work some
         on the road, didn't you?
         
         Yeah. Boy, at that time, butterfat was eleven cents a pound.
         But you could buy quite a bit, you know, with a cream check.
         'Course, other stuff was down, too, it wasn't like it is now, but think
         about—
         What period of time was this, that this happened? What period of time?
         Was it during the Depression or before?
         This was when— let's see, Bonnie was born there in 1930, wasn't she?
         This was about 1928- '27, some where.
         
         EG:  1928.
         
         DG:  Let's see, Virgil was about four years old when we went down there.
         
         SS:  Why did you go to Agatha?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         Why did you pick Agatha to go to? Agatha?
         
         Well, we just found out there was a place there to rent. A fella, Isabel,
         had a place to rent down there.
         
         And we had some cows, you know, and that would be lower down in the country
         and it wouldn't be as hard a winters, and the pasture. And then my uncle
         had some cows and we just kinda wanted to get down, you know, we had lots
         of snow up there.
         
         SS:  Did you own anything at Tekean? Did you own any land?
         
         Yes, we owned a hundred acres up there. I was aimin' to go down there
         and farm this— there was supposed to be sixty or sixty-five acres there
         and I figured to farm that and then go back on top and farm this other.
         I had a couple of fellows that was aimin' to help me up there; said they'd
         help me if I needed help. But I didn't get done down there and they didn't
         get done up their way, so I never got a thing done up on the other place.
         too
         
         DG:  But our land that we owned up there wasn't much of it clear, you know.
         
         EG:  It wasn't very much—
         
         DG:  And kind of stumps.
         
         SS:  Had you homesteaded that land or bought it? At Tekean.
         
         EG:  Bought it. Yeah.
         
         DG:  We finally let it go for bills that we owed up there.
         I finally let it go for a store Let it go for a store bill and
         the fella that finally got it died and they settled his estate and put it
         up for bids, and my brother bid $401 on this hundred acres and got it.
         And they didn't think much of that land back in there at that time, but
         now, since that Dworshak dam is in there, why, that land's worth $1,000
         in there, an acre. Tain't worth it, but that's what they sell it—
         Think of all these years in between that you've had taxes and starvation.
         Your brother being a preacher— where did he get the idea to become a
         preacher? Do you know?
         
         Oh, he always had that idea from a boy, that he wanted to preach sometime.
         His mother— wasn't there some other ministers in the family?
         
         EG:  Yes, we had an uncle.
         
         DG:  And then his mother was a real religious woman. And he just naturallyhe
         had the desire to be a minister, like somebody a farmer or a dentist
         or a doctor.
         
         SS:  Was he pretty rough on sin as a minister?
         
         EG:  Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:  What kind of—?
         
         DG:  He was a Lutheran. Not one of these— what caliche English Lutheran.
         He wasn't a—
         
         EG:  Well, yes, he was a Lutheran.
         
         DG:  The Lutherans here, why, they will smoke or they will drink some. But
         he absolutely was against all of that. There was none of that, you know.
         And, of course, he's been dead now for several years, but he was in his
         eighties, I think when he passed away. He was a minister for what?—
         fifty years?
         
         EG:  Oh, twenty, twenty-five years. He didn't get started in til he was a-
         
         DG:  He was apreachin' when we got married.
         
         EG:  Yes, but then he was, you see, he was forty years old when he got married.
         He begun preachin' when he was about thirty-eight, I guess.
         
         SS:  Did he preach around here?
         
         EG:  He preached around here a while, and then—
         
         DG:  At Arrow, and then he preached at Pullman and at Moscow and then back in
         Kansas. Was he in Missouri for a little bit? Then he went to
         California.
         
         SS:  Did he ever give you trouble then about the way you lived your life? Did
         he try to tell you—
         
         EG:  Oh, yes. He "to live the right way. There were four in the fam
         ily that did try to be religious and there was four of us that didn't.
         
         DG:  Another brother that tried preachin' some, but he never went to college.
         And he never held a regular charge, you might say. He just kinda filled
         in. And then he's got a nephew that's a Methodist minister.
         
         SS:  This brother did go to college? The one that was a preacher?
         
         DG:  Yeah. The one that was a preacher, yeah. Then this nephew that's a
         minister. Well, then, he is the son of the brother that just preached
         a little, didn't have no regular charge.
         
         EG:  Well he got through; Carrol got through-
         
         DG:  Yeah, I'm talking about Bruce. But this nephew became a minister and
         then he hafl only one boy and his boy became a minister, and then this
         Will, that didn't have the regular charge, his brother, and Carrol Grose
         close up here was his son and Carrol has three sons, and two of those
         sons are ministers.
         
         And my oldest brother's grandson is a preacher, too Dallas.
         
         Oh, yeah. So there's quite a few of 'em, down through. hard luck for fun.
         
         Yeah.
         
         We've had a lot of fun in our time. You figure that's part of livin'?
         A lot of hard luck?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  You figure that hard luck is a big part of living?
         Yeahhh. Well, it's like a preacher said one time; "It's a good thing we
         don't know what we've got ahead, if we did ,nearly all of us would com
         mit suicide."
         
         I was going to ask you one thing about— a little bit of what you're
         thinking about religion is.
         
         Oh, religion! That there— I think a whole lot of religion. I used to
         be a pretty wild young buck. And come to talking about religion and our
         country here; when I was a young fella I didn't care anything about the
         Bible. My folks were religious and the further I could get away from it-
         But Ifinally was converted and Igot to liking- and instead of stayin'
         away from church, Ilike to go. And Ialways do like to be with religious
         people. And in our country here, today, they got around and they talk
         about Communism. over there, oh, what a terrible place it is!
         Well, now under the Czar, they had the most beautiful churches in the
         world, in Roosia, but eighty-three percent of the people couldn't read
         and write and all the property in Roosia belonged to the Czar and his
         nineteen and eighteen
         family. And when they went to war in he had bought his cannons
         and his ammunition, all that stuff from Germany, and when they went to
         war, why, the ammunition he had for the cannons wouldn't fit 'em, and
         he was fightin' Germany. So the Roosians— Well, this Communist business
         overthrowed 'em. Now then, well- they're the best armed nation in the
         world. We go on to say it, but we just as well admit to the truth, they
         are better armed and they've got more resources. You see the Czar never
         used any Roosian resources.
         
         DG:  The boys down at the mill—
         
         EG:  They've got minerals and they've got everything over there and they've
         got their people educated now. So, we have got out here in our great
         nation here— they have got the Bible not allowed in the schools
         because it teaches religion. Well, the Bible does not teach religion!
         You can read that Bible and you don't know nothing^ you read through it
         and you won't findanything about a Lutheran or a Methodist or Catholic
         or Adventist or anything in there. Still, one of them fellas comes along
         and picks out certain passages of Scripture and shows you what they do,
         their place. Now the Dunkards, for instance, at the Lord's Supper, he
         told 'em; do this, do this in remembrance of Me. Well, every religious
         outfit has a little different way of doing that. But the Dunkards, they
         go and they have a full supper and then after supper they have a basin of
         water there and one of 'em gets up and takes a towel and ties around him
         and washes one of his feet and one of his brother's feet next to him;
         takes the towel off and stands up and kisses his brother; ties the towel
         on him and he sits down and washes one of his feet and washes one of his
         brother's feet; takes the towel off and kiss him and tie it onto him,
         and they go around thataway. Now, that's thetlT way of having the Lord's
         Supper. They eat the supper. But the others they have a little piece
         of wine and a little piece of bread and a little wine and they drink that.
         Now, the Christian Church they have this Sacrament every Sunday. My
         youngest daughter is a Christian. I've been to their church quite a lot
         of times. The others don't have it so often. But they teach them^things
         and then the baptism, baptiso, means to put water on you someway. Well
         some people sprinkle it on you, Catholics supposed to pour it on.
         
         EG:  Up there the old church is still there, but I don't know any of 'em any
         more.
         
         EG:  See, them religions are taught: ftfcat I believe and what you believe qpd,
         what somebody else believes, but you take that Scripture and read it
         right through, like Philip, when the eunuch was areadin' the Scripture,
         the apostle Philip heard him. He went out and he said, "Do you under
         stand what you're reading?" He said, "How can I, unless some man ex
         plains it to me?" So Philip got in the rig with him and explained the
         Scripture to him and then they found some water. "Well," he says, "here's
         some water, what hinders me to be baptised?" Well, he went down to the
         water and.was baptised. Well, the people that claim you're supposed to
         be immersed, people that's been there, says there's not enough water, to
         immerse a cat.
         
         DG:  Maybe there was more water at the time.
         
         EG:  Well, I don't know what was there.
         
         SS:  Do you have any experience yourself, of being born again?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Have you had that experience?
         
         EG:  Yes- (Chuckles) Yes, I know what that is. Th$ is where I b
         thinking about our country here, trying to say what agood country they
         are, and then takin' the Bible— I claim, and I know there's a lot of
         people like me that don't care for it. And the Scripture says to teach
         it; write it on your porch and write it up and teach it to your family
         all the time; well, then I claim that our Bible should be put in the
         school as a reader in the fifth grade.
         
         SS:  Yeah, you were telling me about that.
         
         EG:  That's what Ifigure,^it should be in the fifth grade as areader. Now
         then, you get our congressmen and people like to do that, will you?
         The Bible is mostly history, Imean it's kind of a history-
         Well, there's an awful lot of history in it.
         and believe in God and what he meant—
         an infidel says that he'd read it three times; he never seen
         anything but what you could do very well without. But then, here's the
         proposition about seein' what you can do without. We have laws in our
         country here that's wrote against murder and all this kind of thing, but
         the first law God wrote with Ms finger to Moses, not to murder and not
         to lie, not to steal and not to commit adultery and all them things: God
         wrote them first. Now that's like our automobiles: Henry Ford started
         out tinkering with stuff and he got a thing that would run on it's own
         power. Well, there had never been a car first, but Ford got in there
         and figured that out and made that motor and got a thing to run. Well
         now, there's all kinds of motors— cars and things out of that.
         
         DG:  Well, all kinds of religions.
         Well, we turned in and experimented and we made the atomic bomb, and
         after World War I, they had a conference and they said- agreed unanymously
         that there would be no military secrets between nations. And England
         and the United States went one to the other and said we can't share the
         secrets of the atomic bomb with Roosia, the other'n said we cain't. Now
         ^who built the Iron Curtain? Roosia's got the atomic bomb, we had it first
         They knowed that there was anatomic bomb and they got scientists and they
         got together and they built it. China's built it. India's got it. And
         they've got that atomic bomb all over now, but the first one that was
         built was very hard to fix. Same way as an infidel come in and say we
         could do without anything that's in the Bible. But the Jaw that we all
         have to go by, or supposed to go by, of not murdering and not stealing
         and lying and the Ten Commandments- God wrote them first. Well, every
         nation in the world has got them laws in their lawbooks. They're fine,
         you don't have to go to the Bible to find 'em anymore, but the first onewho
         wrote the first ones? And who built the first this and who built the
         first that. I know the first phonograph I ever seen; Iwas a little kid
         in Virginia and there was a fella come along atravelin' through the coun
         try and stoppin' at schoolhouses and he had a bunch of records on a Edi
         son phonograph and the horn was supported by a stand that stood out in
         front of it. It was a heavy horn, had to be supported en that, Iremember
         that, and Iwas small enough that my dad- wejjhad amile to go, and my
         dad packed me part of the way home. So you know Iwas a pretty small
         lad when I seen the first phonograph. But, there's lots of different
         things made now since Edison started that. And the electric lightshow
         long did he work to do that? But Edison made the first one. Now
         lots of people can make them things.
         
         The thing I wanted to ask you about- about this religion is that- I was
         curious about how it was important to you, when you were an adult, but
         a long time ago. Did you find that the idea of— was the idea of being
         born again something that was important to you? In those years? The
         revivals and all that. Was that important to a person.
         
         As we grew up, we liked to go to the revivals and most of us have been
         to the altar and like that, but as a child we was always in church, you
         know, every Sunday.
         
         EG:  We was raised in church.
         
         DG:  We were raised, you know, with the background to go to church and so on
         up until you got up in your teens to feel responsible for your own reli
         gious welfare. And, of course, we make a lot of mistakes and don't live
         up to it like we should, but we believe it and we have been to the altar.
         I don't know if we've had a feftling as some of 'em call it, the Holy
         Spirit or sanctification or. like that, why-
         
         EG:  Some people have the ideas of calling it one thing and another. The Lu
         therans call their- what some people call sanctification- they call it
         growing in Grace. Gittin'—
         
         DG:  Trying to get better.
         
         EG:  The longer they live atryin' to- not to get any worse, at least. Get
         better all the time. Live closer to God^. Well, some of 'em they talk
         about their sanctification and well, after they git it, I can't see any
         difference in 'em after they get what they call sanctification than
         they did before. But, now-
         
         DG:  They may feel different themselves, you know.
         
         EG:  Yeah, 'fhe inward feelin' I don't know. I can^ tell my inward feel
         ing; I can't tell yours.
         
         DG:  And then I know some people- I do things that they wouldn't do. They do
         things that I wouldn't do. And I've seen some of 'em, that I know busin
         ess like and everything; I've seen 'em go up for sanctification, and
         you feel real good about it, you know, think it's going to be wonderful,
         but in their daily lives and their business dealings, why, it doesn't
         coincide with my idea of what-
         
         SS:  Do you feel like it's the way it makes you act, more than the way it
         makes you feel? Do you know what I mean? Is it— Do you look at reli
         gion as something that's in the way you, that it makes you live your life
         and the way you treat other people? And it affects the way you deal
         with people?
         
         DG:  Well, I think it-
         
         EG:  It should have a lot of the way you deal with people. But thinking about
         that, it takes me back to the Adventists that lived at Arrow long years
         ago. And there was a fellow come down the road with a team and got stuck
         in about twenty rods of this Adventist's house on Friday evening after
         sundown, after dark. And they went to the Advent to get his team to pull
         him out, it wouldn't a been- it wasn't twenty rods to the top of the hill.
         But, no, it was his Sabbath and he wouldn't take his team out. He wouldn't
         go and help that man, never went out to help him. But my brother was a
         teachin' school at that time and he'd went* to-jJurdin was the clerk of the
         board and he went there to get his warrant for his month's teaching, and
         it happened to be that night. And then there was a grown man there that
         was going with the Jurdin girl and Jurdin and my brother and the man that
         had the wagon; the four of 'em went and took the load off of the wagon
         and packed it up to the top of the hill so the team could pull the wagon
         up and then loaded again, and he went on about a quarter of a mile
         further, the only place in the country that had a barn next to the road
         except the Adventist, and he put up there for the night with that fella.
         So, that was the way the— Well, that fella says, "I would take my team
         out to help a man out on my Sabbath." And Jesus got took apart because
         he healed a man on the Sabbath day. And he asked -em if any of 'em had
         an ox in the ditch if they wouldn't. it out.
         
         DG:  They picked the corn on the Sabbath, too, didn't they?
         
         EG:  Yes. They talk about corn, and I don't know what kind of stuff it was,
         if they had corn, some kind of a something. They have something they
         call Jerusalem corn, that's a kind of a headlike cane, and then they had
         wheat. But corn, what we know as corn was originated in America.
         
         DG:  We believe it's alright to do good on the Sabbath, but just not to s*t
         around all week and leave everything and then try to get it all done on
         Sunday. But if anybody is in need, you know, why, we wouldn't hesitate
         to stop and—
         
         EG:  Well, there was an old fella used to live over here that was an Adventist,
         used to live up in the same country, and he used to talk about going out
         to the churches in Leland; they used to have two Methodist churches there;
         but he talked about going down to church there, well, you'd come out just
         before twelve, you know, and he'd say— seemed like that Advent would have
         it worked out every day to pass the church just as they come out, he'd
         have a load of wood; going home with a load of wood. He hadn't worked
         on Saturday, but then, on Sunday he'd be passin' this church—
         
         DG:  I think the Adventists are very sincere, very good people, and they do a
         lot of good, but-
         
         EG:  In a way they do a lot of good, but I've heerd a lot of people say,"I
         don't understand the Bible." Now this one thing here- a preacher thatand
         old Methodist preacher that had been in Alaska as a missionary, he
         said the Catholics come up there into Alaska and the Methodists and then
         the Adventists come up there, and he said them people didn't know what
         to do. The Catholics was a different i; the Methodists was different
         to the Adventists
         
         SS:  The denominations get in each other's way?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  All these different denomination, they get in each other's way?
         
         EG:  They do. They do get in each other's way more with men that are not re
         ligious, because the men that's not religious, you see, this one and
         that one and the other and they all tell you what to do. Now, I got a
         cousin, or did have a cousin, that was a Seven Day Adventist . His
         father was a strong Lutheran and a good man, and this fella he left Vir
         ginia between two nights- between two days- and he come into Mexico and
         there he got turned to be an Adventist. And they had him arrested for
         disturbing worship- and I've got his picture here, it was sent to his
         that'd be mother- to my mother,Ahis aunt, you know- his picture lookin' through
         the iron bars, you know, he's in jail, and it said, "Blessed are ye when
         you're persecuted for my namesake." Well, my oldest brother went East
         with Uncle Jim Castle, that was this fella's dad had come out here, anc1
         then he went back around and visited the boy, and my brother went with
         him as he went East, my brother went back and got married. So my dad
         told him after this come out, he said, "Now, Levi, I want to ask you
         something about Kelly Castle's place there; hasn't he got a blacksmith
         shop? And isn't there a church on the other corner on the other side of
         the street right from his blacksmith shop?" And he said, "I believe there
         is." And said, "That's it." Says, "I know Old Jim Castle, I used to go
         by his place and he'd spit on the anvil and put a hot iron on it and hit
         it to make a racket to scare my horse. Bailey Castle was aworkin' in his
         blacksmith shop right across the street from that church. While they
         were having worship on Sunday he was disturbin' that worship by workin'
         in his shop." And there he had it up there, his picture looking through
         the bars; "Blessed are these who are persecuted for my namesake."
         
         SS:  Where was he thrown in jail?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Whereabouts was he thrown in jail?
         
         EG:  This was somewhere in New Mixico. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  New Mexico.
         Then he would be an Adventist. He would be doing his work on Sunday.
         I was going to ask you something about Adams, this guy in Juliaetta. Did
         you ever hear about his deal with that wheat?
         Oh, Adams wheat! Yes, sir. I know Adam's wheat!
         
         SS:  What did you hear about that? What did you know about that? About that
         wheat of his; what did you know about it?
         Well, he said that he got that, found it in a wild goose's craw in Ala
         ska. But there was a fella, Lee Hall, lived down in the- had a homestead
         up the Little Potlatch Canyon, and he was a great hunter, and he said he
         went up on the Genesee Ridge, and it looked like the wheat had froze out
         or something and he went up there and it looked like it had been drilled
         crossways and this here peculiar wheat was in that field. And the heads
         of that wheat was like this- kinda double, and a^fcki Gne head seemed
         to be a little shorter than the other, but it was a big head, and I don't
         know that it had- well, it's like some wheat you know, soem of 'em the
         heads are awful tight and shorter and others are looser and look like
         bigger heads, and yet they don't have any more grain in 'em than the other,
         Well, that was kinda the way with this. It was a looser head of wheat
         than the other and had abig head there. But this Hall^he brought that
         home and planted that in his garden. Well that'll grow, you know; one
         grain of wheat'11 make a great big bunch, that fall he brought a hand
         ful of it up and put some in the bank, that peculiar wheat, and he had
         some money in his hand, and he'd got kinda mad at Old Adams and he thought
         he'd just tell him a good yarn, you know. He met him on the street, said,
         "Mr. Adams would you like to have a few heads of the Klondike wheat?"
         That was great gold country up to Alaska country then. "A few heads of
         the Klondike wheat?" He said, "You plant it in your garden and it'll
         produce a hundred and sixty times what you plant." Well, any wheat'11
         do that. You plant it and when it grows good, why it'll make a whole
         handful of heads there. I believe it would beat that; most any wheat
         agoin' on good ground, just one grain put in place and keep the weeds
         out from around it. But Adams he took it and he done that and he started
         it, kept multiplying from that little bunch that Hall give him til he
         got enough to get acreages of it, and then he put up this story of Alaska
         wheat, found in a goose's craw and got to sellin' it for twenty dollars
         a bushel for seed. Well, he shipped some to Kansas, back there from here.
         And then the government got to thinkin' about such an outlandish price
         as that for wheat. Ordinary wheat then wasn't, oh, I don't know, whether
         they ever got eighty cents a bushel. But consider the general run of
         wheat at eighty cents a bushel and then this stuff here at twenty dollars
         a bushel; the government went to investigatin' to see what it was. And
         when they actually found out where it come from, it was the old Egyptian
         wheat. The oldest wheat in the world.
         
         SS:  That Vlhat Hall had gotten up off the Ridge, was the old Egyptian wheat?
         
         EG:  That was what it was. He was the one that got the original kernels of
         stuff, but this Adams said he got it out of a goose's craw.
         
         SS:  Did you know Hall?
         
         EG:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Did he tell you that story?
         
         EG:  Yeah, he's the one that told me that. Yes.
         
         SS:  Why was he mad at Adams? Was there any special reason?
         
         EG:  Well, he was aworkin' on the mill, puttin' a roof on it; some kind of a
         combination roof and it had some wire in it like, and he give Adams a
         piece of it and he wanted to know how I cut it. "Well," he said, "you
         cut it with your knife if you want to." And Adams he took it and that
         wire in there and he dulled his knife and it made him kind of mad.
         
         SS:  This made Hall mad?
         
         EG:  This made Adams mad, because Hall give him this stuff and he dulled his
         knife tryin' to cut it. And that^of miffed Hall, too, so he just thought
         he could— he was a pretty good guy, you know to make up a pretty good
         yarn, Hall was, and so he told him this. And then he changed it
         from Klondike to Alaska and then he made himself a lot of money.
         
         SS:  Adams really believe that this was— the Hall story? That this was Ala
         ska wheat?
         
         EG:  No, he changed the story around. I don't believe Hall told him this. May
         be Hall did tell him it come out of a goose's craw, but Hall didn't tell
         him it was Alaska, he told him it was Klondike.
         
         SS:  Didn't Adams say he found it up in Alaska himself?
         
         SS:  Did they stop him from selling it? Or what happened?
         
         EG:  Yes. After they found out it was the old Egyptian wheat, then they stop
         ped him from sellin' it, and stopped him from shippin' it out of the coun
         try. Well, he had a son-in-law that was a banker up here.
         
         SS:  E. W. Porter. Yeah. And the two of 'em, they shipped a carload of hay from here
         to
         Kansas. And they thought that was funny shippin' hay from here to Kan
         sas, so they inspected the car and found it with this rtieat inside of
         the hay. And that was smugglin'. So, I don't know what the fine for
         smugglin' is. But I never heard of 'em ashippin' any more. (Chuckles)
         I believe he did.^ Claimed he got it himself out of a goose.
         
         Did E. W. Porter get in trouble over that, do you think?
         
         I don't know. I don't know what happened, that's all I heerd about; they
         caught 'em asmugglin' that wheat out of here in that hay. And I don't
         know what fine they got or anything about it. I don't know any more
         about that.
         
         Did you run across any- during the First World War: I know there was a
         lot of anti Germar, feeling. People around here who kind of disliked the
         German people for a while because of the war. I know like they weren't
         supposed to speak the German language and that kind of thing. Did you
         ever hear about that? During that time?
         
         EG:  None of 'em around here.
         
         One I was going to ask you about coming from Virginia, was that I
         know that some of the bitterness about the Civil War and all, with the
         Grand Old Army and all that stuff; I was wondering if anybody in your
         families ever had the idea that some of the people around here still held
         some kind of grudge against Southerners, or didn't like Southerners, be
         cause they were from the South?
         
         Well, I don't know whether they do or not.
         
         SS:  I mean back in the early days. 1910?
         
         EG:  Back in the early days, yes, they did. Some of 'em had something to
         say about the Southerners. One time there was a young feller wanted to
         run for road boss, and he come up to Albright's down here, and left a
         note for 'em, they wasn't at home. Told 'em to come down and vote for
         him and help beat the Southerners. And my cousin, Ben Crabtree, he went
         up there to get 'em to vote for him and found the note and put his name
         on it, too and he come back and told 'em that this here fellow went up
         there to try to get to be road boss to get somebody to come to help beat
         the Southerners. So that made everybody that was from the South mad and
         they all— two or three of 'em was gonna run for road boss and they all
         drawed off for Crabtree, except one, Wilson didn't; but they beat this
         other fellow way outta sight, he had no show at all of being a road boss.
         And he mighta got it if he'd. put that Southernern talk in there,
         because the others mighta all went ahead and run. Yeah, there was lots
         a people that had differences, didn't like Southern people, and Southern
         people didn't like Northerners. It was a long time to get it ironed out.
         Like Leland having;1 two Methodist Churches in it. You know what Leland
         is now, don't you? It had a steam run flour mill. It had a school and
         a post office.
         
         DG:  Real good store.
         
         EG:  Two good general stores and a hardware.
         
         SS:  You had two churches, 'cause one was Northern Methodist and one was South
         ern Methodist?
         
         EG:  Yeah. One set on this block here lookin' at the street thisaway, and the
         other one set on this block here looking thisaway, there. And the people
         claim.' ed— some fellas claimed they went by one night and they was singin'
         in one, "Will There be Any Stars in My Crown?" And the other'n was
         singing, "No, Not One." (Chuckles) It wasn't only the Methodists, near
         ly all the people- all the churches was split for a while over that. And
         
         (a break in here __ )
         
         somebody's bright idea of pickin' up that old Scripture that Noah-/which
         is right and which is left, so I went off in the corner and sit down. I
         wanted to do what was right, you know, and a fella got just so drunk he
         wouldn't care. He wouldn't care whether he went right or left- that was
         alright, he'd just be havin' a lot of fun anyway.
         
         SS:  This was a quadrille dance?
         
         EG:  Calla quadrille, allemande left, and you turn to the right, why, that
         would tangle up the whole business, but if you was drunk enough to- really
         drunk, why, you wouldn't care.
         
         DG:  What made bad, he never- he wasn't used to drinking or smokin' either,
         and they'd slipped out and found a bottle- they was drinkin' a bunch of
         'em, some guy had it hid out in a barn. And then they smoked cigarettes,
         when they wasn't used to smokin', to kill it on the breath and come in
         around the girls and it made him pretty dizzy.
         
         EG:  Yep. The other fellas, they all tell it too that did smoke. I found out
         afterwards that that's the cheapest drunk you can have, is to smoke on
         drink. Smokin' and drinkin' together will set your head a whirling.
         
         DG:  Your's, 'cause you're not used to it.
         
         EG:  Well, it will other people.
         
         SS:  I was going to ask you another thing. Why do you like to write poetry?
         
         EG:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Why do you like to write poetry? I don't know many people that do write
         poetry.
         
         DG:  He never considered it poetry, I don't think. He was quite a hand to
         make upK
         
         EG:  Oh, I don't know. Just got a few ideas in my head, and just got awritin'
         thataway.
         
         DG:  Just every once in a while.
         
         EG:  Now, I don't know, - a fella that married my niece he was quite a poet.
         And he wrote quite a lot of pretty good poems. And he says that before
         you got to write a poem- he was a well educated man- he says you've got
         to have an inspiration to write before you can do that. Well, there is
         times I think of something that way that will make a rhyme and keep a
         rhyming out a little ways and at other times, why, I couldn't write three
         words that would rhyme "To save your life. Just some foolish ideas.
         
         DG:  Lots of times he'll try to make a joke outta things, like worry, I'm al
         ways a big worrywart- well, I guess he worried, but he didn't say very
         much about it, he just could make himself more or less accept.
         
         EG:  Who was that?
         
         DG:  You!
         
         EG:  Oh. yeah.
         
         Just accept it and go on, you know. And he's quite a hand to figure that
         the other fellow had rights the same as he did. And I know that one time
         we was all needing work so bad and there was several guys after the job
         and there was a little road work come up and I insisted that he try to
         get on, and he said, "There's a lot after it." And he said, "You've got
         two brothers that's after it," and he said, "if they can get on, they've
         got your mother to take care of." Mama was an invalid, or practically so,
         and the brothers, you know, they growed up, why, they had to do the sup
         porting. And so, he said, "Everybody can't get on, we can't all be on
         there," and he said, "if they don't get on your mother's going to suffer."
         He said, "If there's room for all, fine, but I'm not agoing to-"
         
         EG:  Where was that?
         
         DG:  Oh, down there at Arrow one time, you know, you said, that you wasn't
         going to push anybody out, you know.
         This railroad or just road work?
         This was road.
         Just road work. Before he went onto the railroad.
         Sounds like just road work was one of the only jobs that a person could
         get. Was that WPA?
         WPA or PWA, whatever they called it.
         They had that a while, NRA, and—
         And then he'd get a few days.
         They give you ten- they give one fella ten days and then another one
         ten.
         
         DG:  So everybody could have a little bit.
         
         EG:  That was after Roosevelt come in and started that- started up agivin'
         people a little work, you know, road work or— . Well, then it wasn't
         all road work. He went to makin' these trails through the country, too.
         And people got on that. Make roads or trails all over the country.
         
         SS:  Do you think that that was a real good thing to happen? Roosevelt to
         get in and start trying change?
         
         EG:  Yes, he done a lot of good things.
         
         EG:  He opened up business. Now Hoover, they always make fun of him, but what
         Hoover done, he appropriated a lot of money and give it to the wealthy
         men to hire— they was supposed to go and hire the poor people and put
         them to work. But instead of that- of them adoin' that, they went and
         repaired their machinery, their factories, made them better and never
         hired any outside work, so that left the people worse off than ever and
         everybody hated Hoover.
         
         EG:  and when he got in there and made an appropriation^ money, he
         put it out so that he knowed the poor man was goin' a get it! He put
         it out there so now— there was a few places that they goofed up. on that.
         Now up here at Lenor$, they was a man up there, that .had something to do
         with handling that money, but he got his son— he was a merchant, his
         son was- he wasn't needy because his father had stuff, but he got his son
         on as timekeeper. And timekeeper worked straight time, you know, all
         through, he didn't work ten days and out Timekeeper works all through,
         so he got his son in as timekeeper on the job. Well, I got in, I think
         I got in twice. I gotcheats at ten days while the job was a goin' on.
         But this son of his he got in there and then he was assistant foreman,
         and he didn't know a thing about the job. I was workin' there one day
         a puttin' some road in, and I'd worked on the road before, and I knowed
         what I wanted and a slope von a fill for a cut. A one to
         three was ^ bank here; one foot slope to three feet up to the bank and
         the other was one to one, that was the road that come out to the road
         from the ditch. I knowed how to make them, but he come along and started
         to tell me one day about it. "Well," he said, "perhaps you know more
         about it than I do." Well I did. And that was all he said. A one to
         three and one to one, and said, "Most likely you know more about it than
         I do." And he went on. But then that was it. He was the boss and he
         didn't know what a one to one and a one to three was. Well, they had an
         old railroad man that worked on that*-and he come down and started to make
         some of that, and he didn't understand what a one to one and a one to
         three was. (Chuckles) And then the bosSjhe didn't understand reading
         stakes and things like that, and he got my brother-in-law, George Wilson,
         to come up there and work on the job. He kept him on there quite a while
         because he had worked on the road work and he understood all stakes and
         all slopes and all stuff like that. Well, the man that he worked for for
         years as a road contractor^ he^senfc George out to finish any job of work
         they had. But he done most of his work in Washington. So when they put
         this road in across the river over there, why, they had some work over
         there to be done, that George could do, he knowed how, young fella,
         he went over there and told 'em, and I don't know what the fella- what
         the boss told him- but it just so took George back so that he never did
         try to get in again. He brought in men from somewhere else that done the
         work. They was supposed to hire local men, but they brought in some of
         their own men from somewhere else to do the work that George Wilson
         coulda done, if that boss woulda listened to him, but he was just a kid,
         you might say, but he started in young on the road work and he knowed.
         He knowed how to tractors and run graders and all kinds of stuff.
         
         SS:  But, he wouldn't go back?
         
         EG:  He never went back to again. Then he got in on the railroad.
         
         SS:  One thing I was going to ask you about. Did you live in a section house
         on the railroad?
         
         EG:  Yeah. I lived there.
         
         SS:  What was that like? What kind of accommodations were they; the section
         houses?
         
         DG:  What was a sectionhouse like?
         
         SS:  To live in? Yes.
         
         DG:  Well-
         
         EG:  Well, it was just about such a— not quite as good a house as this one 
         here.
         
         DG:  It was a common,ordinary house and hadn't been anyone in it much for quite
         a little while. Pretty well rundown when we moved there. But the com
         pany did put a roof on and put in some screen porches. It was only a
         four roomed house, and they built a little bedroom onto the porch after
         we were there. And there was a well just outside - just back of the
         house.
         
         EG:  It was as good as we'd ever been used to. (Chuckles)
         they called it
         
         DG:  And it was sealed with just lumber, beaded sealing,Ayou know, the walls
         and* was all lumber.
         
         EG:  'Cause we lived in some pretty sloppy places in our time!
         
         DG:  It was handy to the work. Just had to walk across two tracks and he was
         on the motorcar. And so it was handy.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13459</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Groseclose2</previous>
      <next>Grove1</next>
      <disp_name>Groseclose3</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
