<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">11/7/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Clara P. Grove, 1975-11-07, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:59:58</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Grove, Clara P.</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Editor; cook; nurse's aid; columnist; leader of Women's Christian
         Temperance Union
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1879</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Born in Iowa, she lived in the Dakotas and Montana before coming in 1925</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#WCTU"&gt;WCTU&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pioneers"&gt;pioneers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#poor"&gt;poor&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#boardinghouses"&gt;boardinghouses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#students"&gt;students&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13464</file_name>
      <mp3>13465.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13465.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>How one ancestor came to America and a family chest and its westward trek</title>
            <synopsis>Ancestor kidnapped on a ship and worked his way from
               Ireland to America. Story of an ancestral chest and
               its westward trek.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Meeting an Indian in winter. Grandmother braves
               Indians to get her rug striped.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Meeting an Indian in winter. Grandmother braves
               Indians to get her rug striped.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Why she moved to Troy; purchasing the newspaper</title>
            <synopsis>Moving to Troy to work halftime on the Troy Weekly
               News with Mr. Jones for whom she'd been correspondent
               in Moore, Montana. She purchased the newspaper.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Why she sold the newspaper; a man complained because his relative was given credit
               as a businesswoman
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>She sold out because of opposition among some highly
               placed foreign-born men to a woman owning a
               business. English tradition of female subservience.
               A man complained because his relative was given
               credit as a businesswoman.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Father was a Republican; hear a speech given by a suffragette in South Dakota</title>
            <synopsis>Father a staunch Republican. An orator explained
               "free silver." A speech by a suffragette about
               women's right to vote in Redfield, South Dakota.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Living in a women's dormitory build by a women's group at Redfield College</title>
            <synopsis>A women's group got a dormitory for women built at
               Redfield College. A poor woman student who managed
               to get through school there.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Women's Christian Temperance Union is family tradition; Grandparents' courtship and
               marriage; how grandparents got started in WCTU
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>WCTU as part of the family tradition. The old-time
               pioneer women did not talk freely. Grandparents'
               courtship and marriage; their conversion by an
               evangelist to the WCTU.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Grandmother's gift for gardening; experiment of growing food form a single potato</title>
            <synopsis>Grandmother's gift for gardening. Experiment of growing a great deal of food from
               a single potato, (cont.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>A bushel from one potato.</title>
            <synopsis>A bushel from one potato.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3780</time>
            <title>working as a jail visitor for WCTU; discussions of different people she saw as a jail
               visitor
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Working as "jail visitor" for the WCTU. Story of a
               boy set-up by a gang. "Jail visitor" as a department of
               WCTU, carried on individually. A mentally disturbed
               boy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>WCTU doesn't do much except fight booze; trying to locate needy families for Thanksgiving
               dinner
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>WCTU does much work besides "booze fighting"
               Difficulty locating needy family to give Thanksgiving
               dinner.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Stories of how she gave charity in the early days</title>
            <synopsis>Giving charity in early days - a painter who drank his
               earnings; a lady who wouldn't take a dinner. Visiting
               a terrible home; they were forced to leave town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Mother fed all hungry men who came to the door</title>
            <synopsis>Suffering of people in hard times. Mother fed all
               hungry men who came to her door. A businessman
               begged Mrs. Grove for food in DesMoines. (cont.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>More about hard times. A tramp and a businessman
               traveling together.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>More about hard times. A tramp and a businessman
               traveling together.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>A mysterious woman who appeared on Mrs. Grove's
               doorstep in Moscow.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A mysterious tramp who appeared on Mrs. Grove's
               doorstep in Moscow.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6180</time>
            <title>Acquiring and living in her Moscow home. Paying a
               carpenter in lean years.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Acquiring and living in her Moscow home. Paying a
               carpenter in lean years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6360</time>
            <title>Boarding college boys in Moscow; advantages of having butcher choose meat cuts</title>
            <synopsis>Boarding college boys at her home (1932-1934); one is still in touch with her. Two
               big-eating freshmen who fortunately went elsewhere. Congeniality and
               appreciation of the boys. Their sadness at the close
               of the year. Advantage of having the butcher choose the meat.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6840</time>
            <title>She matriculated at the university at the age of
               eighty-two.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>She matriculated at the university at the age of
               eighty-two.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>WCTU work: jail visiting, charity, temperance conversions. Editing newspaper
         despite opposition to businesswomen. Boarding students. Feeding the hungry. A woman's
         struggle through college. Women's suffrage; early politics. 11-7-75 1.9 hr
         38p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: What year were you born in?
         
         CLARA PAYNE GROVE: 1879. May, 13. And I never have attributed any of the odds
         and ends to the fact that it was the thirteenth!
         
         SS:  Had your parents homesteaded at all? Were they homesteading folks?
         How did they come to be in Idaho?
         
         CG:  I come of pioneer stock as far back as I know anything about; my family
         line. One pioneer was a nice, big, strapping young Irish lad of sixteen
         who had gone to the seaside to see the wonder of the boats; the ships.
         That undoubtedly was somewhere in 1700's. And a sailor approached him
         as he was on the wharf staring at the boats, and asked him if he'd like
         to see the inside of a boat. So they went on board. And the sailor
         showed him all about the deck, and he said, "Let's go below deck, and
         see what's down there." So they went below deck and they came to one
         door that was shut, and the boy said, "What's in here?" And the sailor
         said, "Go in and see." So he opened the door and let the boy in ahead
         of him and pulled the door shut and bolted it. And it wasn't unbolted
         until the ship was so far at sea there was no possibility of anybody
         swimming ashore. And he was put on deck with the hands and lived with
         the hands. And all the while, this was summertime, all the while they—
         the crew slept on deck. They just lay down on the deck and slept. Well,
         when they got to this side of the Atlantic, the boy knew about the plan
         tation owners indenturing a man. And indenturing means that they took
         him as a slave until he was twenty-one. At that time the plantation
         owner was supposed to give him a horse, bridle and saddle, and some
         times he did, and sometimes he didn't, as he chose. But being indent
         ured was enough of a slave that anyone attempting to run away was fair
         game for anyone who shot him down. That was not murder, that was mere
         ly capturing a slave. 
         
         But, anyway, that's the Irish line which I al
         ways claim as my nationality. I have a mixture also of Swiss Dutch
         and of English and in late years I found out there was Scotch mixed in
         it. I hadn't known that until later years. But, on the other side,
         back in the 1700's an ancestor on my Swiss Du^ch side, in the forest
         around his house cut down such an enormous black walnut tree that he
         made a chest out of the boards that he made, and the boards were so
         large that the chest, which stood about two feet high, had no piecing
         in it. The cover, the bottom, the ends and the sides each was one board,
         No metal at all fastened it together. It was dovetailed together. And
         dovetailed so expertly and exactly that to this day that chest, I don't
         have it but my daughter does have it, to this day, that chest can be
         pulled apart and put back dovetailed together. There was that ancestry.
         And he made it as a wedding chest for his daughter, and immediately af
         ter the marriage ceremony the daughter and her nice husband with
         the chest in his two-wheeled, one ox cart, and they walking beside,
         started West from— now I'm not sure whether it was from Carolina or
         from Virginia—at any rate, it was back in 1700 before either state was
         divided. They started West and one place they came to the forest was
         so dense that they couldn't get through just as they were, so they took
         the chest off of the cart and took the ox loose from it and led the ox
         through for what trail that would make, then they turned the cart up on
         one wheel and carried the cart through, then they carried the chest
         through and put it back on the cart and went on West. 
         
         They came to an
         other place that they couldn't get the chest through, so they pulled
         the dovetailing apart and laid the pieces and the contents out on the
         ground and led the ox through for what trail that would make, and then
         they went back and picked the chest up piece by piece and carried it
         piece by piece through. But still they went West. We have word of them
         in Indiana, where my mother and eleven other children of the same fam
         ily were born. And then from there they went to Minnesota and from
         there— well, they were there at the time of Indian war— but, they were
         never disturbed. At one time, perhaps not during the wartime, but at
         one time, an extremely cold winter morning, Grandfather got up and built
         the kitchen fire and put the teakettle on with what water was in it to
         get it boiling to thaw the pump so he could get a pail of water. So,
         when the teakettle boiled he took it out to the pump and just at that
         time an Indian came along, just one Indian alone, he was dressed solely
         in his breechclout, his mocassins and a blanket, and he asked if he
         might have a drink of water. And Grandfather told him, yes, as soon as
         he could get the pump thawed so he could get water. So, he went on and
         used what water he had to thaw the pump and got water. And he said to
         the Indian, "Aren't you cold?" And the Indian said, "Your face cold?"
         Grandfather said, "No, my face doesn't get "Indian all face!"
         
         And it may have been at that special time or some other time, Grandmother
         was having a rag carpet woven;,that was what you did for a carpet in
         those days, you saved everything you could to sew into carpetrags, and
         then you got the person who had the loom to weave your carpet. Well,
         Grandmother was having this carpet woven, and she said to Grandfather
         one day to saddle a horse for her, she wanted to ride over to the woman
         who had the loom and tell her exactly how to stripe the colors. And
         Grandfather said, ho,, the Indians were out, she couldn't go, that he
         would go. And Grandmother said, "No, you'd forget before you got there
         how I want it striped, and I want it like I want it, and I'm going. You
         saddle old Dolly for me, she's afraid of the Indians and I'll know if
         there are any about. So Grandfather saddled old Dolly and Grandmother
         mounted on the sidesaddle. And when she got home, she said she knew
         that in a certain clump of bushes beside the road there must have been
         an Indian, because old Dolly just refused to pass it, and she had quite
         a time to make Dolly pass that clump of bushes. So she knew there was
         an Indian in it. But that was nothing compared to striping a carpet!
         That sidesaddle was in our family until, oh, it's been more than forty
         years ago, my sister, who had the sidesaddle, died. The children by a
         of her husband, by former marriage, swarmed in and took what they
         wanted and burned what they didn't want. Whether they burned the side
         saddle or took it, we never knew. That was the last of the sidesaddle.
         
         Well, I came to Idaho; I came to Troy. The reason was, that the
         home of myself and my daughter, which was my family, lived in Moore,
         Montana, and we had come West; pioneer stock and didn't know anything,
         any of us except to go West. We came West to the home of a brother at
         Ruby, Washington, which is north of Spokane, north of Newport, Washing
         ton. He was away. We lived in his home for a time. And back in Moore,
         Montana, there had been a weekly newspaper that was edited by a man by
         named -Wilbur Johns. And my daughter had set type a little for
         him in the office and I had been his local correspondent for news, and
         I wrote to Mr. Johns at Moore, where I still owned $„. house, to know
         if he would have work on the paper for me if I returned to my home in
         fcftoore. In the meantime, unknown to me, Mr. Johns had come to Troy,
         Idaho and taken over the weekly newspaper there. And he answered me
         from Troy, saying that if I wanted to come to Troy, he would give me
         half day work in the office. So, daughter and I, after we had been
         as far West as the land goes, which is Sliverdale, across the narrow
         neck of land from Seattle, out in the Pacific, and we had been at Sil
         verdale keeping house there for some people for a time. And
         then we went to Troy for me to take this half day position in the week
         ly with Mr. Johns.
         
         SS:  Did he ever tell you why he came to Troy?
         
         CG:  No, he never did. I never asked him and he never told me why he went
         to Troy. But, I think it probably was because the little town of Moore
         had mostly dried up and blown away and times were hard there and I imagine
         he was not making a living off of his paper. So he just discon
         tinued it and went to Troy where the pickings were a little better. I
         am sure that was why.
         
         So, I worked half day  And in Troy, the women schoolteachers,
         secretaries and a store clerk got together and rented a furnished house
         and lived there, wanting a housekeeper. So, my daughter and I went
         there, she was in high school, and the next year graduated from the
         Troy High School, in 1927. We were in the house with the girls for a
         little while. Well, that just didn't do very well, because the child
         needed a home, which you don't get in one little upstairs room that
         isn't heated, nor in the kitchen. So, I got the loan of a cookhouse
         for a threshing crew that the man very kindly hauled up into the yard
         of the house where I was housekeeping. And my daughter and I lived in
         there and kept the house and did the cooking and so on for the girls.
         And we did that for the remainder of the year.
         
         SS:  Was your daughter able to help with the housework very much while she
         was going to school?
         
         CG:  Oh, she did help some, but it wasn't difficult because the cooking was
         practically the only part of it. And that was nothing to cook for half
         a dozen people. She did help, yes, but there just wasn't so much to do.
         It didn't bother me any at all to put in my half day at the office.
         She was busy with her high school, and I was busy with the office,
         and in our second year: One day Mr. Johns and I had been sticking type
         and we both met at the stone to empty our sticks at the same moment and
         as we emptied them Mr. Johns looked up at me and he said, "Do you want
         to buy this paper?" Well, that was the first I'd ever heard of such a
         thing, but just as though we had been talking about the weather.
         I said, "Yes, I do." He said, "Well, let's go to the bank and make out
         the papers." I said, "Alright, let's go." So we did. And as they were
         making out the papers, the banker— oh, you know his name—Ole Bowman,
         said, "And you will pay this amount every month." I said, "Well,
         make the contract that I will pay that amount and may pay as much more
         as I please." And, he said, "Oh, you won't need that." I said,"Well
         put it in the contract anyway," I said, "put it in." Well, he and Mr.
         Johns exchanged a little look between them of real amusement. But any
         way he put it in. There wasn't one payment but that I made the payment
         and a little more. Because the people seeing it under new hands swarm-
         ed in to hand their business to the Troy News. But any rag has it s
         own pet name. So, we were working on that. One day a man came in and
         offered me $500 for the plant and the building; everything, lock,stock
         and type. I told him "No, I wasn't interested." But I did begin to
         try to sell. And right out of the blue there came a man who at a form
         er time had had this same paper and given it up and gone elsewhere,
         and wanted to come back. And he came in and he offered me much more
         than the place was worth. It was said, for one thing, that the press
         was the one that Mark Twain had brought across the plains with him.
         And I always said, "That's pure nonsense, Mark Twain never brought any
         thing as useless as that old press across the plains!!" So I don't
         know whether or not it is the press that he brought. It was a huge thing
         it would have practically have filled that alcove. A huge thing.r I
         stood on a box, this high, to feed it by hand. But, anyway, we filled
         out the paper, and Mr. Johns as he was leaving said, "Now here's some
         boilerplate, you're going to need it when you have a vacant spot and
         nothing to put in it." I said, "Alright." Well, instead of having
         ever a vacant spot, I'd had it only just a little while, until I had
         to put out a supplement to have room to put all the news in! And I
         did really love that.
         
         SS:  Tell me how it changed under your hands; that it got to be so much big
         ger and that it got more business. What is it that you did that made
         you have to put out a supplement?
         
         CG:  Well, people bringing in news. Nobody could go to Moscow for a day of
         trading. Nobody could go to Spokane to spend an afternoon. Nobody
         could do anything, everybody brought me the news. And when you
         have a town newspaper, what the people want and demand and frequently
         can't get, is whether Mr. and Mrs. John Smith spent the day in Spokane
         or whether Lillian Smith took a prize at school, or every little thing
         that happens, is what they want to know. And those were the things that
         people were just pouring into the office, and I was printing all of it,
         because it's what they wanted. And if they wanted it, I wanted 'em to
         have it. So that is how it happened that I had to put out a supplement.
         And as for knowing anything about owning a paper, or the legal aspects
         that are necessary to be conformed with or how to feed the press, or
         much of anything else, I didn't know anything about it. Not anything.
         I knew how to be a good correspondent for news, yes, but it takes a lit
         tle more than that to put a paper into the post office!!
         
         SS:  Did you have to learn the rest, or did you have help for the rest?
         
         CG:  I had a woman there that Mr. Johns had wanted me to put on for help.
         She didn't know as much about it as I did. And she was just a real
         nuisance, and I found that she had come because it was supposed that
         after just a little her husband would get the paper for practically
         nothing, and she'd already be there in the office!! So, I just kept
         her a little while and she was highly indignant when I told her I
         couldn't keep her any longer. But she was making the work so much
         harder for me that— it was hard enough before. And then I couldn't
         lift the chase —well dumbly, it didn't occur to me to have the chase
         put on the press and kept there. Mr. Johns hadn't done it that way.
         He put everything in it on the stone and then carried it to the press
         and then put it back on the stone. And it didn't occur to me that that
         chase could just sit on the press all the time and I could fill it there
         as well as anywhere. So—well, he was one of the Olsons in Troy, which
         one I can't tell you now—who would come in on press day and take the
         chase to the press and later take it off and bring it back to the stone
         for me. So, we got along.
         
         SS:  Did you have regular correspondents?
         
         CG:  I had one, or possibly two, I'm not sure which, regular outside corres
         pondents. And Ethel and I both kept our ears wide for news all of the
         time, and people just came and brought it to me, because they were so
         happy to know what the news was. And I did enjoy it very much, but Ethel
         was graduating the second year; ready for university. And, we had de
         cided that we would go on with the paper and get a car and Ethel would
         drive from Troy to the University in good weather, or live in the hall
         through the winter. But, there began to be opposition to a woman own
         ing any business, and I wasn't hard enough— I've grown harder since, I
         hope— I wasn't hard enough to take it and tell them, "Well, object if
         you want to, I don't care!" So the opposition grew so pointed that I
         sold, when this man came along and offered me so much more than the
         place was worth.
         
         SS:  On what basis could these people be opposed to a woman owning a news
         paper?
         
         CG:  They were all of foreign extract. It was common saying that the post
         master and his family and myself were the only Americans in there!! It
         was the foreign element where women do not, at that time— see this was
         forty-eight years ago— that's quite a little while— and a great many
         of these people themselves had come across, not descendants, but^them
         selves. And it was just simple this foreign idea—
         
         SS:  In Europe and the old countries, you were starting to say, the women
         didn't have that kind of authority. Is that the case?
         
         CG:  No, women didn't own business. A woman didn't own a business. She
         owned her husband's name. That's not only in the foreign speaking peo
         ple— there was here in Moscow a woman whom I well knew; her husband
         was English and she said to me one time, she'd been asking me if I
         thought she should do this-that-or-the-other, and I said, "Yes." And
         she said, "Well, you know how it is, the English do not expect their
         women to have the-liberty that women in the United States have." So it
         isn't only the foreign speaking people who objected to women owning bus
         iness. But, according to her, an Englishman has an idea that a woman
         owns her husband's name and that is sufficient. Maybe it is!
         
         SS:  Do you think that the women in Troy supported your being the editor more
         than the men did?
         
         CG:  I think that the common people did. The trouble did not come from the
         common people; it came higher up than that.
         
         SS:  The prosperous ones like the farmers or the businessmen?
         
         CG:  Well, I think some of the businessmen did not object. I know I had one
         item about a woman who was actually the head in Troy of a business that
         was part of a business in Moscow at that time. It was the outlying Sta
         tion, and this woman was the business. There was no question on it.
         And I had a nice little write-up for her, something about a woman doing
         this work, and so capably. And a relative of her's came in— he did
         read me the riot act!! For writing that article. He said, "She is not
         the head of that!(chuckles) Well, she was and there was no denying it,
         but, anyway, this man who was related to her, wasn't going to have any
         body say that any woman could run a business!!
         
         SS:  How deep-seated do you think this idea was, that the women were supposed
         to be in the home and be sort of subservient?
         
         CG:  Well, I don't know where that idea came from, but I think it was always
         there. To me, this idea of trying to decide which is greater, male or
         female, is just exactly as though the steering wheel on an automobile,
         and one of the wheels under the automobile got into a discussion and
         each of them claimed to be the greater! And the steering wheel said to
         the wheel with the tire on it, "I'd like to know how you'd get where
         you want to go if it wasn't for me up here guiding you?" And the wheel
         with the tire comes right back, "Well, how would you get there in spite
         of all the steering you do if I didn't run?" So, for one to say it's
         any greater than the other, is nonsense. Each one in place is it,
         and that's all there is to it!!
         
         SS:  Where you were, were you in such a place to see the struggle for the
         right to vote for women? Did that come about?
         
         CG:  Yes, yes, I remember distinctly about that time, that there really was
         quite a struggle about women getting to vote. But they persevered and
         all the womens' organizations took it up and finally carried it over.
         And, I remember one campaign speech that I heard when the vote was new
         er than it is now, a good deal, and this woman was talking about the
         candidate "having a rainbow around his shoulders!" And I thought,
         "Well, that's a funny campaign talk." So I thought the women were sort
         of new at going at the business of voting and talking, and so on. I
         remember quite a number of things. I remember when Williams Jennings
         Bryan was so much in the public eye. My father— what I was going to
         say sort of slips from me. But, anyway, he was a politician first,
         and he was father afterwards, if there was any time left, but usually
         there wasn't much time left after the politics! So, I guess I come
         of my political activities honestly.
         
         SS:  What were your father's politics?
         
         CG:  He was straight Republican! There wasn't anything else on the face
         of the earth that was any good but a Republican! A Democrat, was just
         dirt, that was all!! We had the two parties for a while and we had
         various other parties. We had the Populist Party. It happened that
         an uncle of mine was a Populist, and he wasn't in our county, but in
         his county, there was one Populist vote, and since he was a Populist,
         of course, they would know who had voted it! And someone was razzing
         him about it, says, "Well, how do you feel now?" He said, "Oh, I feel
         just like a good egg in a bushel basket of bad ones!" But the Populist
         Party did make quite a mark for a while.
         
         SS:  Your father, as a Republican, what did he think of the La Follette Re
         publicans? What did he think of those progressive Republicans. The
         ones that wanted to reform the party?
         
         CG:  Oh no, no, no— no reform was needed, they were perfect like they were!
         
         SS:  He wasn't for the free silver and what Bryan
         
         CG:  I never heard him discuss silver. I do remember that I was at a gath
         ering where an outside orator— and he was a real orator— was discus
         sing the silver question, and he explained it, that it was just a
         matter of sixteen to one, and very simple, and went on explaining it,
         and he says, "If I had a boy of sixteen who couldn't understand that,
         I'd whip him." Well, I wondered how that'd make him understand it.
         (Chuckles) But, this was a real orator and one of his remarks stuck
         with me, I was just a kid at the time, and he said','They go around talk
         ing about prosperity, parity, parity!" And he could put over little
         things like that just instantly and sweep on into other things with such
         ease that I just sat there and admired the way he could talk. And I
         heard— I wonder if I can remember her name at all— she was one of the
         greatest advocates of the vote for women, and she spoke from the rost
         rum in our courtroom, we were the county seat, she spoke there, and I
         went to hear her. And I admired— she was a large woman, tall, and
         wide and thick— and I admired the way, without a particle of self con
         sciousness, she went up onto the rostrum and took chair there. And
         she took for her text, telling us just where in the Bible it is found,
         which I do not remember now, "Let no man take thy crown." I've always
         remembered how she could bring out that word,  But she gave a great
         talk, why women should vote.
         
         SS:  Do you remember the arguments she used in that talk? What her reasoning
         was?
         
         CG:  I do not remember, excepting her giving the topic and in the way she
         did. But, at the time, I fully agreed with her, that she was perfectly
         right about women having the vote.
         
         SS:  Where was this? That you saw her? What was the town, and the state?
         
         CG:  Redfield, South Dakota.
         
         SS:  Did many speakers come through and speak to the people there?
         
         CG:  We had many speakers. We were a county seat town and we were a very
         large town when I first knew it. I think there might have been two
         thousand people there, and it grew and grew. And we had, what we cal
         led Redfield College. It was a denominational college of the Congre
         gational Church. And the campus consisted of one three story red brick
         building with the customary path, of course. And the basement, at first
         was just merely a storage place, but very soon, it was made into a kit
         chen and dining room and a cook was employed. The men students— that
         was the basement, then the first floor was the classrooms; the second
         floor was the dormitory for the men students; the third floor was the
         dormitory for the women students. Well, a women's organization in the
         town took it up that that was not the proper way to lodge students. That
         there had to be a separate building for a dormitory for the women stu
         dents. So, about a block from the one building that we had at first,
         they put up a two story building with a bedroom and a sitting room for
         the housemother, and I think it was two extra bedrooms, and the second
         floor had bedrooms, what it would hold, and that was sufficient for the
         women who had no other lodging.
         
         There was one student there that I always remember very distinctly.
         She had been to the college building, or near it, and then she came to
         our home, which was a block from the college building, and Mother took
         her in, and she was inquiring about how to get connected with the col
         lege. And Mother said, "Well, Reverend Beeton is the President, and
         Clara will take you over there to Reverend tfeeton and he will tell you
         all these things that you want to know." So, Clara listened carefully
         to her conversation with Mother, so that her ears didn't miss anything,
         and then she took the girl across town, clear to the other side, where
         the President Reverend Jeeton and his family lived. And when we got
         there to it, Mary Hart said, "Where is the house? Which one is it?"
         And I pointed, and I said, "That's the one." And she said, "Well, then
         you can go home now." Well, I didn't want to go home now, I wanted to
         take her right to the door. I wanted to know everything I could know.
         So, I kept going and she said, "You can go home now." And when we got
         somewhere near it, she said, "You'd better go home now." Well, I took
         the hint finally and went home. And she went on to see Reverend Jlfeeton.
         
         Well, she made out someway. I found out later that she had given out
         at her home on a farm near Aberdeen, which was forty miles or so north
         of us, that she was going to college and her father told her she could
         n't, that he had no money for her to go with. She said she was going
         anyway. She was going to college and nothing was going to stop her.
         So, when she was ready to go to college he gave her a ten dollar bill,
         and he said, "Now, Mary, don't ask me for anything more, I cannot give
         you another penny and pay the taxes too." He said, "That is all I can
         give you for the whole year." So, with her ten dollar bill she got her
         self to Redfield. And I don't know just where she lived or how she got
         by that year, but she did. And she put in her four years there. Her
         brother joining her for the two last years, and when the brother was
         with her, they got a room over the drugstore. It was a drugstore and
         and, oh, sort of a general store, in a way, and up above there were two
         rooms that had a stove and a couple of chairs and she and her brother
         lived up there and they lived practically without heat through the whole
         university-college year. It wasn't a university, it was a college. And
         for their supper they would build just fire enough that she could cook
         some supper and when that fire was gone there was no more fire until
         the next supper. She and her brother, on the two kitchen chairs would
         sit at the table with their books and one blanket around the two of
         them, so they could keep a little warmer, and there they did their work
         for the next day. And she took all that, and living entirely without
         money—and it was just terrible how destitute she was, but she graduat
         ed anyway. And I don't know what became of her and her brother, but I
         do know that she graduated, and we were all proud of her.
         
         SS:  Did you see her during those years?
         
         CG:  I saw her frequently. Yes, I saw her frequently. And I guess she nev
         er had more than money enough to barely subsist. But she did live in
         the girls' dormitory. And the girls' dormitory, of course, had a nick
         name, why not? It was the Cheese Factory! (Chuckles) That is the way
         it was known.
         
         SS:  Did she visit with the family? Is that how you saw her? Or did you
         used to go over to the college to see her. Where would you run into
         her during the school years?
         
         CG:  Where was I?
         
         SS:  No, where did you run into her? Did she come to the house and visit?
         
         CG:  She had come to our house, and we lived only a block from the college
         and at one time we lived a block in front of it, and then we had our
         own home a block sort of to one side of it. But going to and from town
         the students passed by our door as we lived in front of the building,
         and I'd see her, as she'd go back and forth. And sometimes I'd meet
         her here and there. Never had any close connection with her.
         
         SS:  You said a while ago, that the women's organization wanted the building
         of the new dormitory for the girls, and I'm wondering—were the women's
         organizations very active when you were young?
         
         CG:  Yes, they were. There weren't so many of them by any means. There was
         the Ladies Aid of the churches; that was one group. And that was it,
         for the women; was the Ladies Aid. But it was very active. I do not
         recall any name of any other womens organization.
         
         SS:  What about the Womens Christian Temperance Union?
         
         CG:  The Womens Christian Temperance Union was organized by Frances Willard
         in 1876. Next year is our centennial year. My Grandmother Connor was
         one of the first members of that group. My mother was a member of that
         group. I am a member of that group, and have been District President
         for several years, and for two years was state organizer with national
         recognition,to work across the border in Washington. That happened,
         because as I was driving from one place to another in Idaho, naturally,
         because the highway ran on both sides of the state line, I was sometimes
         in Washington and a group there would ask me for help there, and so I
         wrote to National and explained it to them and they gave me recognition
         to work in Washington as well as in Idaho.
         
         SS:  Your grandmother was one of the earliest people to—?
         
         CG:  She was one of the earliest of the members of the Womens Christian Tem
         perance Union.
         
         SS:  Did she ever speak to you about it? Did you know why she became a—
         she grew to want to join it?
         
         CG:  It's very plain to me (Chuckles) that you don't know the old-time pion
         eer women! They didn't speak,(Chuckles) they were quite a silent group!
         Everything was scarce with them, even words! No, my grandmother didn't
         talk with me. I can't remember any time that she ever really talked
         with me. And I did her housework for her for several months one time,
         but she would speak to me, if necessary, but she didn't talk with me.
         But my grandfather— how he came to be my grandfather—he was the beau
         of his community, away back when. And Grandmother was the belle of her
         community. My grandfather heard about that belle Sally Lillie— he'd
         go over and break her heart and go back home! Grandmother heard of that
         beau, Elias Connor, "Huh, he didn't need to come seeing her!" So,
         Elias left his community and rode his horse over to Sally's community
         Huh, six weeks later they were married. (Chuckles) Their first morning
         in their new home, Grandfather went out to take care of his saddle hor
         se, and Grandmother was going to show him how lively she was, how she
         could get around and do things. She'd have breakfast ready when he got
         that horse taken care of!! So, she fried a skillet of eggs on the fire
         place, which was the only way of having fire they had. She fried a skil
         let of eggs and pulled it back onto the hearth of the fireplace, and
         turned around and stepped in it! (Laughter) Her children never got ov
         er teasing her about that. But, anyway, they lived together for more
         than fifty years. And, as usual, she got up very early in the morning,
         got the breakfast, washed it up; got the dinner, washed it up; got the
         supper, washed it up; went to bed and died instantly. After, I think it
         was about fifty-four years they were together. And Grandfather expres
         sed himself this way, "I have a good home, I have one of my children
         still with me, but I am utterly bankrupt." That was his way of expres
         sing his thought for the death of his wife.
         
         SS:  Sounds like they must have had a very good marriage.
         
         CG:  They had a good marriage. And, as far as the Womens Christian Temper
         ance Union is concerned; he drank quite a bit when he was young. And
         when some of his children were teenagers, there was an evangelist came
         to their community in Minnesota and Grandfather and Grandmother and
         some of the children were thoroughly converted from the life they'd had
         to a Christian life, a Grandfather never drank another drop in his life!
         And none of his children drank. And Grandmother was all for everything
         that could be done to fight the liquor traffic. She made her mark in
         her community. And, by nature, she was not a mother; she was never in
         tended for a mother. But she was the most marvelous gardener that the
         world has ever known. When they moved to South Dakota it is said that
         the government report of the annual rainfall for that portion of South
         Dakota was fourteen inches. Well, that's below anything that is sup
         posed to be able to raise a crop. But, have a garden, this woman would!
         The very first thing she did was to begin to pick up stones and she did
         n't have to look anywhere for them; they were all over everywhere. She
         picked up stones and built a stone wall, oh, probably nearly three feet
         high around a plot right by the house for her garden.
         
         Well, when I knew it, I wasn't even in South Dakota, Territory, when we went
         there. But she built the stone wall around this garden plot, and at
         the time that I knew it, in the fall she would have several inches deep
         of litter from the cattle barn spread all over her garden and left there
         until spring. The garden was plowed as deep as possible, getting this
         litter mixed into the soil. Then after it was plowed with the two-horse
         plow as deep as possible, she had it raked and raked and raked with the
         horse rake. They went over and over and over that with the horse rake.
         Then, when she would finally let the horse rake go, she took the hand
         rake and she hand raked every inch of it. And only then, could seeds
         be put in the ground. But when that little old lady put a seed in the
         ground and said, "Now you grow!" it grew and it produced! She had, in
         that dry country— they had no water except what was hauled in a bar
         so you can be sure she didn't water her garden, and she didn't raise
         plants in the house, because there was no place in the house to put a
         plant, for one thing. But she planted the seeds right in the ground
         and she had tomatoes, watermelons and muskmelons— they were not canta
         loupe at that time, they were muskmelon—and finally they degraded into
         cantaloupe. And asparagus. And she would plant a few potatoes, just
         for early new potatoes. And she had corn aplenty, and lettuce and rad
         ish. She had one radish that was known as a winter radish, and it got
         to be about six inches long and, well, about half an inch in diameter
         and it was white and she took great pride in it at harvesttime having
         those radishes on the table for the harvesters. And they were good and
         sweet and tender at that time of year. And I had the seed of them at
         one time, but I finally lost it. Now, talking about that—
         
         SS:  May I just ask you one thing here? I take it gardening was her pride
         and joy, was it especially
         
         CG:  That was her pride and,,joy! Was gardening. And there wasn't anything
         that anybody could tell or knew about gardening that she didn't already
         know! And she had currant bushes that were just loaded, and she sold
         the currants, and she sold her garden stuff, too, so that she had a lit
         tle supply of cash of her own all the time. Uncle Will would hitch Old
         Kate to the buggy. Kate couldn't run away if she'd wanted to, and Grand
         mother would hold the lines— I wouldn't say she drove— but she held
         the lines and Old Kate took her to town and around the little streets
         and she sold her gardeware that way. And she had just about everything
         that is raised in a garden.
         
         SS:  Was this a lifelong interest of hers, or one that she developed in her
         later years?
         
         CG:  I think she had been born with a hoe and rake in her hands! And she
         had gardened before she went to South Dakota. She had gardened in Min
         nesota. And she had one hoe that she used for more than fifty years!
         And it was worn down until the blade was only half the usual width. But
         the things she could do with that hoe!! She would get up at four o'clock
         in the morning and go right out to her garden and start hoeing, and
         when she would get it hoed from this corner to that, she would come
         right back and start again at this corner. She hoed continually! She
         said there was water in the ground; she was going to have it up where
         her plants could get it and she did! She proved her theory. And, her
         gardening ability showed up in many of her descendants. Many of them
         were great gardeners. I'm not a great gardener and never was, but I
         do kno w an experiment that possibly if our population continues to in
         crease so rapidly, and if the adverse elements continue taking land
         away from the common people into government hands, this thing that I
         know maybe a real lifesaver. 
         
         It is this: Up near Everett, Washington,
         a little town there, a man was given, what the one who gave it to him
         said was a separate kind of potato— just Irish potato—that you plant
         deep in the ground and keep covering it til you get to ground level
         with the cover, and at each joint it will put out a crop of potatoes.
         Well, this man planted the potato, oh, perhaps a foot and a half or
         even deeper in a hole in the ground and at Everett, in that country up
         there, the soil is bigwoods loam, which never hardens like the clay.
         And, he harvested almost one bushel of potatoes from that one little
         hole in the ground. Well, I had that seed, and I had it for years un
         til I had ten years of illness—did quite a lot to me— and during that
         time I lost the seed of it. But, when I was able again to do some gar
         dening I planted a common potato and it performed in the same way. A
         year ago I had a student gardening my ground here in Moscow and I plan
         ted just a common potato in a hole that he dug and I was going to keep
         track exactly of the produce from it, but low and behold, he,an Ag major,
         senior, without my consent or knowledge, just to be good to me, at po
         tato digging time, went out and dug that up and never kept any record
         at all of anything about it, an Ag student, a senior!! So I don't know
         just how performed, excepting that when I happened to go out and found
         what he was doing, he was almost through with it, he had on the ground
         about four good sized potatoes and a large number of very small po
         tatoes of various small sizes; they were really small, and it was so
         many— I was 50 furious at him doing this, although he had meant
         it for kindness, that I wouldn't ask him anything about it. I wouldn't
         speak to him about it. But he had so many of these small ones, that
         it looked to me as though they could not have come from one joint, they
         must have been from more than one joint, because there certainly were
         twenty or more of them.
         
         SS:  —WCTU— When did you yourself become interested in the WCTU, and become
         an active member?
         
         CG:  I became a member of the WCTU after I came to Moscow. And, it is a fact
         that I didn't join when I was first asked to join because the dues were
         a dollar and I didn't have quite dollars enough to feed myself and my
         daughter as we should have been fed. So I waited two or three years
         until I had a dollar I could spare for the dues. And that's more than
         forty years ago, I don't remember what year it was, but I've been here
         forty-eight years, and I think it's about forty two or three years ago
         perhaps, that I joined. And I have now given up most of the activities
         of it, excepting that I have charge of the devotions at every meeting.
         Not because I want to give up, but ninety-six years makes you give up
         quite a number of things, whether you will or no.
         
         SS:  And your mother was active in WCTU before you?
         
         CG:  My mother was jail visitor in Redfield, South Dakota. And for years
         I was jail visitor here in Moscow. And I confined my jail visiting to
         the juveniles. There was one juvenile, I wouldn't mention his name if
         I did remember,names and faces have no meaning for me any more. They
         don't register. I remember the person, all the incidents, but the name
         and the face don't register.
         
         SS:  In some ways that's the least important part anyway.
         
         CG:  But there was this one boy who was a perfectly good boy, but a bunch—
         a group, and this was a blood-sworn group of boys— can you feature it?-
         just young boys in grade school being blood-sworn? Every one of them
         had had his wrist slit for blood token of his loyalty to the group. Well,
         this boy was not that kind of a boy at all, either by raising or by
         nature, but they heeded, a stool pigeon, and they got him in some way
         or other and he didn't know how to get out. And when it came to a mat
         ter of the officers, low and behold, here's this stool pigeon to put up.
         And I visited him in jail. And the sheriff was very considerate. He
         took me and the boy into his private office and let us talk there. Well,
         the boy was— in spite of the fact that he nearly bit his tongue out
         trying to avoid it— he was crying bitterly. His ideal was that every
         thing for him was over; there was no future; there was nothing. Well,
         I talked to him and showed him that there was a future. That he could
         recover from this and finally got him comforted and quieted. And I
         kept track of him the while that he was in the jail. During this time
         I was cooking on the campus, but, anyway, found time to visit this
         boy in the evening. And at that time, the sheriff would let a jail visi
         tor in at any time that she could be there, so there was no question on
         that. When I'd get home in the evening, I'd go visit this boy every
         now and then. He was in the jail a while. And they sent him to the re
         form school.
         
         SS:  Did he actually commit a crime?
         
         CG:  He was with the boys who did, and how much of it he did, I do not know.
         But he was with the boys.
         
         SS:  Do you think he came to trust you? Do you think he grew to trust you
         as someone who wanted to help him?
         
         Well, he was just in this position that he was jailed, and they had to
         keep him, and I am sure that the sheriff, himself, saw the proposition
         as it was; that he was merely the stool pigeon who had been taken in
         for the purpose of being taken, and he was with the boys when they com
         mitted whatever it was, I do not remember. But, whether he actually
         was a committant, I do not know. I didn't try to find out. But anyway,
         I wrote to him all the while that he was in the home, and as soon as
         he came back to Moscow discharged from the home, he had a good home
         here, he had a good Christian Mother, had been well raised. As soon
         as he came he came to see me and I kept track of him. Well, as years
         went on, he grew up and married a good girl; had a nice family, and he
         brought me home from a church nursery, that I had charge of— he brought
         me home from there one day with his son with him; I don't remember, per
         haps he had two children with him, I know he had a son with as he brought
         me home. And his son was a lively rascal and he wanted to know if I
         knew his father, and I said, "Yes,"I knew his father. Well, I could
         see instantly that the father's record was not known to the children
         and that he was afraid that it would leak out now. (Chuckles) I took a
         lot of care that it didn't leak out. It was his business, not mine,
         whether this record was known to the children. He was just on nettles
         for a minute for fear of an answer that I would make to the boy, but I
         made a round about answer that quieted the boy, and said nothing.
         
         SS:  It sounds as though he appreciated you for helping him then.
         
         CG:  He did. He was very appreciative. And, there was another boy who stole
         oil or gas or something in Troy. And he was sent to the Home. I visit
         ed him while he was in the jail here. And I wrote to him all the time.
         And one time I said, "Now is there anything you want, that I could send
         you?" He replied, "Yes, I'm building a chest and I want you to send me
         a lock that nobody can open!" (Laughter) Evidently he didn't remem
         ber that he'd opened a lock! Because he had opened a lock to get in.
         But sometimes you get a little fun along with all these things you do.
         
         SS:  Was this position of "gail walker"— this was a responsibility that the
         WCTU had a person take on?
         
         CG:  It's a separate department. We have a lot of departments of work. And
         this was one department, and the "jail visitor" carried it on in her
         own way. On one of my organizing trips in South Idaho, I went to a Sun
         day morning service at the jail with the jail visitor there. And every
         Sunday morning at this hour, she went to the jail and the sheriff had
         the men all congregated where she could stand in the hall with every-
         thing between the men— the men were not given any liberty at all, they
         were confined-— but they were all in one place and she could stand in
         the hall outside, and she sang with them and prayed with them, and talk
         ed with them. And that was her regular Sunday morning service as jail
         visitor. And each one carries on the department in her own way. My
         way was to visit them personally. I visited one boy in the jail here—
         there was something wrong with his mentality—to destroy and steal and
         kill. It was the only thing he knew anything about. But, anyway, I
         went to visit him and the sheriff said that he really was dangerous,
         but if I wanted to I might talk with him. I said, "Yes, I would like
         to talk with him." So the sheriff took me upstairs to the boy's cell
         and put me in the cell and locked the door. And, I had just gotten the
         boy from his braggadocio mood to where he could make some response to
         what I was saying to him, when the jailer got worried about it, because
         the time had gone along, and he came up to see if I was still alive or
         not. He said when they took the boy he was carrying a six shooter.
         And he was just a kid. But, anyway, I didn't go back to see this boy
         because, apparently there was nothing in the brief time that he would
         be here that anybody could do, that would have been lasting with him.
         He was just mentally down. But, we do have— One woman said to me the
         other day, she said, "Well, I don't care so much about your WCTU. All
         you ever do is just to fight booze." "Oh," I said, ,"I don't believe
         it is." I said, "It happens that the woman who created the WCTU was
         responsible for the eight hour law, and for the child labor law." I
         said, "We do quite a lot of things besides fight booze, although we do
         fight it tooth and toenail all of the time." We do have all these dep
         artments, and at present, whether they have found the person or not, I
         don't know, but we are looking— if they haven't already found it— we
         are looking for a family, a whole family, that absolutely cannot buy
         a real Thanksgiving dinner, so that we may send them a dinner, so that
         we may send them a dinner. We do that each year. Last year we sent
         two dinners to two families. You don't know how diff icult it is, when
         you want to give somebody something to find the person who ought to
         have it. It's just like finding a needle in a haystack. Last year
         we couldn't find anybody that fitted the classification of someone who
         simply could not buy a dinner. But, we were given two names; one of
         them was a family where the mother worked, the father was invalid and
         while they got along, it was just to the end of everything every pay
         check. And the other one was a woman whose husband was incarcerated
         eiVWer in Idaho or somewhere, I presume in Boise, and they were not only
         welfare cared for, but in each year the lodges have their Thanksgiving
         dinners that they give— you probably know about that—they were to
         get one of those dinners. So the President said to me, "Well, what will
         we do?" I said, "We were given the name, let's give her the dinner any
         way." And, I said, "This other one that you mention, since they are
         sort of provided for, but just on a shoestring basis,"I said, "let's
         give them a dinner, too." So, we gave two dinners last year, which is
         unusual.
         
         SS:  Was it easier in the early days— was the suffering or the want of fam
         ilies much more obvious than it is today? Was it more apparent? Well,
         in the early days, if you were looking for families to help, were they
         easier to find?
         
         CG:  No, they never have been easy to find. For instance, there was a fam
         ily— well it's over right on the border of the campus where they were
         living—Railroad Street, somewhere over there, and I said — this was
         at Christmastime, we were looking for someone, because they had suggest
         ed to find a family with children and send toys for the children at
         Christmas besides^Thanksgiving dinner, which we had done. And, I said.
         I thought that we had no business giving just helter-skelter, that ev
         ery name that we got, that person should be visited and find out if
         they 5hould receive help or if there was no use for it. "Well," they
         said, "if that's the way you feel, go and do it!" (Laughter) So, I
         was going around visiting these people, and I found one place where the
         father was a painter and, at that time, the painter, if you please, was
         getting the enormous wage of eight dollars a day. At that year eight
         dollars was a lot of money. And he was getting eight dollars a day,
         but the saloon was getting it. And we had been given that name. And,
         when I went there, they had an apartment, a good sized apartment, and
         there was a bay window, like an old house would have, and that bay win
         dow was fairly well filled with donations that had been given them.
         But, anyway, there was a University professor and his wife wKo took
         me around to deliver the gift and they had some huge oranges, a special
         shipment of them at the store, those immense size oranges, and so they
         left oranges there.in spite of all that had been given them. Another
         place that I went to previously for a visit I asked the woman about what
         they would need for dinner; what they would like to have besides the
         turkey. "Why," she said, "I don't want a dinner given me." I said,
         "Well, we were given your name." "Well," she said, "before my husband's
         death he had made provision for me. I don't need anything. I have ev
         erything that myself and the children need, because my husband provided
         it." Her husband's death had been very sudden and very recent. He was
         in an accident of some kind. And, I said, "Well, but you put your name
         in at a certain place, that I designated and I do not know what the de
         signation was. She said, "Yes, but I thought it merely meant some littie
         treat- candy or something, for the children. A woman said to me,
         ''Why don't you put your name in? I put mine, why don't you put yours.'
         So, I put my name in, just thinking it'll be something that will help
         to make the day for the children." "But," she said, "I will not take a
         dinner. I wouldn't think of it!" Well, that place was providing din
         ners, that's what they were for, was dinners, but she had thought dif
         ferently, so that one was out.
         
         SS:  What about this family that got all the other food—that was getting
         so much, that you just old me about? Did you give them a dinner?
         
         CG:  No. No, we weren't giving dinners for Christmas. We were just giving
         a treat. And, we had, I think it was two little Christmas trees, one
         anyway. But, anyway, there was another place that had been given me.
         I was in the car with this University man and his wife and when we were
         half a block from the place, we knew it by the odor. Oh! It was ter
         rible! Well, I hadn't visited them before, I was just simply taking
         the treats. So, I did the best I could about the odor and went to the
         door. Well, it was very plain to me what the place was for. I didn't
         know whether the man at the back door had just come in and was inter
         rupted by my knocking at the front door, or whether he was just leaving.
         But I found out that it was place that was being maintained—well,what
         will I say— the upper class men who wouldn't go there? I don't think
         there is any such thing as upper class and lower class, I think we're
         all people, but still to express it, it was a place kept for other than
         upper class. And I found out later, not then, but later I found out
         that the mother,who had just died, was getting welfare for herself and
         the family; that the son had a fulltime job; he was a moron— that he
         had a fulltime job at something or other,, was getting his full wage and
         then the daughter was making this extra money. And, yet, we were asked
         to take them a Christmas treat! Well, there were two little boys, the
         woman didn't make any pretense at all that she'd ever been married, but
         she had two little boys. And, it looked to me like they were both of
         at least first grade school age. They were playing in the backyard;
         it was a nice day. And I asked her if she would like to have a Christ
         mas tree, thinking of the boys. She said, "I wouldn't have anything to
         put on it if I did have one." And I said, "I think the boys
         would like it, and we have with us some things to put on it if you'll
         let us come and put it up." So, she said, "Yes, put it up." So we did
         with the things to put on it. And that's my kind of experiences we had.
         
         SS:  When you said odor, by the way, was that just stink? You said the house
         smelled from a half a block away.
         
         CG:  It was just their way of living, that was all. They had been there for
         years in that one spot. And I just can't describe it. It was sort of a
         one-room place with some of it curtained off. And the moron son was
         standing there grinning at me, and the woman was really much embarrassed.
         But she didn't get up from her cot, where she was lying.
         
         SS:  Was the house itself— probably filthy.
         
         CG:  It was, absolutely filthy and the yard was filthy. Although other places
         were not rain wet, this place seemed to be. I don't know whether they
         threw out their dishwater or what, but, anyway the ground was wet around
         it and there was a plank from the street to the door. I never have seen
         anything quite as terrible as that was. And, I complained so loudly to
         the health officer, Dr. Litch was health officer at that time, and I
         knew him, and I just laid it on in complaining to him. No— he was
         health officer at one time—somebody else was at that time. But, any
         way, I didn't spare anything to tell him about it. And not long after
         ward the family went to California. And someone said to me, "Well, you
         didn't do anything for them, did you?" I said, "At least I did enough
         for the town that they're gone." "Yes, but somebody else will have them."
         I said, "It will take them some years to get another place to be like
         the one they left. And, at least, where they were can be cleaned up."
         I think that making them move was a perfectly right thing to do, even if
         somebody else did get them.
         
         SS:  What about times when there were people who were in need? In very des
         perate need? Do you remember situations like that?
         
         CG:  I've seen way back in Redfield when I was a kid— Redfield, South Dakota-
         Mother fed every man who came to the door. There was a string of them.
         Sometimes it'd be a businessman in his business suit; sometimes it'd be
         some bedraggled tramp in his Levis, although they weren't Levis at that
         time, they were overalls. But, Mother fed everyone who came. Someone
         said to me one time, "Well, your mother has no business to do that, she'll
         be found dead there by one of those fellows some of these days." Well,
         I ran home as hard as I could go and told Mother. And Mother said, "Well,
         there is no man as dangerous as a hungry man." And she went right on
         feeding them! But, really, it was pitiful. It was hardttimes after that
         I was temporarily, just for a short time in DesMoines, Iowa and one day
         when the landlady was gone, and I tended the door for her when she was
         gone, a man came to the door. He was just a common businessman in his
         business suit. It was very apparent that he was not a tramp in any way
         whatever, and he asked me if he could have something to eat. Well, my
         self and a little girl in an apartment just for a little short time—
         but I found something for him anyway. And, he said to me, "Do you have
         any coffee?" I said, "No, I never drink it. I don't have any in the
         house." Oh, was so disappointed. (Chuckles) And at one time, later "'
         than that, I was at Heath, Montana in the country. He had evidently
         lost his means and something about a picture machine— well, at that
         time, a picture machine was a very new thing; the movies, it was very
         new. And he would mumble to himself about a picture machine. Well, it
         was plain that his mind was turned. Well, here I was, alone with a lit
         tle child in the country, I didn't know whether he was going to go or
         not! But finally, he did go on. But a person meets all kinds.
         
         SS:  Do you have much of an idea of what caused businessmen or people who
         had some means to lose what they had? Was it just hard times in the
         country? What happened?
         
         CG:  The banks were all closed, with all the person had in the bank. He had
         just what he had in his pocket. Just one bank after another went out.
         And it was real hard times. At your age you've never seen real hard
         times! But, there were people who had been living in comfort that when
         they ate what was in the house;they were out! I remember one time, we
         were living on a farm at Geyser, Montana, near Geyser, and there were
         two men came along. We were seven miles from town. I don't know, maybe
         they came out with my husband when he drove out from town. Anyway, they
         were there to supper. My husband gave them a blanket and they slept
         in the manger. One of them was a tramp. I don't see tramps any more.
         We used to have them, they were known as tramps and they were tramps.
         They had no other destination than some place that isn't here! And
         they had that all^the time. And they lived on what they could get at
         back doors. But, anyway, these two men were there at our ranch and
         they came in and supper with us. And then, they had this blanket
         and slept in the manger and they came in to breakfast and then they went
         on. One of them was thoroughly a tramp, and the other was absolutely
         an educated businessman. And, I marveled at the combination and why
         this businessman was out like this, 'it is possible that he was running
         from the law. He may have been in on some crooked deal, I don't know,
         that was as near as I could get p,t- any guess that seemed reasonable.
         But, anyway, the two men were so different, but when they had their break
         fast they just wandered on. But why they would be here seven miles from
         town— so I thought probably the man might have been running from the
         law.
         
         SS:  When you were young and your mother was feeding the men who came to the
         door, was it common for someone to come to the door? Knock on the door
         and say, "I'm hungry?"
         
         CG:  Just very common. There were just one after another. And, sometimes,
         they would— oh, if there was a piece of wood to be cut up, maybe they
         would cut up, or something like that. But usually they were just
         fed, and that was all. And, Mother always had coffee for them. Of course
         that was a treat. It was so common that we thought nothing of it at
         at all.
         
         SS:  Would this be during one very bad year, or two bad years, or did it go
         on year after year?
         
         CG:  No. It was, I think not more than two years anyway. It might have
         been even shorter, I don't know.
         
         SS:  Perhaps a depression going on in the country?
         
         CG:  The depression was general; the whole United States. It was general.
         That was about 1890. I have that as a pivotal date, because my baby
         brother was born in 1890, so I have the date. And he was, I think he
         was about a year old at this time.
         
         SS:  Were most of these men just traveling around from town to town?
         
         CG:  Just going. Of course, the tramps were finding it harder because there
         were so many cutting in on them to get handouts! And perhaps someplace
         wouldn't give so many handouts as all that.
         
         I had one odd circumstance right here on this doorstep, and I've
         wondered about it ever since. I happened to be looking out, it was
         summertime, and a big, longrown tall man carrying a sack in his
         hand, was coming up the drive, and I wondered who or what. So I stood
         looking out the window, and he went to the steps that go up the bank,
         of the garage, and he looked up there quite a little bit and then
         he turned and went away. And after a while, here was this same man at
         the door. So I went to the door, and asked him what it was, and he
         said,— he wanted to know if there was a Mission in this town. I said
         "well, but what kind of a mission?" "The kind that have dinners, that
         kind, I haven't eaten much for the last two days." And I said, "No,
         there is no such Mission here, but you sit right down here on the door
         step and I'll bring you something." Well, it happened that I had just
         a very little bread in the house. And one person alone, one old woman
         doesn't have a lot of food around like families do, but, anyway, I took
         the bread and some butter and something else, what I could find
         and told him that it was all the bread that I had in the house. And
         later he said to me, "When I asked you, I wondered if you would have
         supplies in the house." Well, he very evidently was not the ordinary
         traveler; he was something more. And I took a little folding stool
         and went^and sat on the other end of the step and talked with him.
         After a little I said, "If I make coffee for you will you drink it?"
         Well, you know, some people drink it and some don't. And he said, "If
         it wouldn't be too much trouble." I said, "It's no trouble at all."
         So I a bowl full of coffee, and he was very grateful for it.
         And we talked on. He had this sack that he was carrying and around his
         neck he had a strap with a billfold— not a billfold but a briefcase—
         hanging around his neck. And finally, my curiosity got the better of
         me and it came into the conversation that I could fit it in, I said,
         "And what is in that?" He said, "That is some personal items." So we
         didn't say any more about it. And, among other things, while we were
         talking, he said that at one time he owned his business. Well, I
         didn't doubt that he was correct. And, we had quite a conversation,
         and when he had gotten up he said, "I want to do something for you. What
         can I do that will help you?" I said, "Well, I have a little piece of
         ground that is hard to spade, you could spade that if you would." Well,
         it was plain to me that he had never handled a spade, he didn't know
         what they were for!! But he did the best he could at it. And I thought
         that he was gone, he had brought the shovel up and left it, and I thought
         he was gone, but he came to the screen— there was a screen in the outer
         door at the time, it was summer— he came to the door and he said, "Good
         bye, Mrs. Grove." Well, I was too overthrown to say, "How do you know
         who I am?" And he left very quickly. How did he know who I am? Who
         was he? I would like to know. I have thought it out from every angle;
         there was no newspaper, no no nothing with my name on it any
         where. So he didn't get it here. Well, where did he get it? How did
         he know it? Evidently I had known him somewhere; perhaps back in school
         I don't know. But he had come to those steps and gone away and then he
         had come back. He was that determined to find me.
         
         SS:  There are things that are just impossible to explain. I don't know the
         explanation either.
         
         CG:  I've wondered and wondered about that. There was one old flame that
         disappeared. But when I compared the two, I didn't see how it could be,
         because there wasn't the physical resemblance. So, I never have known
         and I have often wondered who he was.
         
         And when I bought this place I had no fitting of any kind for shift
         ing for myself, and I wasn't making a very good out at it. Well, I was
         offered this place for a small sum, naturally, they were going to pave
         right away! Well, it didn't occur to me that you inquired about anything
         like that before you bought. But, anyway, it was a small enough price
         that I could pay it right down and be done with it. And there were just
         those two rooms, nothing more. The water was in, but it wasn't out!
         And from right here to the street, it was alfalfa about this high-(mea
         sured with hands) oh, it was a wonderful crop of alfalfa! Well, we got
         along with the two rooms for a little til we could kiMcf"/V get settled
         and get our breath and find where the University was and one thing and
         another. And, then I had a little shedroom built right on there, from
         that door for a bedroom. And that was there for years before.it was so
         I could have this part built on. One of my brothers built this in 1940.
         You see, I had come in '27 and it was '40 before I had got financially
         fixed so that I could have this built. And in that year, and I think it
         was at least two years later, carpenters were working for forty-five
         cents an hour. I have to this day some cupboard shelves and doors that
         a man— he was the best carpenter I think, that had ever been turned
         out— and when he got through, he was a very rapid worker, when he got
         through, I asked him how much I owed him and he said, "Sixty-seven
         cents!" And he had put up two sets of shelves with doors. Well, I gave
         him three quarters, and he said, "But I have no change with me." I
         thought, "Yes, and you don't have any home either." So, I said, "Well,
         never mind, give it to the children for candy." Well, I knew it wasn't
         going to anybody for candy. But, anyway, he accepted the three quarters.
         I wasn't so awfully flush myself, I was feeding college men and while I
         had a profit every month, it wasn't big by any means. But you know, that
         time I had those college men is one of the highest lights of my life!!
         And there's one of them, from whom I hear a real folio every Christmas,
         telling about the whole You may run across his name sometime around
         this country— Paul Rice; Dr. Paul Rice. He was getting his masters at
         the time that he ate here for two years. And later from an eastern univ
         ersity, I don't know where, he got his doctor^ degree. And he was an
         entymologist with Uncle Sam. And Uncle Sam sent him to-huh— oh, it
         was a place that was a place that was in all the papers and on every
         tongue at the time— across the waters—sent him there. And he wrote
         to me every now and then and even yet, after all these years, every
         Christmas I get a whole folio about the whole family.
         
         SS:  When you say it was one of the highest lights in your life, was that be
         cause the young men were looking for a home away from home, or why was
         it such a special occasion?
         
         CG:  It was the calibre of the young men, and their suitability to each other.
         I had two frosh here a while, and I wasn't making any profit on those
         two frosh! They were farm boys, both of them, and it took about as much
         to feed the two as it did the others, all the others. So one day, one
         of them came in and he hated to say it, and I was just tickled to pieces
         about it, he said, "Mrs. Grove, we found a place where we can get lodg
         ing and board and laundry for fifteen dollars a month." I said, "Well,
         Wayne, if I knew a place like that, I'd go and take it and shut this up!"
         (Chuckles) So, the two of them left, and I was so delighted. And that
         left these older men.
         
         SS:  Were they lodging here as well as boarding?
         
         CG:  No. No, they just ate, just the same as at a restaurant, that was all.
         
         SS:  But they came every day?
         
         CG:  Three times a day, except Sunday, they came twice. They had an invita
         tion if they wanted anything later on Sunday, they could come in at any
         time and I'd get them something. Well, there was one time that Paul
         came in, and I said, "What shall I fix for you, Paul?" "Well," he said,
         "how about an egg?" I said, "Just fine." He said, "Do you think I
         could possibly make you see twice?" I said, "Yes, I believe you could!"
         (Chuckles) And there was only one other time, and that was one of these
         frosh, at the time they were here, came in on Sunday evening, but other
         wise .
         
         SS:  You served them all the same menu?
         
         CG:  They all sat at the table and ate family style. Well, I fed them really
         feed, with plenty of it. They had meat every dinner, and sometimes other
         times, but they had the best of meat every dinner and we had, always,two
         vegetables at dinner, instead of only one, and there was hot bread, home
         baked frequently. Just exactly like home. And they were all so congen
         ial. There was Floyd, who was teaching in the high school, and Paul, who
         was getting his masters and Louie, I don't know whether he was getting
         his masters or not, I don't know. And I don't know just who
         
         SS:  How many?
         
         CG:  I had six. That was the limit of what I should have.
         
         SS:  Could you make a living from doing that? Was that enough for you to
         make a living?
         
         CG:  That was my living. That was all I had, was what I made out of that.
         
         SS:  And you could save from that, too, to put it aside?
         
         CG:  A little, a little. Yes, I saved a little every month. Yes. And they
         often spoke about the marvel of getting so much food and the kind of
         food, and they were so congenial. They would discuss, you know, their
         math problems and oh, this, that and the other. Politics and everything
         under the sun, like men do when they are gathered together and are con
         genial. And the last meal that they ate was evening dinner, and they
         were very silent, looking at their plates. And finally, Floyd, at the
         far end of the table, lifted his head, and he said, "Well, there is one
         thing sure, we will never meet this again. There is no such thing as
         another bunch like this." That was the general opinion.
         
         SS:  Was this the end of the school year?
         
         CG:  It was the end of the University year.
         
         SS:  How much did you charge them for board?
         
         CG:  I wonder if I know.
         
         SS:  It's not important, I just was wondering what it would have cost. This
         was in the late '20's?
         
         CG:  It was in '32 and '33, ,and '34. I can't remember what I charged
         them. I know I charged them in advance. I wasn't taking any chances on
         it at all! And, more than that, _I paid for the food as I bought it.
         And in that way I got the best of it. For instance, with the butcher,
         I never told him, "I want chicken today." "I want beef roast today."
         I always said, "Well, what are we going to have today?" And he'd say,
         "Well, I'm long on pork roast today." I said, "That's fine, send me one."
         And that's the way I bought my meat. And did I get the best of meat on
         the market, and lots of it!! I know that finally one day, he said, "I'm
         long on steak today." I said, "Fine, we'll have steak." So we did.
         But he always chose the meat, and it was just as easy as any other way,
         and^I chose what to put with that meat. I wish I could remember what I
         did charge.
         
         SS:  Mrs. Grove, I'm going to have to.
         
         CG:  I matriculated at the University when I was eighty-two. And, of course,
         I filled out the blank and at the bottom of it it said, "name the occup
         ations you have followed." Well, I filled that line and I filled all
         the space below it and I went on both sides (chuckles) and if there was
         anything I hadn't done, I don't know what it was! And I have had many
         adventures.
         
         SS:  I'd like to come back again at another time, in a week or so, and tape
         up some more. Lots of things to ask I'm sure. But I think it's very
         good to take this down on tape, because in the future, when people want
         to know what these early days were like, I think your voice will be a
         good source to tell them. I know that your articles are good, too, but
         it's different you know.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13464</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Grove1</previous>
      <next>Grove3</next>
      <disp_name>Grove2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
