<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/19/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Verna Palmer Hardt, n.d., Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:00:47</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Hardt, Verna Palmer</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker</occupation>
      <birthyear>1905</birthyear>
      <residence>Viola</residence>
      <origin>Grandfather first came to the region with Captain Mullan's Army outfit (c. 1858);
         parents' families both moved from Oregon (1876 and 1880)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fishing"&gt;fishing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mining"&gt;mining&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#CCC"&gt;CCC&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#armed forces"&gt;armed forces&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#post offices"&gt;post offices&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bears"&gt;bears&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Hatter Creek"&gt;Hatter Creek&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#California"&gt;California&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Colfax"&gt;Colfax&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Oregon"&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Washington"&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Canada"&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13465</file_name>
      <mp3>13466.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13466.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Early settlers; Grizzly Camp names after Griswald</title>
            <synopsis>Early settlers. Grizzly Camp named after Griswald.
               Fishing trips to Grizzly Camp, St. Joe, Honey Jones Falls,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>Mining muddied streams; Palouse had sawmill and brick plant; origin of Potlatch's
               name
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mining muddied streams. Palouse had a sawmill and brick
               plant that made jugs, etc. Origin of Potlatch's name.
               Bad logging practices in early years partly remedied
               by CCC's.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Viola Meek's funeral; Meek's sawmill; early businesses in Viola</title>
            <synopsis>Watching a fifty wagon procession come to Viola for
               Meek's funeral. Meek's sawmill. Listing of early
               businesses in Viola. Beasley's girl is killed by the
               tumbling rod at the gristmill. Stecker's boy is accused
               unjustly of burning down the church and schoolhouse.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1080</time>
            <title>Uncle Wes Palmer raised large horse herds for cavalry</title>
            <synopsis>Uncle Wes Palmer raised large horse herds for cavalry
               remounts. Wes and George Hill race to Colfax and back.
               Their hired man borrows her father's team and ruins them
               by forgetting to blanket them.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Wes sells out and moves to Canada</title>
            <synopsis>The pasture in Eastern Washington is fenced up and Wes
               sells out and moves to Canada. The drive across the
               tundra to the Peace River. Wes buys his winter clothes
               at David's and wears them all to avoid paying duty. A
               blizzard blowing when he arrives in Canada.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Wes Palmer and his father Asher Palmer work on Mullan Road for the Army</title>
            <synopsis>Wes Palmer and his father, Asher Palmer, work on the
               Mullan Road for the army. Asher Palmer's eye is kicked
               by a mule and they return home to Missouri. One night
               they camp at Viola and are struck by its beauty and Asher
               Palmer plants some apple seeds.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>1870 family returns west by wagon train to Oregon City; winters at Almota to Colfax
               one day; builds cabins; gets Post Office on Palouse Bridge
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>In 1870 the family returns west by wagon train to Oregon
               City, over winters at Almota and then homesteads at Viola.
               Her father goes from Almota to Colfax one day for the
               mail in the snow. They build two cabins, send for the
               women from Oregon and Asher Palmer gets a full-fledged
               Post Office, Palouse Bridge. Grandma makes an apple
               pie upon her arrival.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Maxwell's maternal grandparents' journey west after Civil War</title>
            <synopsis>The Maxwell's, her maternal grandparents', journey west
               after the Civil War. Their stop in the mid-west is
               ended by grasshoppers and a hard winter. They took an
               immigrant train to San Francisco and boat to Oregon
               City where they stayed for a few years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2880</time>
            <title>Maxwell's came to Colfax for railroads and homestead</title>
            <synopsis>The Maxwell's came to Colfax and cut rails for a couple
               years and then homesteaded near Whalen. Mother's
               schooling and caring for the family when Grandpa Maxwell
               broke his leg.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>A coyote sneaks away with Uncle Wes and Grandfather Palmer's
               breakfast in the night while Wes watches.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A coyote sneaks away with Uncle Wes and Grandfather Palmer's
               breakfast in the night while Wes watches.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Incidents of when Grandpa Maxwell served as orderly in Civil War</title>
            <synopsis>Incidents related of when Grandpa Maxwell served as an
               orderly for General Sherman in the Civil War. Scared
               during a retreat by the army mule. Setting a turpentine
               forest on fire.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>The stage driver, Green Chambers, has a Chinese passenger
               from San Francisco.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The stage driver, Green Chambers, has a Chinese passenger
               from San Francisco.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Chinese man at Grizzly Camp mistakes bear carcass as human;collects gold dust every
               month from miners
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>(continued) At Grizzly Camp the Chinese man mistakes
               the hanging bear carcass for a human and is scared. He
               collects gold dust every month from the Chinese miners.
               Bob Nugent's tale of the pot of gold of the Chinese.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Story of Grandma Maxwell befriending the Native Americans</title>
            <synopsis>Indian scare. Grandma Maxwell and Mrs. Roland not afraid
               and don't go in the fort. Grandma Maxwell's story of
               the Indians befriending them when Grandpa broke his leg.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4200</time>
            <title>Experiences picking beans in later years with an Native American
               friend.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Experiences picking beans in later years with an Indian
               friend.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>Glen and Claude herd cattle on Hatter Creek; she goes out to cattle camp near Elk
               River
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Glenn and Claude(two brothers) herd cattle on Hatter
               Creek. They pick huckleberries, and skin out a lost lamb
               with a pocketknife. She goes out later with her violin
               to the cattle camp near Elk River. The car motor blows
               so they stay a week during which time Verna goes with
               Ranger Stoddard and his daughter to Elk River Falls and
               to install a phone line on Elk Mountain. She and Delva
               Stoddard get food scraps for stock the last day she's
               at Elk River. The Stoddard's well-stocked log cellar.
               The section workers listen to the Palmer band playing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5100</time>
            <title>Fourth of July celebration</title>
            <synopsis>The Fourth of July celebration. Patsy wins the horse
               race, the horses are stolen and Glenn tracks them down.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5340</time>
            <title>Escaping from a fire over Neva Pass with Old Joe, the bull, in the lead</title>
            <synopsis>Escaping from a fire over Neva Pass with Old Joe, the
               bull, in the lead.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Visiting cattle camp with her cousin and encounters with cougars</title>
            <synopsis>Visiting the cattle camp with her cousin. Hearing cougars
               howl. One cougar is chased right through camp. Next
               day one follows in her horse's tracks until right near camp.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>She cuts through Malcolm on the way home several times</title>
            <synopsis>Cutting through Malcolm's on the way home. A week later
               she takes two horses back up to camp. She cuts through
               Malcolm's again.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6120</time>
            <title>Betty starts to run home from near Flannigan Creek and
               Pete takes her time to catch her.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Betty starts to run home from near Flannigan Creek and
               Pete takes her time to catch her.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6300</time>
            <title>Herding cattle on the stubble</title>
            <synopsis>Herding the cattle on the stubble. A badger hole, losing
               two cows on the railroad tracks and one cow dying of bloat.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6480</time>
            <title>Myrtle slashes Mr. Gray's cattle with a knife to save
               them from dying of bloat.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Myrtle slashes Mr. Gray's cattle with a knife to save
               them from dying of bloat.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Stories and proverbs; bears show up near their camp</title>
            <synopsis>Stories and proverbs. A bear shows up near their cabin
               and they shoot it. An ode to the Hoodoo country.
               Another bear shows up near their cabin.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Family adventures, migration and settling. Viola events. Cattle herding
         experiences. Indians. Chinese miners. (Tape recorded by Mrs Hardt for her brother,
         Glen
         Palmer, who was the donor.) no date 2 hr 49p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/4873_lcoh_4873.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13465</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Handlin</previous>
      <next>Hazeltine</next>
      <disp_name>Hardt</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
