<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/25/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Joseph Holland, 1974-07-25, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:03:54</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Holland, Joseph</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Depot agent at Bovill (1925-66); school board chairman; mayor; justice of the
         peace
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1900</birthyear>
      <residence>Bovill</residence>
      <origin>Grew up in South Dakota and Saskatchewan</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumberjacks"&gt;lumberjacks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#CCC"&gt;CCC&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#police officers"&gt;police officers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#funerals"&gt;funerals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#alcohol"&gt;alcohol&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bootlegging"&gt;bootlegging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Prohibition"&gt;Prohibition&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#doctors"&gt;doctors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sheep"&gt;sheep&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Basque"&gt;Basque&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Clarkia"&gt;Clarkia&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Washington"&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13645</file_name>
      <mp3>13646.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13646.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Sketch of his depot work before coming to Bovill in 1925.</title>
            <synopsis>Sketch of his depot work before coming to Bovill in 1925.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>240</time>
            <title>Winters in Bovill; Potlatch horse barn and selling horses when horse logging ended;
               blowing money in town
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Snow and Bovill winters. The Potlatch horse barn; selling off horses when horse logging
               ended. The old-time lumberjacks. Most wintered in Spokane, but returned in the spring;
               blowing money in town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Differences between lumberjacks and railroad "extra gangs"</title>
            <synopsis>The railroad "extra gangs" were a different class than the lumberjack. Joe saved a
               drunk from an extra gang from getting run over.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Work as justice of the peace; letting Ted Collins jump a train; disagreement about
               a body identification
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>As justice of the peace, Joe let Ted Collins jump a train. Later a body in Moscow
               was identified as Ted; but on examination Joe disagreed with the others. Later Ted
               walked into the depot, and was warmly received.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>What happened with the Depression hit the Potlatch Lumber Company in Bovill</title>
            <synopsis>When the Depression hit in 1931, Potlatch Lumber Company "pulled the pin" and most
               people lost their jobs in the Bovill area. Joe was in charge of the relief program.
               The distribution of food and jobs.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1860</time>
            <title>Working on WPA road from Bovill to Elk River; trouble gardening around Bovill; how
               the community kept going during the Depression
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>WPA road work from Bovill to Elk River. The state took over the road to Elk River
               from the Highway District. Difficulty raising gardens around Bovill. Business troubles
               for Groh store ended with the second war. CCC work kept the community going.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Pat Malone's work in Bovill; didn't drink, gave treats to children; going after a
               stolen safe
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Pat Malone's work in Bovill. He spent all his spending money on treats for kids. He
               didn't drink. Pat's favorite story, about catching some desperadoes coming from Clarkia.
               Pat went after the safe stolen from the depot, in a situation that could have been
               dangerous.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Pat Malone thought he would be buried in a pauper's grave; his children still visit
               their father's grave; Pat wanted Joe to give a jail sentence to a man for possession
               of two pints
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Pat was afraid he would be buried in pauper's field, and knew that he was going to
               die when the doctors didn't. Joe raised money in Bovill for a headstone, and his children
               still visit Pat's grave each Memorial Day. Pat had worked in Duluth. Pat wanted Joe
               to give Nick the Greek a jail sentence for possession of two pints, but
               Joe didn't because it would have been his third
               conviction.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Pat was angry at Joe for giving a fine; Pat liked to catch bootleggers</title>
            <synopsis>Pat was angry at Joe for giving Nick a fine instead of jail. Pat delighted in catching
               bootleggers, but wasn't much of a detective.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Drinking was not seen in Bovill during Prohibition; Palouse had a bad reputation</title>
            <synopsis>Drinking was not seen in Bovill during Prohibition. Palouse had quite a reputation
               for saloons from the early days.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Socials were popular during the Depression in Bovill; Sandwiches made from wild meat</title>
            <synopsis>Socials were very popular and enjoyable in Bovill
               during the Depression. Sandwiches were made from wild meat. Nogle, the supervisor,
               got low pay and had little work to do, and few were on the payroll at all.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Charlie Albright died during basketball game and men hauled him through deep snow
               to the hospital; most of Bovill went to the funeral
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Charlie Albright died while playing a basketball game in 1927. The men hauled him
               through deep snow to the hospital, although Dr. Brown didn't tell them he was dead.
               Most of the town took an excursion train to Palouse for the funeral; Elmer Helm, the
               engineer, scared the people by roaring into the station.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>Baseball teams in the area caused a lot of interest; local sports have declined</title>
            <synopsis>Baseball teams in the area aroused much interest, except in Moscow. Local sports have
               declined.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Running for the doctor for a birth in the dead of winter</title>
            <synopsis>When Joe's wife had her baby unexpectedly early, Axel Anderson got the doctor down
               to Bovill from Elk River, in the dead of winter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5520</time>
            <title>Bovill losing it's doctor during the Depression; Potlatch keeping their veterinarian</title>
            <synopsis>When Bovill lost its doctor during the Depression while Potlatch kept their veterinarian,
               folks said "horses are more important than people". The vet was often their
               doctor.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5580</time>
            <title>Axel Anderson hurt in railroad accident; Joe having to work a 25 hour day</title>
            <synopsis>Axel Anderson, the Big Swede, got hurt badly in a
               railroad accident. Joe Buck gave Axel a union retort; Joe once had to work a 25 hour
               day.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6000</time>
            <title>Joe's responsibilities as a depot agent in Bovill</title>
            <synopsis>Joe's responsibilities as depot agent at" Bovill. Getting along well with management
               made his job pleasant. To get a corpse accepted by the baggageman for shipment by
               train, Joe had to sign the supervisor's name.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6600</time>
            <title>Keeping two sets of books for the railroad companies; One of the reasons the Milwaukee
               railroad bought the WI and M
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The Milwaukee and the WI and M ("Will I Make it") had the same policies, but Joe kept
               two sets of books. By buying the WI and M, the Milwaukee gets to ship most of Potlatch's
               timber.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Train loads of sheep that had grazed on Forest Service land were shipped from Bovill
               to Chicago
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Train loads of sheep which had grazed on Forest Service land from June to Labor Day
               were shipped from Bovill to Chicago. Joe was told there were less sheep because there
               were fewer Basque herders.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7080</time>
            <title>Leo Guilfoy tricking Joe's cousin; Leo was a story teller; had to raise his children
               as well as work
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Leo Guilfoy tricked Joe's cousin when he was checking poles. Leo got egg on Buck's
               face for stealing his eggs. People said new stories around Bovill were made up by
               Leo. Leo never seemed to worry, despite having to raise his children in addition to
               working.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Bovill's way of life. Experiences as depot agent and judge. Relief in the
         depression. Lumberjacks and extra gangs. Pat Malone. Leo Guilfoy's humor. 7-25-74
         2 hr
         41p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: A little bit of background on before you came to Bovill. The
         first thing I noticed on that background sheet is that you grew up in
         South Dakota and Saskatchewan. Were your parents homesteading?
         
         JOSEPH HOLLAND: Yes, they were farmers in South Dakota, and then they homesteaded
         in Saskatchewan. Yeah, I was a farm boy until I come to Spokane.
         That was the end of farming.
         
         SAM: Did your whole family leave Saskatchewan?
         
         JH:  Yes, yes. I left just a few months before them, and went back to South
         Dakota for, well, from about July to December. I worked there and then
         I joined them.in Spokane. They came to Spokane, I'd say about in Oct
         ober of that year. Yeah, they sold out. And then, I said on the back-
         ground sheet, went up there at the telegraph school- Spokane Telegraph
         Institute it was called— finished that, and then started working for
         the railroad, Great Northern. I worked right in Spokane for a while,
         right down there on Havermale Island, where the fair now is, in the build
         ing where the tower is left. Oh, I worked quite a few places on the
         Great Northern— Priest River, Newport and west over to Harrington— Oh,
         I never got as far as Wenatehee— Edwall, and Lyons. Well, then the
         next spring there wasn't much work for extra board, and a new man, you
         see, you're on the extra board. So this Inland Empire, which runs be
         tween Spokane, Moscow and Colfax, they needed somebody so I went to work
         for them. I said in there, Iwas cashier and operator different places,
         and relief agent, and wound up in Moscow. I was cashier and operator
         there. Stayed for about two years. And then this job at Bovill came
         up as joint agent, and it was abetter paying job, so Ijust quit and
         took it. The railroad at Moscow was very good about it, too. When I
         was leaving they said, "Well, we moved you in here" they do that, you
         know, your furniture and anything you have- "moved you in here and
         we'll move you out." So I had free transportation of my household
         goods, myself and my family.
         
         Well, that's when Istarted in at Bovill. Oh, things were humming
         there then. The roads into Bovill, in the wintertime, there just wasn't
         anything. The snow covered and they never tried to keep 'em open. Peo
         ple would put their cars up on blocks, oh, sometimes as early as October,
         November, when winter hadn't set in hardly, and they were there until
         the next May or more. Iheard some say that that was apretty good thing,
         they got achance to catch up on their grocery bill, they wasn't spend
         ing so much for gasoline. Left thedepot every time the trains came in,
         which was shortly after noon, one-something, the Milwaukee come up there,
         and the WISH passenger train met. And oh, mail and everything that
         came into the town came on the train. So quite often there was alot of
         people gathered around the depot, that just seemed to be adaily event.
         Gather around there to see the trains come in and go. Two or three dray
         teams backed up against the platform to take the mail, express, and what
         not, deliver it over the town.
         
         The winters there sometimes the snow used to get, oh, real deep. They
         still have snow there, but it's nothing like it was in those days. It
         seems to me, that about, oh, by the fifteenth of December that fence that
         was out in front of the depot- it was agood five and ahalf feet highbut
         that would be covered. The posts would disappear, and you wouldn't
         see them again until March, maybe, when the snow started down. And
         the railroads, it was.quite a job there plowing out the tracks, the
         side tracks^ and we had all kinds of equipment to do it. Sometimes
         three or four engines stalled, snowed in, take one to pull another out.
         They'd get going, oh, they'd get through it. And it was the same every
         winter there for quite a while, and then finally the winters wasn't
         quite so severe, less snow.
         
         'Course, sometimes the logging company would be down for a few
         months in the winter, in those days. But now it's kind of reversed: they
         log now in the winter, but spring come, then they have their layoff for
         maybe a couple of months. Things are wet in the woods. Those days it
         was all horse logging. Potlatch Lumber Company, which it was called
         at the time, they had oh two or three huge barns across the meadow
         from the depot where they would keep their horses when they were not
         working. And they never had a horse that wouldn't weigh at least a ton,
         and a lot of them weighing twenty-one, twenty-two hundred pounds. Big
         horses. But I guess it takes big horses to do heavy work in the woods.
         Yeah, then all at once there was no more horses, they started using
         cats. They sold those horses as they could. Some of the farmers from
         around the country would come in and buy 'em. I think they said they
         had two hundred sixty head there at one time, just wintering. That's
         a lot of horses. Took a fair sized crew of men to just take care of
         'em. But then they'd do anything to get rid of them. They'd sell 'em
         for whatever people wanted to give, and then some even they shipped,
         loaded them in stock cars and shipped 'em to Portland, I think it was,
         where they would be slaughtered, and I don't know what they would be
         used for. They used to say they were going to the glue factory.
         
         SAM:  Did many of the lumberjacks winter over?
         
         JH:  A lot of them would come to Spokane. This was kind of their headquar
         ters, see. A lot of the single lumberjacks would come to Spokane. Of
         course the family people and then some of the others would remain there
         in Bovill in a shack or two, you know. Out on the edges of town they
         would be shacking up, different ones, just waiting for spring. But
         the big majority of those single men, they'd hike out to Spokane. But
         they always kept in touch, and next spring when it opened, they'd be
         back.
         
         SAM:  So they really had a lot of continuity from one year to the other, a
         lot of the same people would be coming back in.
         
         JH:  Oh, yes. Yeah, they did. Well, the foAan and the superintendent
         and all of them, you know, they get to know certain lumberjacks, and
         they know they can do the work. They like 'em, and they like to have
         em. Old lumberjack is a lumberjack and they just don't make 'em
         anymore! No, there's no lumberjacks, because they were the single
         men, and for quite a number of years now, the woods work is done by
         young married people who drive their cars to work and whatnot. Drive
         as close as they can to the work. But oh, yeah, those old fellas— a
         lot of them were sawyers, that's when they used crosscut saws, one
         on each end of it. That's a thing of the past too. Trees are all
         felled now by power saws. So that element in the woods isn't there..
         any more. One young fella with a power saw'11 knock down more trees
         in a half a day than, why, I don't know how many good men with hand
         saws could do in three or four days. There's just that much differ
         ence.
         
         SAM:  Was being tough, being able to get out there and take it and put in a
         real long day's work, was that really important to the lumberjacks
         themselves?
         
         JH:  OH, I don't think so, you know. No. The weather was never that bad.
         You worked long hours, but when you go back—well, we're going back
         about forty-nine years now, seeing I came to Bovill in 1925— every
         body worked long hours. Even when I left the depot at Moscow, I
         was working ten hours a day. When I went to Bovill, however, it was
         eight hours, and the eight hour day in the woods was coming in. Oh,
         they worked long hours. A lot of them, you see, sawyers, and more
         than sawyers, it was so much a foot, so much a thousand. So
         they didn't mind the long hours, 'cause the more they worked, the more
         they made. There would always be a considerable percentage of the
         group that was on hourly pay, pretty small pay too. then, about oh
         thirty-two and a half cents an hour was probably a pretty good pay
         then. And a lot of the extra gangs on the railroad was only twenty five
         cents an hour. No, it didn't take any super person physically.
         Of course, doing that kind of work, you know, you get used to it and
         put out a lot of work, eat heavy.
         
         Those old lumberjacks, for the most of them, they could stay in
         the woods just about so long and then they had to get out of there.
         They'd get what they call that, some kind of afever, (Chuckles) not
         that they were sick, but they had to get out and go tq town, in some
         place where they could call "Timber". Of course, in those days when I
         went there it was Prohibition, so there wasn't any place around there
         that they could do that. I guess maybe that's what attracted some of
         them to Spokane in the winter. (Chuckles) Oh, yeah, the lumberjack
         would have a pretty good stake and go to town and go broke. And if
         he was known he could borrow quite a little bit. And then after he
         spent that, well then he was ready to go back to work. And the same
         thing over and over and over. They were regarded as pretty honorable
         men. There didn't seem to be any bad ones at all. They were good,
         help everybody they could. Well, Inever worked aday in the woods.
         I heard lots of things about 'em, you know. Some of them would darn
         their socks when they started to wear out at the heel, they'd roll
         it a little ways, and when that wore, roll it again, roll it, and keep
         rolling it until finally it would cut right in two. Well, then they'd
         have to get a new pair of socks. Now they would do that, but then
         still when they'd.go to town, money was nothing. Free, timber, (Chu
         ckles)want to treat everybody. And there were really no fights started
         amongst the lumberjacks, they didn't do that.
         
         Those extra gangs they used to have on the railroad though, that
         was a little different. About every year there'd be an extra gang
         come up, and they'd have their own cars on the railroad, bunk cars,
         probably about a hundred men in the camp. And they would renew ties,
         that was their main work. But they picked those up from everywhere,
         you know, get 'em fresh out of jail or whatnot, to just go out there
         for twenty-five cents an hour. But they did get their board, bed and
         a place to sleep. Oh, they were coming and going all the time. But
         some of these were pretty rough characters. (Chuckles) There was one
         of them, I looked out the window of the depot one time, and I seen
         him laying with his head across the rail up near the water tank, and
         there was a train coming pretty soon. So I hiked up there and it wasn t
         too far. He was dead drunk, and I pulled him off the rails, pulled him
         off by the feet, and he woke up a little bit, and I told him, I says,
         "Fella you got your neck right over that rail", I says, "there's a
         train coming along here right pretty quick that'll just cut your head
         off!" "Oh," he said, "that'd be all right." And I think ke meant it!
         (Chuckles) Well, I dragged him around back of the water tank, and then
         it seemed like he kinda went back to sleep and I went to the depot.
         Kept my eyes peeled, and it was only five minutes or so till the train
         came. And they couldn't have stopped.
         
         Yeah, that was a different class. They were a different class of
         people altogether than the ones in the woods. They were honorable men,
         the lumberjacks. But when the old crop retired, died off, there just
         isn't any more of them. And old Pat Malone, he probably knew every
         one of them. Superintendent there Nogle, C. G. Nogle, he knew a lot
         of them personally, and liked 'em. He knew they'd break loose once in
         a while and go on an awful drunk, but anyway you'd get 'em back in the
         woods, they were good men. So he went along with them.
         There was one oldtimer there, Ted Collins. He was a lumberjack.
         He decided to leave Bovill, and they'd had him in jail there for a
         while, more or less to sober him up. Well I was justice of the peace,
         and I used to hold court right in the depot, and that time I did. And
         it was Ted, just for being drunk. And he was looking out the window
         and there was a train going by with log flats. And he said, "If I was
         free," he said, "I'd go right out there and jump on one of those log
         flats and get out of here." I said, "Is that what you want to do, Ted?"
         "Yes." I said, "Go right ahead." He said, "You mean I'm free to do
         that?" I said, "Go right ahead, if that's what you want to do." And
         he did. You couldn't do a thing, he didn't have a dime, you know, no
         need to fine him, no need to put him back in jail. All he done was
         being dfcunk, he didn't harm anybody here. And he was gone for quite-a
         while, I don't know where he went to. But oh, it must have been a year
         afterwards, in Moscow, they found a man dead in a box car. We had a
         few people that had lived in Bovill, that then was in Moscow, and one
         of them identified that man as Ted Collins. They said, "That's Ted."
         Well, then when that was the case, they asked some of us at Bovill if
         we would come down and see what we thought. '- Well. I was surprised,
         there were quite a few knew him much better and longer than I did,
         they said, "yeah, that's Ted Collins.". But Imyself couldn't see it.
         Well first of all, when Iwent over there, Howard Short was gone, but
         his wife was there. It was at night, but she said, "We got the body
         down in the basement, and we can go down and see him. And Ilooked
         at him, and I'd look from one angle and it was just adead ringer for
         him, and you go around the other side and it wasn't. And Iasked her
         if she had atape measure there, she said, "Yeah." So we measured
         him, and he wasn't near as tall as Ihad figured this Ted Collins to
         be. So they had, you say- alittle something there, you know, if you
         thought it was Ted Collins, or if you knew who it was. Well, Iwrote
         down, "I don't know who it is, but I'm satisfied it's not Ted Collins."
         Well, another year or so went by, and by gosh here old Ted Collins
         rolls off of aflat car, walked in the depot. (Chuckles) Iwasn't
         too surprised because Iwas satisfied in my own mind that that wasn't
         Ted Collins that was buried in Moscow. And I told him, "Well," I says,
         Ted, you've been dead now for, oh, let's see(I don't know whether it
         was one or two years), one or two years." "Oh," he said, "where did
         they bury me?" "Moscow1.' "Well, well, well," he said, "I ought to be
         good for a meal then." I said, "You bet you will be!" And, I said,
         "You just go over to Mrs. Watts," she was running the restaurant, and
         I said, "you'll get a meal." And she was so glad to see him that she
         just kept him there, working around, bull cooking. He stayed there for
         a long, long time.
         
         SAM:  Sounds like dying was one of the best things that ever happened to him.
         
         JH:  Yeah, yeah, but, you know, one more detail about examining him, his
         clothes— he had different clothes, you know, than a lumberjack would
         have, like light shoes, and little rolled black, cotton socks. Well,
         lumberjacks, you know, they got generally wool socks and the wool pants
         ans whatnot. So his clothing didn't check out to me either. And then
         when Imeasured him for height, and Iasked about that, too: "Now that
         this man is dead, how tall would he be if he was living?" They said,
         "Taller, laying on that slab. But the way we're measuring him, he'd
         be taller than if he was walking around." So that was the last con
         vincing point to me. Oh, yeah. Well there was alot of those old
         fellas that way.
         
         SAM:  Like Ted?
         
         JH:  Oh, yeah. Yeah. Ted was probably one of the most likable ones.though.
         He was happy-go-lucky. He didn't bother anybody. But he never wanted
         to sober up. He'd get drunk, and he wanted to stay that way. But
         then they always said when he got in the woods he was as good aman
         as they had, and drinking didn't bother hto at all, until he'd come to
         town again. Ithink he was ateamster, I'm quite sure he was. They
         used to have lots of teamsters, you know. Oh, yeah, there's lots of
         other characters, you know, but you haven't thought of them for awhile,
         then it skips your mind. But the woods was full of them. Of course,
         that Depression come along then. The outfit shut down, oh Idon't
         know exactly, but Isuppose '31, and it didn't turn awheel for prob
         ably ayear and ahalf or more. It was probably about '31 when they
         pulled the pin. Oh, alot of people moved away then. Things was pret
         ty hard. There was no unemployment compensation, you know, no social
         security, that's all ahead of that. They didn't have adime, and peo
         ple, generally speaking, didn't save ahead. They would always, most
         of them, be good at the grocery store for sixty, ninety days or more
         credit. But then that was running out, and this was different, you
         know, when the company pulled the pin, it was early in the fall, early.
         It wasn't for winter coming on, so it was a different deal.
         
         That was pretty tough going there! however, people seemed to en-
         joy living, though. Nobody had a dime. I was fortunate in having
         the job that I did have. Before that I had a cashier and a ware
         house man, but the business was down so bad that they laid both of
         those of, and I was running the job alone. But, as I say, I was very
         fortunate to have been on the payroll all the time. And there were
         a few that were— the school teachers, and a few people that were tak
         ing care of the horses, and you about had it. Oh, yeah, there was a
         few on the railroad— the section foreman, a couple of men. But it
         was looking pretty black then. I know how it was, because I guess it
         was because I had a job that they made me relief director. Only had
         a limited amount of money, very little, to keep the town going. And
         you'd just about have to go into everybody's house to talk to them and
         see what you could do; to see, you know, maybe they had some canned
         fruit or something that another family didn't have. Well, you wouldn't
         ask them to share, but then you knew better how to distribute the
         money, trying to keep everybody alive. So it was about the most re
         warding work I believe I ever had, for self-satisfaction, I really
         think it was. Yeah.
         
         SAM:  How did it work out? How did you manage to distribute, things?
         
         JH:  Well, we formed a committee, of course, and listed everybody in town.
         And then we'd have so much money, and there was a little work, you see,
         WPA. But they were, oh I don't know, slow in getting that going; but
         when that got going then, well, like Bovill would be allocated so
         much money a month for this work. And then they'd have to say people
         with the larger family— like some of them would have as many as six
         kids— well a man like that, he'd have to work more days. Maybe he'd
         work four days a week out of the six. And then somebody that maybe
         it was just a man and wife, wel] two days at the most. There wasn't
         too many single men, they got out of there. The ones that didn't kind
         had to work for themselves. But they mostly got out of there, I don't
         know where they went to, up here,AI guess. But that's the way you had
         to kind of divide it, you know, to try to keep everybody alive.
         We coui(in't set it up "anything, it'd have to be approved. But what
         we done was road work, grading and whatnot. Our work there was mostly
         between Bovill and Elk River. 'Course, it didn't go clear to Elk River;
         went out there about seven miles. Oh, it was kind of bad. We didn't
         have anything to work with. But Potlatch Lumber Company was very good
         on loaning us their equipment without charge. Then they would have
         scrapers, you know, and they'd have picks and axes and crosscut saws
         and peaveys and shovels. It was more or less hand work. Anybody that
         had a team, we had them working hauling rock in a little old wagon of
         some kind, and some on the scrapersj but well, we got something done
         anyhow. But the jobs were manufactured, you know, just because we had
         to get some money to people and that was one way of them working for it.
         In our case the road work that we done worked out pretty good because,
         well, we had some real good men, see. Some of them that worked in the
         woods, they could do about most anything. They'd build a bridge just
         out you know, the fallen timber, trim it— they knew just how to go
         at it.
         
         And we did get enough rock on that road. It was a problem with
         the highway district, and I was secretary-treasurer of that Highway
         District Number Four, and I know how short they were on money. They
         owed bonds. They couldn't hardly pay the interest, so we didn't have
         any money, and we had to maintain that road. But through this work we
         got the road widened enough and a little sprinkling of rock on it to a
         point where the state then accepted the road as part of the state system.
         Well that relieved us, the highway district, from maintaining it,
         which was a big thing for us as the highway district. Quite helpful
         moneywise. And then the state, kind of piecemeal, they would extend
         it a couple of miles or so. I think now, I haven't been over it just
         lately, but I believe it's fair road all the way through.
         
         SAM:  This is the Bovill to Elk River road?
         
         JH:  Yes.
         
         SAM:  It's pretty good now?
         
         JH:  Is it all hardtop?
         
         SAM:  No, not yet. But it would seem to me that it would be harder maybe in
         a place like Bovill than in a farming area where you got all your pro
         duce pretty much right to hand on the farms, and everybody's growing
         his garden. It may be harder for food purposes in Bovill.
         
         JH:  Oh, yes, Bovill, you see, they didn't That's turned off isn't it?
         
         SAM:  No, it's still on.
         
         JH:  It's still going. No, Bovill was a poor place to raise any food, you
         . know. I don't know, it isn't all that high; it's high, but it's only
         about ten miles down there to Deary and they can raise about anything
         they wanted to. But Bovill, it's the nights that were so cold. Oh,
         you couldn't think of growing potatoes, never, or tomatoes. In the
         late years, some of them seemed to raise strawberries, but for a long
         time there, nobody tried to raise strawberries. So there wasn't much
         gardening going on, little bit, but very little. And you might say
         no farming at all. A couple of places on the edges of town maybe raised
         a little oats or hay or something like that.
         
         SAM:  Do you know how the merchants did in Bovill during the Depression?
         
         JH:  Oh, they didn't do good at all, and eventually they had to close up.
         Generally speaking, no, they'd get behind on the taxes, you know, they
         couldn't pay the taxes, and most of them went out of business. There
         was one store there though, the John Groh store. They were in real
         bad shape, real bad financially. And John Groh passed away, then his
         wife took over, hung on for a while. Oh, she was threatened there, too
         with the county tax collector— they'd have to do something, they'd
         have to take the property or something for the taxes— but they held
         off for a while, and then they got out far enough to where business
         started to pick up a little bit. And that war scare in Europe, of
         course, that must have been in '39, I guess— things started picking
         up pretty well from there on, and then, of course. we got into World
         War II, and you could sell anything you had. So that one place came
         out of it in good shape, but the others more or less went out of
         business.
         
         SAM:  Did most of the families hang on until the Potlatch started up again?
         
         JH:  Yeah. Well, during that period a lot of them worked in the CCC's,
         that was
         
         SAM:  Civilian Conservation Corps?
         
         JH:  That's right, that's right. So a lot of them, especially anybody that
         worked in a supervisory capacity, such as foreman or assistant foreman
         or anything like that , it was easy for them to get on in the CCC's
         as foremen. So a lot of them got pretty fair jobs, well, you know,
         fair as of the time. And then the others also got on as just laborers.
         So the town was pretty well taken up with just CCC's. And over the
         spell— I don't know how long it lasted— a year and a half or whatever
         it was before the lumber company went back to work. So there were
         some people that of course moved away, quite a few of them moved
         away and never came back. But, generally speaking, there was a lot of
         them that stayed there and stuck it out and ,come out all right. Yes,
         it was a bad period. I hope it never happens again. Sometimes you
         never know.
         
         SAM:  Well, to look at some more pleasant things. Could you tell me what
         you remember about Pat Malone?
         
         JH:  Well, Old Pat, everybody in town loved him, you know, generally speak
         ing. I don't know how long he'd been on the sheriff's force because he
         was on there when I came, but I think it was quite a number of years
         before that. He was deputy sheriff, and he had all the authority, the
         arresting authority, that any deputy sheriff would have; however, he
         was situated there in Bovill to report things of course that he fig
         ured should be reported to the sheriff's office in Moscow. That was
         mostly, I suppose, Pat's work, because he didn't make too many arrests,
         some. If he did, generally speaking, it would be somebody that got a
         little too drunk. But he lived there in the Spokane Hotel. Dave El
         lison and his wife, Sophie, run the hotel, and Old Pat lived right
         there, both sleeping and eating. And the county paid him just a tok
         en amount. At one time, I know, it was thirty dollars a month, but he
         did have his board and room. So Old Pat, with that thirty dollars,
         as long as it would last, he'd be treating the kids going by, ice cream
         cone or pop or something, till the thirty would be gone, and then he'd
         be broke for the rest of the month. But he didn't need any money, be
         cause he had a place to eat and sleep. But he'd sit there in the win
         dow with his corncob pipe in his mouth. Well that was something,
         there was the law enforcement agent. It helped, I know it helped.
         The county was lucky to have him there. But Old Pat could tell some
         tall tales about things that happened in his life. All amusing and
         well, could have happened. He was a big man, and I'll bet you when
         he was young there wasn't too many that wanted to tangle with him either
         Of course when I even first knew him, he was getting old. Oh yeah
         he was death on bootleggers, moonshiners. That seemed to be his main
         line of work during the Prohibition period. Oh., yeah, they used to
         pull tricks on him too. But generally speaking, Pat was well liked
         by everybody. Nobody took him too serious. But he was all right,
         he was well worth the little it cost to keep him there.
         
         SAM:  When you say playing tricks on Pat, was there any kind of practical
         jokes or....
         
         JH:  Oh. yeah, but Idon't know, those better stay like they are, I think.
         (Chuckles) Yeah. No, as to my knowledge Pat didn't drink. Idare
         say that he did when he was younger, but in my time knowing him, I
         never knew him to drink. But I suppose he did in his younger years.
         Oh, every once in awhile, you know, he'd get acall from Moscow to
         look out for somebody, and he got a little work like that. I know
         there was something or other in the area; Idon't know just what hap
         pened there, but they were watching for somebody, and Old Pat was down
         on the highway at Helmer this night when the family and I was coming
         home, and stopped me. But he was stopping all cars. And of course
         as soon as he'd look in the car and know who you were, "Okay!" Well,
         that was a job for him. I forget just what that was.
         
         SAM:  Can you remember any of the tall tales that Pat used to tell?
         
         JH:  Oh, the one that he used to tell me, it seemed about every year or so
         he'd come over and tell me the same story. Of course, Iknow that
         he'd forgot that he'd said it. Idon't know the start of this either,
         but there were two desperadoes, and he got word they were coming from
         Clarkia on the passenger train, and he was over there. But they jumped
         off on the opposite side of the train and started across the meadow.
         And by the time he got around to the end of the car they were running,
         and he said he took ashot at one. And he said, "I'm pretty sure hit
         him. But Ididn't get him though, because by the time I got over there
         he was gone and the other fella was gone. But Iknow Ihit him. Yep.
         Iknow Ihit him!" But it was along story. Old Pat, he'd tell me
         the details of what he'd done. It kind of slipped my mind, because,
         well, while I'd be listening I'd be doing my own work at the same time.
         And I'd think, you know, well it's about time for Old Pat to come
         over and tell me that same story again, and sure enough.(Chuckles!
         But Inever let on to him that I'd ever heard it before. It was all
         news to me. Then when he'd get through, he'd get up, go out, back on
         the job. Well, his job was sitting there in that hotel. Had abig
         window there, set right in there in one of those leather rocking chairs.
         No, that's the one Iremember him telling about.
         
         Well, this was the truth, about the Oh of course, that time- 
         time the safe was old Pete Caldwell, the
         conductor woke him up, told him. The first thing he'd do was put that
         corncob in his mouth, of course, and get his shoes tied. And this was
         in June, and Pete Caldwell stayed there while Pat was getting dressed,
         and Old Pat said, "I'll be jeepers if there was just afresh snow." But
         there wasn't. But then, he called me and he called Sam Peterson, the
         banker. Idon't know why he called him but he did, and by the time I
         got uown to the depot Sam was down there too, and Old-Pat. Vou could
         see what happened. These people broke that window out, and they broke it
         out completely, took it out, so it just looked like aclean window in
         stead of abroken window. Inside, the doors all opened from the inside.
         This safe, it weighed 1,350 pounds Ibelieve is what the safe weighed.
         And it had casters on it, and they rolled it out, out on the platform,
         and they got apush car from the tool house, and with the gangplank just
         rolled this onto the pushcar and pushed it down the WUM, which was a
         little bit down grade. Well Old Pat guessed that that's where they'd
         had to have've gone  was no motor or anything
         to push it by hand, but slightly down grade
         they could do that. So then, well, better get the section boss. His
         name was Charlie Eller. But Charlie Eller had to get the car out and
         go down there. Well then, Charlie, he had to call his whole crew. He
         had about four men, laborers; he had to get them out. This was probably
         about three in the morning. And so he got to going, and Old Pat sat
         right on the front with the flashlight and the gun drawn, going down
         through those cuts. And here was the safe, oh two and a half miles
         down, I suppose. They'd rolled it off the side and blew it. There wasn't
         much money in it. There was express money orders, but in blowing it
         the explosion burnt the money orders, so they didn't try to take those
         at all. Otherwise I think, they would have, and tried to pass 'em,
         but (there was) a little burnt mark right along the edge of all of 'em,
         so they left those. they just took what cash was there, they didn't
         take any checks. The car tickets was blown up in trees for twenty-five
         feet or more. We recovered most of the tickets; that was no loss, any
         way. But by shaking trees for a couple of days afterwards you could
         get more tickets down. I believe there was very few tickets lost. No,
         we didn't see anything of any men.
         
         SAM:  Did Pat have his gun drawn all the way down?
         
         JH:  Oh. yes, he sat right on the front of the gas car with his gun drawn
         all the way down. Oh, it'd a been so easy if they had a been bad nen
         and wanted to kill all of us, they could have done it, we was just sit
         ting ducks, going down through those cuts with trees on each side. One
         side.anyway was all trees. Oh, I never thought at the time how danger
         ous it was, but afterwards I sized it up—my lord!I Oh, there for two
         or three nights there, gangs of us organized a watch out around the edge
         of town, if those fella^ be coming back in, because they'd have to get
         somewhere for food. But nobody showed up. But Pat thought— I think
         this was over near Park, there was a schoolhouse over there, and I
         think Pat was with some of the sheriff's force that kind of had a lead
         over there. And there was somebody, I guess, running across a field,
         and again Old Pat said he took a shot,(Chuckles) but he didn't get him.
         He was too far. "But I think I hit him", he said. "I think I hit him."
         Yeah. So that was one experience I had with Pat. Oh, they always said 
         he had a lot of grit. But there was a lot of foolishness there too, I
         could see afterwards, the way we done that job.
         
         SAM:  I wonder if Pat was drinking and keeping it from ya. I mean, I wonder,
         'cause I hear a number of stories that make it sound like if he wasn't
         drinking, he sure was letting his friends get away with it.
         
         JH:  Yeah. Oh yeah, there was stories, you know, too, about Pat doing his
         share of drinking, but, as I say, I never seen it, I never seen any ef
         fects on him. But I didn't see him all the time either. Sure, I'd see
         him every day.
         
         SAM:  One story I can still remember, somebody told me when these medine shows
         came through, one of the jokes, they said is, "What's an island?" The
         answer is, "The city marshall surrounded by a keg of booze." (Laughs)
         Yeah. I think Pat for a while there, that's kind of before my time
         too, he was I guess kind of city marshall as well. I think the village
         may have paid h*mr something. But that wasn't the case when I was
         there, he was strictly county.
         
         SAM:  Would you tell me about the last time that you saw him?
         
         JH:  Oh yes, that time I didn't know that he was even sick. But oh, it was
         along about eleven o'clock in the forenoon, and Mrs. Elison called me
         at the depot, Would Istop and see Pat on my way home for lunch? And I
         yes, and I did. I went into that little room where he stayed and he
         was in bed, and half crying. And all that was on his mind was he didn't
         want to be buried in pauper's field. And that's just the way he'd say
         it. "I don't want to be buried in pauper's field." Well, I assured
         him that that would never happen. And he questioned me a little bit
         about it, "You're sure about it?" "Oh, yes," I'd say, "that'll never
         happen, Pat." Well then he felt better, and he threw the covers back
         and he sat on the edge of the bed. It seemed to me he felt a good deal 
         better, he was relieved of something he'd been worrying about.
         Well, when I got home, which was only a few minutes, I called the
         sheriff's office in Moscow, and told them about talking with Old Pat,
         and he was sick and in bed. So they said, "Well, we'll send a car up
         and get him." And they did. And when they had him in the car and start
         ed out of town, he told them, he said, "That's my last trip up that hill,"
         the grade going out of Bovill toward Deary, "my last trip up that hill."
         Well the next day I called the sheriff's office to see how Pat was. And
         said, "Well, the doctors can't find a thing wrong with himi All he
         needs is a little hospitalization, and we'll keep him here for a day or
         two. He'll be all right." Well, that would have been on Saturday*- it
         was Friday that they took him over, and this was Saturday. And then
         Sunday the family and I went to Lewiston to the Lewiston Roundup and
         there was another couple with us. I told them I wanted to go home through
         Moscow, I wanted to see how Old Pat was. Okay, and so we went back through
         Moscow, arrived there I suppose eight o'clock or such. And Old Pat was
         dead. He had died. So I guess he knew more about it than the doctors.
         He knew that was his last trip up that hill, and they didn't know it.
         So he had a nice funeral in Moscow where he's buried. And then a
         little later I circulated a petition around amongst his friends in Bovill
         for a headstone, and got a price on one from Sturdevant in Moscow. I
         figured out the people in Bovill that would give toward it, and come down
         and figured out if I could get five dollars,apiece from the ones that I
         thought I could, that would be enough. And with one exception, everybody
         that I contacted said, "Yes, glad to." They gave me five dollars. And
         there was one fella that said, "Well, now, if you don't get enough, come
         back and I'll give you more." That was Dave Elison. But we got enough
         on the first run, and so he has a headstone today.
         My kids, oh. they thought alot of Old Pat. And every Memorial
         Day when we go to the eatery, after we've taken care of the two graves
         we have there of the family, the next place they head for is Old Pat's,
         put some flowers on Omlad Ppaatt-'s« egrraavvee.. S»o he's well remembered by a lot
         of people. Oh, Ithink Old Pat was honest enough and he done his job.
         However, it was in his way, that was the way it had to be! It'd have
         to be in his own way. Ithink he had been apoliceman earlier in life,
         well for short time in New York City, but then again, in where?
         
         SAM:  Was it Duluth?
         
         JH:  Duluth, Duluth, absolutely.
         
         SAM:  That's what I heard.
         
         JH:  That's it. Duluth, Duluth, Minnesota. Yeah, he worked there for quite
         awhile, I guess. Well at that time, Ithink, there was probably log
         ging around Duluth. I'm quite sure there was lumbering and logging in
         there. Ikind of think he attached to that and maybe that's why he drift
         ed West. Icertainly did know, but Idon't remember now what got him
         out West. That's right, I'm glad you said that.
         
         SAM:  I've heard it from acouple of people. I've heard other places, too,,
         but Duluth is the one.
         
         JH:  Yeah, yeah, Iguess he was probably there for quite awhile, because he
         talked a lot about Duluth.
         
         SAM:  What about the time you mentioned to when you was justice of the peace
         there and wasn't tough enough for Pat's liking?
         
         JH:  Oh yeah. There was one time there. This Nick the Greek, they called
         him, he was bootlegging. He wasn't moonshining, but he was bootlegging,
         Pat was trying to catch him, and he'd had a couple of raps before
         that for bootlegging. And this time Old Pat searched his little cabin
         where he was staying, shack, whatever you want to call it, from floor
         to top, and he came up with two half pints of moonshine. That's all he
         could find in Nick's place, but then he took him for that, for possess
         ion. That was the law too possession or transportation or manufact
         uring, any of that was unlawful— but this was for possession. There
         was only two half pints, and, well, I could see that Prohibition was
         just about to be repealed, and it was not too long afterwards, so I
         didn't feel too strongly about it then. But yes, Old Pat wanted me to
         give that Greek a jail sentence, and that would have been his third time,
         and that would have been pretty severe
         
         SAM:  So pat wanted you to give him a jail sentence.
         
         JH:  Yeah, Pat wanted me to Jive him a jail sentence, and that would be the
         third time for him, and he'd get quite a jolt. But I couldn't see it
         that way for only two half pints. I think I gave Nick his choice of a
         fine or jail sentence, and I think I said fifty dollars a half a pint,
         and that would have been a hundred dollars, because he had two half
         pints, or fifty days in jail for each half pint, and that'd have been
         a hundred days. Well Iwas pretty sure that Nick had the money, and I
         wasn't wrong on that. Well, he elected to pay the fine. And Old Pat
         was shaking his head all the time. (Laughs) He didn't like that.
         And Nick says, "Well, Ihaven't got the money on me." "No," I said, "I
         didn't expect you to, but you can get it surely." "Well," he says, "can
         I go and get it?" I said, "Sure, go and get the money." Why it was no
         time, an hour, and he was back with the money. But Old Pat, he cussed
         a little bit under his breath as he was going out the door. No, he didn't
         like that. (Chuckles) He wanted that guy to go to jail. But this fella,
         he wasn't a bad guy at all. Sure, he was selling a little moonshine, but
         he wasn't selling it to kids or anybody like that. And I knew in my own
         mind that it was going to be legal in just a short time. But no, Pat
         was disgusted with me there for a while. He didn't visit with me very
         much for a little while after that, but it wasn't long till he got over
         it. And he never talked about it again. No, he was just as friendly
         to me afterwards as before.
         
         SAM:  Did Pat go after many moonshiners, do you think? Or were the guys left
         pretty much alone unless they sort of got in his way?
         
         JH:  No, it was the other way around. It seemed to me that Old Pat liked to
         go after em. That was one thing that it seemed that he liked to do.
         Well, he thought he was a pretty good detective himself, you know, but
         (Chuckles) really he'd have to have a fresh snow. I think that's where
         Pat did pretty good. And he was pretty good at scaring some of them, too;
         whether he scared them or not would be another thing, but he'd always
         think he scared them out. (Chuckles) Well I don't know, oh I suppose
         he got a moonshiner or two in his life, but mostly he was for bootleg
         ging, it'd be bottle men you'd see around, selling. To catch a moon
         shiner you'd have to get out in the woods some place, you know, where
         they had a cabin or something like that. See a lot of smoke, heavy smoke,
         coming out of a chimney for a long period of time, you'd know that some
         body in there was brewing something, cooking that mash. Yeah. No, it
         always seemed to me and others too there, that that was one of Pat's.de
         lights. If he could really catch a good moonshiner or bootlegger, that
         was something he liked to do.
         
         SAM:  I suppose that everybody knew him so well they'd just stay out of his
         way, if that was their business.
         
         JH:  Oh yes, and oh, some of them said they could follow right behind him
         if they'd see where Pat was going, then they-could walk behind, (Laughs)
         that he never looked back. I don't know, oh you'd hear things like that,
         you know, make fun of him.
         
         SAM: Well, did you see much of it in town? You say that when the lumberjacks
         came into town it was often to get drunk, these guys coming out of camp.
         Did you see much of it?
         
         I, No, you see Ididn't because, well, there was no places of business in
         town that you could do it. Oh the poolhalls, there was acouple of
         them, soft drinks and pool tables, card games, but oh they wouldn't
         allow it at all, you know. It was quite apenalty, you know, you could
         shut 'em up and put '«. out of business. No, it was never allowed in
         those places, you didn't see it in there. Ithink really the talk about
         the lumberjacks and going to town and getting drunk was before Prohib
         ition. Sure you'd see it at one time, there^W of saloons in Bovill.
         Inever seen it, it was out when Icame there. In those days that's
         what would happen, and every other little town would be the same way.
         Palouse was quite aplace they said, Iworked at Palouse for awhile
         for the railroad. That along Main Street right from the Northern Pacific
         Depot, up and back, and Idon't know how many saloons, something like,
         oh gosh, twenty or more, twenty-seven I believe they said at one time.
         If you made the rounds, the depot up to the end of the street and back
         down. But Palouse was akind of jumping-off place too at one time for
         the railroad. And that's where you get the railroad to go up the WIM
         to the logging country, you see, Bovill. But no, Inever seen the ^
         lumberjacks doing that, I've only heard of it. And I'm sure it's true.
         Oh and you'd see one just like Imentioned about Ted Collins- sure you'd
         see ted, he'd be drunk around sometimes because of alittle moonshine
         that he'd ^et from somebody. Have it ditched somewhere, you know, out,
         but not in the places, no. You wouldn't see them drinking it.
         
         SAM:  Was there much social life in Boville in the '20's when you first came?
         
         JH:  Oh yes, oh yes, they had amoving picture show there, they had shows oh
         three nights aweek, Isuppose. And then the upstairs part was adance
         floor, dances, two or three every month. Card parties. Oh yes, the
         social life there- and even during that Depression the social life was
         probably better than at any other time. They'd have dances there- as
         Isay, nobody had adime, you know, so the music would be volunteers. I (
         know we had one superintendent of schools that played the violin, some
         one else played something else, my wife played the piano, and it was all
         for free. And then for lunch oh people would bring little things they
         could sandwich, you know. You see there was quite alot of wild game
         around that area, deer and elk. There was alot of meat come in there
         that way. You could make up sandwiches you know with that pretty good,
         (Chuckles) you could grind it up, well little things like that. And
         then they would pass the hat, and everybody knew now, "If you don't have
         anickel, for Godsake, don't use your last nickel to put in." It was
         just to buy coffee, that was the only thing, that was the only expense,
         was to buy the coffee. Oh they had good times, good times. And then
         some you see was making home brew, and you would go to ahouse and have
         abottle of beer. Yeah, I'd say the social life during that Depression...
         And then the people stayed together better, you know. Oh before that
         some of them you know that had cars would go to Moscow, to shows or some
         thing like that; that depression come along, you didn't have that kind
         of money, you know, to drive cars. So they stayed at home and made their
         own entertainment. It was good. I've heard alot of people talk about
         that afterwards, that really, socially, that was the best times of their
         life right there, during that depression. Well you know they always
         say, "Misery likes company." Well maybe that isn't agood definition,
         but just about everybody was broke is what I'm trying to get at. So
         the guy next to you was no different. Idon't know, you could count
         the people on the payroll there on your two hands, Iknow, because the
         school teachers and myself and afew people working, taking cere of the
         horses, that was about it. Even the superintendent Sogle, they put him
         down on such alow wage, he told me, "I wouldn't miss it if Inever got
         it at all." But it was down and you could see the company didn't know 
         if they'd ever get going again.
         
         SAM:  What was Nogle doing then?
         
         JH:  He was superintendent.
         
         SAM:  Same thing.
         
         JH:  Yeah, well he had nothing much to do at all then, you see, only, oh they
         had buildings there, abig warehouse and an office building. Nobody in
         the office, but abig warehouse where alot of the stuff was stored. Oh
         he didn't have much to do, but this group of men that were taking care
         of the horses, he had to supervise them, you know. Buy alittle hay and
         grain once in awhile. Ithink they said there was 260 head of horses
         there. Well they had quite afew camps around when they were working,
         and every camp was about ahundred-twenty men. Inever did know how
         many horses was in each camp though, isn't that funny? I knew the amount
         of men.
         
         SAM:  I was curious about the single lumberjacks that stuck around, that were
         there logging for anumber of years. Did they sort of get adopted by
         families? Did they have real close ties where they became part of the
         social life of Bovill too?
         
         JH:  Oh in some cases yes, the single lumberjack, he had special family
         friends. Yes, that happened. But when they'd talk about going to town
         it was Spokane, you know, they wouldn't stop short of Spokane. Always
         by train too in those days. They had two ways of going there by train.
         You could go down on the WIM to Palouse, and have two chances there,
         either the Great Northern or the Northern Pacific get to Spokane; or
         they can take the Milwaukee to St. Maries and in. So they went both ways.
         Iknow one time there, this must have been about 1927 I'd say.
         We had abig fella, Charlie Albright, he died right on the basketball
         floor. We was having atown team basketball game there and Iwas man
         ager of the team. And it was anice night in the winter, February I
         think probably. And we'd had agood team that year, and this was the
         playoff, the winner would be sort of declared the champion. Ithink
         we were playing Kendrick, and the crowd,- the gym was full, anice night.
         And this Charlie, put up his hand, "Time out!", and down he went.
         We got over there, abunch of us, and he wasn't coming too, and every
         body done everything they could, you know, artificial respiration. I
         remember we got abarrel in from outside the door of the gym, and put
         him on that, rolled him back. Everybody had an idea, you know, what to
         do. And there was acouple of nurses in the room. Well one nurse said,
         "I can't feel any pulse." But the other one, whether she could or not,
         she didn't say.
         
         We had adoctor stationed in Bovill then, Dr. Brown, so somebody
         tore out to get Dr. Brown. That place was getting panicky, you know.
         The man was there and hadn't come to and nothing was being done. And
         then finally Dr. Brown showed up. Of course he was just afoot, oh the
         snow was awfully deep then. And he got inside the door, "Well, settle
         down," he says, "the doctor is here, the doctor's here now." And he
         walked over to him and examined him alittle bit. "Well," he said,
         "we'll have to take him up to the-", well it used to be ahospital,
         but it wasn't operating then as ahospital, but that's where the doctor's
         office was. So he said we'll have to take him up to the hospital It
         was the hospital building, see, so then they sent somebody for astret
         cher somewhere close, Iguess. Got there with the stretcher and we put
         Charlie, on it, and he was abig fella, about 240 pounds. And that snow
         the other one walked the path, and then they'd shift over just alittle
         ways and they'd change off. And I remembeAound up being the one that
         was carrying him in the door. I'd interchanged different times, Iwas
         one of them. And the doctor said, "Thanks boys!" And he held up his
         hand and he said, "His relatives will be here tomorrow." Well,he was
         asingle man. He says, "His relatives will be here tomorrow." Well that
         was the first that any of us knew that Charlie was dead! Isuppose we
         should have known more, but we didn't. We thought, you know, there
         was achance that he was alive, and would be. But that doctor knew
         all the time. But Ithink he handled it just right, because the crowd
         you know, was getting kind of panicky: do something, do something! Well
         everything was being done that could be. He died right there apparently,
         because he never stirred.
         
         But then he had lived at Palouse I guess, so the funeral was sched
         uled for Palouse a couple of days later. And we had a special train
         come up from Palouse and took pret' near the whole town down to Palouse
         to the funeral, and of course, had to bring 'em back. I'll never for
         get that day either. This engineer, Elmer Helm, he was quite aguy.
         Well he seen that big crowd on the depot platform, with asteam engine
         you know. And he set up there, the train would run right on by the
         depot for oh half amile or more, and then there was aYout there where
         they'd Ythe engine. And when he seen that crowd out there- this Helm,
         he was kind of ashowman- he must have give it everything it had, be
         cause he came by that depot, and that old engine was just a-swayin',
         you know. He was putting it as fast as he could. For his own reason
         is all! But you know it scared that crowd half to death. But still
         for all they wanted to go to the funeral, and they did! They got there
         (Chuckling), but there were people got sick on the way down. But I
         know they didn't get sick from the ride going down there. They were so
         scared with him coming in, they didn't know what he'd be doing on the
         way down. But we all got down there and back. But now that's the way
         people would do there, you see, just something like that. The whole
         town would turn out for it. They were good people, real good people,
         generally speaking. 'Course that ended the basketball for the season,
         and should have.
         
         SAM:  Were sports very big in Bovill?
         
         JH:  Oh they always had abaseball team, always. And apretty good one.
         And we'd have little leagues made up of, well Potlatch always had a
         strong team, Genesee always had agood outfit, they were in the league.
         Kendrick always had a good one, they were in. Bovill, and then some
         times Elk River would come up with a pretty good team. They had a
         sawmill up there in Elk River until about oh, 1930 I think that saw
         mill went out. When the sawmill was there Elk River was amuch lar
         ger town than Bovill was, and they had apretty good baseball team.
         It. went down after that, of course, Oh. yeah,Troy would have a
         team some years, and some years they didn't. But we had a league and
         real interest in it. The townspeople would follow the team around the
         country. We'd go to St. Maries, and sometimes Emida and different places
         But the league games were interchangeable with these other towns. Oh
         we have won the championship there and we've lost too, more times than
         we won. But once in awhile we'd come in with a winner. Yeah.
         It's a funny thing: Moscow couldn't support a town baseball team.
         Too much university there, Iguess. For some reason Moscow never had
         a town baseball team. You'd think there'd be enough university stud
         ents that'd stay around there during the summer that they could get up
         ateam, but no. Sometimes we used to get some guys from the university
         to come up and we'd find them a job for the summer and they'd play ball
         with us. Red Jacoby was one of them. He was with us, oh I don't know,
         three years I think. He later went on, you know, to Wyoming, and he be
         came a graduate manager there. In fact he just died about a year ago.
         I met a man here in Spokane about a year ago, and he was from Wyoming.
         And I said, "Do you know, I only knew of one man," I guess I probably
         said, "I know one man in Wyoming, and that's Red Jacoby!"
         That's kind of funny, isn't it? There's a whole state, and he did,
         he knew him. Oh yeah, we had baseball, basketball, we used to play
         volleyball. Yeah. But that isn't so today, you know, those towns now,
         they don't have a baseball team. Oh there's probably some of them might
         have a basketball team, but it's never organized like it used to be,
         you know. We had, as I say, those leagues drawn up, we had rules and
         we had officials made up of the county.
         
         SAM:  That story about the doctor reminded me of that story that you told me
         about when your wife was having the baby.
         
         JH:  Oh.
         
         SAM:  Would you tell me that?
         
         JH:  Yeah, well yes, that was when our youngest boy Jack was born, on April
         5th, 1931. And we had a doctor in Bovill, I believe that was Dr. Porrall,
         I wouldn't just swear to his name, but I think it might have been
         Dr. Porrall. He visited my wife on this day which was Saturday, I
         think, yes. And, "Oh," he said, "nothing to worry about," he said,
         "you've got a week or maybe two weeks yet." So he told her that he
         was taking the train to Elk River that day and he'd be up there over
         the weekend. So during that Saturday night here the labor pains start
         ed, and we knew the baby was coming. So I hiked up to the doctor's of
         fice which was the old hospital and asked the doctor's wife to come
         down with me and she did. I was awful glad that she did come because
         she knew so much more about it than I did. But of course got ahold of
         the doctor by phone at Elk River. Well he had no way of coming ft :it
         course impassable, nobody could get over it. You couldn't
         call it a highway, it was just a road at the time, but you couldn't get
         over it. So well, couldn't do anything about that.
         
         But Axel Anderson, some way he found out about that. I hadn't
         talked to Axel, he found out about it. And they had this old Dodge bug
         that they used to run on the railroad sometimes, nothing but an old Dodge
         car with the four railroad wheels on it. But it had been put away for
         the winter, hadn't been used again that year, and the battery was out of
         it. And he scouted around, and he got a battery and got it in that old
         rig, and he got the doctor and brought him down to Bovill. I didn't even
         know they were coming. Here they showed up at the house. I was awfully
         glad to see them. Well the doctor said everything was all right, glad
         to hear that too of course. But I was so excited, you know, I didn't
         even ask Axel if he'd like a cup of coffee. I told him about it some
         time later. "Oh," he said, "I understand. I had kids too, you know."
         I always thanked Axel for that. How he got the word I don't know. He
         did find out, but somebody told him. And this was late at night too.
         You know, and then when the Depression come on hard, a little worse,
         we didn't have a doctor. We didn't have a doctor in Bovill. But here
         they had 260 horses across there, and the Potlatch Lumber Company did
         have a veterinary. So you'd hear this around town: "The horses are
         more important than the peoplel" Yeah.
         
         SAM:  Did people go to the vet when they got sick?
         
         JH:  Quite often, especially if they got hurt, you know. And he did have a
         reputation, he could set a bone probably as good as a medical doctor—
         your wrist, or your leg or something. He also knew a little something
         have him in jail some place. Oh yes, alot of people would take his
         advice. And they'd say for an injury he'd go right ahead and fix them
         up until, you know, they could get to adoctor, which would be the next
         day. Yeah, that's the way that worked.
         Do know what they used to call Axel, what his nickname was?
         
         JH:  "The Big Swede." Yep, whenever anybody would say the Big Swede,
         Yeah, he was in the snowplow one time on one of their logging roads,
         and the goldarn snowplow derailed and went over atrestle, is what it
         was, went down there quite aways. Had astove in there and of course
         it fell over. It's awonder the thing didn't burn up. Axel, he got hurt
         pretty bad. But he came out of it. Ithink he might have broken his
         shoulder, but he was awful lucky that it wasn't worse. And another
         fella with him, Joe Evans, he got banged up some too, broke his leg or
         arm or something, he was laid up for awhile. Oh, I'll betcha Axel's
         had a lot of experiences in the woods.
         
         (Chuckles) They had a fella there, his name was Joe Buck. Well
         he was, oh Idon't know, ajack of all trades, and hewas sort of a
         painter too. But he was working for the Potlatch at the time in what
         they called the basin, which is between Bovill and Elk River but off
         to the east some. They had, oh about three camps out there I think,
         A, B, C, D, maybe they had four camps out there. The logs were trans
         ported into Elk River for the mill. Then they had abig coal dump out
         there, and the coal would come into Elk River, and then it would have
         to be taken out to these camps with the shay engine, oh maybe four or
         five cars at a time. And this Joe Buck, he was working out there as
         ,an engine watchman. Well that would be at night when the engines were
         tied up, he was watching engines. Well it seems like there was no crew
         around. This Joe, he was akind of astrong union man too. They didn't
         know it though until then. So it was this night and they were getting
         short on coal and there, as this story goes, Axel asked him, "Joe,
         could you take the engine and run into Elk River and get one carload
         of coal?" Joe says, "Sure Axel, sure I can, but will T?" (Laughs).
         And he didn't.
         
         SAM:  Axel didn't even can him?
         
         JH:  Oh no, no. And Ithink it was the sanguy, I'm pretty sure it was Joe
         Buck, he was kind of abull cook around the camp one time. Oh, there
         was little jobs, you know, maybe they'd have a little pump out here
         somewhere to pump water into the camp, or other little duties. "Well,
         we'll give you two hours for this or four hours for this," and then
         cleaning out the bunkhouses and whatnot. Then they were getting these
         extra duties onto 'em, you know, "Well, how about an hour for that?"
         Anyway, it all added up to twenty-five hours, and Joe, he wondered how
         he was gonna work that, (chuckling) with only twenty-four hours in
         the day. Well, I guess they got it straightened out. But you see
         that would be kind of along the line of gyppo, give you an hour's pay
         today if you take care of this.
         
         SAM:  Do you know if the men considered Axel as a big management person, or
         if they they thought of him more as aworker like themselves?
         
         JH:  No, I've never known of Axel to do aphysical day's labor in his life.
         He was always some kind of aboss, when Iknew him. No, and Idon't know,
         he was in the United States Army in World War I, but Idon't know what
         he done just when he first come out. He may have worked in the woods
         then, but that was way ahead of my time. But from the time Iknew him,
         from 1925 on, he was always in the supervisory capacity. He was afore
         man or assistant foreman, or well, I don't know. No, Inever knew
         him as an assistant foreman, he was either a foreman or higher ranking.
         Foreman, and then you see they'd have what they'd call the walking
         boss, he was higher than the foreman. And then ahead of him would be
         the superintendent. But the walking boss was kind of a trouble shoot
         er, you know, that'd get around the camps, see what the foremen were
         doing. His work would mostly be with the foremen for the different
         camps. Of course, he'd hike out into the woods too, to see what was
         going on.
         
         SAM:  Would you tell me what the responsibilities were of your job, being
         depot agent there?
         
         JH:  Well, it was just like depot agent any other place. I was the tele
         graph operator, of course, and there I did the telegraphing as well.
         An agent is responsible for everything that happens in and around his
         station. And you had to see that things was going right, and you'd
         have to keep in good touch, good relations with the business people.
         Those days everything was handled on the railroad, there was no truck
         ing. Trucking didn't come along for quite a while afterwards. And
         then of course the telegraph, you're manager of the Western Union,
         and then the express company, you're the express agent. And with your
         help, you know, you had the cashier there, you had to supervise him
         and see that he's doing his work right, same with your warehouseman;
         you do have to oversee those two, I did anyway, and would be the case.
         Well that's about it. Well if you was at a station where there was
         a competitor railroad, then as a railroad agent, a lot of your work
         would be soliciting business. But that at Bovill I didn't have to do,
         because the two railroads were right there in the same building, and
         going different difections. So there was no soliciting to do. And
         then, of course the mail is handled on those trains, you were res
         ponsible for that mail until after it leaves the station. You were
         responsible for just everything in and around the station.
         Well, after I stayed there for so long you see, and after a num
         ber of years, the management of both railroads more or less left me
         alone. Very seldom did they ever give me instructions of what had to
         be done that wasn't being done or anything like that. They kind of
         relied on me to run it up there, and I did the best I could. And I
         really enjoyed my work. I think one reason that I did is because I
         got along quite well with the management. I didn't try to bicker or
         fight with them. That's not pleasant work when you don't have boss
         es that you get along with. I didn't have any bosses on the jobj but
         here like Spokane, the Milwaukee, this was the headquarters for them,
         Potlatch for the WI and M. But I got along with them good, and you did
         say you talked with Walt Gamble— he was my boss from the WI and M for
         quite a number of years. Got along well with him.
         
         Everything you know, those days came in and out of town on the
         railroad. Oh you do things sometimes, probably you shouldn't, but
         then you do it anyway. I know one time there we had a fella died
         right across the meadow. And these people, the relatives, were from
         Spokane, and they wanted the body brought into Spokane. Again this
         was in the winter, deep snow. But this undertaker I'll call him
         (mortician, whatever you want to), came out from Spokane, and the
         drayman took him across the meadow to this place where the man had
         died— and he'd been dead for a couple of days— a day and a half any
         way, I guess— while this passenger train went to Elk River and back,
         which would take about two and a half hours. And the drayman took
         this man over, and he prepared the body over there well enough to ship.
         But he thought it was— all he had was a basket, and they're narrow
         you know, narrow as a body, well, nothing but a basket is all it is,
         wrapped around. And then the drayman brought it back to the depot.
         I should have known this, but I didn't, and here we had the body on
         the truck and ready to load into the baggage car.  this baggage
         man on that train, he was all right, Steve Kinnard was his name, but
         he was one that wanted to stay right as strictly to the letter of the
         law and rule as he could. And when he seen the carrying basket, that's
         what they called it, and no handles on it, he said, "No, no, no hand
         les!" "Why," I said, "it can be handled easy enough." He said, "No
         handles on it!" Well, I couldn't argue with that, you know, because
         there wasn't any handles on it. "Nope!" "Well," I said, "I'll go in
         and see." So I went in the depot, and the conductor was still in there
         because Bovill was a registered station and the conductors had to come
         to register. And I told the conductor, "Can you hold up for a minute
         or so?" "Yeah." He didn't know what I was doing,none of his business,
         and no use in me telling him. This I shouldn't have done, but I didn't
         have time to do it properly (phone rings) I'll have to answer that
         phone. (Break)
         
         SAM:  You were just telling me about how you did a little short circuiting
         of the rules there on that dead man.
         
         JH:  Oh, yes, yeah.
         
         SAM:  You were talking to the conductor.
         
         JH:  Yeah, he said, okay, he'd wait a little bit. Well I set down to the
         typewriter and wrote out a message addressed to this baggageman to
         accept this corpse as is, and signed the superintendent's name to it.
         And I took it out and handed it to him. He said, "That's good enough
         for me, the superintendent's name." He took the message he took the
         corpse, and I never heard another word about it. It was all right.
         Now this was on Saturday, see, and no trains on Sunday. If that body
         couldn't have been transported, they'd have to have held that body
         some place until Monday! And you know I would have done most anything
         erintendent. you know in Spokane.and get this thing cleared. And I
         couldn't expect that conductor passenger trains leave on
         that's when they want the minute, you know, when they're due to leave,
         to leave. So that worked very good a I wasn't exactly holding
         my breath for afew days afterward maybe something
         come of it. But nothing did. No.  oonnee of the things
         this particular agent done, (laughs.)
         
         SAM:  Were there real differences between the two lines, besides the fact
         that one was organized by alumber company, in the way the lines operated,
         that you had to follow?
         
         They all had the  rules, you know. All the trains run under
         good deal the same train orders and timetables, and it's all just go
         system. Their account.,inga 4is« jwustt aaggooooad deal on the same order, only
         there was one separate set of accounts for one railroad and one for
         the other. Oh, as one brakeman said there one time, he was arguing
         aiittle bit whxth the brakeman from the Milwaukee, he said, "Well,
         in away arailroad is arailroad. And the HUM was an Interstate
         Washington and then into Idaho. And their plans apparently had been
         hut fire or something in the area where they in to go on to Montana, but tire or 
         tended to go changed the plans. into Montana, but
         railroad is Washington, Idaho and Montana. today still the name of the raiiroao i
         Yeah, some of them used to say, "Will I Make it," for WIM, "Will I
         Make it?" And then another fella I heard say, "Maybe I Will," turn
         it around. Oh yeah. Oh there was an awful lot of logs went out of
         there by railroad in those days.
         
         SAM:  Which way did more logs go?
         
         JH:  Potlatch. Potlatch see had a good size mill there. One time, I don't
         know whether it was regarded the second largest in the country, I be
         lieve it was. I believe it was considered the second largest sawmill
         in the United States. But then shortly after there was some bigger
         ones went in. The one at Lewiston was bigger, and I think Longview
         was a bigger one.
         
         SAM:  Did a lot of that same timber come back through when it was sawed up?
         
         JH:  Oh yes, oh yes, a lot of it from the Potlatch mill come right back
         through Bovill and go on East. I think that was one of the reasons
         that the Milwaukee bought that road, tyou see, before that the busin
         ess out of Potlatch was sort of divided up. Now at Palouse there's
         two railroads, the Northern Pacific and the Great Northern, and we'll
         just say that each of them got a third, and then a third of it would
         go to Bovill for the Milwaukee. They didn't hold right onto those
         bases, but that's roughly speaking, you know, they divided it up.
         But then, the Milwaukee buying the WI and M, well now they get the lion's
         share of it, you know. I don't know how much they get, but probably
         seventy-five percent I suppose of the lumber that's cut at Potlatch
         will go through Bovill and generally speaking on to the East. Most
         of it goes 6ast. Very few carloads of lumber out of Potlatch ever
         goes to the West, so these sawmills on the west coast, I guess, takes
         care of this area. But feast, yeah.
         
         SAM:  So Bovill being at that juncture point sounds to me l±ka it was really
         at a very central location for shipping logs.
         
         Oh yes. Yeah, the logs, you see, came in there and then went to Pot
         latch. We had a pole yard there too, cedar pole, and it's still going.
         They shipped a lot of poles out of there, creosoted, you know. It
         used to be in the summertime we'd have quite a few sheep, quite a few,
         sometimes you know a straight, strictly sheep train. They'd come in
         about Memorial Day; I think^that they would have with the Forest Ser
         vice to have the sheep on the forest land— and that's where they
         mostly done their grazing— was June 1st, but they always seemed to
         always get in about a day or so before. And they'd graze all summer
         until September. Generally around Labor Day they'd start shipping
         them out. And then trainloads, you see, not carloads, but trainloads—
         mostly on to Chicago. You wouldn't know where they'd go to from there,
         but you know they had the yards there.
         
         But that's all a thing of the past, there's no more sheep grazed
         in the country at all. I don't know why. Somebody told me why, but
         I didn't believe it. You know those sheep tenders or sheepherders, or
         whatever you want to call them— a lot of them were Basques— came
         over here, and they liked sheep and they knew how to handle sheep,and
         just everybody can't. Oh. yeah, an owner told me, "Oh it makes a big
         difference if you've got a man tending herds that knows how and one
         that doesn't." But this fella told me why there's no more sheep any
         more, because those fellas quit coming over here to herd them. He
         said, "That's why, they can't get them." Whether it is or not, I don't
         know. Yeah, with sheep you got to keep 'em on the move, now isn't
         that funny. Now with hogs it's always been my understanding, although
         I don't pretend to be an expert at all on that, but you keep hogs in
         a sort of small pen and feed 'em heavy, and that's where they put on
         the most weight. But with sheep, of course, they're grazing, you got
         to keep 'em going. A sheep will eat about so much then they lay down.
         Well a herder, you can't let 'em do that. You got to keep 'em mov
         ing. And when they move they eat. Isn't that funny? (Chuckles)
         Just the opposite of the hogs— keep 'em moving and then they keep
         eating. The only time you want 'em still is at night.
         
         SAM:  When you mentioned the cedar yard there, it reminded me of Leo, I was
         wondering if you can tell me what Leo was like? I've heard that he
         was a jokester, and certainly was a comic fellow.
         
         JH:  I'll tell you, he pulled a good one one a cousin of mine. This cousin,
         that was a long time ago, he was here in Spokane, and well, he had a
         little job of some kind. He was single and young, he didn't like that
         job he had. And Ihappened to be in town. "Well," I said, "if you
         want to come back with me to Bovill, I said, "I'm pretty sure you can
         go to work in the pole yard." "All right, I'll give it a try." So
         he did. And his job was to count the poles on each car. After a car
         was loaded,see, then you count the poles to see how many was on there.
         They know how many is supposed to be on there, you see, and of course.
         the loaders and the checker, whoever it is, tries to get exactly that
         number of poles on, but then they always have one to count 'em after
         wards. Well the best way to do it is to go to the end where the butts
         are, you see, and then count those butts. You can use a little chalk
         mark if you want to know that you've counted that. And then you go to
         the other end. Well, sometimes you see the poles go that way so there'd
         be butts on each end, and the small part would be to the middle. And
         this cousin, he was counting, that was part of his work that day. He
         was counting and he'd get a different number on the other end -one
         more log. And he done it and he done it so-many times that it was
         driving him crazy. Like each time he'd count on one end and maybe
         hundred Doles and the other end was a hundred one. Well
         that doggone Leo, there was a little open space there where there was
         nothing, and around the cedar yard there's lots of cutoff pieces, you
         know. He took one of those little short pieces that wasn't two feet
         long and he shoved it in that space, (chuckles) That made it, yeah.
         He'd do things like that. For quite a few years he was in charge of
         creosoting. That was part of his work there.
         
         SAM:  What is the story you told me about getting his eggs stolen?
         
         JH:  Oh yeah. He had a barn, he had cows and chickens. And he knew that
         he was losing some eggs. Well he had a neighbor, he was a good enough
         fella but he was different, Buck Chambers. And he figured that it was
         probably Buck that was stealing his eggs, but he hadn't seen him do it.
         So this time, it was early in the morning, I guess it was, I think he
         seen Buck go into the barn. And there was nothing to say, you know, or
         reprimand him or anything for being in there, that was all right. But
         when Leo went in, "How are ya, Buck!" Buck stuttered, you know, and
         Leo kind of sized him up, and then he walked over to him, and (slapping
         hands on his trousers) on the pockets, and he heard eggs breaking, and
         come down on top of his head just playful, you know, down on top of his
         head. Here Buck had eggs under the hat, the hat pulled down and he had
         eggs up there, and Leo broke the whole works. Oh his pockets, and the
         eggs started coming down Buck's face. Well, the jig was up then, of t
         course. He didn't do anything about it; he didn't want to do anything
         about it. He just wanted to stop Buck from stealing his eggs! (Laughs)
         Oh I don't know, stories used to come up around Bovill there, and
         somebody would say, "Where did all these new stories come from?" So I
         heard somebody say, "Don't you know? Leo Guilfoy makes them up!"
         
         (Chuckles) I don't know whether he did or not. Leo to me didn't
         ever worried about anything. Maybe that's why he lived so long.
         If he done any worrying he kept it to himself. It couldn't have been
         just an easy life, you know, after his wife couldn't be home to take
         care of the family. There, he had those three kids, he had to earn a
         livelihood as well as supervise the kids until they could do for them
         selves. It was a big job, it was a bigger job than most men would do,
         I think. He done a real good job. Real good.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13645</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Herzog2</previous>
      <next>Holland2</next>
      <disp_name>Holland1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
