<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/7/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Gerald Ingle, 1976-10-07, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:44:48</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Ingle, Gerald</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>County commissioner for 20 years; farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1910</birthyear>
      <residence>Big Bear Ridge, Kendrick</residence>
      <origin>Son of Florence Ingle. Grandfather was a homesteader from Tennesee (1883)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooperatives"&gt;cooperatives&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homemakers"&gt;homemakers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#banks"&gt;banks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#University of Idaho"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fraternities"&gt;fraternities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farmers"&gt;farmers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#grange halls"&gt;grange halls&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Big Bear Ridge"&gt;Big Bear Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Little Bear Ridge"&gt;Little Bear Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Juliaetta"&gt;Juliaetta&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Kendrick"&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Viola"&gt;Viola&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13480</file_name>
      <mp3>13481.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13481.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Early farming in the area and going to Kendrick with father</title>
            <synopsis>Early farming. Going to Kendrick with father.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>360</time>
            <title>His father's interests in the area; farming their land and chores he did as a boy</title>
            <synopsis>Father was on board of directors of Kendrick Roachdale Company, the farmers' co-op.
               Father's interest in development of country and civic work. They farmed more than
               300 acres, part owned by relatives. He ran plow as a boy; family chores.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Not missing school for work; how learning took place; and differences in size of the
               boys in school
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His family very seldom missed school for work on the place. Schools on the ridge.
               An amazing amount of learning took place from listening to others recite. Overgrown
               boys in school were mean to the small kids.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Mother's work; going to high school In Kendrick and adjusting to school in town</title>
            <synopsis>Mother's work - she quit teaching after marriage.
               Getting to high school in Kendrick. The dangerous grade; shortcuts by foot. Adjusting
               to school in town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>School activities; Holidays at school; Dancing not allowed and then allowed in the
               1920s
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Social activities in the community - Christmas celebrations. Dancing was taboo, games
               permitted. In the twenties they built a community hall for dances.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Social activities and father's opposition to them; Conflict and cooperation on small
               communities; building a new church and church social activates
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Dances at the community hall. Father's opposition to dancing, cards and drinking.
               Conflict and cooperation in small communities - living with differences. Building
               of new church from United Brethren Church. Church socials, little work on Sunday;
               Sunday socializing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Neighbors were also family; why grandfather came west and first winter; preparing
               for winter then not going anywhere for its duration; winter work
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Neighbors who were relatives. Grandfather's settling on the ridge. He came west because
               of his asthma. Grandfather's story of the first winter (1883), living on rutabaga
               and bear meat. Yearly trip to Moscow for winter supplies. People holed up for the
               winter. Turnover of early population. Winter work.               
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Hard times during the Depression; banking in Kendrick and Juliaetta; dislike of Vollmer</title>
            <synopsis>Hard times for family in depression. Father's optimism about future. Closure of Kendrick
               State Bank in a run, when his father was president, reorganization with little loss
               of money. Juliaetta people withdrew money from Kendrick State, because it had absorbed
               their
               bank. Dislike of Vollmer, who foreclosed on some forms; S.D. White, Vollmer's hard-boiled
               agent.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Being able to go to college; experiences at the university and working during school</title>
            <synopsis>He didn't drink as a young man, though many did. Lack of opportunity in community
               for those who went to college. Few went to high school,
               extremely few to college. He naturally wanted to go to college, as did his siblings.
               Some resentment towards them for going to college.
               Friendliness of university. He worked while in school. A proctor cautioned the students
               about fraternities. College dances and other social life. Wife's family. The girls
               were controlled, which controlled the boys; Dean French. Lack of money for gas.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>What he studied in college but took over the family farm; leaving school because of
               the Depression; how the depression affected area farmers
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He studied business but took over the family farm. He had hoped to work in the bank.
               He left school for home during the depression, because his help was needed. Farmers
               had enough to eat. Some gave up their farms: a man persuaded to stay by federal banker.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>Issues in local politics; grandfather running as democrat; vary successes with bonding</title>
            <synopsis>Grandfather's joke about Republicans; grandfather thought he was "counted out" when
               he ran for county commissioner as a Democrat. Moscow hasn't dominated county as much
               as many think. Road districts and varying success with bonding.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5340</time>
            <title>School consolidation: he was on the reorganization board. Effects of temporary consolidation</title>
            <synopsis>School consolidation: he was on the reorganization board. Effects of temporary consolidation.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>School consolidation and the problems associated with it</title>
            <synopsis>Burden of cost was on towns under temporary consolidation, beginning in the mid-thirties.
               Consolidation made it easier for high school
               students to get in.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>Which schools consolidated with whom; opposition to school consolidation</title>
            <synopsis>Bovill wanted to consolidate with Elk River and Clarkia, but those towns opposed it.
               Acceptance of plan at Troy was won by Anna Marie Oslund's support. Overcoming Potlatch
               Corporation's initial opposition to consolidation, Disagreement over consolidation
               between Kendrick and Juliaetta; Juliaetta's last graduation.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6300</time>
            <title>Rivalry between Kendrick and Juliaetta was intense; Involvement in Kendrick civic
               affairs; closing Southwick grade school
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Kendrick got started by giving land for the depot, while Juliaetta people wanted money.
               Rivalry over baseball. Rivalry was intense
               between the towns. Kendrick's business district has been more successful. Involvement
               in Kendrick civic affairs. Process of school
               consolidation around Kendrick; closing Southwick grade school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Dealing with criticism as a public official; why he ran for county commissioner; how
               he farmed while also working as commissioner; workload for commissioners
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His response to criticism as a public official. Decision to run for county commissioner.
               Importance of help from wife. Hiring help for the farm while he worked as commissioner.
               Increasing workload for commissioners caused by greater responsibilities. Less welfare
               responsibility now. North Idaho fares well in terms of state.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Working with state legislators and extension services; criticism of taxes and bad
               roads; keeping farming methods secret
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Acquaintance with state legislators who had similar backgrounds to his. Working with
               extension service - some farmers would have nothing to do with them, but picked up
               the new advances. There's more interest in government now, and more complaints. Criticism
               of taxes and bad roads. Farmers kept their personal methods secret.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7860</time>
            <title>How the Grange provided social lives during Depression; patriotism during World War
               I
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Growth of Grange in the depression provided social life. Nailing a flag to the home
               of a German who wouldn't buy liberty bonds.
               Necessity of patriotism in First World War.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8100</time>
            <title>Decline of population and farm consolidation; lack of social life after marriage;
               IWWs were an issue and not trusted
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Consolidation of small farms, decline of population. Community life on the ridge in
               the thirties. Lack of social life after marriage during hard times. Meeting in schoolhouse
               against IWWs; unfounded suspicion of them causing a threshing machine fire.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8520</time>
            <title>Threshing and the need for coordination; early clannishness of Scandinavian communities</title>
            <synopsis>Threshing time. Coordination essential for quick threshing, which people preferred.
               Early clannishness of Scandinavian communities.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8820</time>
            <title>Connection to the Wells family</title>
            <synopsis>Joe Wells; Wells brothers were close friends of his grandfather. Chuck Wells - his
               acceptance. Dan Ross.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9000</time>
            <title>Loss of Stony Point district to Lapwai, instead of Kendrick. Viola problems. Moscow
               made districts pay their own debts.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Loss of Stony Point district to Lapwai, instead of Kendrick. Viola problems. Moscow
               made districts pay their own debts.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9300</time>
            <title>Differences between Republicans and Democrats in the county</title>
            <synopsis>Little difference between Republicans and Democrats on local level, although Democrats
               seem to have more compassion for the poor. His acceptance of poor. He listens to people
               so they can speak their mind.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>County school consolidation. Community life on the ridge. Father and grandfather.
         Depression and bank closure. Growing up; attending the university. Attitudes as a
         public
         official. 10-7-76 2.7 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This conversation with GERALD INGLE took place at the Latah County Courthouse
         on October 7, 1976. The interviewer is SAM SCHRAGER.
         
         GERALD INGLE: During the Depression, it made it pretty rough.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: Really? Really it was?
         
         GI:  My dad was president of the bank, when the bank closed.
         
         SS:  You grew up on a farm, right? On Big Bear. Your parents had been
         here considerably early, hadn't they?
         
         GI:  Yeah, the place that I grew up on was my grandfather's old homestead.
         Then when my father took over the farm my grandfather built another
         house on another piece of land, so we still have that place. In
         fact, I own that place now, the old homestead.
         
         SS:  What do you remember the farming being like when you were still just
         a kid? Was it still early pioneering pretty much or had it passed that
         stage.
         
         GI:  we a lot of land there after I was a kid and helping, and of course
         in those days we used horses. I think in 1923 or '24 was when we
         bout our first tractor, farmed with horses up till then.
         
         SS:  Were the kids expected to do a lot of that work, a lot of the breaking?
         
         GI:  Well, we helped to pile brush and cut brush and stuff like that. We
         did some of that after Iwas big enough 
         
         SS:  If you tried to characterize the condition of the average farmer when
         you were still pretty young, you were born in '10, so figure out between the teens
         and in the '20's. How were they doing?
         
         GI:  They were pretty hard up, really. the country had a lot more people in
         it, a lot of people justA160 acres of land, some had a little more
         and some had smaller places. They milked cows and sold cream and sold
         eggs and sold butter those days. They didn't have creameries so much
         then they churned the cream into butter and sold butter. And that was
         how they paid their store bills for the food bill
         
         SS:  Was that their main source of money?
         
         GI:  Their main source was their crop, but as far as the household needs
         in the kitchen and put the food on the table a lot of that came from
         the- the things they bought in the grocery store- the things they
         bought in the grocery store- the sale of butter and eggs and so forth.
         
         SS:  They traded at Kendrick?
         
         GI:  Right. In that area, yes.
         
         SS:  Would they go mostly to Long's store, or were there other stores?
         
         GI:  There was Long's store and there was Stanton's store and there was
         store. There was the three stores when I was a kid. The
         Long's store was there where Erickson's is and Stanton's store was
         there where the drugstore is and store was where 
         hardware is.
         
         SS:  How often would your family make it into Kendrick?
         
         GI: Oh, I think probably once a week or so, probably.
         
         SS:  How far is it?
         
         GI:  Nine miles from town. See, my dad bought his first car in 1914, so
         I was only four years old when they bought the car. It used to be
         back years ago when I remember? most of the farmers went to town on
         Saturday afternoons. Took the day off and did their trading, 
         Would that be just the man of the family or would their wife go?
         Some of 'em would take their wi?e? Later on they did more. Probably
         earlier there was just the man and maybe take the kids or one of the
         kids along with them to town. ^1 used to go to town with my dad
         by myself with him, and maybe my brother the next time, took our turns.
         It was quite a treat getting to go to
         
         SS:  What would you do'.when you would go, in town, as a kid?
         
         GI:  I'd just gawk, as I remember now. And I remember one time I went down,
         the first time I ever drank soda pop. Got me a bottle of lemon pop,
         and I thought that was really something!
         
         SS:  Did he do much visiting with other guys?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes. He was on the board of directors of the Cooperative Ware
         house, Kendrick Roachdale Company, that's the oldest, one of the
         oldest co-operatives in the county.
         
         SS:  The Kendrick-?
         
         GI:  Roachdale. It's still there. He was on that board of directors for
         thirty, forty years, I guess J I don't know, more than that I guess.
         
         SS:  Was it a farmer owned co-op?
         
         Yes. Farmer owned co-op. The co-ops they have nowdays, they each far
         mer had to put up for $100 stock, and of course now the laws are a
         little different, I guess. Of course, they could do business with
         anybody but these stockholders got to receive dividends from the bus
         iness returns
         
         SS:  1 wonder how broad the ownership was, how many people had put in $100.
         
         GI:  0h don't know. I've seen that old stockholders list, there must
         have been seventy-five  hundred people. At that time, I'd say
         there were a lot more people in the rural area, smaller farms. It
         was a pretty good size and he was on that board of directors. He
         to go down once a month for the meeting of the board of directors
         of the Kendrick Roachdale Company.
         
         SS:  Did that come out of the farmers union?
         
         GI: remember they used to have the Farmers' Union, too. Probably origmally
         it first started that. I remember Dad used to have a big
         Farmers' Union sign on the ' there when I was a kid. I don't know
         whether there was a connection with that, but I just imagine it was
         sort of an offshot of that co-operative deal.
         
         SS:  Do you know what your father's attitudes were about bettering the
         position of the farmer in a political sense?
         
         GI:  I always felt Dad was pretty interested in developing the country and
         a real good attitude about developing. He used to get pretty irked
         about some of thefpeople that held back on things. He liked to see
         good schools and he liked to see good roads. And I remember several
         times when he had gone to Boise with different people to try to get
         'em to fix a certain road or to get the state to fix a certain road.
         He pretty much liked to see developments made. That's probably what
         rubs off on me over here being in public service.
         
         SS:  Do you have much idea of how he got- became disposed towards public
         service. It seems like a lot of farmers didn't get out beyond their
         own place in terms of their civic interests. What gave him that in
         clination?
         
         GI:  He was working in this grain/co-operative over there and he was also
         a director in a bank there for several years, too and he worked with
         people all the time. I know he was on the school board, too when I
         was in school. And we used to have a local telephone company and he
         was always an officer in our local telephone company. That was esta
         blished about 1908 or '09, and he was chairman of that a lot and sec
         retary a lot. I think he just sort of grew up with it, he sort of
         liked to work with people, too. And he got to be county commissioner
         at one time, too, in his life. That was in '42 and '43, his was only
         one term.
         
         SS:  Wonder where King, the nickname King came from.
         
         GI:  King came from- that was his name; King David Ingle. His dad's brother
         was named King Ingle, too.
         
         SS:  That was his first name.
         
         GI:  King David Ingle. His uncle's name was the same. I think farther up
         the ladder there was somebody named King.
         
         SS:  How hard do you feel that he worked?
         
         GI:  He worked hard. Dad really worked hard. We were a little bigger
         farmers than most of them when I was a kid. We had probably 400,
         350- 400 acres, and we always had hired men when I was a kid and al
         ways had a hired girl to help in the house when us kids growing
         up.
         
         SS:  Year around.
         
         GI:  Well, in the summer. Sometimes in the winter we wouldn't
         have. We had cattle, some cattle, beef cattle and milk cows, too
         and sometimes we'd have a hired man in the winter, but almost always
         they'd start generally in the spring, go to say, November or December
         sometimes.
         
         SS:  Of 300 or 400 acres, how much of that were you farming? Would that
         be most of that?
         
         GI:  0h, I could figure about- I suppose it was actually- it was over 300 acres of
         farmland; 350 probably.
         
         SS:  And did you own all that land, or did you rent?
         
         GI: Well, he rented part of it and some of it he owned and part of it was
         my grandfather's land. See, my grandfather never died till 1934- I
         think it was '34 or '35- '34, I believe it was, and he lived only half
         a mile from us and Grandfather had 320 acres of this land that we far
         med. That wasn't all cultivated, but there was two quarters. And
         then my dad ownedN80 acres adjoining there and my aunt- and these two
         pieces were part of the old estate my dad's sister had an 80 acresand
         we farmed those two eighties. That was originally part of my grand
         father's acreage.
         
         SS:  So it was pretty much all family owned?
         
         GI:  That's right.
         
         SS:  Even if he didn't own it himself.
         
         GI:  That's right.
         
         SS:  Did he need bigger equipment than most of the farmers at the time?
         
         GI:  I don't know whether he had bigger equipment, I guess more people and
         more pieces; twobottom gangplow was a big plow in those days in that
         area. Two of 'em, see, and take six horses to pull 'em. And lots of
         times, with the gangplow and oneLfootburner. walking plow with three
         horses on it. I started on one of those when I was ten years old.
         I was pretty good size for my age. I remember having the gangplow
         ahead and the footburner behind.
         Did you work the whole day on the footburner?
         Oh, yes, after I got up to twelve or thirteen years old. I remember
         the first time I ever rttn one I was ten years old and I
         plowed the garden, and I wanted to run that. I wanted to drive that
         team of horses and run that plow so Dad let me plow a few rounds and
         then he just went off and let me finish it. I got a little tired be
         fore I got done, but after I was up twelve, thirteen years old I ran
         it all the time. Then I got so I ran the gangplow. In those days
         we bound, and Dad didn't like to run a binder very well, so as soon
         as I was big enough, I imagine when I was thirteen, fourteen I started
         running a binder for harvest, and my brother shocked. He was a littie
         younger. I remember one year there before I startedA . the bin
         der; us kids were pretty small and my dad's brother, Dwight Ingle,
         he lived with my grandfather, Dad had us three boys shocking. Some
         of the shocks- a lot of 'em fell down, but we used to have to shock
         the grain, you know. And then a year or two after that I started run
         ning the binder and then my brother did the shocking.
         
         SS:  1 have heard that in the early days that with all the work the kids
         had to do on a place really got in the way of their going to school.
         SS
         
         GI: 
         I mean, they would layout quite abit, in the early days. But by the
         time you were growing up did that conflict with your going to school?
         
         GI:  No, not in our home. It did with some families, but my dad thought
         education^important and we had to milk cows before we went to school
         and do chores. We had to feed the hogs. Generally there was four of
         us in our family and each one of us had a job to do and that had to
         be done before we went to school.
         
         SS:  But he didn't believe in having to lay out?
         Once in a while, like take in the fall, if we had a wet fall and were
         threshing grain and we used to have the company threshing machines
         come and thresh, once in a while then if it was a late fall and short
         GI
         
         SS: 
         of labor, trying to get things done fast, maybe we'd stay out a day
         or two we had the threshers, but as far as my dad was concerned,
         he believed in us being in school every day. AMost of the time when
         I went to school, I had a perfect attendance record.
         Where did you go? Was there a school on the Ridge?
         
         GI:  Yeah, we had a little local school. It was school. It was
         built in 19- 1892, and that was one of the first schools on the Ridge.
         There were five schools at that time on the Ridge, but ours was the
         central school, it was in the center of the Ridge and it was actually
         the biggest school of the five.
         
         SS:  How many kids when you were going there?
         
         GI:  1 think the maximum amount at any time was thirty-five. I remember
         the year I started to school in the first grade there was twenty-eight
         that year and then a year or so after there were thirty-five. I think
         it ran between twenty-five to thirty-five. They might have had a few
         more once in a while.
         
         SS:  Did you go clear through the eighth?
         
         GI:  Yes.
         Ss: What do you think of how good learning you got in school?
         
         GI:  It was amazing. "These school districts were poor and most
         of the teachers they had were people who had gone to their first year
         or half a year or something. Lot of them came from Lewiston Normal.
         Some of them- once in a while we had one just went to summer school
         and took examination to get thejcertificate and some of 'em one year
         and some of 'em two years. Think a lot of 'em it was their first
         school and they didn't get too good a pay. But I think it is amazing
         that a kid could learn as much as they did, and I think one reason
         why they did, the whole eight grades and a recitation
         bench up in front, you know, and you listened to the other classes
         all the way through clear to the eighth grade and you couldn't
         help but listen.
         
         SS:  It's really get drilled into you.
         
         GI:  I think probably that was one reason why some of the oneroom schools
         were so successful, I think^because of it. AHearing this over and
         over all these years going through the grade school.
         
         SS:  When you were a little kid going to school there, do you remember
         there being any real big kids that hadn't had much learning?
         
         GI:  I remember three boys that were in the eighth grade and they were six
         foot tall, great big guys and they used to really give us little kids
         the devil. I don't think they ever did finish the eighth grade, but
         they had to go to - their parents would send them til one would get
         through the eighth grade, so these big guys like that— that was the
         year I went to school, they would work in the fall and then come
         and go to school in the winter and then/quit in the spring. So they
         actually never did- but their folks kept wanting them to get past that
         eighth grade examination. And boy, they were mean to us little kids
         sometimes.
         
         SS:  Sounds like they weren't  if they were big, picking
         on little kids.
         
         GI:  They were kids. I remember one time one of 'em Aung me up in a
         sack behind a horse out in the barn. A lot of the kids rode horse
         back because they had to come quite a ways to school and they had a
         barn there by the schoolhouse where they'd keep their horses. I
         never will forget that I guess. I was scared to beat the band.
         S: He Juing you in a sack—
         
         GI:  A gunny sack- hung me there for a little while back behind a horse.
         They had a lot of fun but I was so scared, but they didn't leave me
         there long.
         
         SS:  How old were these kids? Maybe about eighteen?
         
         GI:  I imagine, seventeen or eighteen.
         
         SS:  It must be kind of embarrassing to them too- you know, they shouldn't
         have been in school anymore.
         
         GI:  Oh, it was sort of bad for them because actually they were bigger than
         the teacher and she had quite a time with those boys sometimes.
         
         SS:  Did she have trouble with disclipine and order-
         
         GI:  With those older ones. Some of those gals that taught, she could
         straighten 'em out, I mean, these bigger kids. I think those big
         kids, as I remember, those three boys I first spoke of whenl was in
         the first grade were the three biggest because eventually I got to
         be one of those big boy, when I got to be in the eighth grade, I guess.
         
         SS:  Did your mother not teach during that whole time that she was there?
         
         GI:  No, she quit teaching when she got married, when she married Dad.
         She had taught three other schools on this Ridge prior to her marrying
         my dad. She was a schoolteacher so she saw that we studied our lessons
         We had to study every night at home after we got our chores done and
         our supper eaten.
         
         SS:  So, she met your father while she was teaching? Did she know him—?
         
         GI:  She met him while she was teaching. She lived on Little Bear Ridge
         across the canyon from Big Bear. And I don't think he really knew
         her until she came over there teaching. He might have known who
         she was. Her name was and they lived on the point
         of Little Bear Ridge, but he never really knew her until she- never
         went with her or anything till she got to teaching over there.
         I did ask you if your father worked hard- I should ask you how hard
         you think she worked.
         SS
         
         GI:  She worked hard. She always canned fruit and we always had a big
         job
         garden. That was one of us boys was hoeing the garden. I
         remember this. This was sort of an incident about my brother. We
         used to have to heo in the garden and he'd do something and she'd
         kick him out of the garden. And one day it rained a little bit and
         Dad was out with us boys hoeing the garden. First thing my brother
         did was chop off a stock of corn and he bawled him out and said if he
         did that again he'd sure give him a good tanning. He said, "
         you going to kick me out of the garden?" Says, "That's what Mom does
         when I do something like that." But she worked hard, she made butter
         from the cream that we got from the cows and did lots of canning and
         she was a pretty good seamstress. She made clothes for us, too. My
         sisters, she always made all their dresses and so forth. She was a
         very good seamstress.
         
         SS:  Did she ever go back to teaching?
         
         GI:  No. She was called in a few times, you know to substitute but she
         never went back to teaching. She always wanted to but she
         always had plenty of work to do at home.
         
         SS:  Wasn't that pretty much the pattern of young women in those days?
         They'd teach and then they'd marry and then that was it.
         
         GI:  That was it, yeah. Very few of 'em went back to school. Some of
         'em would after their family was grown or something, maybe. But
         generally they stayed home and took care of the- ran the household
         and took care of the family. Seemed to be the pattern in those days.
         
         SS:  For you to get to school in Kendrick; was that a hardship? After
         you got out of the eighth grade?
         
         GI:  After I got out of the eighth grade; first year I rode horseback to
         Kendrick in the fall and then in the spring when the weather was good
         and then in the wintertime S stayed in town. Then the second year I
         was big enough- I was fourteen or so—fstarted driving a car. Drove a
         car in the fall and spring. I drove down that old grade and up it
         when it was put it in low gear and stayAin low gear all the way till
         you got to the top. Three mile grade coming up. But I guess,
         pcobably- I did it a little bit when I was a freshman in high school
         but when the weather got rainy and slick, then I rode horseback. Then
         after that first year we never did ride horseback again, we always
         drove in the fall and then we stayed in town in the wintertime.
         
         SS:  Was that a second car?
         
         GI:  No, that was the family car. It was an old 1920 Dodge. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Was that grade ever dangerous- real dangerous to be on? I've driven
         it now, I've wondered in the wintertime-
         
         GI:  You haven't driven that old grade.
         
         SS:  No, I drive the one off of Little Bear Ridge to Kendrick.
         
         GI:  This one was on the other side and it was dangerous. I guess you can
         get up and down^now because some people live part way up on it, but
         it was really a dangerous grade. Now, you take a dangerous grade
         then- you had to be used to driving on it. Once in a while there
         was a turnout where you could see somebody coming, you'd have to wait
         to pass. People that drove it all-time were pretty good about thatthey
         see somebody coming and they were close to the turnout, they'd
         wait or vice versa. Sometimes you'd have to back up, but it was a
         pretty dangerous grade, really. You'd look right straight down in the
         canyon.
         
         SS:  In the winter,say, how did you handle it when there was snow on top
         and nothing down in Kendrick? You couldn't really take a sled down
         there in the early days all the way if there was no snow in Kendrick.
         
         GI:  No, it was pretty rough. Seems like we used to have more snow then,
         and there was another grade on the other side , called the Pine Creek
         grade that they go down in the winter and they'd leave their sled
         at the bottom of the grade and go to town.
         
         SS:  Walk in?
         
         GI:  Yeah, or take one of the horses and ride in. But lots of times used
         a buggy and they'd get the road broke and they'd use a buggy on top,
         cut the tracks, if they couldn't get to town with a sled. When I was
         in high school lots of times we didn't think anything about when Fri
         day night when school was out,alk home. It would kill kids now to
         walk that eight or nine miles! It was about eight miles or eight and
         a half-miles, I guess, home. Lots of times we'd walk down Sunday
         night. And we didn't think anything about that then.
         
         SS:  You never stayed in town except in the winter?
         
         GI:  Wintertime was all.
         
         SS:  Walking nine miles, it took quite a while.
         
         GI:  We used to walk to the top of the grade and we'd take a shortcut-
         We'd run down the grade, we d make it in an hour and twenty minutes,
         probably. (Chuckles) Sometimes the folks would take us to the top of
         the grade and there was two shortcuts on the grade where we could not
         follow the road and go straight down the hill and we'd take the shortcuts
         but coming back up, when we'd walk home, the shortcuts were
         steeper, we couldn't go too fast.
         
         SS:  What about the transition for you from the country school to the Ken
         drick school? Was it a big change?
         
         GI:  Yes, it was. It didn't take me too long to get oriented, but it was
         quite a change at first. You was used to the small group and so forth.
         I sure felt like a big pebble in a lake but it didn t take me long to
         get oriented.
         
         SS:  I've heard people talk about how getting into a town and mixing with
         the town kids, they really feel backwards at first, because the town
         kids are a little more slick. The big difference seemed to be in
         Moscow and the people out of town. Did you feel that?
         
         GI:  I felt that at first, but, I don't know, I was pretty easy to make
         friends and I got along real good with the town kids. They ^ed to
         call us country jerks and that kind of stuff, but it didn't take long.
         With Kendrick there was so many of them that came in from the rural
         areas, too, anyway, so there was a lot of country kids, so actually,
         I imagine the percent was probably 50-50 so it didn't take very long
         to get to knowing each other and working together.
         
         SS:  When you were in high school, was it mostly just studies or was there
         a lot of, what today seems to be so big in high school, sports and
         extracurricular activities.
         
         GI:  Well, we had- Basically, the main thing was studies. We had
         basketball and baseball and we never had football in Kendrick until
         the year after I went out; got out of high school. I graduated in
         the spring of '28 and they never started football until that fall,
         but we had baseball and basketball. I played basketball, I wasn't
         much for baseball, but I was on the basketball team for three years,
         I guess when I was in high school.
         
         SS:  Was there a lot of socializing between the boys and the girls when you
         were growing up? Must opportunity for it?
         
         GI:  Well, we- quite a little, I guess, called it. We used to have
         in our local community up there, every winter, we used to have what
         they called Literary Society. And every Saturday night or every other
         Saturday night certain groups would be in charge of putting on a pro
         gram for that evening and then they'd have their eats and stuff af
         terwards, and then used to have these old basket suppers.
         Auction off boxes and pie suppers, auction off pies and stuff like that
         to money for different things in the community. Then we always
         had I remember, we always had a big deal at Christmastime. Used
         to have what they called UB church, was just a little ways, United
         Brethern Church, from the schoolhouse. All the schools would go to
         gether and put on the Christmas porgram. And they would go around
         the community and collect money to buy treats, so everybody got a
         sack of candy. And every school would be in charge of putting on a
         part of the program. Have some dialogues and have some speeches and
         so forth, and it was really quite a festive occasion, that Christmasthe
         old community Christmas tree.
         
         SS:  When you had like these literaries and that kind of stuff, did you
         have dances after them?
         
         GI:  Dancing was taboo. We could play Skip-to-my-Lou and that kind of
         stuff, but dancing, that was sort of bad for some of 'em, so they
         could play games, you know.
         
         SS:  Was it a divided opinion at the time, some were for it and some not?
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah. And so they just generally just compromised.
         
         SS:  So you played these dancing and singing games? Party games?
         
         GI:  Party games. I used to think it sort of funny, they could play
         Skip-to-my-Lou, but they couldn't dance! But later on, in the early
         '20's they built a community hall there and they used to have public
         dances over there. And then after they got that hall they used to
         have their Christmas tree in the community hall. It's still standing
         there, in fact, it's on one of the places I.
         
         SS:  That hall got a pretty good sized draw, too. Heard people from Bovill
         say they went over there.
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah, those public dances, they used to come from all over. They
         used to have some real whingdings there.
         
         SS:  That's what I heard. (Chuckles)
         
         GI:  My folks wouldn't let me go to the dances. We could go to other things
         over there. But my dad, he was sort of against dancing. I never got
         to until I to Then I took dancing lessons and started dancing, but he was real strict
         about dancing. And he was sort of
         strict about cards. When we were younger, we couldn't play even pino
         chle or something, but anyway after we got up in high school, we played
         anyway and he accepted it. But he " that dancing and cards and
         drinking and all that kind of stuff ran together.
         
         SS:  Do you think for him that that was a religious belief, or was it more
         just morals?
         
         GI:  Well, religious and moral, I suppose. His mother was real strict, I
         guess and she died when he was a teenager, and I guess she left quite
         an impression on him. He was just that way. pother was a lot
         more broadminded about it, but he was pretty strict.
         
         SS:  So, he never had a drink?
         
         GI:  He never drank at all. He was a teetotler.
         
         SS:  He must have been for Prohibition, when it came in.
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah. He wasn't one of the real rabid ones who would go out and
         preach it. But if you was with him and wanted a drink, he'd let you
         drink, but he just didn't do it himself.
         
         SS:  I heard that the dancehall on the Ridge when it came in caused some
         conflict with the people who were really against dancing.
         
         GI:  Yes, it did and still, on the other hand, they actually got so they
         had Sunday School in that community hall part of the time. They had
         Sunday School next morning after they had a dance there on Saturday
         night. So each group learned to live with it. And it was pretty fun
         ny in the local community as I look back, they'd fight like cats and
         dogs if somebody'd have bad luck or out or something of
         trouble then all the neighbors would come in and help. Forget all their
         petty peeves and work for each other. And when they built this com
         munity hall it was a donation of labor and every body helped. I know
         my dad helped work on it, too. I guess he sort of had the attitude,
         if the people wanted to do that, it was alright, but he just didn't
         do it himself and he didn't like his family to be doing some of those
         things, like drinking and dancing.
         
         SS:  Would you say that it was pretty much divided into two groups, those
         that accepted drinking and dancing and those that were against it?
         Is that pretty much the way it was
         
         GI:  I guess it was, but still-
         
         SS:  It is common in a small community.
         
         GI:  Yes, I imagine so. I guess it was. Some of these people that drank
         and tore around would come to church Sunday, too. It wasn't Straight
         down the line.
         
         SS:  I imagine there were some people that believed in dancing and not in
         drinking,
         
         GI:  Yeah, you're right.
         
         SS:  What about the community church, did most of the people from the area
         go to that church?
         
         GI:  Well, they had two churches. The one on the other end of the Ridge
         was the Lutheran. Most of the people at one time lived on the lower
         end of the Ridge were Lutherans and they had their Bethany Lutheran
         Church and then I think most of the rest of the people, even they did
         belong to other denominations would come to church there and take part
         in Sunday School, because it was a church. Later on that church was-
         The United Brether n wanted to sell it, it sort of died out and they
         couldn't furnish the minister therf. grandfather and my dad and
         my uncle bought the building and my grandfather donated the land and
         so the community tore it down and built the church they have there by
         the cemetery from the old lumber, of course, with some new, but bas
         ically the building was built with the timbers and stuff from
         church.
         
         SS:  And now it's a community church?
         
         GI:  Yeah, it's not used very much. Once in a while they have funerals,
         once in a while they have a service there, but there's not near the
         people there used to be here. Used to have quite a group come. Used
         to have regular revival meetings and that type of thing there. Well,
         I guess they did after they first built the church, but the old church
         used to have quite a lot of that, and they had some of that after the
         new church was built. That was moved there in the '30's.
         
         SS:  Would the revivals last very long?
         
         GI:  Oh, they'd have two weeks.
         
         SS:  Were they well attended?
         
         GI:  pretty well. I remember we used to go. When we was kids we used to
         walk down to that church. It was a little over a mile from our place 4~o
         the old church, and we used to walk to church every night in the win
         tertime.
         
         SS:  What do you remember what the actual revival itself was like? Was
         the preaching pretty strong?
         
         GI:  Well, as I remember it was, seemed like. Yeah, I think it was pret
         ty sincere and strong. Affected some people, I guess.
         
         SS:  Because I've heard that the way it affected a lot of people was very
         emotional.
         
         GI:  They still have that, you have your emotional groups, too, I mean
         some churches are a lot more emotional than others, butA had the
         whole bunch. There was some of 'em that were affected a lot more
         than others. Then we used to have the^church parties, too. That was
         part of the community deal sometimes, too.
         
         SS:  What kind of parties?
         
         GI:  Oh, that'd just be a church dinner or something. We call
         'em bazaars now, stuff like that. Get together and maybe on a Sunday
         have a church dinner, something like that.
         
         SS:  Were most of the people expected to go to church on Sunday?
         
         GI:  It seemen.to me like the biggest part of 'em at that time went to
         church sometime. But we had pretty good attendance, as I remember as
         a kid.
         
         SS:  Maybe not every Sunday though. What about working on Sunday? Were
         there a lot of people that wouldn't do any work on Sunday?
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah. There was a lot of people who wouldn't do anything on Sun
         day. Even people that didn't go to church, wouldn't work on Sunday.
         There was a few that worked on Sunday. That was one thing that my
         dad always said, "There was one day for rest." And we never did work
         in the field on Sunday around our home. Of course, we had the chores
         and stuff like that to do, but going out and actually doing work-in
         the field, we never did do that. He always said we'd have one day off.
         
         SS:  Was it a visiting day for you?
         
         GI:  Yeah, used to go visit the neighbors and we used to have family pic
         nics in the summertime. It was a day that either you had company or
         went someplace and was company for somebody else. Seemtf like
         a lot more of that than there is now.
         
         SS:  When you say family picnic, that makes me wonder, too; when you so
         cialized then was it mostly with the family?
         
         GI:  Big part of it. My uncles lived there and my grandmother was there
         and my dad's sister married Amos Moore and they had a family and they
         lived close there and we visitA back and forth among ourselves,
         but still on the other hand, too, some of the neighbors, we'd be in
         vited there for dinner on Sunday or go someplace else on Sunday. But
         I imagine that nearly half of it was among the family itself, or rela
         tives. We had some relatives lived in Moscow and some lived at Col
         fax and then after we got using automobiles we used to visit with
         them on Sundays and they'd visit us. A big part of it was family.
         
         SS:  All these relatives; had more than one family come here originally
         that was related?
         
         GI:  See, my grandfather came here- when he came he brought his hired man
         with him and his hired man homesteaded the same as he did, and that
         family grew up being pretty close. And then my aunt married one of
         the neighbor boys when she was pretty young. She was about ten or
         twelve when she came here and I guess she got married when she was
         sixteen, so that stErted in with another family, so it didn't take
         long. And then my Grandmother Ingle's brother lived in- had three
         brothers lived in Colfax and^another brother lived- no, cousin-
         A brother lived at Colfax and then the cousins- there were three
         of 'em lived at Colfax and one lived in Deary and one of 'em lived
         on the upper end of the ridge. And that came about^ my Grandmother
         Ingle's side. We had those relatives to visit with and they had families
         too.
         
         SS:  Your grandfather; where did he come from?
         
         GI:  He came from originally Tennessee and then he went to Illinois and he
         was in Illinois when he actually came to Idaho. He came out, I guess,
         in the fall of 1883. I think it was '83. At that time they had the
         railroad built as far as Colfax. And they rented a car on the rail
         road and piled all their belongings on one end and the family lived
         in one end of it while they moved out on the railroad. The story that
         I always heard him say that he and his hired man was with him, he
         came at the same time, brought his family with him. He had a wife
         and some children and grandfather had three or four children at that
         time. Some say he - they rented horses and rode over there and found
         this land where we are and others said he rented a buggy, so I don't
         know which he did, but anyway, he got from Colfax over there and they
         settled0on Big Bear Ridge.
         
         SS:  And he was a homesteader? Nobody else had been on the place?
         
         GI:  No. Well, first he had a right for a preemption and he went on the
         preemption first and then this place that he homesteaded, somebody had
         squatted on it and then gave it up so then he- it was open, so my
         grandfather filed a homestead on it.
         
         SS:  Do you think he did it that way because he still wanted to have his
         right to homestead?
         
         GI:  Probably. I don't know what the deal was.
         
         SS:  Did he get the preemption too?
         
         GI:  Yes. Proved up on both of them. Then my uncle, the oldest one of
         the family, there was a piece of land just north of grandfather's
         preemption that hadn't been taken when he got of age, so he home
         steaded that. My cousin has that place and the one that my grandfather
         s old preemption. He it now.
         
         SS:  Did you ever hear from him why he left Tennessee?
         
         GI:  Yes. He had asthma awful bad. And I guess he just had an awful time.
         And somebody told him if he'd go West he wouldn't have it, so he just
         bundled his family up and decided to try it. I remember him saying
         he never had asthma all his life after he got out here. Remember him
         saying as soon as he came over the mountains he started to breathe.
         And I think that was one of the things that brought him out here.
         
         SS:  Do you have an idea of about how old he was when he came West?
         
         GI:  Well, I could figure it out. He was eighty-four years old when he
         died and he died in 1934.
         
         SS:  So, he would have been about thirty-two. You said he came in '82?
         
         GI:  '83. he was a reasonably young man.
         
         SS:  Did he talk to you at all about what those early pioneer conditions
         were?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes. After he moved down to this other place; they built a house
         and he moved down there and he had his garden and he us ed to have us
         boys help put his wood in and he'd come up to the place everyday.
         He'd walk across the field up to our house. He visited with me a
         lot. Us kids, I mean. He used to sit and talk with us. It was really
         interesting some of the things.
         
         SS:  How hard did he make it out to be when it was just-\hese first settlers?
         
         GI:  Pretty rough. I remember him saying the first year when he came here
         in the fall and I guess it was '83, and they didn't have much to eat
         and the neighbors had lots of rutabagas and they killed a bear, and
         he said they lived on rutabagas and bear meat, of co urse, they got
         a deer I guess too ne said it was a pretty tough winter. I guess they
         completely ran out of groceries early in the spring and still had a
         lot of snow. There was one trip they fixed up an old bobsled; took
         the front runners off of the bobsled and put a team on it, put a box
         on it, just had one set of runners and c to Moscow so they could
         get some groceries. That was the nearest place they had to come to
         get groceries. Took 'em two days, to come to Moscow.. Anyway, when
         he first came they used to, every fall, after they got established,
         they'd bring the team and wagon and try to leave early in the morning
         and get to Moscow and get their winter's supply. And they used
         to try to get out of here in time to get their buying done that day
         and that night they'd hitch up and go out to what's called Corwall
         out here and there was a family name of Hobart that lived out there
         that were real good friends and they'd always go out there and camp
         the rest of that night and then drive back home the n ext day. I've
         heard him talk about that several times; how they used to visit with
         old Sam Hobart.
         
         SS:  Did they camp out? Outside of the house?
         
         GI:  Yes. I guess he'd take as many of 'em inside as he could. But that
         was the stopping place for the people.
         
         SS:  Well, this kind of deal was just in the fall?
         
         GI:  Well, that was the fall deal.^ They always made that one trip to town.
         Sometimes they got so they made two trips to Moscow a year, but that
         was the big one but that was in the fall to get their winter supplies.
         They'd get everything fixed up and they had their food canned from
         garden and their potatoes dug in the cellar and they were just
         about holed up for the winter, the way he used to tell it.
         
         SS:  I've often wondered about how much turnover there was among these
         real earliest pioneers, because they say what happened a lot of places
         that you read about, is that there was a lot of turnover. And maybe
         one in ten actually wound up staying. And yet most people seemed to -
         those people that stayed seemed to remember it as a lot more stable.
         And I just wondered,
         
         GI:  I think that maybe the population was pretty stable there for several
         years, because there's two of us old families that's still out there
         now. The Moreys; Mrs. Cecil Chamberlin was one of the Moreys; their
         place joined ours. And their father came and homesteaded a year or
         two or three before my father homesteaded there. I think there was
         quite a few of 'em stayed, maybe when you look back there wasn't too
         big a percent, but I imagine 50-60% of 'em stayed several years, just
         from listening to my father and grandfather talking.
         
         SS:  I was thinking that maybe some of these real early people, say like
         the guy that wassquatting on this place, it might have been a lot of
         people like that right at the very beginning, that they were the ones
         that turnedpver.
         
         GI:  Of course, that probably made a lot of turnover. I think he just
         came there and he put up a shack and he was going to homestead on
         it, prove up on it, and he just decided it was too hard so then he
         pulls out and my grandfather it up, and I think there were
         several places like that. Maybe that caused a lot of the moving, people
         would decide it was going to be too hard a deal and leave.
         
         SS:  In the winters, when you were a kid, did things get really slow? Was
         there a lot of time that your parents couldn't be that busy? Or were
         they really busy in the winter, too?
         
         GI:  Well, they always had livestock that they had to take care of. Dad
         used to raise hogs and he used to have quite a few of 'em, and later
         when I was a kid they had these Potlatch Forest lumbercamps; one
         just south of Deary and they weren't too far off and he used to butcher
         hogs in the wintertime and deliver butchered hogs to these lumbercamps.
         So he kept pretty busy. Of course, it not have been that way with
         some of the families, but I remember he used to do lots of butchering
         in the wintertime. He used to butcher every two weeks, probably.
         Whenever you butchered in those days, the neighbors all came in and
         help you butcher and you'd go help them butcher. I remember he used
         to butcher several hogs.
         
         SS:  Do you think the pace was about the same as the rest of the year, or
         would you say it would be more leisurely?
         I think they didn't near as fast as we do. They kept busy and
         they made wood; some of 'em made wood in the winter and some of 'em
         made posts. And they had their winter jobs that they did in the win
         ter. I don't think they hit it quite as hard as we do now.
         
         SS:  Did he do a lot of repair work in the winter then?
         
         GI:  Some. They didn't have shops on farms^like they do now. And it wasn t
         too much to fix up a gangplow or a harrow drawbar and stuff like that.
         It didn't take very long to do the repair on machinery. Of course,
         the binders, when they got those, there was repair, but a binder's
         small compared to a combine.
         
         SS:  Was there much concern in your family; was he very concerned about
         the prospects of being able to make good on the place? I'm wondering
         how close to the bone it was. Like I've heard after the First World
         War there was a pretty bad falling off in prices and things were pret
         ty tough.
         
         GI:  Well, it was pretty rough. There during the Depression and three
         of us kids in college and he'd gotten up and he'd been on this
         bankA directors and he got to be president of the bank and
         the bank closed and I think he only had $75 to his name. And that
         was pretty tough going, I tell you. And I quit school that year the
         last sememster and went home and we lined up all the beef cows we
         could and milk cows and at that time we had a creamery, cream station,
         in Kendrick and sold cream; and it was pretty rough times then. But
         he always knew it was going to be better someday. I always remember
         my uncle, he aways said, "Oh, the country's going to the devil."
         "Look here Amy." And Dad would say, "It's not that bad"! And Dad always figured it
         was going to get better.
         
         SS:  What did you call him?
         
         GI:  His name was Amos,.that was his brother-in-law and he called him Amy.
         
         SS:  Probably never did convince him, though.
         
         GI:  No.
         
         SS:  What was it that did happen in the bank? What kind of situation was
         it that developed?
         
         GI:  What happened was when this depression came and people got scared and
         they started drawing their money out and the banks had loans on it;
         had the money loaned out and they couldn't liquidate fast enough to
         pay off the depositors. That's what closed the banks in the depres
         sion then. If they'd have just left their money in the bank and
         stayed with them, wouldn't have any trouble, but you can see what
         happens; you got a loan out here say that's due in six months and the
         guy comes in and wants his money and you can't liquidate and that
         guy can't dig up the money right now, so that's what happens to the
         bank. People just pulling their savings out of the banks, afraid
         the bank's going to go broke. It's like in the Depression; it got
         to be a chain thing. One bank goes broke and everybody rushed into
         the next bank and other banks and start drawing their money out.
         
         SS:  Which bank was this?
         
         GI:  Kendrick State Bank.
         
         SS:  Did it close down before the bank holiday? Was it before Roosevelt
         got in?
         
         GI:  Yeah. They opened it again later on and then the two banks went to
         gether and made one bank. But it closed about a month before that
         bank holiday.
         
         SS:  What were the losses at the point that it closed?
         
         GI:  Well, actually, it came out pretty good. Of course it had to be
         liquidated, but they liquidated out nearly 100%. They had good paper,
         good mortgage and good notes and stuff like that, it was just the
         thing that you just can't liquidate^fast enough when the people draw
         their money out. It took over a period of years, but they pretty
         well liquidated out.
         
         SS:  Does that mean that people that owed money paid it back?
         
         GI:  Right. They way they got it started again, they got some of the large
         stockholders that had, they called it big money then, $7,000, $8,000
         to go in and put their money as stock, and they got the thing to going
         again that way. And thesexstockholders they came out all right. The
         people that did that they came out real good, because later on the bank
         was solvent.
         
         SS:  How many years later did they start it up again? 
         
         GI:  It was started up that next year after they closed. I don't think
         it was closed six months.
         
         SS:  How long did it take your father to get his money bank; what he had
         in it?
         
         GI:  I think within a year or so they had what he had in it. Well, he lost
         some, of course, but not too much.
         
         SS:  That sounds like it wasn't too bad then. Like I heard the Moscow State
         Bank only paid back something like fifty cents on the dollar.
         
         GI:  Well, there was several of them that did, but I think that that one
         particular bank, I think most everybody got their money out of it in
         the longrun. Pretty sure they did.
         
         SS:  It seems to me that that's also what happened in Troy, although the
         bank didn't close.
         
         GI:  The Troy bank was just about- they just told the depositors if they
         drew out their money they wouldn't have a bank and the depositors
         stuck with Ole Bdman, the old man that was in there for years, you
         know. They were just about ready to close but they kept it open by
         talking the people out of taking their money out. And Frank Green
         down there help a lot, he was pretty well off.
         
         SS:  So you think that if maybe they'd tried a little harder in Kendrick
         and if they'd have moved on it faster they could have—
         
         GI:  It's hard to combat something like that. One thing that sort of hurt
         em^at the Kendrick State Bank; the bank in Juliaetta was owned by
         the- well, it's the First Security now, but it was Melgar^ that had
         that old bank and they bought that Juliaetta bank and it wasn't going
         very good, and those people were the first to pull their money out.
         Some of 'em didn't like it they were losing their bank and they
         didn't realize what kind of a predicament they were really in. And
         some of those people were the first to^uli their money out. So 
         
         SS:  Out of the Kendrick bank and put it into the Juliaetta bank.
         
         GI:  Yes. After the Juliaetta bank was closed, the Kendrick bank bought
         the Juliaetta bank, and so that moved all the depositors and all their
         paper and so forth. So, when this depression started going and some
         of them didn't like losing their bank in Juliaetta, so they were pro
         bably the first to start drawing their money out.
         
         SS:  Was it the Kandrick State that bought the Juliaetta bank?
         
         GI:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And it had been Melgafd's?
         
         GI:  Yes.
         
         SS:  And there were two banks in Kendrick, too?
         
         GI:  Right. There was the Farmer's Bank and the Kendrick State. My dad
         was a stockholder in the Farmer's Bank, too, but not very much. Just
         one share. They were $100 shares in those days, I think it was.
         
         SS:  That might have also put more strain on the community resources to
         have two banks instead of one.
         
         GI:  Right. At one time Troy had two banks, too, but they just had one
         bank at this time. That made a difference, too, I'll say it did.
         And the other bank was a branch of the- it was a Vollmer bank; branch
         of the Vollmer system in Lewis ton. And they had the backingjdown there
         of the bigger bank and they kept it from closing it's doors, but it
         wasn't in very good shape, either.
         
         SS:  Mentioning Vollmer; people in the early days- did Vollmer have kind
         of a bad reputation around Kendrick?
         
         GI:  Yes, yes, he did. There was some Vollmer land adjoinedJthe place that
         I have now and the Vollmer place, the other on the east- west side of
         the Ridge, too. I think probably the reason- I don't know how this
         happened but undoubtedly they probably loaned people money and then
         they couldn't pay their bill and they foreclosed on their land.
         And they got a pretty big holding. And probably some of the people
         just walked off and left it too, and probably some of them the
         closed. I know they foreclosed on one guy that lived over there by
         us. And they had an old guy, called him S. D. White, used to be the
         for Vollmer and oh, he was hard-boiled. I imagine he was
         pretty rough on some of these renters they had.
         
         SS:  Did he actually come out to these people's places?
         
         GI:  Yeah, I used to see him quite often when I was a kid. When they
         didn't pay their rent and that kind of stuff. I remember seeing him
         a lot. I remember one time that he called my dad up over the phone
         and we had^threshers there and they had this big machine threshing
         and I remember Dad saying, "You will?" He says, "We're ready to go."
         That's all Dad said and I asked him he said and he said that
         S. D. White said that he's going to put the h^ole board of directors
         of the Roachdale Warehouse in jail because they'd bought some crop
         off of one of these places.
         
         GI:  And he used to stop and talk to Dad once in a while, they really rib
         bed each other. I remember Dad was kidding him about what a hard-boiled
         guy he was. I think that's really where he go the reputation from.
         This one old guy he was as hard as nails. I suppose in those days
         maybe they had to be, I don't know. They wouldn't stay in business
         nowdays, I don't think.
         
         SS:  When you were growing up then, do you have any memories of Prohibi
         tion and moonshiners?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes, we had moonshine. There was moonshine a lot when I was a
         kid, and I remember them talking about it a lot. They used to catch
         a still once in a while out in that wheat country, down in the woods
         someplace.
         
         SS:  Did your father, being opposed to drinking, make you feel that you
         couldn't try it?
         
         GI:  Well, I don't know. I never had any desire to try it. Lot of the
         kids did. I've seen lots of it but I just never wanted to try it.
         
         SS:  Then your father's teaching-
         
         GI:  Must have been. Must have been his teaching.
         
         SS:  How much opportunity was there, do you think for the kids that were
         growing up to stay around Kendrick and the Ridge? With these big
         families and small farms.
         
         GI:  Well, really wasn't too much. Way it seemed to work out, the kids
         that went on to schoolJKon to college never came back, but the ones
         that never went to school after the high school and some of them after
         the eighth grade all stayed around home. Stayed in the community
         until they'd find something else, maybe get into some other field,
         but there wasn't too much work for big employment in the area. Of
         course, a lot of 'em went to the timber work, too. So they'd leave
         home to go work in the woods, the Potlatch Forest or some of those
         camps down at Deary and Bovill, and some of them went there. But stayed
         right in their own community. There wasn't much for them to do un
         less they farmed. I know there was one family there that all thevr
         kids stayed on the farm and they'd watch and maybe they'd get to rent
         a farm and get married and live there.
         
         SS:  At your time, did most of the kids go on to high school from the eighth
         grade?
         
         GI:  It was a small percent, really. And college, boy, that was out of
         this world! I think out of high school wasn't very big,
         seven pupils graduated from high school the same year I did, I think
         I was the only one that went on to college. Let's see, one of 'em
         went to business college, I guess.
         
         SS:  Were you set on going to college? Was it your idea or your father's?
         
         GI:  I just grew up with the idea that I wanted to go to college and tiy
         mother had been a school teacher and I guess it was just in my mind
         as I grew up, I just naturally supposed that was the thing that I
         wanted to do. And there were four of us and we all went to college.
         I was the only one that never graduated. I got my four years in. I
         quit the midyear in '32 when the Depression went home. And
         then I came back in the fall of '33, and so I got my number of years
         in but never got the right semesters in. But my brother went on and
         graduated from Ag school and then he came back and he and I farmed
         together and then he went back and got his master's degree in soil
         And my sister, one of em was a commercial teacher, taught school
         seven years and the other sister was a home ec graduate. She taught
         two or three years before she got married and then they went to New
         Mexico andA work(for the Indian Service and so she taught home
         ec down in- was it Albuquerque?- no, it wasn't Albuquerque but Gallup.
         She taught home ec there several years. We sort of had some
         resentment toward us kids in the local community about us going on to
         school with certain people, but we never let it bother us too much.
         
         SS:  What was Idaho like when you went to school?
         
         GI:  It was a lot smaller; I think we had between 1,500, 1,600 pupils.
         And in those days everybody said hello to everybody. They used to have
         these little that had" hello". Most friendly bunch of people you
         ever saw. Quite a change from high school, but it didn't take us
         long to blend in, I stayed at the old Hall, it's torn down now.
         It was a dormitory then and later on they made a co-op out of it.
         Wasn't a coop when I was going to school. Stayed there. The second
         year after I was there I got to working in the kitchen, hashing and
         scrubbing floors.
         
         SS:  Did you work your way through school?
         
         GI:  I was almost selfsupporting then after that. Well, see, my brother
         was just one year behind me and my sister one year behind him and
         then it ended up when I was a junior there was three of us up here.
         And my brother got a job working for a dairy and my sister got a job
         working for the veterinary at that time for the University working
         for room and board in the home. So, there wasn't a real big outlay
         but it was an effort. And we always had the support of our parents
         about going on to school. They never forced us, we just sort of
         grew up with that attitude; we wanted an education.
         
         SS:  You didn't get into a fraternity at all?
         
         GI:  No, I never joined a fraternity. My brother joined the TKEs later
         on. And neither sister joined a sorority either.
         
         SS:  That costs more money.
         
         GI:  Yeah, it costs more money.
         
         SS:  Was that a lot of why you didn't, or weren't you interested in it
         anyway?
         
         GI:  Well, I wasn't too much interested, really. I think one thing, the
         cost sort of bothered me and then I just didn't have the desire. Like
         some kids would come up here and if they didn't get to go to a frater
         nity they thought there was something bad about 'em. But I always
         remember one of our proctors, Bob Green, he's still living here around
         someplace- George Green. He got up in our dormitory dining room and
         he says, "it's rush week now. Some of you people aren't going to get
         a chance to go to a fraternity and some are. Some go to the fra
         ternity, it's going to go to their heads and they won't know you when
         you go to the fraternities. Remember if he's that kind of a person,
         he's not worth a tinker's damn." I thought about that; I knew some
         of the guys that pledged were just as friendly after they went to the
         fraternity and others it did go to their head. They thought that
         was something really out of this world.
         
         SS:  Did you feel that you were here just to learn? Or did you feel you
         were here to have a good time?
         
         GI:  I was coming here to learn, that was the idea of coming.
         We had some good times. You're bound to have good times. But basical
         ly you're supposed to learn.
         
         SS:  What were the kind of social good times that they had then?
         
         GI:  Well, we used to have, I don't know whether they still do or not.
         invite gals over to our dormitory to dinner and then dance afterwards.
         And then you'd be invited over to their place the next month or some
         thing. And then they had theirhall dances and they had dances down to
         the Student Union and the class dances. I learned to dance after I
         got up here, too. I don't know, seems like we went to lots of shows.
         And then I was quite active in the church group. The Wesley Foundation
         was the Methodist Church Group. In fact, that's where I met my wife.
         We had a party every Saturday night and social hour Sunday night and
         Sunday School in the morning. And it seemed like there was plenty of
         places to go and we seemed to have good times.
         
         SS:  Was she going to school here, too?
         
         GI:  Yes, she was a freshman the same time I was.
         
         SS:  From where?
         
         GI:  She was from the Boise Valley, down at Eagle, right close to Boise.
         Her name was Warren. At one time the Warren family had the most
         number of students from one family in the University till a guy by
         the name of Johnson came along and had one or two more. Brothers;
         her older brother was the first- nelCt to her older brother was the
         first president of Lindlay Hall when they first built it. Charley
         Warren. And then she had an older brother named George that graduated
         from law school. He's still living he's up in his eighties in Cali
         fornia.
         
         SS:  Was there a good deal of supervision of you young men and women when
         you were at the University then, or did you pretty much go their own
         way?
         
         GI:  The way they did; they controlled the girls, the girls had to be in
         at certain hours and that sort of controlled the boys. I guess they
         had to be in by midnight.
         
         SS:  I know that Dean French had quite a reputation.
         
         GI:  She was quite an old gal. I remember when I was a freshman and had
         this big deal on etiquette that she used to give every year and sometimes
         twice a year. The proctor saw that we were in to hear Dean
         French's lessons on etiquette; how to behave yourselves and all this
         kind of stuff.
         
         SS:  Did you get much out of it at the time?
         
         GI:  I guess we did. Of course, my mother was pretty strict on manners at
         the table and stuff like that, so it wasn't too shocking to me as it
         was to some, I guess.
         
         SS:  Do you think it helped some?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes, it helped. Of course, we had a lot of fun about it, but it
         helps, I know it .It had to help.
         
         SS:  I've heard people say that they- that it was common for the boys to
         hate Dean French the whole time they were in school and then after
         they got out turn around and think she was the greatest person.
         
         GI:  Yeah, they gave her hell all the time but she was pretty good, really.
         She was really softhearted. I mean, if you'd go in her office and ask
         her about something she was real nice to you. But, boy, at these meetings
         she really laid it down.
         
         SS:  Do you think that there was much fooling around, you know, like
         sleeping together before marriage, like there is these days?
         
         GI:  Not, too much. A Not too much.
         
         SS:  Not common. That's one thing that really seems to have changed.
         
         GI:  Yeah, it seems like they've sure changed a lot.
         
         SS:  Was the depression much of a pall over the way people were at that
         time? Did it seem to affect the students at the school? Because
         it was already started.
         
         GI:  I remember one kid that came to school and he played basketball, of
         course he got a scholarship, came here in an old Ford car and he
         didn't have money enough to run it and we'd throw our pennies together.
         Sometimes we'd buy a gallon of gas and we'd toot in that old car.
         One time I remember we had to push it downtown. There used to be a
         service station down at the foot of the hill down here where the electric
         company is down-there, down in there; we'd push it
         down the hill and we'd pool our money and get - gas was about 23c or
         18 or 19c- get our pennies together and buy maybe two gallons of gas.
         We had a lot of fun. Everybody was the same. Everybody was hard up.
         I don t know, we had just as much fun then as when we had money.
         
         SS:  What were you studying then?
         
         GI:  I was taking business. Took business and ended up farming.
         
         SS:  So you weren't planning at the time to farm?
         
         GI:  No, I was going to go in the bank, was what I really intended to do.
         After I went home Dad wanted me to stay and help him farm and so I
         was going to help farm until my brother, came over to take over the
         farm and he came there a year or two and then he decided to go back
         to school and get his masters degree, and I don't know, I just naturally
         drifted into it. The war came in the early '40's, Dad said, "Well,
         I'll just run the farm over to you if you want to farm." So that's
         how I got to farming. I never intended to farm, but I haven t regretted
         it though. It's quite a business. Business education sure didn't
         hurt me in the farming. And I always worked real close with the
         county extension agent, program and so forth.
         
         SS:  So your brother didn't want to go back to farming then?
         
         GI:  No, not really. When he graduated he went to work tor
         the soil conservation service, then he got drafted in the army. Then
         when he came back he went to work for Libby's and he was a field man
         and buyer down on the coast for over twenty years for them. Then
         they retired him he dabbled in real estate and he's working for North
         west Packing Company. He quit it a while and just seemed to like to
         get back in it. He's quite a social guy and he knows his stuff in
         that line, buying for packers, fruit and vegetables and so forth.
         
         SS:  Did you have it in mind then to stay here if you possibly could?
         
         GI:  Yeah, I intended to go in the bank at home when Dad was on the board,
         really. But I had a chance to go to work there once and my uncle
         sort of- The banker was going to have to be out of town and there was
         only one man there, one man was gone, and they had to have somebody
         to be in the bank by himself and there was another fellow who worked
         in a bank for years that was unemployed, so this guy the
         experience, they better get him in the bank and then he got the second
         job after the this guy came back. He had to be gone a while. I just
         about got started there then. Then I got married; '35 it was.
         
         SS:  Things were pretty severe, I imagine, for your folks to decide you
         should really come home; or did you decide you should leave school?
         
         GI:  Well, yes, I sort of decided. My grades weren't too good and I wor-
         ried quite a lot about things my grades weren t very good that
         semester, and Dad just had to have some help.
         
         SS:  You were worried about the farm?
         
         GI:  Yeah, I worried about that, and so I just went home that year. And
         it was pretty tough pickings, I tell you. The bank had closed thatin
         December, I guess.that year. Then I went back in the fall of '33
         again. wife graduated in the spring of '32 and my brother gradua
         ted in '33. And he came back to the farm about three or four years,
         I guess. He used to get so excited when things were pushing, you know,
         he wouldn't sleep of a night; got to get this done, got to get that
         done. So he decided he wanted to g© into something else. I think
         he had in mind to go into the soil conservation because he took his
         masters in soil
         
         SS:  You say things were pretty tough and slim pickings; did that mean that
         there wasn't that you could do.
         
         GI:  much money!
         SS What did you do then? Just worked the farm?
         
         GI:  Just worked the farm and I did a little bit of everything, if I could
         find something to do. I even hung some paper, papered rooms! For
         people. Worked on the telephone line, did all kinds of things, where
         I could get a few dollars a day. Don't get money very fast!
         Did you wind up taking over a lot of the farming pretty soon after you
         got out of school?
         
         GI:  Yes. After I came back put a lot of the responsibility of running
         the farm actually, say about the time I got married, '34, '35,
         along in there. Of course, my brother was there in '34 but I sort
         of took the lead on things and he shoved quite a lot of the responsi
         bility of running the farm over to me.
         
         SS:  When would you say it started really recovering; really coming out
         of the Depression?
         
         GI:  oh I suppose '37, '38, '39, through there, it started picking up.
         But when wheat's twenty-five and thirty-five cents a bushel, like it
         was in the deep depression, don't bring money in very fast.
         
         SS:  Were you selling it at twenty-five a bushel?
         
         GI: Well, we never did sell any at twenty-five; some of the neighbors
         did. And then some sold at thirty-five cents. I don't think we ever
         sold anything below fifty.
         
         SS:  Did you know any of your neighbors who were in real diee straights?
         Really, barely had enough to eat?
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah. Generally the farm people generally had enough to eat.
         They had their gardens and their food and they canned lots and they
         had their own meat. They had animals they could kill, so they never
         went hungry. But they just didn't have any money to do anything else
         so they stayed at home and ate! 
         
         SS:  Did anybody lose their places around there?
         
         GI:  Yeah, there was a few lost their places. I know the neighbor, he was
         going to throw his place up and he had a Federal Land Bank-note and
         he couldn't raise enough money to pay the interest and we had a real
         good guy here who worked for the Federal Land Bank , and he came
         out there and he just stayed with him half a day and talked him into
         the notion of hanging onto his place. You know most of these guys
         were honest and when they owed something they wanted to pay it when
         it was due and some of 'em just couldn't take the pressure.
         to work it out with some banks and some loaning companies were
         pretty reasonable about it, I mean if you try. But some of 'em, you
         know, they just figured that there was never a chance, they just quit.
         SSS Do you think the people that did give up maybe didn't have to?
         
         GI:  Some of 'em, if they could have stuck it out they could have stayed
         I think. There might have been a few that couldn't. There wann't too
         many in our area but there was some.
         
         SS:  What about politics in those days? I understood that the county,
         and Moscow especially, was extremely strong Republican.
         
         GI:  Yeah, it was, the county was. Ued to be that nearly all county of
         ficers were Republican. And it seemed like then it switched around
         I think that probably now it's about 50-50, the way it looks.
         
         SS:  Was your father a Democrat?
         
         GI:  Yeah, he was a Democrat.
         
         SS:  Was that really from his father's Southern background?
         grand
         
         GI:  Oh, I suppose. I'd tell my Republican friends that my father was a
         real Democrat. He came from Tennessee. He was a real broad-minded
         Democrat because he always said that a Republican was just as good as
         a Democrat as long as the Republican behaved himself. I've heard
         Grandfather say that a lot. (Chuckles) I know they used to really
         have some political battles. Grandfather ran for county commissioner
         one time and he always said he got counted out for he ran on the Demo
         cratic ticket. That was real early in the county history when he
         ran for it.
         
         SS:  He got counted out: What do you mean by that? They fixed the vote
         against him?
         
         GI:  Yes, that's what he always figured. I don't know whether they did
         or not, but he always figured, he always said, "Oh, I got elected,
         but I got counted out!" And I think politics in those days- elections
         and so forth- were probably a lot looser than they are now. In a
         deal like have now it's pretty hard to be counted out!
         
         SS:  Was Kendrick also strong Republican at the time? Or was it more
         even in the early days?
         
         GI:  Well, I think Kendrick- they had both, but probably Kendrick itself
         was at that time probably more Republican. But it was pretty well
         balanced.
         
         SS:  What about the balance of power between Moscow and the rest of the
         county in those days? You often get the idea that they got the county
         seat and grabbed everything.
         
         GI:  You always heard that, I've heard that all my life, that Moscow ran
         the county, but I don't think it really (did). they probably had
         quite a lot of influence on the other, but I don't think they ran the
         county. Because we've always had commissioners and legislators from
         other areas in the county. It hasn't been all elected in Moscow.
         But I think that's one of the things that happens when you have one
         big town in the county that people get that kind of an attitude.
         
         SS:  You think that the rural county did as well with roads and improve
         ments as they could possibly be expected to do in those early days?
         
         GI:  You see, it used to be- I can just barely remember when they formed
         highway districts. They used to have the county road supervisor
         and county roads. And they'd have the county supervisor appointed by
         the commissioners; county commissioners had charge of certain roads
         in certain areas. It was the same then as it is now, if they got a
         good supervisor they had pretty good care and they got a poor one
         they didn't. But then later on, they had highway districts formed and
         we had about twelve- I know they were consolidated a few years ago,
         I think they have nine but I think there had been a consolidation a
         little earlier; probably had fifteen or sixteen, probably, nearly that
         many, maybe not quite. And they were their own governing district
         and it just depended on how- of course, the money was limited, the
         amount they could raise, but it's like anything else, one group in
         one district the board of commissioners would get more out of their
         money- I mean, get more work done for the money than another district.
         It sort of depended on them. At that time road districts had a
         right to bond, too, to build roads and so did that and did pretty
         well and some did it and really loused up. They didn't have Enough
         technical service and so forth. I know the Deary District out there
         bonded and built a lot of roads down below town there one time. Of
         course, I was just a kid and I remember hearing the folks and other
         people talking about how they squandered their money, but maybe they
         didn't. Fact though when the state camexlong and built the roads they
         used a lot of this old road that they had, went the same place, so
         in the longrun it wasn't wasted.
         
         SS:  When you're talking about the consolidation it makes me think of
         the school consolidating that went on and I was wondering whether that
         was looked at, how positively it was concerned by the people—
         
         GI:  Well, quite a lot of concern and I was on th$Torganization board. I
         don't know anything you got chewed out for any more. See, they had
         eighty school districts in this county and this board consolidated
         them down to five. And I was a member of that board. That was in
         the late '40's. And you really got chewed out, they were losing their
         little red schoolhouse of course, but they didn't have the kids to
         put there. Big part of the schools at that time were going into the
         towns, a lot of them were under what they call temporary consolidation
         and they were going in and paying so much per pupil for them to educate
         their kids. And when the legislature passed a law, ten, I think it
         was, if a school couldn't afford to have a school out here then they
         would go under temporary consolidation after so long a time they'd
         have to consolidate. I guess they didn't close the loopholes enough
         so that they way it was fixed they could continue having one temporary
         consolidation after another. And so finally the state passed this
         consolidation law, set up the deal for a consolidation committee in
         each county and I happened to land on that.
         
         SS:  How many were on the committee?
         
         GI:  Six.
         
         SS:  Was it your responsibility to draw up the plan for the whole county/
         
         GI:  Right. Yeah.
         
         SS:  Then did that plan have to be approved by a vote in the county?
         
         GI:  By the district. We had to hold a public hearing in each district.
         
         SS:  Each of the sixty?
         
         GI:  No, each of the five districts we formed. And there was a lot of
         work. In fact, I ran most of the legal description of all of these
         districts. I took interest in that and I knew the descriptions pretty
         well. I ran all except one. I ran all the legal descriptions
         for all of the school districts.
         
         SS:  Legal description; meaning all the boundaries?
         
         GI:  The boundaries.
         
         SS:  What do you think of the concerns of these small communities? Were
         they legitimate?
         
         GI:  Well, not really, because here they would have...
         
         GI:  The old schoolhouse was standing there and the kids were being educated
         in town and they could only charge so much - a certain rate- for the
         education-^tuition, see, and that put the home school in an awful bad
         position. It was costing them more to educate the children within
         their own district than they were getting per pupil from the other dis
         tricts, in some cases. And I think that-
         
         SS:  You mean the burden of payment was on the home district? Was on Troy
         or was on the Burnt Ridge?
         
         GI:  Like in ours there, the burden would have been on Kendrick, because
         they were furnishing the facilities.
         
         SS:  And they were a lot more than they were getting per pupil?
         
         GI:  Yes Per Pupil and they could just charge for the cost of education
         like for the teachers' salaries and that, they couldn't run in their
         depreciation and stuff on their billings, the way I remember it, so
         it actually cost the people in town more per pu£if there than they
         were collecting from the rural district.
         
         SS:  My impression from what old-timers have said, I think the fear of
         what was really going on, maybe, was this emotional fear of the com
         munity itself, which was centered on the school, going down and dis
         appearing, falling apart because they wouldn't have this school as
         a focus. You know what I mean? That's my impression. Do you think
         that was going on, too?
         
         GI:  Well, the rural school used to be the center of the community, where
         they had all their different community affairs and so forth, but still
         they weren't using the school under this temporary consolidation, 
         there were some that were, but a big percent of them would go into
         the towns anyway at that time. All of our schools in my area were
         under temporary consolidation; going in by school buses and so forth.
         
         SS:  So, it was in fact, already- they already had that.
         
         GI:  Had that before they made this compulsory consolidation law.
         
         SS:  What year was the committee operating?
         Oh, let's see, seems to me that was in- whether they passed it in '46
         or '47, anyway, it was before the '50's. I think it was about '48
         when they were consolidated.
         When do you think the little schools started to close up as temporary
         consolidated came in?
         Some of it happened around in '35 to '36, starting back that early.
         
         SS:  Just continued to grow?
         
         GI:  To grow, yes. You see, on our ridge I think they consolidated intemporary
         consolidated in '36, in the school where I lived. Two
         School's went together. One of the schools kept on having school
         and then in two or three more years they went in and first thing
         they had the whole thing. That's about what happened. The high
         school kids had to go in town anyway, and so they'd buy a school
         bus and have a temporary consolidation for the grade school pupils
         and the high school kids could ride on the bus. Used to be the
         high school kids were getting there the best way they can, driving
         cars and so forth. All in all, the people that were having children
         in school would^get by cheaper that way than having all these private
         cars. More tendency then for kids to go to high school than there
         was a little earlier.
         
         SS:  First just the high school kids were going in on the school bus?
         
         GI:  No.
         
         SS:  They were all going in?
         
         GI:  No, when they started in with the bus under temporary consolidation
         then the high school kids could ride on the bus. Prior to that the
         high school kids had to get there the best way they could or stay in
         town or something. But it was quite a radical change, but I think
         it was for the better, because it was getting then that the school
         population in rural communities was starting to dwindle off quite a
         lot from what it had been prior to
         
         SS:  The only part of it that I have been really questioned about- people
         wondering about- is the east end of the county, with Bovill and then
         those parts that are out of the county, Elk River and Clarkia. You
         know, Elk River and Clarkia seemed kind of stranded up there with
         support really too small a population to a ' district. Well, of
         course, I guess, they got the money in Elk River from their land
         taxes and timber. That's one thing that people would ask me about,
         too.
         
         GI: I'll tell you, Bovill and Clarkia- Bovill wanted to try to form a
         district with Clarkia and Elk River coming into Bovill high
         school there. They did not want to go to Deary, Bovill didn't.
         Bovill people were all for that but the Clarkia and Elk River people
         weren't. I remember we had several meetings up there. That was a
         really hot spot out at Bovill when they finally decided to put Bovill
         in with Deary. We were going that way and then Troy and Deary sort
         of got together and they said, "Why don't you make one district out
         of the two and have a high school in each place?" Oh, we had a lot
         of opposition to that and so we held a hearing in Troy, I remember that
         very well. You've probably hear of Anna Marie Oslnnd; taught school
         for years there. We presented our plan, forming that White Pine
         District and we opened the meeting for discussion adn she got up and
         walked out there, and I wondered what's going to happend. She said,
         "I think this committee has done a wonderful job on this plan. I
         don't think they could have done any better. Let's all give 'em a
         hand!" And boy, our troubles were all over then. The ones that were
         there/wouldnft go against Anna Marie! (Chuckles) That was next to the
         last and that last one was the Potlatch District. That was sort of
         an unique district; Potlatch Forest owned the buildings over there,
         the old schoolhouse, that's where the apartments areAthere now. And
         we had a meeting with their board, their superintendent. The super
         intendent's name was Hopwood, Vern Hopwood, I think he lives in Clarkston
         now- and what was the name of the other guy's name that was on
         the board? Anyway he had the depot there for Potlatch?
         
         SS:  Was that Gamble?
         
         GI:  Gamble; Walt Gamble. And we had a meeting there and they weren't
         interested in this consolidation, says, "We've got several questions
         here that we got to ask our attorney." And just sort of made a
         mockery out of our meeting, we ddin't accomplish anything. So there
         was a guy by the name of Bodine of Lewiston who was on the state
         reorganization committee, and Louifl Boas, he was chairman of the reor
         ganization committee and Louif got pretty sore and he called Leo Burdine
         up here and he told him what our deal with Potlatch was and he
         just laughed to beat the band. He said, "The attorney that they're
         going to get their questions from is adjacent to my office," He says,
         "I think I can get next to them." We weren't accomplishing anything
         at all. And all at once we got an invitation for the whole committee
         to come to Potlatch school for dinner. We went up there and after
         we had our dinner they got up there and they presented this plan all
         made out and all ready to go, and.intent of Potlatch Forest giving
         the schoolhouse to the district. So they got that fixed up pretty
         good, pretty fast. But I'm sure that Bodine had quite a lot to do
         with that.
         
         SS:  Quite interesting that that's what it took. They were pretty indep
         endent, weren't they?
         
         GI:  They were independent but still they couldn't be too darn independent
         because they didn't own their building. You see, what had happened
         they had the school levies up there but when the money ran out, tea
         chers teaching there would probably get to the end of the year, they'd
         probably get checks Potlatch Froest paying them. So they
         sort of owned the thing so that subsidized the school that much. They
         were trying to be independent but they couldn't.
         
         SS:  The community?
         
         GI:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  They say up there that they had a really good school district in the
         early days; Potlatch put a lot of money into it.
         
         GI:  I think they did. As I say, when the money ran out Potlatch Forest
         picked up the rest to finish the year out. It went off real nice when
         they- but I m sure they told them down there for the boys up there to
         get with it.
         
         SS:  Were people on the board reluctant to have separate high school in
         Troy and Deary at first?
         
         GI:  Yeah, they were. We had one that was on the Troy high school board
         and one on the Deary board onn planning deal. First when theywhen
         this was first proposed to them they just said, no, then there
         was some people got to talking and decided, well maybe that would be
         the easiest way to do it and they finally went for it. We never
         went into a district to present a consolidated plan until the whole
         board was on and backing the plan, see. So that way they couldn't
         one^was against, that one was for. When we went in with a
         plan we 100% support from the whole committee.
         
         SS:  Was Deary for the consolidated district because it meant that they
         could have their own high school and maybe not go to Bovill.
         Yeah, I think that helped a lot. Of course, the Bovill people were
         against this. As I say, earlier, they wanted this Clarkia and
         Elk River. But they had a pretty good plan worked up there, but
         Elk River and Clarkia didn't want to have nothing to do with it.
         What about Kendrick and Juliaetta? That's the place where I always
         thought we had a good hot rivalry.
         
         GI:  We really did, I tell you, we really had a rivalry there and that was
         my home and I had to conduct that meeting. We had a rule that
         the one that was in the area was the one tht conducted the hearing.
         And Juliaetta came there with a force and they got right in the front
         row and they'd jump up and talk one after the other. And before I
         could get to recognize somebody. Finally Louif Boas passed the
         to 'em, he says, "Let's hear what some others have to say besides
         Juliaetta." I was trying to get to that position so I says, "Is any
         body here that's not from Juliaetta got anything to say?" The
         superintendent of school at Juliaetta got up and he just tore- and
         I says, "Sit down, I didn't recognize you." So, we got quite a lot
         of chatter going, but anyway when it was put to a vote the group approved
         it; approve* the plan.
         
         SS:  Did Kendrick ever get to speak out on it?
         
         GI:  Oh, yeah. Yeah, they got to speak. The people from Kendrick got to
         talk on it. I had one of my neighbors up there, 6rom one of the rural
         schools, that really tore he says, "Any many with any sense
         would know better than to try to do something like this." I'll always
         remember him saying that. He was hitting at me, see. But anyway, he
         didn't go over very big. You started to say for a year- for a year
         what?
         
         GI:  You mean about him saying that nobody of any sense would-
         
         SS:  No, before that, you were saying- you started to say; the upshot of
         the meeting was^proved, but then it just-
         
         GI:  For a few years after that, some of the older people in Juliaetta
         they just kept harping, "We lost our school'.' But the year that this
         happened they had one graduate in their senior class. And Kendrick
         went down and ask them if they wanted to consolidate the1Commence
         ment, and they said, "We're going to have our last graduation." So
         this one poor kid got the whole -° . But the kids works in good to
         gether. It took quite a while for some of the older people, I mean,
         losing their high school But actually what they happened, they had
         a better school afterwards because we took all the first six grades
         down there to Juliaetta. And ' the junior high and the high
         school in Kendrick. So, actually they were having more people in
         school than they ever had, in fact, had to build onto the schoolhouse
         a few years later down there. It took a while for them to get over
         but they still got their schoolhouse and the first six grades
         are down there yet. So it worked out real good, I think.
         
         SS:  You know talking about back in history, tradition, it seems like that
         the two towns always have had a bitter rivalry between them.
         
         GI:  Yeah, it all happened years ago. You've probably heard this story
         before; you see, Juliaetta was the first established town and they
         had the first post office down there. " they built the railroad
         down there they tried to get a right-of-way down there for a turntable
         to turn the train around because they couldn't make the ra ilroad
         clear to Lewiston then, and they was holding the railroad up and they
         couldn't get property and old guy name of Kirby owned the land where
         Kendrick was he says," I'll give you the (Land)." So the train for afew
         years turned around there at Kendrick even though when it went to
         Juliaetta it'd back up there and turn around and go back to Spokane.
         And that's really what gave the boost that started it. Kendrick got
         Kendrick
         a good start. I think probably there was some there be
         fore that, but that was the thing that gave it the boost.
         
         SS:  Then, it's really because Juliaetta people or something would hold
         the railroad up.
         
         GI:  That's the story I always heard, that that was what gave Kendrick the
         boost, because that was the end of the railroad.
         SDS: I just wondered; it seemed to me that maybe part of the rivalry came
         from the fact that the towns are so close. They're both pretty good
         size.
         
         GI:  They always had a fight; the old baseball teams- oh, Juliaetta and
         Kendrick baseball, each town used to have a town team, you know, baseball.
         And I remember them telling about it. And I saw some of it
         after I was old enough, after I got in school. They always had their
         fights over the old town team baseball.
         
         SS:  Was that a regular Sunday—?
         
         GI:  Yeah, that was a Sunday afternoon deal. And there was quite a lot of
         rivalry there. And then in the wintertime you used to couldn't get
         frcm Kendrick to Juliaetta on the road, it would get wet and it was
         muddy and so forth and that was when I was in high school when that
         road was first graveled, that they had a graveled road between Kendrick
         and Juliaetta. And then sometimes when I was in high school you
         hardly couldn t get through there^it would be so darn muddy. It's hard to
         believe now.
         
         SS:  Did the towns, do you feel like, that really between the people in the
         towns there was really a strong rivalry or was there a lot of friend
         ship underneath that? Or was it really more rivalry?
         
         GI:  More rivalry, I think. There was some of 'em that were real bitter;
         but there was rivalry. Now you take the t^epjione company in Kendrick
         was bought by the Schupfers, and they lived in Juliaetta, and things
         like that. They worked together but there was a lot of rivalry. Like
         events and things, especially the baseball and other things. I think
         some of the old-timers all thought Juliaetta should have been the
         bigger town. Of course, Juliaetta now is gaining population, but the
         business center is more in Kendrick. And Kendrick always had the doc
         tor and Kendrick had the dentist and the banks. Of course, they used
         to have a bank down there too. There's more business there; more
         stores.
         
         SS:  Do you have an idea why that's developed that way? That Kendrick has
         become the business center, and Juliaetta has kind of ?
         
         GI:  I don't know, I just don't know, I've often wondered about that.
         Listening to what my dad said and so forth, it probably started that
         way at the time of the railroad thing. Because it always did have
         the biggest business center. Probably the people had something to do
         with it. Maybe a little different attitude, I don't know.
         
         SS:  When you were going to school in Kendrick did you take part in any
         town activities outside of school? In high school?
         
         GI:  I can't remember if I did, much.
         
         SS:  You didn't dance and that kind of thing much?
         
         GI:  I went to church; got to going to church there some and stuff like
         that. Of course, at that time they had two theatres in Kendrick
         and we'd go to the shows and stuff like that. As far as taking part
         in any activities of the town, I never got started taking part
         in of the activities of the town. After I was back on the farm
         and started- well, after I got on this school reorganization committee
         then I started going to the Chamber of Commerce and I started briefing
         them on what the progress and what was happening to the school reorganization.
         So I gave a presentation when had the plan of what
         we were going to do and one of the guys got up and said, "We make a
         motion that we give him a three year membership in the Chamber of Com
         merce for what he's done for Kendrick." And that's how I got started
         there. Then when we had the reorganization .to form the board of direch
         tors- all these schools, I think there was actually- well, there must
         have twenty districts involved or more, more than that involved. There
         was part of Nez Perce County, the one district out of Clearwater County
         and then all of Latah County. I believe we had parts of twentyfour
         districts- of the old districts, and so each district had to have
         a trustee zone and there was a trustee for each district. And so
         they met together, the whole community meeting, and decide who was
         going to be on the board of directors. One guy got up and said,
         "Gerald Ingle thinks this thing'11 work, let's put him on that board
         of directors." I was already on one of the local school district
         boards that were coming in, so that's how I got on the Kendrick School
         District Board. So, we had a five member board. And then I got pret
         ty active in the affairs in Kendrick after that. I've been active
         ever since.
         
         SS:  Was it clear to everyone on the board that it made more sense to go
         and put the High School in Kendrick and the grade school in Juliaetta?
         Or the other way around?
         
         GI: Well, it took a year gr two. We had a school at Leland. At the time
         I was in high school they had a two year high school at Leland; high
         school in Southwick and a high school in Kendrick. The Leland high
         school had folded up and Southwick's high school was coming into
         Kendrick on an agreement at the time of the consolidation. They quit
         and they were coming in on an agreement per pupil day. That just
         left the two; there was Kendrick and Juliaetta. But we had to keep
         the Leland grade school. We kept the Gold Hill school and the Crescent
         school,^rural schools. And there was another school we keptand
         the Southwick. Then we gradually, a year or two then, the people
         from Leland decided they wanted to come into Kendrick.
         And then it was the center and the bigger school.
         
         One of the last things I ever did was when they closed up Southwick,
         that was the last hearing I conducted when I was on the school board.
         I had already been voted a replacement and the new director hadn't
         taken his place when we had that hearing to do away with the grade
         school up there. You see, the state changed its financial deal;
         they gave so much per schoolroom unit; we had two rooms up there/^
         three grades and then the fourth, fifth and sixth in another. Well,
         the population had dwindled down so the state wouldn't pay us only
         for one schoolroom unit and we had to have two teachers, anyway, al
         most, the way it was worked out. So they decided- in fact, they were
         going to count that registration right in with the Kendrick registra
         tion so they wouldn't get credit for that unit up there at all. So
         there was no way for the board to go but to close that. I remember
         that hearing, I conducted that one, and, boy, I really got ironed out
         two or three times. It worked out pretty good. We had the two teachers
         teaching up there and took 'em into the system and it worked out real
         well. Iwas chairman of the board and the guy that took my place
         said, "I'm sure glad it was yuou that conducted that meeting, not me."
         He lived up there.
         
         SS:  That was Southwick?
         Southwick. That must have been '65. It went quite a while.
         Talking about getting ironed out; it strikes me that that happens an
         awful lot to a guy in public office. Ijust wonder if you have any
         thoughts about it now, representing what the law is.
         It didn't bother me as much as it does now, probably. I used to tell
         'em that Iknew people were going to talk about somebody, and if they
         were going to talk, they just as well talk about me, and it's not
         going to hurt me as much as^he other person. But, I've gotten by pret
         ty well, but what gets me is when they start saying I'm dishonest or
         something like that; I've always tried to be honest and I've always
         tried to be fair with people. Do^as you would be done by. That has
         always been sort of my philosophy. This is my thirty-ninth year of
         being a public official, counting the schooljf and I think finally
         after a while it will finally get to you, best to take a rest from
         that.
         
         SS:  Thirty-ninth year? Does that mean starting thirty-nine years ago,
         or were there different—?
         
         GI:  Thirty-nine years counting- see, I was on the school board twentyeight
         years, and then a commissioner twenty years, they overlap.
         I said, elected official. I started in '37, that was when I went on
         the school board, I'm counting that as being an elected official.
         
         SS:  How did you decide to run as county commissioner?
         
         GI:  I took quite an active interest in county affairs and I'd been on the
         Fair Ba9rd fifteen years, and then on the County ASC Committee five
         years ve been quite active in the county, so I finally decided,
         well, why not run for county commissioner? And I'fife enjoyed it.
         
         SS:  Was it easy to get the party nomination at that time?
         
         GI:  No, boy, they had tried; there'd been petitions worked up for me to
         go to the legislature and for county commissioner before, but I
         would never sign it. And so, I went to this meeting down here and
         George Brocke, you've heard talk about George, Jr.'s father was in
         the legislature and I came to this Democrate meeting and I said,
         "You know, I've decided I'll run for county commissioner." And,
         boy, they just whooped and hollered. I had a pretty tough election
         that time, I only won by seventy-five votes, but the next time I won
         and the same guy ran against me, over a thousand votes and after that
         I never had any by either party, so got by pretty well.
         
         SS:  Did it affect your farming very much?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes. I could have made a lot more money by staying home, but I
         had hired help and I had a real good helper, my wife was really
         cooperative. She's contributed a lot to my success. She's got a
         good background. But I had to hire a lot of help, I was there to
         boss, though. I did a lot of work myself.
         
         SS:  Did you find it since the years have gone on since you started thatand
         which was the first year that you were commissioner?
         
         GI:  '56; or it was '57.
         
         SS:  Has it taken more and more of your time as the years went on?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes, a lot more time, just an awful lot more. Then, you know, it
         was pretty simple. You didn't have planning and zoning; you didn't
         have solid waste and you didn't have all these other programs- people
         programs involved in. We didn t have to spend too much time.
         We had two regular meetings and then we were probably on call two or
         three more times in the month and there were some night meetings you
         had to attend. But now you can just make it fulltime if you want to,
         there's something for you to do all the time if you'd do it.
         
         SS:  Has the administrative paperwork that's increased? How would you
         describe that?
         
         GI:  Just more things being added. More responsibilities. You see, we
         didn't used to have Civil Defense; we didn't used to have, as I say,
         Planning and Zoning. Then they^counties responsible for Solid
         Waste Programs. And there's other different programs- Federal pro
         grams to get mixed up in all the time to work with. Lots simpler
         than it is now.
         
         SS:  People told me tsjht in the '30's the commissioners were kind of a
         last resort quite often. You know, people that needed work and were
         really destitute during the Depression.
         
         GI:  I think the county was more involved in welfare then than we are now.
         Of course, when I first came on the board, the state didn't take care
         Aid to Dependent Children and stuff like that. That was our bailiwick.
         If they were under sixty-five, those kind of fellows were under us,
         so actually welfare work has actually decreased to what it was then.
         We had more responsibility, had to work with more people. Now they
         have the ADC and the juvenile deal, too and so forth.
         
         SS:  I've got one old chestnut to ask you about; the relation between the
         county and the state, I mean, there is a very widespread feeling, of
         course,that North Idaho gets the short end of the stick from the
         state as a whole. I'm wondering how you feel about that from your
         experiences.
         
         GI:  Well, I don't think so. But, we think sometimes. Northern Idaho
         that they haven't worked on the state roads like they have in South
         ern Idaho, but they can build roads so much cheaper down there. We're
         getting our share; we got the Whitebird grade and we're going to have
         the Lewiston grade
         
         GI:  We get our share, probably.
         
         SS:  What's it like to work with the state? Do you find in your experien
         ces that they understand the local problems well?
         
         GI:  Some do. I've always had pretty good luck actually working with the
         state officials. I think one thing now that Governor Andrus has done,
         he has this one guy, this Rollie Mooney that is appointive laison between
         his office and county and city government comes in every
         once in a while to visit with us. I think that helps. He was at our
         convention last week in Lewiston the whole time, he attends the city's
         convention, gets a feeling of the local governments and so forth.
         something I ve never had any trouble really
         with the state, and I've been quite active with the legislatures and
         I always go down there two, three, four times a year when the legis
         lature's meeting and a lot of the people in there I've known for years
         and work with them. In other capacities in the state, when I was on
         the school board those years and some of those people were on the
         school board, some of them did the same way I did, they started down
         here^low and some of em went to the legislative way and some of 'em
         went the commissioner way. Of course, now it's changing a little bit
         as I get older, some of them are dropping out but a few years ago I
         just knew an awful lot of people in that legislature that I had worked
         with on other programs, like the ASC Program and the school board.
         
         SS:  ASC?
         
         GI:  That's the Agricultural-
         
         SS:  - stabilization.
         
         GI:  Yeah. And the Victdi program. I've been past president of the State
         Association.
         
         SS:  You said that you were working with that kind of thing when you started
         in farming. Was that mostly with the state or the university?
         
         GI:  The university and the county extension agent upstairs.
         
         SS:  Did many farmers do that, or was that unusual?
         
         GI:  There was quite a few. There was quite a few there was some wouldn t
         have anything to do with them, but there's quite a few.
         
         SS:  What did they do for you mostly?
         
         GI:  They kept you up on the research and the new seeds. Like we used to
         raise lots of clover seed and the bugs came in and starting eating it
         and they'd help us with what kind of sprays to use and this kind of
         stuff and different methods of farming. The University does lots of
         research in establishing new varieties of grains and wheats, barley
         and so forth.
         
         SS:  Were you trying them out? 
         
         GI: I've had tests in my fields several different times years.
         
         SS:  Does this kind of information spread fairly fast among the farmers,
         do you think?
         
         GI:  oh I think so. Like when I had tests plots out on place, we'd
         have field days for the whole community to come in and explain dif
         ferent things. The thing of it is- thinking of an incidence: One
         year they had a helicopter came in and there was these people from
         the University and the extension service to look at this clover field
         of mine, trying to figure out these bugs that were eating up the clo
         ver blooms and cutting the yield. A neighbor across the fence, I went
         over and told him, I says, "Come over and talk to these guys." Said,
         "Naw, I don't have^use for those guys. Those white collar guys, I
         don't pay any attention." The next year they figured out a spray, but
         he was using the same spray I was the next year. He knew where to'get'
         the help but he wouldn't have anything to do with it, he wouldn't be
         classes as being out there with them.
         
         SS:  I wonder why that is.
         
         GI:  Just-
         
         SS:  Independent.
         Yeah. Farmers a class pretty independent. They don't like to
         be told.
         
         And maybe he thinks of them as not really working for a living.
         Yes. But it was sort of funny. He wouldn't have anything to do with
         them but still the next year he was looking for spray to spray his
         clover.
         
         Was that tendency there in the early days, too, of farmers to try to
         keep up on the most progressive ideas?
         
         Some of 'em did and some the old ways suited 'em. All people aren't
         progressive. All people aren't leaders, some have to be followers.
         But they'll swear they won't have anything to do with a certain thing
         but if it works out for me they 11 be doing the - in a year or
         two. That's the way it works.
         
         SS:  I wanted to ask you, too, about what you think of people in generalthe
         interest or lack of interest that people have in running their
         affairs- political, in government and that kind of thing. They talk
         a lot about apathy these days, and I'm wondering if that's anything
         new or how that's changed in through the years.
         
         GI:  You mean, people taking an interest on what's going on?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         GI:  There's some people never pay much attention anyway, there's always
         been some that would take an interest. But I think probably people
         now are a lot more interested on what's going on than they used to be
         as a whole. I've made this statement several times: I wish the people
         that were thinking we were doing alright, would come in and talk with
         us. The ones we get are the ones that are against what we're doing.
         That's the ones we see, the other people say, "Well, they're doing alright,
         why bother." And there's getting to be a little more
         I think than there used to be.
         
         SS:  As far as, like say, being informed and knowing what's being done, it
         seems to me that- that typically, I have the impression that most
         people tend to not know very much what's being done or what's going
         on. Do you think it's always been that way?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes. Like people that's running their public office, they just
         say, "He's alright." and whatever he says is okay, and there's some 
         watch out of the corner of their eye all the time. That's part of it
         I guess. You never will get all the public informed. I've noticed
         in the past things we've done, we've publicized it in the paper and yit'H
         on the air and notified by mail, and when it happens they say they
         never ever heard of it. Never heard of it!
         
         SS:  That's the big difference; communication's really easy now. In the
         teens and '20's most people probably didn't hardly get the paper.
         
         GI:  All they did was get the weekly paper. That weekly paper, that local
         paper was their news, and then when they began to get radios, of
         course, it was a little different. They weren't very well informed
         then, but they still could criticize their officials.
         
         SS:  What were the topics of discussion you've heard them raise?
         
         GI:  I think the one that you hear, and I've heard all my life is taxes.
         Wasting money; taxes. It's a lot different looking in than it is
         looking out. I think that's the thing that you hear the most of.
         They get their tax bill, they don't think anything about it till they
         get their tax bill and then that sets 'em off.
         
         SS:  That's something that the grownups talked about when you were a kid?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes. Still do. And, of course, they used to gripe about our roads.
         But there wasn't much we could do about it, used to be all mud roads,
         you know. The same , mud roads all the way to Moscow. I
         can remember when Kendrick's streets used to get to be about that
         much loblally in the street in the wintertime. Drive down there with
         a buggy and the front axle nearly to the mud in the old buggy. Then
         they'd come to these board crosswalks across the street that they got
         to go over like that, it was a mess, I tell you! I can remember when
         they paved the streets in Kendrick there. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Did they use to talk a lot, exchange a lot of information about farming
         methods and how to do thing, how things should be done? Or was that
         more of a private than public thing?
         
         GI:  I think probablyKthen a lot of these guys considered that was their
         private business. They might figure out some way they could get a
         better yield,,but they was going to keep that a secret from the nei
         ghbors. I think that was sort of the attitude of some of the old
         timers. If they had a better way of doing it he didn't publicize
         it too much, because he wanted to get that little advantage. That's
         just my feeling.
         
         SS:  The advantage, it wouldn't affect the price on his crop. They might
         get ahead a little bit.
         
         GI:  I don't know, that just seemed to be the attitude of the old-timers.
         I remember we had a county agent in this county ever since I was a
         kid that high. I think people looked at the county extension offices
         in the rural areas as being a helpful agency where people could go
         if they wanted to find out something, and if they didn't know the an
         swer they could probably find it for them or partially, anyway.
         
         SS:  Was the Grange an important social activity in those days; the early
         days, or has it grown?
         
         GI:  Well, Grange, I never joined the Grange until But the Grange,
         seemed they came in really the strongest, during the hardtimes, the
         Depression days. Seemed " the Granges grew pretty good. We had
         some pretty active granges. Now, it seems like that they've sort of
         dwindled down a little bit. But they were pretty strong there during
         the Depression and the hard years. Moscow had a real strong grange
         here and they had about 1,000 members. Now, I bet they haven't got
         200- 150.
         
         SS:  Did that, as they grew strong, did that have anything to do with peo
         ple wanting to socialize in the hardtimes?
         
         GI:  I think it probably did. If they belonged to the Grange and they had
         their regular meetings they generally had dancing and entertainment
         which didn't really cost 'em very much. Somebody in the group played
         the fiddle and somebody could play the piano and that's the way it
         was when we joined the Grange in Deary. Old guy get up therewith
         his fiddle. He never charged anything and he didn't want any money,
         but just do it for fun. Well, they had their problems, their business
         problems but cheap entertainment helps a lot I think and socializing.
         I join ed the Grange in '42 or '43. I was elected master. I've been
         some kind of a Grange officer ever since.
         
         SS:  Do you remember having talked with some of the antiGerman feeling
         that went on in the First World War?
         
         GI:  Yes, I do. I remember one time that one guy in the community wouldn't
         buy any Liberty bonds; Bonds, and they elected a delegation
         to go up and nail a flag on that guy's house, and my dad was one of
         the ones that they picked to go up there. You know, they got pretty
         bitter about those people that wouldn't do anything. There wasn't
         very many, but it was pretty strong.
         
         SS:  Was this in Cameron?
         
         GI:  No, this 
         
         SS:  This was right on the Ridge there?
         
         GI:  Yes. And he was German. This guy was a German and he wouldn't buy
         any Liberty Bonds and he talked for the Germans. And they made a
         good boy out of him. Pretty drastic, I guess! But you know what
         kind of a feeling it gave that guy when all these neighbors came in
         yand put a flag on his house!
         
         SS:  Yes, those guys would be in a very difficult position, I would think
         with their national background. Good many of the people have said
         to me, that they were really not patriotic and they had to be patrio
         tic then.
         
         GI:  Yeah, I think the feeling then was- patriotic during the First World
         War that was really a byword then, you had to be patriotic. I mean,
         if you weren't patriotic there was something the matter with you.
         
         SS:  Do you think even moreso than the Second World War, or was it about
         the same?
         
         GI:  I don't know. Of course, it may have impressed me more at that time,
         youngetf . Seemed to me like that could be- at the First World
         War the feeling was stronger or maybe just because I was young that
         it made more impression on me.
         
         SS:  Could you see the change in the dwindling of the small farms as the
         years went on around where you lived?
         
         GI:  Yeah. It just happened slowly. One neighbor buy out another
         one and get bigger farms. It was just a slow process, but over several
         years, you know, it makes a lot of difference. I think the land that
         I farmed there at one time, there was, oh, let's see, there was proba
         bly seven or eight homes, on this 800 acres of farm land, probably
         seven or eight homes where people actually lived at one time on that
         much land. Now there's two families on the old home place, I have
         it rented to another family, but two families live on it where there
         used to be about eight homes in that same area.
         
         SS:  So the neighborhood that used to be there is kind of gone now, it's
         not there at all.
         
         GI:  Yeah. It made an awful difference. The school bus now hauls, oh, I
         don't suppose they have over twelve pupils, they haul now, counting
         high school and grade school. And the school I was in when I first
         went to school, they'd go up to thirty-five and the school down be
         low us had about twenty and the Steele School had, oh, they had
         nearly thirty. And there was the Ferneal School, they had close
         to twenty and then there was ? school, they must have had fifteen
         or twenty pupils. And that whole area now is in the Kendrick school
         district and they have about, counting the high school and grade
         school, I don't suppose they have over a dozen.
         
         SS:  Was there much of the social life left when you got married and were
         living there in the '30's?
         
         GI:  Oh, not too much. There was some. When we first got married they
         still had the school next to us there and we had this temporary con
         solidation came up two years afterward, I guess, and they used to
         have their community affairs. They had- they called it Ladies'
         Guild, that s a little bit like a Ladies Aid, and they'd have din
         ners. Of course, they have their local telephone company, you know,
         had a board of directors. They've still got that system there. Don't
         know how much longer it can stay. Not very many of those left. They
         their cemetery and they had the board of directors for the cemetery,
         looked after that, but that's in the Troy cemetery district. And nobody
         out there is on the board. Those things gradually get b*fgger,
         takes the power away from the local community a lot.
         
         SS:  When you were out there then, what did you and your wife do for social
         life?
         
         We just didn't do too much. The first few yeass we lived up there,
         we had a muddy road going to town in the wintertime, we just stayed
         there most of the winter. I'd go to town some and then as things im
         proved we got more active. We were married in '35 and we never joined
         the Grange until '42, I guess. And she belonged to this Ladies' Guild
         they had there on the Ridge and had their meetings once a month.
         We just didn't go very much. We just didn't have much money to go on
         either! We figured if we went to Moscow, we spent $10, we'd spent
         our wad for a long time. We'd go to Moscow once a month probably
         and then of course, we'd go to Kendrick all the time. Moscow was
         the shopping town. Once in a while to Lewiston. That was a real
         splurge when we went to Lewiston.
         
         SS:  One other group that juat crossed my mind that I wanted to ask you
         about was the IWWs. Did you hear anything about them?
         
         GI:  Yeah, that was during the First World War. This IWW quite
         a lot about the IWWs. Industrial Workers of the World, I guess they
         called that. I remember them talking about it. I remember Dad and
         the hired man went to one meeting; they had an IWW meeting up in the
         old schoolhouse. I don't know what was said, I heard the hired man
         tell my dad, "I'd sure like to know what would have happened if some
         body'd had an alarm clock setting in that building and the alarm would
         have went off!" (Chuckles) Maybe that was a meeting against the IWWs,
         I donft know. Must have been.
         
         SS:  I think it probably was, because I know at the time they were trying
         to form this protective association, you know.to guard the fields.
         And there was a lot of fear among some people.
         
         GI:  Threshingkiachine burnt up over there on the place adjoining us and
         of course, everybody just said, "Well, it was the IWWs caused it."
         
         SS:  Was there any evidence that they did?
         
         GI:  No, there wasn't any evidence. That was the first conclusion they
         drew. But I'm sure there wasn't any evidence. They talked about sticking
         something in the middle and setting fire. It could have been, but I
         don't think so, really.
         
         SS:  Wasn't there a lot of smut at that time?
         
         GI:  There used to be- The grain, the wheat I've seen lots of times when
         they wheat the smut'd fly out so that you couldn't even
         see the machine. And they used to have some of these smut explosions.
         I think that's what caused that machine to burn that time; it was a
         smut explosion, I think. Just get so much dust and it'd just blow up.
         
         SS:  Was threshing a great time for the people around there; was that a
         special time?
         
         GI:  Yaah, it was a special time when the threshers came. They used to
         have a crew of about twenty to thirty men, you know. And they'd come
         in and you d have bundle wagons and you'd have pitchers and they had
         their bedrolls, you know and they'd sleep in the barn, sleep - or roll
         em out in the open or  the haystack. They didn't stay but three
         or four days^ but that was quite a time for us kids, in the old days.
         
         SS:  Would you kids work or just watch?
         
         GI:  Well, first we had our chores to do, but not till I got a little older
         then I got so that I had to work; thirteen, fourteen, and in there.
         Started driving bundlewagon I guess when I was thirteen.
         SS These guys that worked, were they local men?
         
         GI:  Most of 'em were local men. But down there, the machine that threshed
         for us, a lot of the people working there were people from the northern
         country around Deary and Avon where their crops were later they
         down on the Ridge with this threshing crew, work down there ear
         lier then some of 'em have to quit and go back and harvest their crop.
         But a lot of 'em were people from that area.
         
         Was that a very coordinated operation? I've had the idea- I never
         really asked anybody-but it seems like there were all these different
         things going on at once, probably had to work pretty closely together
         to make sure everything went well.
         
         Oh, yeah I tell you, there was a lot of difference in crews. If you
         had a good crew boss running the thing, things just went like clock
         work. When they g$t done, certain guys rolled up the belt, one turned
         the blower down. One did this and one did this and one hooked onto
         the engine on the machine; everybody had their job, you know. They'd
         finish up and they'd be gone. And then the same way when they'd move
         each one had their certain things to do. Of course, in those days,
         the grain was all sacked. Sack sewers had to take care of their sack
         sewing spout and get their sacker up and certain guys put up the blower.
         
         SS:  If you were moving real fast?
         
         GI:  Oh, yes, you bet. Especially in some crews, the guys that were really
         progressive guys got their work done. That s the kind of a threshingmachine
         crew you wanted because the guys that moved like that would
         generally get the work done. They had two or three company machines
         like that come in and the one that- there was competition- and the
         one that really got the work done was the one that got the most thre
         shing done. They got paid by so much a sack.
         
         SS:  Time was really money, then?
         
         GI:  You bet it was!
         
         SS:  Who did you have around there? Were the Olson Brothers over there?
         
         GI:  Bower- Charlie Bower, Old Charlie, young Charlie. out there now,
         his dad used to run a machine and then the Olson brothers used to come
         down, we used to say went down to thresh for the Swedes or the NorwegiansAon
         the Ridge used to come down there once in a while. And
         there was another machine down there, Fairfield, Old Man Fairfield
         had a threshing machine. And he wasn't very much of a pusher. He
         got some threshing, but he didn't get to thresh too many people 'cause
         he fooled around quite a lot, but he had a machine. But the Bowers,
         he was the one that threshed, when I was a kid, did the biggest area.
         
         SS:  I'm glad you mentioned Swedes and Norwegians, because I was going to
         ask you about that, too. Was the communities somewhat separate, fairly
         separate in the earlier times there: the Swedes and Norwegians?
         
         GI:  Well, the Swedes lived north up around Deary and the Norwegians on the
         lower end of nd they were real sociable. As far
         as their own affairs, they stuck together a lot, they were pretty
         clannish at that time. Ater years, you know, got intermarried and
         some moved out, you couldn't tell the difference, but at that time I
         think they were sort of clannish. And of course, that was mostly Nor
         wegians there and then say north of us there were Swedes. I was amu
         sed at one of the guys, lived down there when I was a kid, he
         just two or three years older than I am, but he lives up by Deary
         now, and we see each other. I says, "How you geting along with those
         Swedes, up there?" "Oh, fine." He says "I'm almost a Swede now."
         We joke back and forth, you know. He can remember how it was in the
         old times, I guess. But they were sort of clannish. Course, I can't
         blame 'em, sitcking together.
         
         SS:  They were fairly strict about dancing, too.
         
         GI:  Oh, yes, they were real strict. They were just like the rest of the
         people, some lax and some weren't.
         
         SS:  Did you ever know the Wellses at all, up at Deary? Joe Wells?
         
         GI:  Yeah. He came out West with the Wells brothers; the Wells brothers'
         house was just over the hill out here from buffalo are, that was the
         Wells brothers' house. The Wells brothers were real good friends
         of my grandfather.
         
         SS:  Yeah, being both from the South.
         
         GI:  Joe Wells - he was their slave back before they moved out here. The
         story was told to me, and he set up a farm out there just east of
         Deary there a little ways; the old Wells place, I remember. Then
         he had- I know there were two sons, there was Chuck and Roy and I
         knew Chuck real wweellll. AAnr^d It usedj to pasture cattle back there and
         I used to load cattle out there at Chuck's. And I helped Chuck out
         a lot when he got sick and so forth and in the nursing home out here.
         He was a real good guy, Chuck was. He never asked for any help unless
         he absolutely needed it. Never took advantage of you.
         
         SS:  Was he a pretty tough guy? I've heard stories that he was a really
         tough man in the woods.
         
         GI:  They didn't push him around, he was a real man. He was husky and short
         and heavy set and husky. They respected him pretty well. He was a
         hard worker. He used to^on the threshing crews, he used to haul water,
         be the waterboy for the threshing crews sometimes, Chuck was.
         
         SS:  When he was a grown man?
         
         GI:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  I thought that was more of an old person's job.
         
         GI:  No, I tell you that was a hard job, because you pumped all that water
         by hand; one of these hand pumps. And it took a man to do it. And
         sometimes the places they had to go in to get this water in these
         water tanks for these big steam engines, they'd have to drive a four
         horse team and sometimes took a damn good driver to get into to where
         they had to go to get water.
         
         SS:  Do you think he had to take a fair bit of annoyance because he was a
         black. Negro from some people?
         
         GI:  I never got that feeling. I remember when he used to be in the crews
         and they'd joke back and forth, they all seemed to have respect for
         Chuck. I knew Chuck a lot better than I did Roy.
         
         SS:  Would they joke about his color, was that part of it?
         
         GI:  Yeah, and he'd joke about 'em being white and stuff like that. I mean,
         I don't remember any- he never had any trouble in these crews, that I
         can remember. He was always pretty well respected. Have you heard
         otherwise from others?
         
         SS:  I've heard about him getting into a few fights in the woods maybe
         more with the lumberjacks who wouldn't know him. Didn't know who he
         was.
         
         GI: That was probably was, but he could take care of himself pretty well.
         
         SS:  I've heard that he drank pretty badly.
         
         GI:  I think probably some of these fights and stuff was caused by when
         he did have a little too much.
         
         SS:  I also heard about his wife.who left him eventually. Did you know
         her at all?
         
         GI:  Yeah, she went and married a Ross. Dan Ross. Knew Dan Ross real
         well. Knew his brother better, or real well, he used to be county
         superintendent here and he was superintendent of school at Troy.
         
         SS:  His brother?
         
         GI:  Yes. Dave. And I knew old Dan real well. He was quite a guy, Dan was,
         
         SS:  What was he like? I heard he was a character, but I didn't know why.
         
         GI:  Oh, he was hard-boiled and he called a spade a spade and he was very
         outspoken, and they didn't push much over on him.
         
         GI:  They wanted a line to go in there, take part of that district. So
         they appointed us the committee to go ' and talk to those people.
         And she'd go in- and she'd get the jump on me. And we were talking
         to people, "Which way do you want to go?" when they divided this dis
         trict. Said, "Your kids are going to Lapwai, they don't want to comedon't
         want to leave that school and go to another school do they?"
         But anyway some of 'em did come this way.
         
         SS:  To Kendrick?
         
         GI:  Yes. And so, we got up there and one of her stooges, one of her guysshouldn't
         call 'em stooges, got up and he says, "I make a motion that
         Stony Point District in its entirety go to Lapwai." Well, Lapwai
         wanted them real bad. They were a pretty rich district and they had
         some money that they had to spend, and made a motion. Of
         course, the motion carried. In a deal like that, the people that
         didn't want to go, they were in a minority, they lived at the upper
         end; it should have been divided. And then one of the guys got up
         and says, "Well, if Stony Point go to Lapwai, we just as well
         move this line up closer to Leland." And I got a hold of , I
         says, "Get this thing closed up right now because they're going to try
         to take more." So we got— (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  surprised me.
         
         GI:  She looked after 
         
         SS:  She told me that Lapwai had a lot of problems when they did that consolidation.
         She said that there a stuff going on. She had a
         hard time with it though.
         
         GI:  Yes, I think she ended up on the board down there, didn't she?
         
         SS:  What abottt Viola, by the way? They seem to rankle some over about
         not having a school.
         
         GI:  Who? Viola, out there?
         
         SS:  Yeah. They were really opposed at the time?
         
         GI:  No, they were coming in here anyway.
         Ihey were?
         
         GI:  I'm sure they were. Big part of them were. But, I don't know, Viola
         has always sort of stuck out there, a sore thumb about something, it
         seems like. They've had taverns and stores and stuff out there,Mbut
         I don't remember them putting up much fuss at the time. Moscow Has
         the first district consolidated of the five. See, they were
         281 and Genesee is 282, Kendrick's 283, White Pine 284 and Potlatch
         one thing here at Moscow, the rural people had a bond to pay
         off on this building over here and the rural people wouldn't accept
         paying the bond. But of course, the law is, if they'd have voted to
         do it, they could, but the law is the people the bond is voted against
         is the ones that have to pay it off, so they had a split deal here on
         their bonds for a while, and just the old district had to raise money
         to pay off that bond. Down in our district, they voted- Juliaetta had
         a bond- they absorbed it in the whole district, so it didn't hurt any
         body very much. Some did that way and others- Moscow was the only
         one, I guess just stood pat, "You guys got to pay your own debts."
         I'll bet that's one of the things that came from Viola.. 
         
         SS:  Do you see any difference now between Democrats and Republicans?
         Would you mind being a Republican yourself rather than a Democrat?
         
         GI:  I don't think I'd be any different. I don't think on a local level
         there's too much difference, really. I think in this county, espe
         cially. I think it depends on how many people know you whether you
         get elected or not.
         
         SS:  But in terms of philosophy of the parties?
         
         GI:  It just seems to me working with Republicans and Democrats, the peo
         ple I've worked with, seem to be more interested- seems like . Demo
         crats are a little bit more interested in people; maybe they aren't,
         maybe it just happens to be that the Republicans I worked with aren't.
         I've had Republicans on the board up here and a few of 'em seem to
         have a little different attitude. Like Gracie Wicks, she's a real
         Staunch Republican; she didn't have any compassion at all for poor
         peoplei I always figured it's no disgrace being poor, it might
         happen to any of us. They deserve the same kind of treatment as
         somebody that not poor, and that's.been my attitude. I mean, treat
         people the same, rich or poor. But she was real hard-nosed about
         some poor people. I always wanted to be able to talk to either one.
         Then I think some Republicans are that way, too. Maybe that's how
         1 got my impression, I had a little bit more compassion toward peo
         ple than some. But that probably run different in different communi
         ties.
         
         SS:  You can see that in the presidential campaign right now; that kind
         of difference between the two men in the way they approach-
         
         GI:  Yes I noticed that, too. I remember the next day after I got elected,
         a guy walked up to me and he says, "I've been a Republican all my life
         and I voted for you." And, he says, "I'll tell you one reason." He
         says, "I can come and talk to you and you'll listen, that guy you
         running against I couldn't talk to him, he talks." So, I've
         always had the philosophy, somebody come to me- I have a little bit
         hard time with the board here now, somebody comes in to blow it up,
         I always let 'em run down, then I can talk, but you start arguing
         right off the bat, you never get anyplace. But if he gets
         his say in, gets run down, then I'll have a pretty good chance. That's
         always been my philosophy.
         
         SS:  It makes sense. It sounds like human relations.
         
         GI:  Sometimes it's pretty hard to sit there sometimes, but they general
         ly run down pretty soon.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13480</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Ingle_Florence</previous>
      <next>Jackson</next>
      <disp_name>Ingle_Gerald</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
