<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/13/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>William Kauder, 1974-02-13, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>0:56:46</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Kauder, William</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1868</birthyear>
      <residence>Cedar Creek, Southwick</residence>
      <origin>Homesteaded alongside parents, after moving from Illinois (1889)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bears"&gt;bears&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hotels"&gt;hotels&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#literary"&gt;literary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#parties"&gt;parties&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Southwick"&gt;Southwick&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Kendrick"&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Gold Hill"&gt;Gold Hill&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Rob Moore</interviewer>
      <file_name>13489</file_name>
      <mp3>13490.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13490.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>1893 Depression</title>
            <synopsis>1893 Depression. Bill could find no work at all,
               still doesn't know how they got through those years.
               A lot of people mortgaged their homesteads and left.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>180</time>
            <title>Clearing land, burning the brush and log piles; no sawmill</title>
            <synopsis>Clearing land; burning the brush and burning the log
               piles. There was no sawmill where the logs could be
               hauled.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>Farmer's Alliance ran stores for farmers; dissatisfied with the government</title>
            <synopsis>Farmer's Alliance ran stores for the farmers. Most
               people were dissatisfied with the government and
               Cleveland's Free Trade policies, but couldn't do any
               thing about it. Bill voted for Harrison and the
               Protective Tariff. Coffee was 8 pounds for $1.00.
               1893 Wet Harvest.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>1896 election; Bryan vs. McKinley</title>
            <synopsis>1896 election; Bryan vs. McKinley. Many people
               associated Free Silver, with Free Trade and voted against
               Bryan.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Homesteaders</title>
            <synopsis>Homesteaders were the best people in the world. You
               never asked any questions about your neighbors, but
               were friendly. People came west for free land. Bill
               looked at one 160 above Pasco: good flat land but
               too dry.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Bears were wild and didn't bother you. Indians were
               civil and peaceable.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Bears were wild and didn't bother you. Indians were
               civil and peaceable.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Kendrick, bigger town then than now; couldn't go to Kendrick during the winter because
               of snow
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Kendrick. A bigger town then than now. Beefsteak
               meal at the hotel for 250. Didn't go to town too often.
               Couldn't go to Kendrick during the winter because
               there was snow on the ridge and bare ground in Kendrick
               so you couldn't take just one rig.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Literary and Sunday school; dances in Gold Hill country</title>
            <synopsis>Literary and Sunday school. Sometimes the Literary
               chose a humorous subject. Dances in Gold Hill country.
               Play-parties on the ridge, religious bias against
               dancing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>J. P. Vollmer bought out many homesteaders and used
               the land as backing for the bank.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>J. P. Vollmer bought out many homesteaders and used
               the land as backing for the bank.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>1904 Kendrick fire; political campaigning</title>
            <synopsis>1904 Kendrick fire. Political campaigning. Most
               homesteaders not too interested in politics.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Making shingles in the winter. Potlatch.</title>
            <synopsis>Making shingles in the winter. Potlatch.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Tug-of-war (continued). Fourth of July races, dances.</title>
            <synopsis>Tug-of-war (continued). Fourth of July races, dances.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Moving from Illinois to Missouri to find cheaper land</title>
            <synopsis>Moving from Illinois to Missouri to find cheaper land.
               It wasn't too healthy for Northerners in the South.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>Watergate; coming West by train; Coxey's army</title>
            <synopsis>Watergate. Coming West by train. Coxey's army.
               Eight days by wagon from Dayton to Cedar Creek.
               House-raising. First winter in a box-house sixteen
               feet square. Helping each other out. Trading work
               to help pay back the people who helped in the house raising.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Weather changes.</title>
            <synopsis>Weather changes.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Homesteaders with a little extra income had an easier time</title>
            <synopsis>Homesteaders with a little extra income had an easier
               time of it. Once people were settled in it was easier.
               Most people fed their grain to cattle or hogs then
               drove them to market, because it was easier to drive
               livestock than wagons over the bad roads.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3000</time>
            <title>Working with horses and mules; plowing</title>
            <synopsis>Working with horses and mules; twelve-inch plow and
               AA harrow. Mules were steady all day. Bill's favorite
               horse was a chestnut sorrel gelding.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>1893 depression. Getting settled; help from neighbors. Political views of
         1890's. Entertainment. Land clearing. Kendrick. 2-13-74 1 hr 16p RM
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         ROB MOORE: Well, you were here during the hard times around 1893 then, weren't
         you?
         
         WILLIAM KAUDER: I sure was. That was some pickings, I'll tell you. Yes sir,
         right at that time I was twenty-one, two, and three, when I should been
         a'making something and you couldn't get a job and you...it was some living.
         
         ROB:  What did you do to get through those years?
         
         WK: Well sir, I'm guessing at that yet. I don't know how we managed that.
         
         ROB:  Did you...
         
         WK:  It was slim pickin', I'll tell you.
         
         ROB:  Did you stay on the homestead?
         
         WK:  Yes, on father's homestead.
         
         ROB:  At that time were there many people around here who were interested in that
         Coxey's Army that was kind of protesting against the poor times?
         
         WK:  There was more people in here. There's quite a lot of homesteaders hadn't
         proved up yet, you know. In there where we were, what is called Crescent
         now, and Lenville and on beyond, they was all homesteaders. They all lived
         on their places. They proved up and happened to...I think along about 1894,
         '95 a lot of them proved up and mortgaged and left their homesteads. There
         was at that time more people in there than it...more heavily populated than
         it is today.
         
         ROB:  Were they all mostly on small farms?
         
         WK:  Urn?
         
         ROB:  Were they mostly on small farms?
         
         WK: Oh no, they had the hundred-and-sixty, all timber. They had to clear up,
         there wasn't any cultivating land.
         
         ROB:  Was it pretty hard to clear that land up?
         
         WK:  Oh gosh yes.
         
         ROB:  How would you go about it?
         
         WK:  Well, we cut down a tree. Trim him up and burn the brush, saw him up in
         about 8, 10, 12 feet lengths. Take a team and drag it up into log piles, and
         set 'em afire. There was thousands of dollars worth of good timber burnt
         up just thataway.
         
         ROB:  Was it too hard to get them to a mill?
         
         WK:  Was no sawmills around then.
         
         ROB:  Was the Farmers Alliance or the Farmers Union working around here at that
         time?
         
         WK:  No, but I heard of them around through the farming country.
         
         ROB:  What kinds of things did they do?
         
         WK:  How was that?
         
         ROB:  What kinds of things did they do?
         
         WK:  I don't know. Did you call it the Farmers Alliance?
         
         ROB:  Yes.
         
         WK:  I don't know. They started in, I guess meant pretty good. They were quite
         well organized yet and they had stores of their own. That is, grocery stores,
         and hardware, what the farmers needed.
         
         ROB:  Uh-huh.
         
         WK:  But that didn't last so long.
         
         ROB:  Were most people pretty angry about the hard times then?
         
         WK:  Yes, they were dissatisfied. You couldn't do nothing about it, you know.
         They got plenty of that Free Trade. You know, Cleveland run on a Democratic
         ticket, on a Free Trade. He believed that this country and other countries
         should exchange free, you know. They ship things in here free of duty and
         America ship out free of duty. That's the way they believed. And Harrison
         was the opposing nominee of the Republican ticket and he believed in Protective
         Tariff. And that's where I picked my ticket. I consulted a lot of pretty
         well-educated men, you know, that been through the mills, and they told me
         that this Free Trade business wouldn't work. We had to have Protective
         Tariff. And I come to that conclusion myself, that that was right. Because
         in them foreign countries, you take Germany, France, Russia, they had cheap
         labor. So much cheaper than we had here. And they manufactured their goods
         for less than a half of what we would here. They could ship them in, you
         take dry goods such as clothing, why you could buy a shirt there for fifty
         cents. Why, they couldn't make it in the United States for less than seventy five,
         at that same time. It was that way with everything: hardware, coffee.
         You could buy coffee then a bit a pound, eight pounds for a dollar. It was
         parched but not ground. That's in packages, pound packages. There was two
         brands of it; there was a Lions brand, and Arbuckle.
         
         ROB:  Well, do you think it was Cleveland's free trade polices that brought on
         that 1893 depression?
         
         WK:  I didn't exactly catch you.
         
         ROB:  Do you think it was Cleveland's free trade polices that brought on that
         1893 depression?
         
         WK:  Why of course. Nothing else could bring it on.
         
         ROB:  Well, there was a bad harvest here that year too, wasn't there?
         
         WK:  No, the harvest was all right, but it was a wet one. A good many people
         lost quite a bit of grain on account of rain. It started about the middle
         of September, by gosh, it did rain and it rained! I worked down in the
         Dayton country. I was with a thrashing machine then down there. But we
         happened to get most of the crops taken care of before the rains come. They
         didn't come about 'til after the middle of September.
         
         ROB:  What was the next election after that? Who ran in the next election after
         that?
         
         WK:  Four years later William 3ennings Bryantrun against William McKinley.
         Bryantrun on a Free Silver ticket; sixteen silver dollars to one gold dollar.
         And McKinley run on a Gold Standard and McKinley won.
         
         ROB:  Didn't most of the working class people support Bryant?
         
         WK:  I don't know about that. Anyhow McKinley was elected. But I think the
         people...well I know around here there was an awful lot of people voted
         for McKinley regardless of whether democrats or republicans, but they voted
         for McKinley. They got that silver trade was something similar to that free
         trade. They figured that out thataway.
         
         ROB:  What were the early homesteaders like? What kind of people were they?
         
         WK:  The best people in the world. There was people from Kansas, Oklahoma,
         Nebraska, Iowa, Missouri, Illinois, Ohio. I didn't know a thing about my
         neighbor and my neighbor didn't know a thing about me, whether I was a re
         spectable character or not. But we never asked any questions. And we were
         neighbors. And all friendly one with another.
         
         ROB:  Why did most people come out here?
         
         WK:  Well, I have an idea that they didn't do so well in the East. And there
         were a lot of homestead land at that time, back east you had to buy it.
         When we left there, land was all the way from twenty-five to seventy-five
         dollars an acre. You'd get here, it'd produce just about as good as that did,
         only you didn't have the market here that we had there. But then you had the
         same amount of land if you could crop it. But we...we didn't have nothing
         when we come out here and we had to just take a brush claim and clear up our
         land. We did go down and kind of up the river from Pasco, we looked at one
         hundred-and-sixty there just as level as you'd want land but I don't know how
         many thousand feet above water. Nice level and flat land, but it was too
         dry. That was the trouble here then.
         
         ROB:  Was this a pretty wild country when you arrived?
         
         WK:  What do you mean, wild animals?
         
         ROB:  Oh, wild animals and a hard country, a harsh country? Was it a hard life?
         
         WK:  No, it wasn't bad. You'd go through the woods and you might travel all
         day and never see anything. And all at once maybe you'd run up against a
         bear, something like that. But then the bear was wild and he'd give you
         plenty of room.
         
         ROB:  How about the people? How did the people kind of enforce the law in those
         days before there were marshalls and sheriffs?
         
         WK:  Well, I don't know about that. We had officers just about the same as you
         got now, pret'near. Only without..we didn't have them what you might call
         automobile...we met quite a lot of Indians and they were civil and peaceable.
         
         ROB:  Were the Indians still moving pretty freely through this part of the country?
         
         WK:  No, not here. They generally remained on the reservations.
         
         ROB:  What town would you go to when you wanted to get supplies?
         
         WK:  How was that?
         
         ROB:  What town did you go to when you wanted to get supplies?
         
         WK:  You mean for groceries and that stuff?
         
         ROB:  Yes.
         
         WK:  Kendrick.
         
         ROB:  What was Kendrick like in those days?
         
         WK:  Oh, pretty thriving town. I believe it was better than it is now. They
         had several dry-goods stores, and grocery stores, saloons, hotel. Go to the
         hotel and get a good meal for two bits. Beefsteak.
         
         ROB:  About how often would you go to town from the homestead?
         
         WK:  Well, not very often. In the fall of the year we tried to get our supplies
         so we didn't have to go in the wintertime. Because the snow where we lived
         would get about four feet deep and down in Kendrick it was bare ground. So
         you couldn't...one rig wouldn't work all the way.
         
         ROB:  Uh-hm.
         
         WK:  That's the reason we'd take in the harvest, you know, and get enough money
         and get us a good supply of grub, and as the fella says, we'd hole up in the
         winter. And the snow got so awful deep.
         
         ROB:  Well, how would people keep themselves entertained then?
         
         WK:  Well, we had we had a school, and I believe there's about twenty or twentyfive
         kids going. And every Friday night we had a literary. And on Sunday's,
         why we had Sunday School, and church when we could get a preacher, but we
         always had a Sunday School.
         
         ROB:  What was a literary?
         
         WK:  Well, it's kind of a debating society where they get a subject and then
         they'd debate on it. Then we had a program, you know, declamations and...
         
         ROB:  Would everybody participate?
         
         WK:  Oh yes. Yes some of them old ranchers are pretty good talkers on a subject.
         Sometimes they'd have kind of a funny question up, you know, for debate. Like,
         which is more essential the dish rag or the broom. (Laughs.) Yeah, we used
         to have lots of fun at them meetings.
         
         ROB:  How about parties and such, were there many of those?
         
         WK:  Well once in awhile they had a dance. Not in our neighborhood, but across
         over in the Gold Hill country they'd have dances there. And we'd have...
         once in awhile we'd have kind of what they call a play party, you know. No
         dancing allowed.
         
         ROB:  Why wasn't there any dancing allowed?
         
         WK:  Well, they was kind of religiously inclined, you know, and they didn't
         believe in it.
         
         ROB:  Oh.
         
         WK:  And they'd have a party at those places.
         
         ROB:  Do you think many of the early homesteaders cleared out around that 1893
         time?
         
         WK:  Did what?
         
         ROB:  Do you think many of the homesteaders cleared out in that 1893 hard times?
         Did many of them kind of go broke and have to leave?
         
         WK:  I don't know whether you'd call it go broke or not, but lots of them about
         that time would have served their five years. And they'd go prove up and
         then mortgage it and leave it. There's lots of land in there now still in
         the hands of companies.
         
         ROB:  Would they sell out to the timber company or what?
         
         WK:  Do what?
         
         ROB:  Did they sell out to the timber company? Usually?
         
         WK:  No, Vollmer bought most of the...
         
         ROB:  He was the banker up in Troy wasn't he?
         
         WK:  At Lewiston.
         
         ROB:  Was he a pretty good banker?
         
         WK:  Yes, he was a good banker. He looked out...
         
         ROB:  Did he kind of watch out for people and try and help them out?
         
         WK:  No, no he wasn't that kind of a man. Now he...I don't know how he worked
         it but he would take a mortgage on their property and of course foreclose
         it. And he put that in someway, so much deposited in the bank. It was a
         backing for the bank.
         
         ROB:  Do you remember the Kendrick fire in 1903?
         
         WK:  Was I here then?
         
         ROB:  Yes.
         
         WK:  Yeah, we lived up here on Cedar Creek. I went down there after it all
         cooled down. Pretty sorry looking place.
         
         ROB:  Were the businesses still trying to operate?
         
         WK:  Yes. They put up kind of temporary buildings and start over.
         
         ROB:  How did the politicans campaign for office around that time?
         
         WK:  Oh, there was quite a number running for office. But of course like all
         the time, some was successful and some weren't.
         
         ROB:  Well how would they come around and kind of let people know who they were?
         Or who was running?
         
         WK:  Well, you take now...I don't know...in Moscow that man Snow, is he running
         for Congress?
         
         ROB:  Now, you mean?
         
         WK:  Huh?
         
         ROB:  Now, you mean?
         
         WK:  Uh-huh.
         
         ROB:  I'm not sure. I think he might be. I'm talking about back in the early
         days? Would the politicians who were running come out to the different little
         communities?
         
         WK:  Well, that's just what I was going to tell you. They...well, they'd have
         their cards you know, and they come and maybe they'd announce that they were
         speaking in certain places a certain night. We'd meet there with them. Some
         times there'd be a dozen democrats or a dozen republicans. They'd be different
         times, you know. Now they'd come there...from Moscow they would come out and
         they'd talk. They'd have their meeting there at the school house. And we'd
         go over there and hear them. There'd be maybe a half a dozen or a dozen
         republicans or maybe next time that many democrats would come. They'd have...
         each one had their story.
         
         ROB:  Were most of the early homesteaders pretty interested in politics?
         
         WK:  No, they wasn't. You might say they wasn't crazy about it. They didn't
         care too much.
         
         ROB:  What kind of things were they crazy about?
         
         WK:  Oh, I don't know if they were very bad on anything or any subject. They
         had the work. They had...some of 'em made shakes, some of 'em made shingles.
         Everything to make a dollar, you know, to buy grub. They were busy. I know
         father and I made shingles one whole winter. We made a better kind of a
         building, we had a shed in front. We'd drag a log in there and saw it up
         in shingle lengths, sixteen inches. Then we'd split 'em up, rive 'em and
         shave 'em. Put 'em up in packs.. We'd get maybe two dollars a thousand for
         'em or...we had to do something.
         
         ROB:  When people went on down into Kendrick for their supplies, would they pretty
         often go on a bender or something to get away from the pressures of working
         so hard?
         
         WK:  Never heard of it.
         
         ROB:  I heard at one time in the early days at the Fourth of July celebrations
         in Kendrick they used to have big tug-of-wars and the people from Potlatch
         Ridge would take on everybody else. Do you remember those?
         
         WK:  They'd have kind of a tug-of-war?
         
         ROB:  Um-hum.
         
         WK:  Oh yes. The Potlatch had quite a bunch of big heavy men, way over two
         hundred. And they got on one end of the rope...
         
         WK:  And several from Leland there. Men that weighed, oh, 200 and 20 and 225
         pounds you know. There was about a dozen of them. And the workers, the
         workers were big heavy men.
         
         ROB:  What other kinds of things would happen at those Fourth of July celebrations?
         
         WK:  Oh, I don't know. Down at Kendrick they had...on one Fourth of July we
         was down there and they had races of all kinds and they had a large platform
         outside, you know. I don't know what you'd call it, pavilion or something.
         They'd have a dance there. They start the dance there after dinner about
         3:00 o'clock, 2:00 or 3:00, and they'd dance I guess maybe all night, I don't
         know. I left there about 11:00 or 12:00 o'clock and they were still a'hammering
         away.
         
         ROB:  Where was it that you were born again?
         
         WK:  What state?
         
         ROB:  Yes.
         
         WK:  Illinois.
         
         ROB:  When was that?
         
         WK:  1868.
         
         ROB:  Why did your father decide to leave Illinois?
         
         WK:  Well, land at that time was quite high in Illinois and we got just as
         good a land a whole lot cheaper across the Mississippi River in Missouri.
         The land was just as good as the Illinois land and you didn't have to pay
         half as much. Take land in Illinois that was selling for fifty and seventy five
         dollars an acre, and you can go over and buy just as good a land for
         fifteen and twenty dollars in Carr County, Missouri.
         
         ROB:  Were there still a lot of hard feelings around that time about the Civil War?
         
         WK:  No, not right in there. But south further there was. Wasn't very healthy
         to take a family from the North and go into Arkansas or Mississippi and them
         places and locate.
         
         ROB:  Where did you go from Missouri?
         
         WK:  Iowa.
         
         ROB:  How long did you stay there?
         
         WK:  One year. Broke up.
         
         ROB:  Did your father homestead in Iowa too?
         
         WK:  Huh-uh. There was no homestead land in Iowa then. (Tape pause.)
         Wonderful, awful changes.
         
         ROB:  What do you think is the most impressive sort of change that you have seen?
         
         WK:  Well, the biggest change is in the way things are running. That's the
         worstest change I think. Now this Watergate business and this gasoline
         business got things mixed up pretty bad.
         
         ROB:  How do you think Watergate compares to something like Teapot Dome?
         
         WK:  I don't there's much difference is there?
         
         ROB:  I don't know. I wasn't around when Teapot Dome happened.
         
         WK:  How old of a person are you if I'm allowed to ask?
         
         ROB:  I'm 25.
         
         WK:  Ohhh. Oh, if you stay alive you're going to see lots of changes.
         
         ROB:  How did your family come west? How did they travel?
         
         WK:  Well we come on the train. We bought our tickets in Sioux City, Iowa ,
         and we went from Sioux City to Omaha, Nebraska. And we got on the Union
         Pacific and we come on out to Walla Walla.
         
         ROB:  That was about 1891?
         
         WK: No, that was in 1890. 1891 we come up in this country.
         
         ROB:  I asked you before about Coxeyfe army and you didn't say much about it.
         I wonder, were there many people got interested in that Coxey's army thing
         around here?
         
         WK:  No. No, they didn't take no stock in it.
         
         ROB:  What kind of thing was that anyway?
         
         WK:  Well, it was a lot of people that was dissatisfied with the way the govern
         ment was running things. Really there was no work for 'em, you know. And
         that was what they was after was, They want wages.
         
         ROB:  What were they going to do about it?
         
         WK:  Well, they wanted to talk to the President of the United States to start
         something. But I don't know what they wanted to start, but so they could
         have employment and make a living.
         
         ROB:  Was there much business with the IWW's in this area?
         
         WK:  No, not around here.
         
         ROB:  What kind of jobs did you do throughout your life?
         
         WK:  Oh, worked the ranches and sawmills. When we first come west we landed
         in Walla Walla. I think It was the 17th of March when we landed in Walla
         Walla and they had all their crops in. So we moved from Walla Walla on up
         to Dayton and father and I got a job in the sawmill there. And we worked
         that summer and that winter in the sawmill. We made enough to get us a
         team, harness, and kitchen supply stuff, and we hauled that up here.
         
         ROB:  Did you know where you were headed for when you left Dayton?
         
         WK:  Um-hm.
         
         ROB:  And you came all the way by wagon?
         
         WK:  Yep. I don't know...it don't take it very long to go from here down to
         Dayton now, but it took us about eight days to move up from Dayton to what
         you call Crescent. Cedar Creek.
         
         ROB:  When you arrived at your homestead it was just unproved land wasn't it?
         
         WK:  It's what?
         
         ROB:  When you arrived at your homestead it was just empty land wasn't it?
         
         WK:  Um-hm.
         
         ROB:  What did you do first when you got there?
         
         WK:  Built us a cabin to live in.
         
         ROB:  How long did that take?
         
         WK:  Well, I was out in the harvest that fall and father he cut and hewed the
         logs. And when I come back from harvest I took the team and drug 'em up
         and we had what you call a house-raising. We put up the framework that fall
         and then it snowed us under and we couldn't work anymore until the next spring.
         
         ROB:  Where did you live that winter then?
         
         WK:  There on the homestead, we put up a box house. I don't know, it was I
         think sixteen feet square. Just had a fire place in one end of it, and
         cook stove and a couple of beds in there. Oh, we fared pretty good.
         
         ROB:  How many people came over for your house-raising?
         
         WK:  Oh, we had I guess a dozen or more. Just what was in the neighborhood, you
         know.
         
         ROB:  How long did it take?
         
         WK:  Oh, the best part of one day.
         
         ROB:  Was there a celebration or a big feed or something afterwards?
         
         WK:  Yeah, we had a dinner.
         
         ROB:  Was helping-out like that pretty common in those homesteading days?
         
         WK:  Um-hm.
         
         ROB:  What other ways would people help each other out?
         
         WK:  Oh, sometimes sickness or something like that, they was always willing to
         help. We had a doctor at Leland and we had another doctor lived on a home
         stead there at Gold Hill.
         
         ROB:  Were you and your father supposed to come and help other people out who'd
         helped you out raising your house?
         
         WK:  Yes.
         
         ROB:  What kind of things would you do to help pay back?
         
         WK:  Well some had barn to raise, to put up a log barn. And help on that.
         
         ROB:  Were there any people who weren't very neighborly, who didn't participate
         in those sorts of things? People that you might call sort of hermits or...
         
         WK:  Oh yes. Yes they all...When you had a gathering of that kind everybody
         was happy, well pleased. (Tape pause.) Is it clear outside or...?
         
         ROB:  No, it's cloudy today.
         
         WK:  Is it?
         
         ROB:  There was probably about an inch or two of snow this morning. It's not
         snowing now but it's cloudy out.
         
         WK:  Hum.
         
         ROB:  Do you think the weather has changed much from the early days?
         
         WK:  Oh yes. We don't get near the snow that we used to. Get more rain in
         the wintertime than we did then.
         
         ROB:  Do you have any idea why that is?
         
         WK:  No. I don't.
         
         ROB:  What kinds of words would you use to describe the old days, in general?
         
         WK:  How was that?
         
         ROB:  How would you describe the old days? The homestead days?
         
         WK:  Well, there was differences, lots of differences. Some people that had
         income, or didn't have to get out and scratch, why they could make it pretty
         good on the homestead. But if you had to...couldn't make it on the homestead
         and had to work out for a living, it was pretty tough going. Whenever you
         worked out you was losing that much on the homestead. Clearing.
         
         ROB:  About how much of a year did you have to work out?
         
         WK:  Well, I generally went out in harvest and that's about all.
         
         ROB:  Do you think people were happier in those days?
         
         WK: Well, I don't know about that. Some of 'em were quite well contented
         and some of 'em were not, just the same as they are now. I don't see much
         difference.
         
         ROB:  Was there much difference between the real homesteading years and 20 or
         30 years later?
         
         WK:  Oh yes. They had more land in cultivation and they was awhole lot further
         advanced. That is they had more stock, something to sell, you know. They
         had cattle, maybe some hogs. They'd have something to sell. Hardly any
         grain or anything, not from these timber ranches. They generally fed it.
         And the roads wasn't much more than a common trail. You couldn't haul much
         of a load over 'em, so If you could feed it and drive over it like driving
         several head of stock it was better than hauling a load of grain over a
         trail and bumping over them darn rocks in the road.
         
         ROB:  That was when you were coming out with horses wasn't it?
         
         WK:  Um-hm.
         
         ROB:  Did you prefer working with horses?
         
         WK:  Oh yes, I never learned to drive a car.
         
         ROB:  How about mules, did you ever work with mules?
         
         WK:  Sack east father had a span of mules. It was about as good a team as I
         ever worked. When I was about fourteen, fifteen years old, we raised a lot
         of corn; corn was a principal corp. And then we started plowing about the
         first of March for oats. We sowed maybe twenty or thirty acres in oats and
         then we'd plow for corn, put in about thirty or forty acres in corn and do
         it all with them two mules, a twelve-inch plow, and a double-A harrow.
         
         ROB:  Do you think a span of mules can outwork a span of horses?
         
         WK:  No, I don't think that, but what I liked about the mules was they were
         steady. Just lug along, you know, all day. Horses being a little faster
         in the morning, slower in the evening. Mules not. Mules had that gait and
         that was it all day.
         
         ROB:  Why didn't you use mules out here then?
         
         WK:  I don't know why they didn't. There was a man moved in over there to
         Gold Hill, they come from the southern part of Missouri, pretty close to the
         Oklahoma line. And he brought his span of mules with him out here. He kept
         them three or four years, and I don't know whether he sold 'em or traded
         'em for horses, but he got rid of 'em. I don't know why.
         
         ROB:  Are mules as stubborn as they say they are?
         
         WK:  Well, this span we had wasn't. They're a little tougher in the mouth, you
         had to pull a little harder to guide them.
         
         ROB:  About how many years could you work a horse or a mule before it would give
         out on you?
         
         WK:  Oh I don't know, I never tried that.
         
         ROB:  Did you ever have any horses that were real favorites of yours?
         
         WK:  Had what?
         
         ROB:  Did you have any horses that were real favorites of yours?
         
         WK:  You mean an animal I liked better than others?
         
         ROB:  Yes.
         
         WK:  Yes, I had one gelding. He was a chestnut sorrel. Weighed about 1200.
         A heavy, blockish animal. I don't know, I could do anything with him. Plow
         him single, double, hitch him up to anything he'd work with that. And when
         I ride him he was a nice animal.
         
         ROB:  What was his name?
         
         WK:  Selurn.
         
         ROB:  How many years did you have him?
         
         WK:  I don't just remember. I guess about 10 or 12 years.
         
         ROB:  Could you work him even when was getting to be an old horse?
         
         WK:  Did I work him with other horses?
         
         ROB:  Did you work him even when he was getting to 10 or 12 years old?
         
         WK:  Yes, he was alright then yet.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13489</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Justice_Lena2</previous>
      <next>Kauder2</next>
      <disp_name>Kauder1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
