<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">5/25/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ruth Leland, 1976-05-25, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:32:15</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Leland, Ruth</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Store clerk; minister of United Brethern Church</occupation>
      <birthyear>1890</birthyear>
      <residence>Juliaetta</residence>
      <origin>Moved from Wyoming with family (1906)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#doctors"&gt;doctors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#festivals"&gt;festivals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Jewish Americans"&gt;Jewish Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#discrimination"&gt;discrimination&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Christian"&gt;Christian&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Juliaetta"&gt;Juliaetta&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Kendrick"&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13662</file_name>
      <mp3>13663.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13663.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Foster School of Healing;</title>
            <synopsis>Foster School of Healing was the center of Juliaetta. It
               didn't increase population, but brought in outsiders. His
               cancer cure. His belief in nutrition and natural foods.
               Self-help.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Church History;</title>
            <synopsis>Church history of Juliaetta and Kendrick. Presbyterians
               were probably the first. Sharing ministers between the
               towns. Foster started his own Christian Church in
               Juliaetta. Baptists in Juliaetta couldn't sell their church
               building to the Nazarenes, although they wanted to. The
               life cycle of congregations in towns.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Religion;</title>
            <synopsis>People were not much more religious then than now; human
               nature has always been the same. When revivals came
               people went regardless of denomination because it was
               something to do.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Meeting in the Juliaetta Park;</title>
            <synopsis>Meeting in the Juliaetta Park on Children's Day of all the
               Sunday school classes and people from all around, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Children's Presentations;</title>
            <synopsis>Children's presentations at the Children's Day celebration.
               The picnic. A misunderstanding during the war led to the
               end of the program.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Armistice Day;</title>
            <synopsis>On Armistice Day the German Methodist minister was the
               only one who knew The Star-Spangled Banner. Then the
               children sang all the verses of My Country 'Tis of Thee.
               Anti-German sentiment: Kendrick decided to try to wipe
               out Cameron.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Many people wouldn't trade with Alexander</title>
            <synopsis>Many people wouldn't trade with Alexander because he was
               Jewish. He was a good man who willingly gave credit. He
               was very community-minded. After his death his wife
               took over, let help go, and might have made it except that
               the store burnt down.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Trading with the Indians;</title>
            <synopsis>Trading with the Indians at the store - they liked the way
               Alexander treated them. Indians bought only one item at
               a time - they were afraid of being cheated by whites.
               Discrimination against Indians in Lewiston. Divided opinion
               about them to Juliaetta. Racism against Indians because
               we think our culture must be better than theirs. She very
               liked the Indians in the store, although they required patience.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Indian church services;</title>
            <synopsis>Indian church services - The Lord's Prayer in sign
               language. Acceptance of Indians and other racial groups.
               The Bible speaks of the common blood of all mankind.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4020</time>
            <title>Indian Children;</title>
            <synopsis>Indians seldom brought children into the store; if children
               came in, they were extremely well behaved. Because of
               their rejection, Indians do not initiate speaking or hand
               shaking. Indians are now uniting as a people.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4380</time>
            <title>Indian Prayer Meetings;</title>
            <synopsis>The beauty and unity of Indian prayer meetings. Their
               feeling that they have all the time in the world. Indian
               denominations.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Revivals;</title>
            <synopsis>Revivals. Their purpose. The altar call. Today's
               emphasis on revival rather than conversion. Conversion
               there were many who were not Christians.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Local church history and revivals. Children's Day. Nez Perce Christianity.
         Discrimination against Nez Perces. Alexander's Store Foster School of Healing. 5-25-76
         1.5 hr 21p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         RUTH LELAND: That was in nineteen-six.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: was it big part of the town?
         
         RL: Yes, it was considered th thing in town. You see, there were a lot
         of people heretaking the treatments, as well as several students he
         had he was teaching the business. It was quite a big thing. I don't know
         whether, you've probably been told where it was.
         
         SAM:  The building still stands.
         
         RL: Yes. Somebody lives in it now. It's their home. Well, you go up this
         block and the next block, and its around the corner. And, 
         There was a family living Tn there in nineteen-nine. So sometime
         in that time he must have left. I imagine about nineteen-eight. But I
         was'nt iiving in town then, see? In fact, this is why Ican't help you
         too much. I've never been a part of Juliaetta. That is, unless you can
         count the last few years. But I have lived here steady. I was here about
         six months that winter, absorbed in the school. Then he moved to this place
         between here and Kendrick. Two miles out of town. Now, I'm giving you
         all this background so you'll understand this is not
         
         SAM:  Well, let me ask you about what you do remember about the Foster School.
         There weren't a lot of people around the area in 1910 and that's why
         we know so little about it.
         
         HL: I don t mean it brought any great population into the town. It was considered
         the big thing of the town, see.
         
         SAM:  Do you think it was building up the town when it was here?
         
         RL:  I really don't. It brought in outsiders.
         
         SAM:  Who mostly stayed for a cure and then left?
         
         RL:  Yes. That was all. It didn't bring in any people to live here. And
         when he left he took with him his students had lived here. There
         wereabout three or four.
         
         SAM:  What kind of cure was it? Was it more than one?
         
         RL: He claimed to have a cure for cancer. That is, skin cancer. And some kind
         of a 
         
         SAM:  A what?
         
         RL: Sauve or pasteror something of the kind that he'd put on. And he claimed
         cures for it, which is quite possible, because there's many types of skin
         cancers. And different things that work on them. But as far as Iknow, he
         did not claim to have it. Now, this is as far as I know. He did not claim
         to have any cure for interior cancers.
         
         SAM:  I see.
         
         RL:  He was not really, as Iunderstand it, an M.D. He was more of an osteopath.
         off the top of my head because I really don't know too much
         about it. But Ithink he claimed to have run on to this cure accidentally.
         He was very strong on nutrition, and that type of thing. Natural foods and
         all that.
         
         SAM:  He was?
         
         RL: Oh, yes. He was awful good with that. I'm rather in favor of that kind of
         thing, myself.
         
         SAM:  Well Ihad read in that old edition of the 'Juliaetta Sun', the one around
         1910 that came out when it mentioned the school, I think they said that he
         gave lectures regularly.
         
         RL: Yes,
         
         SAM:  That kind of surprised me. I was wondering if they were for the town or
         for his patients.
         
         RL: Ithink it was in the sanitarium, but anyone was welcome to come, who cared
         to come.
         
         SAM:  The sanitarium?
         
         RL: That's what they called it.
         
         SAM:  Did it have a resident population?
         
         RL: Oh, yes!
         
         SAM:  They lived right there?
         
         RL: It's a big house. It was always known as a sanitarium. And. a lot
         of people. In that way I suppose it did help the town. There were a lot of
         people who were staying in homes,.too. Getting room and board in homes.
         And then they'd go over for their treatment and their lectures and so forth.
         
         SAM:  In that 'Juliaetta Sun they mentioned a number of other forms of treatment
         besides the cancer one. They mentioned use of magnetism. And self-healing,
         too, I think was a part this idea.
         
         RL: I tell you, he was an osteopath. I know.
         
         SAM:  Did you know of anyone that would say they were cured by him?
         
         RL: There were quite a who did. I think there were about fifty of them.
         Even if it was cancer, because I know there's so many different types of
         it, since I have had radical surgery for cancer, I'm quite interested in
         that kind of thing. I know some of them used to call him the "Rubbing
         Doctor". 4fo I know he must have given that, of treatment. And like most
         of the nutritionists, they believed quite strongly in the self-help. Almost
         all of them do. The idea is, if you think this is going to help, it will.
         If you don't, it won't help, no matter how good it is. It is
         perfectly true. Most medical doctors, in fact, most all medical doctors do
         the same, believe in the same. They know that a person's attitude toward
         treatment they're''given? A.going to have an awful lot to do with how
         much good they get off the treatment.
         
         SAM:  l had this idea that this interest in natural foods was a recent develop
         ment. It's interesting that his use of natural foods would be a part of
         his method for staying well.
         
         RL: Did you ever hear of the Seventh Day Adventist church?
         
         SAM:  Yes.
         
         RL: They have taught natural foods from the very start of the church.
         
         SAM:  That's quite true.
         
         RL: But, it's not new. It did not get popular .like it is recently. In the
         last few years it got very popular.
         
         SAM:  Was the:.Seventh Day Church at all around here in, those days? I know Troy
         had a very strong group at Troy and at Viola. They had that academy in
         Viola in those early days. But I hadn't really heard about it in this area.
         
         RL: There hasn't been a Seventh Day Church here until the last few years.
         There's a small church here now. Composed mainly of people who have come
         in from outside, that is one thing I can tell you about, the church.
         
         SAM:  We find very little about the early religion in the country.
         
         RL: Well, I don't know who was theflones here. I very much SGspect the
         Presbyterians, since they started the thingraround Spaulding and Lapwai,
         and all. When I came here, there had already been a Presbyterian church.
         They had a building across the corner from the school
         up here. Burnt down, I think, later. Dust before, or not long before I
         came here, they built another church down here which eventually was made
         Lutherans
         into the apartments where tags live. And sold that to the 
         
         SAM:  (Asks for the word)
         
         RL: To the Lutheran church. There was also a Catholic church here in town, but
         I don't know how far back that dated, either. It was up the hill, here.
         I don't know what happened to. I guess maybe it burnt down.
         I really don't know. But, the Presbyterians shared a minister with
         Kendrick. And Kendrick wanted all morning services. So he would come down
         for Sunday night services. walked down from Kendrick,'cause that was
         the only way he could get here. He didn't have transportation, otherwise.
         But he would walk down and walk back. I got to know him quite well,
         because he was English and my mother was English. He used to stop halfiway
         down, for a cup of tea. We got very friendly. He was a very nice man.
         But then, in the morning services, the had Union sunday School.at
         practically all the churches in town. And there were several ministers,
         The Methodist minister, and another branch of Lutheran', minister. An
         Americanminister. UV minister. And I forget. There were others who would
         come in and preach.
         
         SAM:  This minister shared with Duliaetta as well?
         
         RL: Yes. They were regular ministers. I mean, they came on a regular basis.
         The same one came.
         
         SAM:  But it wouldn't be every week, like the Presbyterians?
         
         RL: No, I think there were about three of them that came regularly.on a
         specified Sunday. But toJback to Dr. Foster. He had been in it
         too. He was a member of the Christian Church. And I suspect they had, this
         is before my time, I expect that they had minister
         But he fell out with a bunch up there, and this is something you may not
         hejar from other people, but they may not know too much about it or may not
         want to talk about it, but he fell out with the church up there, I heard
         Khe couldnt run'.it and Dr. Foster I imagine that was the
         Jos-V beyond 
         reason. So with his ownchurch down here.A Church. His denomination.
         So he was minister of his own. He came out to preach and.didn't know him
         when I got here . I used to attend church there.
         
         SAM:  This minister was a visiting minister or a resident?
         
         RL: I don't know if it was possible, but he might have resided with
         Dr. Foster. They ."stayed up there and I might have a standing rememberance
         that he was not resident, but came in from one of the other churches.
         So there were two Protestant churches going here. Then, the Lutheran church
         burnt down. And they were offered this church over here.But, eventually,
         members of the Christianhurch moved away. They werehfrt very enthusiastic
         or something,after Dr. Foster left. It was hard to get ministers here.
         But they got a minister, excuse me, and they brought him to the Baptists
         who had had a falling out with the Presbyterian minister and theydecided
         they wanted their own church. So they bought'the Christian church and came
         down here. Then after had moved
         away and decided there uoftn't any, by the way, that was the church
         minister, decided he couldn't go it any more. But they dropped their
         meetings. And the Nazerenes came in and started meetings, and started a
         church, which met in this building down here, which was a bank and various
         other things. Now it has apartments over it, right next door to the service
         station. They tried, when they outgrew that they so obviously was going
         to have a church here, they were gaining quite a lot of people. They tried
         to buy the Baptist church. The Baptist church was perfectly willing to
         sell it to them. But, becausehe)had borrowed money from the national
         board to buy it, they had to put the deed in the hands of the national
         board, and the national board would not sell it. And the Nazerenes had
         always..
         
         RL: Would have nothing to do with it. They were quite willing to sell.
         They were glad to sell. And it was a nice church. 
         their
         
         SAM:  The Baptists maintained " ~ congregation after...
         
         RL: Until-Vieymoved away, - too. I think I am possibly the only person
         in town that ever belonged to that Baptist churchi I joined it when I was
         a girl. But then, it was sold to a local man, and he wrecked it. 
         the Nazerenes built their church on up, further up here. The Seventh
         Day Adventists jNcame from the outside had decided that they a church. There were
         quite a lot of them, then. So they built a church
         just this side of it. And how, that is the history of church denominations
         in ay town. They start, they grow, they thrive,and they die. And somebody
         else comes in, I think that they simply get to thinking too much of their
         church, The denominations,and the Lord can't use them anymore. That's the
         way I feel. The Seventh Day Adventists who were mostly people,
         Gould come here, anyway. There's a lot of them gone. They still
         hold their services with the minister from Troy, but believe it or not, the
         Mormons are using their church. Every so oftens, they have services there.
         So there's your church history.
         
         SAM:  That's just fascinating.
         
         RL: That's over many years, of course.
         (Teapot is whistling in background. Sam asks if he may remove it from the
         stove)
         There's one thing that I didn't get in there. The Methodists drew out from
         the Union up there, too. And they built this {church out on Main street.
         They were Southern Methodists.
         
         SAM:  This from the Union at Kendrick?
         
         RL: No. It was the one up here. The] in the Presbyterian church.
         
         SAM:  I see.
         
         RL: The church at Kendrick was North Methodist had been. .this was
         Southern Methodist.
         
         SAM:  So what, were the services then like they are now?
         
         RL: Like they would be in any small church you would go into. Some of them
         very formal Some of them informal. But following the general line.
         
         SAM:  Do you think that the earlier settlers took their religion more seriously?
         
         RL: People are people. Circumstances donaft change them 
         Some of them took it very seriously. Some of them had no more use for it
         than a lot of people today. Human nature is the same as it has been from
         the start. You find all kinds.
         
         SAM:  How much of community life was centered around the churches?
         
         RL: Well, looking back, I don't believe was a great deal more than is
         now. to extent if got in a revivalist for a meeting, uk
         every was apt to go because there wasn-'t anything else
         to go to. Whether you could call that centering or not, I don't know.
         It was just something to go to. So they went. One thing we used to have in
         Duliaetta was $ big Sunday School.meetings. We used to have a beautiful
         park here where the mill is now. And some of the Sunday Schools got
         the ideagoing down there on the Sunday Childress Day and having
         a Union program and a picnic. So they invited  nearby Sunday School and they
         came. The next year, why, more of them wanted to come. They'd get an outside
         speaker, and then the different Sunday Schools would furnish items for the
         program. We'd have an all-morning program, then.a big dinner, and sometimes,
         an afternoon one. Usually the speaker would be in the afternoon. And it grew
         until one year, there were over a thousand down there, from Sunday Schools.
         they came in horse and buggy, there were a few cars. And it was really quite affair.
         
         (End of side A)
         
         RL: The third Sunday in June for many at the Protestant churches has always
         been observed as Children's Day, with special programs from the Sunday
         School, and special recognition..
         
         SAM:  What type of presentations would the children be making?
         
         RL: They'd have recitations, and their psalms and their drills,- Some of
         those things down there(she is laughing). A whole group of them in
         the most intricate  Perhaps flags, sometimes flowers or . .
         Marching in and out. It took some work to get into those. And usually, I
         had to manufacture them myself. Each school was supposed to furnish, at least,
         two members and not more than four. And finally they had to limit them to
         two,it got so terribly big, because to take it down.the mountains for
         a program, they had to build a platform for it, move an instrument down
         fOr. Why, each item would be pretty elaborate. Group of psalms,
         possibly a of some kind. It was really something.
         
         SAM:  When you said "drill" would kind of drill would you say it'd be?
         the up to the next Usually the whole class
         
         RL: Like any drillyou'd see a marching band. In the middle of the street.
         ASome intricate figures. That type of thing.
         
         SAM:  How large of an area would this draw from, roughly?
         
         RL: They didn't have the transportation they have now. They would come from
         iroy, they would come from Southwick around up in there. Teaken, down
         
         SAM:  That's a very large area, even for those days.
         
         RL: it would be an all-day affair and they would bring their dinners, and
         very often a lot of them would bring dinners together. There'd always
         be food if somebody hadn't brought something. There»d always be food to
         spare.
         
         SAM:  Would this have been well before uorld War Two? Possibly after Worid yar
         One or even before that?
         
         RL:  It was between the orld Wars. It, Icouldn't tell you how many years
         it did last, but it must be quite a long time.
         
         SAM:  I wonder why they stopped it.
         
         RL: it stopped in the middle of World War Two. And there again, there was a
         misunderstanding that broke it up. By that time, we weren't able to use
         the park for some reason that Icannot remember why it was? we couldn't use
         the park then. I know the last one we had was in a big Chautauqua tent
         that sit in the middle of the square right here. And I forget who the
         speaker was. But I know that those in charge said that they got am order
         from the government if they used that speaker, they must also use a group
         of G.I. s who were back on furlow.That was during the war, you see.
         Possibly they thought he was too anti-war, or something
         
         SAM:  Do you mean use a group of G.I.s, do you mean, to speak?
         
         RL: On the program.
         
         SAM:  That was the last year?
         
         RL: That was the last year they had it.
         
         SAM:  Perhaps he was of Gorman descent.
         
         RL: I think he was rather anti-war.
         
         SAM:  Would the speaker talk about secular subjects as well as religious ones at
         these?
         
         RL: They were entirely free to talk about anything they wanted to. In fact, they
         were often brought in for some special thing that you might call secular.
         But speaking of the German descent, during the war, we had, that was
         during World War One, the Methodist minister down here was a German.
         He quite an accent. And a very nice guy. American citizen. But there
         was quite a bit ofi feeling in town about him and against him. But on
         Armistice Day, that is the false armistice, the one that came a week ahead,
         you know, everybody, although it was raining, gathered down here in the 
         square, and to celebrate, it was just"arizzling. I was just .. with the
         flu, didn't have any business being there, really. But, they all around
         just had a happy time. Sointbody thought they ought to sing The Star-
         Spangled Banner, nd everbpdy bravely started out. "Oh, say can, you see".
         Everybody stopped. They didn't know it. Except the German minister, and
         he knew it all the way through. He sang the first verse, and they decided
         they'd start it on... oh, I know it perfectly well, and you do too. The
         hymn 9 My Country Tis of Thee. And not many of the grown people knew it.
         Some of them did. All the kids did, because all during the it was
         part of the program at the Union Sunday School. So they knew it all the
         way through, all four verses. The grown-ups knew the first. I've laughed
         over that so many times. The only thadknew the national anthem was the
         German. 
         
         SAM:  I heard that some time around there, thekids had jammed a flagpole into
         the wall of the Methodist church.
         
         RL: I wouldn't know.
         
         SAM:  Someone told me that. I would like to know that same type of sentiment, wbere
         because he was German, they didn't like him. I'd like that type of information from
         you.
         
         RL: Kids might have done it, but I bet some grown-ups were it. He
         was a very likeable guy.
         
         SAM:  Was he still able to take part in the Union activities at that time?
         
         RL: He took part when the churches went together.
         
         SAM:  I heard there was a dislike and an opposition of speaking the German
         language during that time. Frank Brockfc said, who was German, that when
         he would talk on the phone line to neighbors in German that... other
         people listening on the line didn't like that, because they were talking
         in German and they didn't know what they were saying. There must have
         been quite a bit of wondering being done.
         
         RL: We didn't have too many Germans arpund here at the time, but the feeling
         was pretty high, alright, this I have heard, maybe Mr. Brock. might have
         said something about it. Kendrick took a notion to try and wipe out Cameron.
         Maybe he wouldn't say anything about it.
         
         SAM:  He probably would if I asked him. Did they get very far?
         
         RL: (Laughs). Cameron caught on to it and I think they figured they bit off 
         too much.
         
         SAM:  I've heard of that kind of thing. It's really too bad when you think that
         people are American as everybody else, having to defend their patriotism.
         
         RL: That racist feeling is at the bottom of so many things. I know that my
         boss in the store, Alexander was a Dew. And there were a lot of
         people who wouldn't go into his store. 
         sam; What was he like to work for?
         
         RL: Fine. A very considerate man.
         
         SAM:  Do you think he himself felt accepted by the community or do you think that
         he wondered a lot?
         
         RL: Oh, he was accepted by the community, but only from certain people, see.
         He felt it. You can't help but feel it.
         
         SAM:  Did he do a good business?
         
         RL: Real good.
         
         SAM:  There were a number of Jews around the area that ran stores. You may know
         a few.(He recounts names). Was Alexander here when you first came?
         
         RL: Yes.
         
         SAM:  So he, was a pioneer merchant?
         
         RL: Yes.
         
         SAM:  Did he build his business up here in Guliaetta?
         
         RL: I imagine he did. Of course, the Alexanders were a big firm in Leuiston.in
         pioneer days.
         
         SAM:  Same family?
         
         RL: Same family.
         
         SAM:  Did he give credit?
         
         RL: Yes.
         
         SAM:  Have you heard of Rosenstein from Genesee?
         
         RL: Yes.
         
         SAM:  I heard that many people who went to that store talk of the willingness
         to give credit by Rosenstein. I am aware of the stereotype people have
         of Jews, that they think they are tight with money.
         
         RL: No. Joe Alexander of course was careful who he gave credit to. But I am
         certain there were cases when he gave credit when he knew he would never
         get anything out of it. And any community project, that type of thing we could
         count on him. 
         
         SAM:  Did he have a family?
         
         RL: Yes. They used to live right here where this house is now. After he passed
         away, his wife tried to the business, and that was during World War One,
         toward the end of it. It was after World War One. That was when I lost my
         he couldn't afford to keep the whole crew on. She tried to
         to take my place herself. The.bookkeepebecame her brother-in-law. And
         one man, 'cdu se they had to have a man in the grocery department, thpy tried
         to go on. I think she might have made it, only the store burnt down.
         
         SAM:  Dust the store, or was it a regular Main street fire?
         
         RL: Dust the store.
         
         SAM:  Did they know how?
         
         RL: Never were sure(how the fire started).
         
         SAM: Was she Jewish too?
         
         RL: No.
         
         SAM:  Was she a local girl?
         
         RL: Yes. She was a Dohnson.
         
         SAM:  And he died young?
         
         RL: Yes, you might consider it rather young. They had three boys. But, he wasn't
         old, by any means. I couldn't give you his exact age, but, it was middle
         age, I think.
         
         SAM:  Was there much Indian trade? In the store.
         
         RL: He had an awful lot of Indian trade. They liked to trade with him because
         he'd , with them. And when the store burned down, he had over
         a thousand dollars, and a thousand dollars at that time was something, in
         Indian goods that he'd bought from the beadwork, and all that type of thing. And they'd
         come and Dust a
         real good time of it. That dealing with the Indians, dealing withIndians
         at that time especially, was something. You could sell an Indian, oh,
         maybe fifty dollars worth of stuff, one item at a time. He'd buy one
         item and pay for it.Then the next one 
         it. You'd have to have patience aplenty, but it would pay off. They
         couldn't be hurried.
         
         SAM:  You couldn't give them the idea to buy everything at one time?
         hem. He would buy goods from them,
         
         RL: No.
         
         SAM:  i wonder why?
         
         RL: They wanted to know each one cost. That they weren't being cheated.
         I think the whites had taught them that. They knew just what one thing was
         going to cost, they could pay for it then. But if they bought several things,
         how theyAknow you hadn't slipped in an extra price on them. They
         weren't that much up on our money. Oh, I can see the reason to it, alright.
         And you couldn't sell them anything. You could show them stuff. If they
         wanted it,they would buy it. But that was it. You could tell them how good
         it was and that kind of thing. But, Mr. Alexander
         . He'd say,"This is what you need. You see, you neefca this that and
         the other"'.AThey had a good time over it.
         
         SAM:  You say he would take more time with an Indian than an average storekeeper
         would?
         
         SAM:  So maybe they realized that he was more concerned about them.
         
         RL: I think so. The reason I think that is that some of these people would
         come clear from Lapwai to deal with him. They could have gone to Lewiston
         just as easily. To the bigger stores down there. But there the people
         wouldn't have fussed with them. In fact, they wouldn't have been welcomed
         in Lewiston. Long about that time, there unre plenty of places with a sign
         up"No Indians". Tisn't too many years ago that you might find one of those
         signs in certain places in Lewiston. I know, oh it can't be more
         than fifteen or twenty years ago, if that long, I remember a certain
         resturant in Lewiston, we serve only whites.
         
         SAM:  I can imagine it because of what I've heard about the outh, but to imagine
         it against the Indians around here seems strange. Unfair.
         How were the Indians welcomed in Duliaetta?
         
         RL: Accepted in some places, others they weren't. They found it hard to get
         work here, for a while. There's still a lot of ppbple say, i wouldn't
         have an Indian work for me." And yet, you'll hear others say,"The best
         help I ever had was Indians."
         
         SAM:  What do you think the difference comes down to, why some people would 
         one opinion and some the other?
         
         RL: Well, it's the color of the skin. And yet, it isn't really that. It's
         because the color of their skin means, to a. lot of people, a different
         culture from what we have. A different way of life. And because we think
         ours is the best, we don't want the other. Well they think theirs is the
         best, too. And we can't understand that, because we know ours is the best.
         That's it boils down to. It's taken me eighty years or better to
         realise it. That's what it boils down to.
         
         SAM:  What did you think of the Indians that you had dealings with in the store?
         
         RL: I liked them veryt much. I sometimes had to grab my patience with both hands.
         Especially when I was somewhat rushed, but....
         
         (End of side B)
         
         SAM:  ...considered that you knew them?
         
         RL: I individuals more than families. I had some very, very good
         friends among the Indians. By the way, the Indian churches would come up
         to our Sunday School thing, too. The Indian Sunday Schools would. I
         I remember one of the most impressive things we ever had in one of
         those programs was one of the Indian men giving The Lord's Prayer in
         Indian sign language. Believe me, he said it, as he gave it, there
         wasn't a stir in that whole audience. That was one of our big ones, too.
         But they would come up with their Psalms, sometimes in Indian, sometimes
         in English, and join.with the rest of the group.
         
         SAM:  I have found in talking to old-timers, far more caring and liking of the
         Indians than I ever expected when I first started talking to people.
         I feel some places in the West that feeling towards the Indians by the
         older folks was not a good one.
         
         RL: It has changed a great deal in the last twenty-five or thirty-five years.
         I can rememer very well when that was not the attitude at all. And even
         today there will be some people who...
         
         SAM:  Of course, the people I talk to are old-timers,people who lived with, or
         knew them when they were young. Maybe people have come to understand
         better through the years.
         
         RL: If one §juld have had something against the Indians, of the people, I
         guess I did.For,I was born in the middle of the Sioux uprising in Dakota.
         I was born in Wyoming. And I know my folks told me how much trouble they
         had keeping baby Ruth quiet. Blankets over the windows and all that. They
         wondered if one of the raiding parties would come across. They didn't have
         any idea. And my folks never held it against the Indians, and therefore, I
         never did. And when I ran into Indians down here, well they were just people.
         Like other people. It's always been my feelings about the Negros. The Asiatics.
         Any of them. They're people. And our guide-book tells us that God made but
         one blood all nations of the earth. And any scientist will tell you it's
         absolutely true. You take samples of blood from all of them and you can't
         tell the differece, no matter what cclor their skin is, no matter where
         they come from. And that book also tells us that the blood is the
         and we know that that's true. Without it we could not do it. Therefore,
         where is the difference? I could put on paint to change the color of my
         skin, I go out in the sun, I change it.Stay indoors, I change it again.
         What difference dees it make?
         
         SAM:  When you said you dealt with individuals rather than families, does that
         mean only the husband or the wife would come into the store?
         
         RL: As a general thing, they didn't bring their chidren in. Occasionally, they
         did.Believe me, when they did, those children did not touch anything.
         There mothers would say,"Leave that alone right now!" They might have
         wanted something and asked about it, but,no no, no touch. They were very,
         very well-behaved. Much better behaved than the white ones.
         
         SAM:  The people that you got to know, were they people who traded at the store?
         Or ones that you met through the church?
         
         RL: Both.
         
         SAM:  I wonder how the Indians felt in those earlier days when there was behaved.
         descrimination. Maybe that's why they felt the children should be better
         
         RL: The Indian way of training. They don't believe in this permissiveness.
         
         SAM:  It's hard when you think this whole country was once all theirs.
         
         RL: There's one thing that to me shows more than anything else, that they feel
         that they are not accepted. You'll very rarely, in fact, I can't say that
         I've ever known an Indian to speak first. Oroffer his hand. When you speak,
         they're quite willing to respond. Quite willing to shake hands. But you
         must start. How would you feel under the circumstances?
         
         SAM:  I never thought of that and what that means. Do you think they've retained
         the closeness of their communities through the years?
         
         RL: It's hard to tell, I believe more than we realise. And I think it is coming
         out right now. This new Indian movement. The Indians are, the i:tribes
         are taking up the cudgel, you might say, for the other Indians. They seem
         to be uniting as a people.more than they had.
         
         SAM:  Do you think the form of Christianity they follow is different because of
         their cultural traditions?
         
         RL: I'm not sure I understand just what you mean? You mean their form of
         worship?
         
         SAM:  Yes.
         
         RL:  It is alittle different just as you will find a form of worship alittle
         different in different sections of this country, for instance, as well as
         in the other countries. I don't suppose you've ever had the privilege,
         as I have had one, of going to the camp meeting that had up here by
         Winchester. If you ever get a chance, go up there. They have it every year.
         And it is absolutely fabulous. For instance, in one of their prayer meetings,
         there will be hundreds there. They will be praying aloud all over that
         group. Yet there is no sense of any confusion. I can't explain it. All these
         voices coming. Everyone praying their own prayers. Some in English, some in
         Indian. But there's a unity about the whole thing that you can't explain
         at all unless it is that the Holy Spirit, Himself is there, is guiding
         it. And that is a thing you wouldn't ordinarily find unless you
         were in a Pentacostal church, find that sort of thing. But the Pehtacostal
         churches I have attended, I have felt much more disunity than I did up
         there. They have their own way of holding the services, theylre ape tp
         ask forjxiurs  They're very annoyed if the minister dares to speak more
         than thirty minutes, or if the service lasts over an hour, they just can't
         take it. Now the Indians, they have all the time there is. They're there
         to worship and they'll just on worshipping as long as they want to.
         In that you might say their form of religion is quite different "to ours.
         But don't think that ours is any better. And I think that the whole thing5
         might rest on that. The Indian feels he has all the time there is. Well
         that's all any of us have. But the rest of us don't feel it. We feel we've
         got to get out and do things. This, that, and the other. And the Indian
         thinks,"What difference do it make in the long run?"
         
         SAM:  He knows perhaps better.
         
         RL: He knows and we don't.
         
         SAM:  Is Presbyterianism still the strongest denomination among the Indians?
         
         RL: Catholicism is quite strong. A lot of Methodists too. It depend mainly,
         I think, on where you happen to be. Down here at Lapwai, it was Presbyterian
         church started, the in Walla Walla. But in other sections
         where it might have been another denomination that went in, the story was
         probably different.
         
         SAM:  I was thinking of the Nez Perce. I was thinking of the
         
         RL: Sisters.
         
         SAM:  Were they here when you were first here?
         
         RL: I never met them, but they were still alive when I came. The Indians are
         
         SAM: 
         quite strong on tradition. And so it would carry over into that.
         i liked to ask you about the revivals. I understand that the revivals
         seemed to have been more important in that there were' a 1ot more of them,
         as you said, that's what there was to do. Theyhad a great deal more
         participation from the population in general. How frequent were they and
         what were they like?
         
         RL: They differed depending on who was doing  But as a general thing,
         each church would have at least one a year. Sometimes two. And it would
         be in the summer or in the winter. Sometimes it onAa summer
         camp meeting when everybody went out and lived in tents and things.
         And in the winter it would be held in the church. There would be one or
         more speakers each evening. Usually they would get in a main speaker.
         Not the pastor of the church, but a main speaker from outside. Perhaps
         a singer or two. A psalms deader. And the whole sermon would be a whole
         series of sermons would be around the thought of getting the people
         who were already professed Christians that weren't working at it too hard
         back where they ought to be. And getting those who had never become
         Christians to be saved, to become Christians. They were called "revivals"
         because of the idea of reviving the ones who had kind of strayed away a bit.
         And they would have some service, half an hour or so, singing and perhaps
         some special numbers. Then they would have the sermon. And the speaker
         would make what called the "altar call", invite all those who felt
         they wanted to do better to come to the altar and pray. And other Christians
         would gather around with them and pray. And if they seemed to need some help
         orAunderstanding what it was all about, why, they'd council with them.
         They would show them that they understood it all and that they knew what
         they were doing. And the words of the Scripture, were born again. It .Saved,
         really let Christ enter their hearts.The people would come from miles and
         miles around. And horse and buggy in the summer. . Cars
         later on. Practically every church today, every one of the Protestant
         churches plan on it at least once during the year. But with this change.
         In most of the churches today,.,the emphasis is really on revival, on the
         people who have been Christians or claim to be Christians and have
         strayed away. And not nearly so much on the unconverted people although they
         are welcomed and if a church really gets revived, there areAquite a lot of
         people converted, too. Because they see there is something there that they
         really need, that they want. And when you can show people you've got
         something they wanitt,,..tthhaatt''ss wworth having, they're going to want it, they're
         going to try to get it. And that is the root of revival. Some of them are
         quite quiet, others got quite noisy.
         
         SAM:  I think that's a good overview of it, a little more than I really quite
         understood.When people converted, were , they usually people who were
         nominally members of the faith but who had not actually been born again?
         
         RL: Many times it was people who had never had anything to do with it whatever.
         They'd stray into the meeting, simply because it was someplace to go.
         
         SAM:  Would this mean that they wouldn't have been a member of any Christian faith?
         
         RL: May not even be. a Christian family. May have been the first time that
         they'd ever heard of it.
         
         SAM:  Was this common?
         
         RL: Not at all uncommon.They might have been people who had gone to church or
         whose family gone to church or gone to Sunday School or something
         of the kind. I'm thinking now of a man who was a member of one of my churches
         who told me that as a young man in Seattle, not a boy, a young man,he had
         strayed into, I think, into a mission. Some meeting, anyway, and heard the
         Gospel for the first time in his life. And he was an American, born and
         brtdiHe said it was the first time he had ever heard it. He said,"I knew
         right then it was something I wanted I ha to have it." He was converted
         that night. He lives in Lewiston now. He's still a very devote Christian
         man. May I ask you a very personal question?
         
         SAM:  Sure. Are you going to ask me what my faith is?
         
         RL: Are you a Christian?
         
         SAM:  As a matter of fact
         
         (End of side C)
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13662</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Lawrence2</previous>
      <next>Lepard</next>
      <disp_name>Leland</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
