<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/25/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Martha Lowery Long, 1976-10-25, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:06:39</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Long, Martha Lowery</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Extension specialist for Chelan County and Washington state; homemaker;
         teacher
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Kendrick, eastern Washington</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from North Dakota and homesteaded near Quincy, Washington (1902)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#water"&gt;water&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#customs"&gt;customs&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cards"&gt;cards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#boardinghouses"&gt;boardinghouses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooking"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#isolation"&gt;isolation&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Pullman"&gt;Pullman&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Culdesac"&gt;Culdesac&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Washington"&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Kendrick"&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13669</file_name>
      <mp3>13670.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13670.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Settling in Quincy Valley, leaving North Dakota</title>
            <synopsis>Settling in Quincy Valley, leaving North Dakota.
               Family joke about her coming from a badger hole.
               Long drought drove many from the area. Father
               worked off poll tax for others by doing road
               work. Germans used Russian thistle for cattle feed.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Strict observance of Sundays; importance of faith for homesteaders</title>
            <synopsis>Strict observance of Sundays - the children
               couldn't even use scissors to make paper cut-outs.
               The Presbyterian minister generally came for
               Sunday dinner. The "jack rabbit" preacher who
               was close to the family. Importance of faith
               for homesteaders. Children's view of Sundays.
               First community Christmas tree was sagebrush.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Reliance on sagebrush for fuel; her first cookout on a wood-gathering trip</title>
            <synopsis>Reliance on sagebrush for fuel. Her first
               cookout on a wood-gathering trip. Sandstorms
               got sand in the house. Board-and-batten
               construction. Keeping warm in the house.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>recycling sacks into cloth and clothing; mother's family was from New England; early
               garden; defending chickens from coyotes
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Recycling sacks into cloth and clothing.
               Mother's family was from New England. Orchard
               and garden in the draw; early garden. Defending
               the chickens from coyotes. Jack rabbits ate
               up the haystacks; rabbit drives. May basket
               for the teacher with fresh food instead of
               candy (continued).
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Teacher was pleased to get gift of fresh food; celebrating May Day; Halloween; homemade
               valentines
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The teacher was pleased to get a gift of fresh
               food. Celebrating May Day. Halloween.
               Homemade valentines- her favorite one was
               from her mother; saving them for the future.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2100</time>
            <title>Conserving scarce water; reuse and hauling; making paste; taking bathes in wash tub
               in kitchen
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Conserving scarce water. Reuse and hauling.
               Making paste. Taking bathes in a wash tub in
               the kitchen on Saturday evenings.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Family Christmas customs</title>
            <synopsis>Family Christmas customs. The hanging
               gunnysack for Christmas presents. Making
               shaving pads for father, needle books for
               mother. Mother renovated their dolls, which
               were sent to Santa Claus. Family singing;
               father taught her alto for his tenor. Custom
               of giving presents at the church wasn't good
               for poorer people. Mother read to the children,
               With the dollar she made for tending a plot,
               she got two books, including Beautiful Joe.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Reusing cans and bottles for storage or play; remedies for sickness</title>
            <synopsis>Reusing cans and bottles for storage or play.
               Remedies for sickness - cold treatment.
               Hiding rubbers that they had to wear to school.
               Mother's strictness - reaction to daughter's
               saying "dickens". She was teased about not
               knowing another language, like the other
               ethnic groups, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>How mother helped her prove she was Irish; mother's opposition to dancing and playing
               cards; didn't learn to dance till college
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>How mother helped her prove she was Irish.
               Father could stand on his head and dance a
               jig. Little proximity to drinking. Mother's
               opposition to playing cards. She didn't learn
               to dance until college. Playing games.
               Opposition to dancing and cards was to protect
               them from worse influences. Socializing with
               other families. Her pleasure at seeing
               wallpaper, getting a peacock egg. Cards in
               baking soda packages; use of soda.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>Chores in the family; singing and reading while working; closeness with siblings</title>
            <synopsis>Chores in the family - singing and reading while
               working. Closeness with siblings. Mother read
               to children, and they play acted the stories.
               Remaking old clothes. Townspeople and some
               farmers were better off.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>Decision to move to Pullman so children could go to college; knowledge of farmers
               that Quincy Land would produce water
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Decision to move to Pullman so children could
               go to college (1914). Mother took in boarders.
               Knowledge of farmers that Quincy land would
               produce with water. Going to Crescent Bar for
               peaches, and salvaging bruised ones. Going
               to Moses Coulee for prunes. A rope around the
               tent was thought to protect from rattlesnakes.
               Cellar storage.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5340</time>
            <title>Father came in 1901. Drought and rain - some
               other areas were better for crops than Quincy.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father came in 1901. Drought and rain - some
               other areas were better for crops than Quincy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Magazines received at home; children's enjoyment of comics; she was a tomboy</title>
            <synopsis>Magazines received at home. Children's
               enjoyment of comics. Drinking yeast instead
               of pear juice. Kneading bread. She wore
               overalls at home but not in public - she was
               a tomboy. Mother believed play was important.
               Playing with hoops. Her friend, the minister's
               daughter, who played marbles for keeps.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5880</time>
            <title>Discipline and upbringing wat mother's responsibility; didn't want to move until oldest
               siblings had graduated
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Discipline and upbringing was mother's
               responsibility. They didn't want to move until
               oldest siblings had graduated. Mother
               lowered hem of sister's skirt at her graduation,
               Her isolation from her family in North Dakota.
               They sent an organ to them. Mother couldn't
               sing second part.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6300</time>
            <title>Extreme importance of getting an education to the mother; she cooked for threshing
               crew at LaCrosse with a friend; interest in home economics and teaching
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Extreme importance of getting an education to
               mother. She cooked for threshing crew at
               LaCrosse with a friend. Interest in home
               economics and teaching. Importance of teachers
               to communities - at Cul-de-sac they didn't
               like teachers who went home to Lewiston on
               weekends. Most married women couldn't teach
               because unmarried women needed work.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6720</time>
            <title>Home economics curriculum as WSC; science requirements; opportunities in the field;
               practice teaching in Pullman
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Home economics curriculum at WSC. Science
               requirements. Opportunities in the field.
               An impossible job of canning chicken with
               girls was her introduction to extension work.
               Practice teaching in Pullman.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7140</time>
            <title>Importance of beauty to mother. The children
               learned to value a tree or flower of their own.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Importance of beauty to mother. The children
               learned to value a tree or flower of their own.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Youth on a drought-stricken homestead. Family holiday customs. Mother's
         character. Family move to Pullman. Attending Washington State College. 10-25-76 2
         hr
         61p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         MARTHA LOWERY LONG: How do you want this started? Do you want it to be just
         what I remember or family- my sister had a lot of family anecdotes
         in there that I just know real well, but I just know them from lis
         tening to the family tell them.
         
         SS:  Well, those that seem interesting I think, but really your own ex
         perience most of all. What you remember it being like there when
         you were a kid. You say it was rough.
         
         MLL:  There was no money in those early days, pioneer. They came out
         there and settled and a dollar was just a fortune. There was no actual
         cash. They raised what food they could and they had to buy a
         few things. And they brought what they had with them when they came
         to settle those homesteads. The fact that it was the Quincy Valley,
         which was a sagebrush country, you see then, a flat, sagebrush co
         vered desert country, and later became this lushirrigated country
         that you drove through. That's why Quincy is interesting to a lot
         of people. They don't know what it was like in that early day when
         my folks- it was opened up for homestead- that's how they happened
         to go there.
         
         SS:  How was it that your folks actually happened to go there?
         
         MLL:  Well, they had lived in North Dakota and Dad was a carpenter, I guess,
         And North Dakota was a meadow and prairie country, level prairie coun
         try. And my mother believed that a family was better off g H„,.w up
         away from relatives rather than too close, although she was very de
         voted to her relatives. And so, this Quincy Valley in the Big Bend
         Country in Central Washington was opened up for homesteading. And
         you could go out and select a quarter section of land and if you made
         Certain improvements and lived on it a certain length of time, I
         don't know the exact length of time, then you owned it. And that's
         what they did. Dad went out first and chose this- it was a mile and
         a half directly north of Quincy, the town of Quincy, there wasn't
         much town yet, but there was a town, small town with a store there
         then. And he chose the southwest quarter section. It was all square,
         it wasn't like this country where sections are irregular; they were
         all laid out square because it was level country. And he started to
         build a little house. It only had one room at first, one large room
         and it had board and batten, that's boards that go up and down and
         ;the cracks are covered with another board, and a tar paper roof and a
         stovepipe. It had no chinmney; there was no bricks. And when Mother
         first came in- he was there a year building this little house; getting
         started, and then Mother and the four older children came and these
         cracks were still open- my sister told that in that other story- how
         I'd been
         scared she was that somebody'd peek in with those cracks. scared
         too. Anyway- I was the first child born on the homestead. And I was
         the biggest and healthiest and I still have the best health, and the
         others are all gone except two sisters- and I've always laid it to that
         virgin soil. They broke up this- and from my study of nutrition, I
         think this might have had something to do with it- my health, don't
         you?
         
         MARVIN LONG: They found her one day out there-
         
         MLL:  Now Marvin! Well, let me tell it.
         
         SS:  What is the story?
         
         MLL:  Well, we had a doctor- my sister got this part wrong- his name was
         Dr. Widby, and he was an eye specialist in Wenatchee, later when I
         lived in Wenatchee I knew him. But at the time he was a young country doctor. And
         so, when the baby was- there were no hospitals or
         anything, and when it was time for the baby to arrive why Dad got on
         one of the plow horses, we didn't have a riding horse, you know, just
         work horses; got on one of the horses and rode to town to get the doc
         tor. And the doctor borrowed a saddle horse from Jack Gaither, it was
         a bit lively, and they started out to our farm, and the horse stepped
         in a badger hole and threw the doctor, and the horse wasn't hurt but
         he ran back to town and the doctor's bag settled there, and the doc
         tor picked up his bag and had to walk the rest of the way. So they
         always said the doctor got me out of the badger hole! And on the way
         to school later when I was school age and I walked to school through
         the sagebrush here was this big badger hole right by the trail, and I'd
         go around- I can still remember looking down it every time I went past
         thinking there must be another baby in that hole! I sure that was
         the one. I never found any babies in that badger hole.
         
         SS:  Did he get there in time?
         
         MLL:  Yes, he got there in time and I was a ten pound baby. I had a good
         start, and I kept it up all my life. And I was healthy and I think
         it was because they were on virgin soil and that soil was producing
         good vegetables. I don't the badger hole had anything to do with my
         You
         health, but the virgin soil might have. know very well it could have
         although my mother's healthy condition, of course, did, too contributed.
         Anyway, years later, I was working in Wenatchee- this is going ahead in
         the story- but Dr. Widby went to Vienna and became an eye specialist.
         And Dr. Widby fitted my first glasses.
         
         SS:  In Wenatchee?
         
         MLL:  In Wenatchee. And one time- I was in extension work at that time, and
         the county agent belonged to Rotary Club along with this doctor, and
         I told him- my father came to visit and he told him this story
         about Dr. Widby delivering my mother when I was born, and oh, he
         couldn't wait. So one time I was at Rotary Club as a guest with 4H
         Clubs, you know or on the program. And I knew something was coming
         but I didn't guess what it was. And he said, "I have an important
         guest to introduce." And he asked me to stand and then he said"l'd
         like for Dr. Widby to stand." And he told that whole Rotary Club at
         Wenatchee that- And Dr. Widby was a small man and very much liked in
         Wenatchee- that Dr. Widby delivered me when he was a young prac
         titioner at Quincy. I liked 'em both so I didn't care, but it was
         real funny.
         
         SS:  Well, you know, in just glancing at your sister's story, I have the
         idea that from ' that she gives of your mother, that it was
         somewhat rough on her. The living in that time.
         
         MLL:  Well, yes, it was- of course, all pioneer women- most pioneer women,
         had it- but they were happy doing it. I mean, my mother knew how tofor
         us to have great fun. Oh, my childhood was just happy and we had
         great fun as a family. There were finally seven children; there were
         two more after me. Two more born there.
         
         ML: I was born up here in Kendrick- Avery- and when I was born there was
         women come in and took care of me.
         
         MLL:  But there wasn't any money, and they broke up this sagebrush and expec
         ted to raise crops like they had in North Dakots where there was more
         rainfall. Well, the first few years there was enough rainfall so that
         times were not quite so hard, and they got crops and all- wheat crops.
         And then the climate changed in that country and it became drought and
         they weren't able to even raise a crop. And so then, my father had to
         work out at whatever he could get. In the hills north of Quincy there
         were wheat ranches that did produce and my Uncle Jim lived there and he
         used to go over and work in harvest and earn money that way. Then there
         was another way that they earned money that was sort of interesting.
         They had- what do they call it? A road tax. They taxed everybody to
         build the roads in those days, and if you couldn't pay your tax- if
         you didn't want to pay your tax, you could hire somebody else to do
         the work for you. And he did that kind of work. And he'd be gone all
         week. He used to roll up a bed that was real heavy quilts On Sunday
         nights we'd help him roll up bed and then heM load the wagon and the I'd
         go out. Sometimes the boys had these jobs, too, and they'd go off and
         work on the road all week and then come back. They'd do their own coo
         king and sleep under the wagon if it rained a little; didn't rain much
         in that country, but if it did. And that's the way they made a living.
         
         ML: That's the way they paid taxes, too.
         
         MLL:  The only people that survived the dpughts- we moved away- and the farm
         went for taxes finally because of this long drought period. And it was
         these German people that had moved in there that were thrifty, that knew
         how to survive. They would take- the Russian Thistles had come in as
         one of the pests, the rail brought it, and they're the things you
         see on Western pictures, the big tumbleweeds that go down in the ghost
         towns, you know, a lot of those were Russian Thistles, I think. Ours
         were big like that. And they used to cut these in the green stage and
         stack them and feed them to their cattle. These German people knew how
         to do that and they could survive, but we didn't; we moved. My mother
         was determined we would have an education so we moved to Pullman.
         But I was going to tell you about some of the fun we used to have.
         We used to play games, you know, family. And we played lots of
         games sitting around the big dining room table. It always had white
         oilcloth on it. We had a big table, that would seat all nine of us,
         of course the youngest children didn't play much. We played games like
         not cards! My mother was against cards; against liquor and cards, base
         ball on Sunday, and she had very strict standards about those things.
         A lot of people did in those days. You were either one way or you were
         the other. So we didn't know anything about baseball because it was al
         ways played on Sunday and you couldn't play games on Sunday, like that.
         We couldn't play with a ball at home on Sunday, even. We couldn't cut
         paper dolls on Sunday. I've never understood that, but there was a hook
         on the wall where we kept the scissors- and the paper dolls were a big
         thing in our life, but Sunday you couldn't take down the scissors and
         cut paper dolls. Sunday had to be special. And that impressed us.
         We went to church. We got ready on Saturday. And no work was ever
         done on the farm on Sunday. My people were Presbyterians.
         MARVIN: We never had that kind of thing
         
         MLL:  Well, that's the way it was in those early days. And there wasn't any
         work done on Sunday. The horses were allowed to take yo u to church,
         but the horses weren't worked, they rested, too. And then the preacheroh,
         we had a big dinner. We got up and had to kill a chicken- there
         wasn't any refrigeration, so you had to get up and kill the chickens
         Sunday morning and get it started cooking. And then bring the preacher
         home for dinner. And my mother worked hard, but then that was all in—
         for the good of the Lord, because it was the preacher feeding,
         you know.
         
         SS:  Did he come to dinner often?
         
         MLL:  Oh, he came to dinner often. The preacher was just like a member of
         our family. He was always one of my mother's best friends. And the
         first preacher I remember was a- they called him- he was quite well
         known in that country. They called him- what did they call him? He
         was like an itinerate preacher- they called him the jack rabbit preacher
         because jack rabbits were prevalent in the country and he came from
         one town to the other.
         
         SS:  Circuit rider?
         
         MLL: Yes. On that order. And he used to ride a bicycle. The Great Nor
         thern Railroad went through Quincy, and he would ride that bicycle
         down that railroad, just imagine, bumpity bump, from the little towns-
         Not Soap Lake- but the next little town, Adrian, I guess it was up the
         road. He'd ride to Quincy to get there in time for the service on
         this bicycle! And then Mother would take him home to dinner. He wasn't
         married; he had been married and he would have had a daughter my age,
         so he was very fond of me, and I just adored him. As a child, I still
         remember him. His name was Herbert M. Course. And he was a big, lanky
         man. But everybody just ltWed him. And she'd bring him home to dinner.
         I mean, we would. And then she'd cook dinner; cook chicken dinner for
         him.
         
         SS:  Do you know what happened to his family?
         
         MLL:  Well, his wife died at childbirth. And so, he married later and we
         kept in touch with him and I knew his second family years later. When
         he left Quincy, I was just a child, just quite small,I don't know how
         old I was, nine- no, six or seven years old, I suppose. And so, he
         said, because of my two older sisters, he said, "When you get ready to
         get married I'll come back and marry you." Oh, me, it was me he was
         talking too, because I was his little favorite, so I always talked about
         when I was ten, Mr. Course was going to come back and marry me. Of
         course by the time I was that old, I realized what he meant. He didn't
         mean he was going to marry me, he was going to perform the ceremony
         But he neyer got to do that,
         for all of us. ^But he was quite a talented and interesting man.
         
         SS:  Do you think that religion was particularly important to your mother?
         
         MLL:  Oh, it was their life. It was why they could do these things. Why
         they could take up homesteads. They had to have it;.depended on it.
         They had faith, you see. They knew that it would come out alright,
         and it did. Everything came out alright. Four of her children gradua
         ted from WSC up here. That was her aim in life, to have her children
         educated. The boys didn't graduate, but the girls all did.
         
         SS:  Were the women- this I am a little curious about- were the women more
         involved in the church than the men?
         
         MLL:  Not in our family. My father was- he was very musical - he was an Irishhis
         parents had come from Ireland and he had an Irish tenor voice, and
         he always led the singing in the Sunday School and church and sang in
         the choir, and was a superintendent of the Sunday School. And my mo
         ther was so busy having children that he did more work, I think, that
         way than she did, but she was back of him in all of that,
         
         MARVIN L: Our family— my father, of course, there was a big family of us and
         Mother had to-
         
         MLL:  They had to do the work at home.
         
         MARVIN L: had to do the work at home.
         
         MLL:  But she saw to it that we were always clean and dressed
         
         MAEVIN L: But we always had to go to church.
         
         MLL:  Made over handed down clothes. You know, everything was recycled
         in those days, but we didn't call it that. Nothing was ever wasted.
         
         MARVIN L: Everybody went to church.
         
         MLL:  Yeah. We all went to church. And we never missed. I've got a little
         gold pin that I got for perfect attendance at Sunday School. I've still
         got my little gold pin that I earned.
         
         SS:  Weren't you able to play any games on Sunday?
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, we could play with our dolls, but we couldn't— arid we often
         had company and we could play- go out and play. But it was limited
         somewhat. We had to know it was Sunday. And then sitting around in
         your Sunday clothes, that alane was a bit of a hardship, you know,
         when you wanted to have on your play clothes. And you kept them on
         if you had company, and so that made Sunday kind of a stuffnecked
         affair, too, I think.
         
         SS:  Do you remember what those early sermons were like?
         
         MLL: Oh, I don't suppose I ever heard the sermons.
         
         SS:  Oh, the kids didn't?
         
         MLL:  I'll tell you- well, children, I don't think even yet listen very much
         to sermons- do they? They learn in the Sunday School classes- I can
         remember things we learned in Sunday School classes. I had a lovely
         Sunday School teacher, and I can remember the stories- Bible stories
         if that we learned there. But I don't remember the sermons. 
         there was the singing- I know the songs that we sang. And I can re
         member mostly what the beautiful hats and the clothes that the women
         sitting in front of us wore! You know, and people around- the young
         couple that held hands under the songbook, and that sort of thing.
         We were more interested in the children- more interested in the people
         in the church or the colored window. There was a colored memorial
         window in this church. This preacher I was speaking of had it put in
         in memory of his wife that died. And that church is still there in
         Quincy. The Presbyterians built a big new church, but that little
         church is still there.
         
         SS:  The Presbyterian church there- was it a community church?
         
         MLL:  No, it was a Presbyterian Church, but it seems to me that sometimes
         the Methodists also- that they kind of alternated. It seems to me
         there were years when they alternated, but it was built as a
         Presbyterian Church. And when they first went there there was no
         church. And they held services in a hall, they had a hall called the
         Dickerson Hall. And it was used for all sorts of community affairs.
         I think my sister in that story told about the big sagebrush that was
         used as the first community Christmas tree because they didn't have
         any evergreen trees. And later they shipped them in, but at that time
         they used this great big sagebrush, and it stood up in the corner of
         the hall and they decorated it just like a Christmas tree. At home
         we had to burn sagebrush, but I don't remember that we ever took a
         sagebrush in for— it probably was too dangerous, because they burned
         easily. But we did burn sagebrush. And sometimes up in the drawsdo
         you know what a draw is? We called it a little ravine- was called
         a draw- spring runoff would wash the little-^ they called them draws in
         that country. And the sagebrush that grew in these draws, up in the
         lower part of the hills grew very large. Sometimes as large as six or
         eight inches across the trunk. But around where we lived were
         smaller, but those big ones made good fuel and my dad would take the
         wagon and go up there in the fall and get a load of that for fuel. In
         later years they shipped in slabwood and we burned that, but the early
         days they burned sagebrush, so you see there was no expense, it was
         just labor.
         
         SS:  It would take a lot more work when they could cut up sagebrush to
         burn-
         
         MLL:  Well, you know it's soft, so it isn't hard to cut and they just cut it
         with an axe. This big stuff they probably had to saw, when they found
         those big ones. I don't know, I don't remember that. One time Dad and
         the boys, the two older brothers went with him, and+heytook me, I was
         sort of the tomboy and I liked to go more and there was two girls at
         home to help with the dishes and things, so I never relly did much
         housework then, and I still don't. (Chuckles) But they took me with
         them and it was an allday trip with the wagon up into the hills to get
         it and we took our lunch. And I remember we cooked out. That was my
         first cookout. And Dad took potatoes and onions and built a fire and
         we roasted those. Oh, I can still taste them and were they ever good!
         And I was just a little girl, you know* and I played. And there was
         big grass, Dad called it rye grass that grew around where they were
         cutting the sagebrush, and after the manner of children I built me a
         hut, you know children go through that stage of building all kinds of
         houses at different ages, you know. And I built a hut out of this rye
         grass. And of course, it probably was nothing, but to me it was quite
         elegant- Then they would pile this sagebrush up in the yard by the
         cellar, a safe distance from the house. One time it caught on fire
         from a spark and we lost it and he had to go back and get a second sup
         ply. That was tragic, of course, all that extra work. But you know
         it burns real quick and hot.
         
         MARVIN L: My grandparents, uncles and aunts was pioneers in the Yakima Valley
         sagebrush. Cleared the land they had.
         
         MLL:  The land at Quincy was real sandy and light, and all it needed was
         water.
         
         MARVIN L: — sandy and every house there had to be well plastered.
         
         MLL:  Well, our house wasn't plastered, and when there was a sandstorm co
         ming, Mother would say, "Children, run and close the doors." But
         it was no use the sand would come right in anyway, you couldn't keep
         it out. Those awful dust storms^they had in that country, they still
         have them. Now of course with irrigation it isn't so bad, but south
         of Quincy they still have 'em.
         
         SS:  Well how were the slats tightened up.
         
         MLL:  Oh, well, board and batten- that means boards that are put together
         as close as possible, but there is still a crack and then a board is
         put on the outside over that crack. And that's the kind of construe
         tion it was. That was homestead houses- were built that way. And^some
         times they had- I don't think our house ever had anything but a tar pa
         per roof. It had to be replaced often, of course. I think it always
         had a tar paper roof. That was another fire hazard.
         
         SS:  Would you be warm in the winter?
         
         MLL:  Well, we had a cookstove in this one room a cookstove and a hea
         ting stove. And of course, at night the fires went out, so then it
         was cold. And when you went to bed, it wasn't extremely cold- not like
         North Dakota cold that they'd been used to, but it was cold at night.
         But in the winter we had some snow, usually, always had some. They'd
         take hot stone wrapped in an old flannel cloth to bed with you to heat
         your bed, you know. Or a brick sometimes; we didn't have brick, we
         had stones or flatirons, we'd take to bed. We had some hotw ater botties,
         but not enough to go around. So you'd take one of these- and you
         also took 'em when you went on sleigh rides, too. You'd take those in
         the sleigh to keep your feet warm while you were on the sleigh rides.
         
         SS:  Who got up in the morning to start the fires?
         
         MLL:  Dad. And then later, one of my brothers liked to get up. They'd get
         up and start the fires and put on the oatmeal and start breakfast. We
         always had oatmeal at our house, or Farina. And it came in sacks; -
         everything came in cloth sacks in those days. Sugar and flour and
         cereals were all in cloth sacks. And I started to talk about recycling.
         That wasn't used as a word, but everything was used over. And these
         sacks were different quality. And the flour sack was a firmer material
         and it was made into dishtowels and sometimes dyed and made into quilt
         tops. And everything was saved. You opened them so you didn't tear
         the sack. Then the sugar sacks were a finer cloth, and if it was wa
         shed arq starched a little it was almost like linen, and it was made
         into garments quite often, too. And the underwear and nightgowns were
         made out of sacks of the finer quality, softer sacks. And the small
         ones, the salt sacks were small and they made good handkerchieves 
         they were bleached. That was quite a chore in those days to get that
         printing out. It didn't always come out but if you were skillful with
         it you could get it out and bleached; homemade bleach— water
         and that type of bleach. And then my mother would hem them on the
         sewing machine and make the men's handkerchieves out of the little salt
         sacks.
         
         SS:  Where did she grow up?
         
         MLL:  Well, she came- her folks were New England people, and she was born in
         Wisconsin, and got her education in Wisconsin. She was a normal school
         graduate and had been a teacher. And then her folks moved to North
         Dakota and she was married there. And she taught in North Dakota before
         her marriage, and after that of course, she didn't teach any more. Mar
         ried women didn't teach in those days.
         
         And in these draws- I was going to tell you about the food- we
         raised- they set out an orchard and it produced for quite a long time
         before the drought. The trees died by the time we left, there weren't
         too many left. But we had cherry trees and peach trees and a crabapple
         tree and some other apples. Quite a few cherry trees, and we had some
         currants- currant bushes- and then in these draws where the spring runoff
         would hold the moisture for one thing, and also the topsoil, you see,
         so it was rich soil- my mother planted her early garden. And we had
         radishes and leaf lettuce and those early things in that little garden
         in the draw and then the other crops, corn and peas and squashes and
         those things were raised up in the orchard. But there was no irriga
         tion; there was no water. So if it was a dry summer you didn't always
         get too much from that garden, but usually we had some garden. And
         then we always kept some pigs and a cow, milk cow; made our own butter.
         If there was any excess, there wasn't much at our house, but she could
         sell butter at the store; get a little grocery money. And we had a
         few chickens. And of course, coyotes were plentiful and so chicken
         raising was hazardous. At one stage- or after I had gone to school, my
         grandparents were having their golden wedding and it came after school
         started, so Mother and the small children went to North Dakota the
         golden wedding but those of us in school had to stay home and go to
         school. And I was the first one out in the lower grades, I would get
         out first, so my chore was to go home by myself- I always went home
         alone anyway- and let the chickens out because if you left them out
         all day- Dad was away working- these coyotes would come down and you
         wouldn't have any chickens. So they had to be kept cooped up. 
         
         But in
         those days chickens, you know, had to go out and rummage for food a
         bit, and so they had to be let out, and so when I got home from school
         I had to let out the chickens and then I could play til the other chil
         dren got home. And one night when I got home, and I fixed a teetertotter
         in front of the cellar, we had some apples in the cellar and I
         would go down and get me an apple to eat and then I was alone, but by
         using a big chunk of wood on one end of the teeter-totter I could teetertotter
         pretty good, you know, get it to balance,and have fun and with
         this apple and I let the chickens out. And I had one old pet rooster,
         and here he came and got up on the teeter-totter with me and he wanted
         some apple, and I'd hold it behind me and then he'd go behind me to
         eat the apple and then I put it in front and there he'd be on the tee
         ter-totter and looked around the next time to see where he was and here
         was a big coyote, just real close, oh, I was a bit scared, but I knew
         that coyotes were cowards, my folks had taught us that, to really not
         be too afraid of them. But that coyote wanted that rooster awful bad
         and I got up and I yelled and he skedaddled and I was safe, but I was
         a little scared after that to go home and let out the chickens because
         those coyotes were lurking all around, and there were lots of them in
         that country.
         
         SS:  Did they have those coyote chases?
         
         MLL: Well, those were rabbit- well, they did coyotes- they used to shoot
         all the coyotes they could, they were so plentiful in Quincy Valley.
         But the jackrabbits were so plentiful and the coyotes fed on the jackrabbits,
         you see, and then when they killed off the coyotes why then
         the jackrabbits practically took the country. And they were very hard
         on crops. And we'd stack up the hay- in those days we used he aderboxes
         you know, there were no combines yet- they used a threshing machineand
         they were itinerate. They'd come around and thresh for you and go
         on to the next farm, so you stacked up your \rfheat and then in the win
         ter you would have a strawstack or a haystack- you'd have some hay to
         feed the livestock and these jackrabbits would come down and live off
         your haystack, and you just couldn't afford that. My father never owned
         a gun; he trapped, he trapped the rabbits to try to keep 'em down, but
         they got a lot of our grain, you know because there were sd many. And
         then in later years- I don't remember the rabbit drives, but they had
         those rabbit drives that are historically interesting, where they would
         corral
         build kind of a tight fence and run the rabbits in and then knock 'em
         down with clubs. It was very cruel, but at the same time they had to
         get rid of 'em, I guess. And now that country is all irrigated and
         doesn't have that problem.
         
         MARVIN L: After they got the sagebrush cleaned off they had to clean off the
         
         MLL:  In this gardening that we did- one time you know it was- my
         mother always had fun on holidays. We all had fun, no matter what the
         holiday. We never spent any money but we had fun. May Day was one of
         the big days and we made May baskets and took our teachers May baskets.
         So my mother helped make this May basket for me to take to my teacher
         when I was in just the first or second grade, I don't know just which
         grade it was, but I was just small. She took a shoe box, we never threw
         away boxes of any kind, they were used for many things. She took a
         shoe box and she put some of these long white radishes that she'd rai
         sed, a bunch of those all scrubbed nice and clean and some red radishesthe
         white ones were called white icicle radishes and they were real
         crisp and delicious, and a bunch of leaf lettuce and a little dish of
         homemade cottage cheese in this shoe box with tissue paper to hold it
         firm and wrapped it up and put a big bunch of crabapple blossoms on it.
         The children would bring May baskets tht had candy in and I didn't like
         this idea at all, but I never disobeyed my mother. So, I took it to my
         teacher and it looked real pretty on the outside.it was wrapped with
         white tissue paper, that came out of a shoe box, too, and with this
         bunch of crabapple blossoms on top. She opened it and everybody was
         standing around looking and here inside was this stuff; this food and
         oh- well, in those days, there was no fresh stuff shipped into little
         towns, and if you didn't raise it, you didn't have any, so my wise
         mother knew that that would be the biggest treat that the teacher could
         have, would be some fresh vegetables like that. And so I was the pet
         that day, and it turned out alright, but I didn't like the idea when
         I took it.
         
         SS:  What was the May Day celebration? That's one I haven't heard much about.
         
         MLL:  Well, May Day- at school we decorated the room for occasion. The
         children made decorations for every holiday. I think they still do in
         school, but it was big in those little schools. And so for May Day,
         if we had flowers we'd pick wild flowers and bring them and decorate
         the school room, and we kind of had special programs. I don't remem
         ber anything special. I don't remember winding the Maypole at that
         early age, I did later at Pullman. We used to have it out on the c ampus.
         The school children would wind the Maypole and I remember being
         in that one time when I was older. But I don't remember it at Quincy.
         
         SS:  Was Halloween celebrated?
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, and it was in a bad way, you know. The boys went out and did
         all these tricks that you read about. And put wagons up on buildings
         and all those kind of things. But we lived so far from town that no
         thing bad ever happened at our house, and we didn't go trick and trea
         ting. I never did that as a child. We had neighbors but we just
         didn't- there wasn't any way to go easily, you see, because we just
         had horses.
         
         SS:  Was thetfr the same business about goblins and witches and all?
         
         MLL:  Yes, yes, but it was fun. It was great fun. Stories, just stories at
         our house because we were by ourselves. We didn't have Hallowe'en
         parties with anybody. Valentine's was a big day at our house, and it
         was all homemade. And one thing we used to make valentines was sample
         wallpaper, you could get them free from the mail order houses, and they
         had these beautiful samples. Sometimes they were about a foot by six
         inches, the sixe of the sheets, so it was big enough to make a nice
         valentine. And then another thing we used for valentines was the pink
         paper that came in the rubbers. When you bought rubbers, they came in
         a box and they were wrapped in pink tissue paper instead of white and
         this was a great treasure but always smelled of the rubbers. That's
         the only thing we didn't like about it, it had an odor. But because
         it was pink we thought it was pretty and if you would take that and
         fold it- a piece of tissue paper, you can still do this, and fold it,
         and then cut it with the scissors, not too fine, not clear through to
         the fold but kind of fine and then you pull that across the sc issors,
         you can curl it, and then that would go around'- we'd cut heart shapes
         and then we would paste that around the valentines and it made a ve ry
         beautiful valentine. My mother used to make us valentines, too, as
         well as we made them for each other and we made them for the children
         in school. And the one I treasured the most was one of these with this
         pink tissue paper, it was a cardboard and she had saved a beautiful
         picture of a girl- my mother's got curls and there wasn't a curl in
         our family that's got curly hair but she loved curly hair. And on this
         valentine was a picture of a blond girl with beautiful curls and then
         all this curled pink paper around it and on the back- my mother had
         beautiful hand writing- they used to teach penmanship- great em
         phasis on penmanship- and her handwriting was beautiful. And on the
         back she had written my name which was Martha Minibel Lowery in her
         beautiful handwriting and then this little verse: "Be good, sweet girl,
         but let who will be clever." I didn't know what that meant, but I
         knew it was something very lovely, and I treasured that valentine for
         years. In fact, we kept our valentines. We each had a brown manila
         envelope that something had come in that she had saved, and w e saved
         these valentines, and we played with them for two weeks after Valentine's
         Day, and then they were put away and the next year we got them out and
         everybody had their own, and the old ones were just as much fun as the
         new ones. You see, that's the way she knew how to have fun, to make
         use of what we did have. Everything was used. Everything was used—
         tins cans- why, when I look at the garbage- there was no garbage. The
         food garbage was fed to the pigs, even the dishwater. All';water was
         very precious at Quincy. And the dishwater was put in a special bucket
         and that was called pig slop. Not a very elegant term, but that's
         what it was called, and it was fed to the pigs because there was a lot
         of nourishment in that dishwater, you know. And then the wash water
         and the bath water was put out to water the yellow rose, and the matrifrom
         mony vine. The only way they could be kept alive was^this water. And
         our water all had to be hauled. In very early days it was hauled in
         barrels. In the very early days when they first went there, it was
         hauled even on a stoneboat from a place called Willow Springs, which
         was about five miles away. just think of that chore with no roads
         and a stoneboat. You know what a stoneboat is? There were no wheels
         on it, just a platform and barrels of water. But later on they hauled
         it in barrels in a wagon and then later tanks. We had a tank and our
         was filled with a tank. But water was very precious. And all
         this paper doll work and valentines took paste, and we made our paste
         with flour- a little flour and""we would take a spoon, cause you couldn't
         waste water- I'm not sure I should tell this part, it's not very ele
         gant- because water was so precious, and there was a bucket of water
         with a dipper in the kitchen and in trying to get some water into that
         paste, you would waste water, so ire couldn't do it very often, but we
         liked to have lots of paste and sometimes we would spit in it! (Chuckles)
         That's not very elegant, but that we actually did as children to get
         paste. But you would mix a little water with this flour and then you
         would have paste to make paper dolls or your valentines or scrapbooks.
         We made lots of scrapbooks, too, that way.
         
         SS:  I want to ask you another question. How would kids take their baths?
         Did they use the same water?
         
         MLL:  Oh, that- oh, well, if they were small, but not older people,
         never did. Not even . the water was very scarce and very precious.
         And it was heated in two ways; it was heated in the wash boiler on the
         stove for the Saturday night baths; they were the most popular, you
         sometimes had other baths, but always Saturday night baths. And you
         let down the oven door- there was no bathroom, no privacy- you let
         down the oven door for heat, and the children were bathed earlier, and
         the water was heated in the reservoir. That was a part of the early
         cookstoves at the back. And the small children were bathed together
         in the same water, but the older ones weren't. And then that water
         was thrown out on the rose bush and the garden, maybe, sometimes. And
         the chairs that we had were rather high backed, and if it was necessary
         to have a little privacy those chairs with a blanket were arranged around
         this washtub; it was the washtub that the baths were taken in.
         We were clean.
         
         SS:  But it was somewhat of a sponge bath?
         
         MLL:  No! No, it was a washtub, it was a washtub that any grown person could
         sit down in and curl up in. No, no. They weren't sponge baths. There
         were sponge baths, alright, taken in a basin.
         (This is one I used to tell-
         
         MARVIN L:(We lived on a fruit ranch one time, we had seventy acres and went broke.
         And we got so hard up 
         
         MLL:  That wasn't true though. You just nagged your father telling that story.
         We never went hungry on our farm. We didn't have lots of things, but
         we never went hungry.
         
         MLL:  We had another Christmas custom that's kind of- that I don't think very
         many families would have thought of this- it was my mother's invention.
         They'd find the biggest gunny sack, you know burlap sack, the biggest
         gunny sack, clean gunny sack, and eventually Dad built a stairway in
         this homestead house, and there was a loft- we never used it for any
         thing but storage. It was very useful as a place to put things, you
         know, and so at Christmastime- about two months before Christmas, this
         great big gunny sack was hung about half way up this stairway, up where
         it was out of the way, but it was in sight, and then we made presents
         for each other and as they were made they were put into this sack, and
         that's the only time you were allowed to go up there near that sack
         was when you had something to put in. But you could delay a little
         and sit on the step and kind of listen and maybe feel a little if no
         one was watching, because the Christmas presents were accumulating in
         that sack and it was very tempting- we never dared reach in and feel
         anything, but we could feel through the sack a little bit. We made
         all kinds of things for each other. And one of the things I remember
         making for my father; he shaved with a straight edge razor^stropped
         you know, and there was no running water, so the soap, the shaving
         soap and.whiskers as he would shave it off his face would have to be
         put some place and he would use paper. So we would make him a shaving
         pad. We would take an old catalogue- we always had mailorder catalogues,
         and we would take the soft pages and cut them about six inches
         square, he liked that size, and we would make a pad of those papers.
         And then we would punch, with a darning needle, we would punch a couple
         of holes in the top and make a pretty cover, maybe a piece of this
         one of these wallpaper books, or maybe we would draw a picture fo the
         cover and then tie that with a piece of yarn and make him a shaving
         pad and that was the kind 6Tpresents- homemade presents. We would make
         Mother a needle book. And the needle book was made with pieces of soft
         cloth that was blanket stitched around. And that's one of the first
         stitches that you learned as a little girl and with bright thread
         and then you would put several of these pieces of cloth together with
         a cover and she would keep her needles in. Or you would make a pin
         cushion, and stuff it with something soft. And those were the kind of
         presents we made for grownups, and then the presents for the children
         were toys. 
         
         And then of course, Santy Claus came too, that was separate,
         the Christmas sack was our presents to each other. That wasn't Santy
         Claus. But Santy Claus came Christmas Eve and we would hang up our
         stockings and what was in the stockings, Santy Claus brought. And about
         two weeks before Christmas we would send our dolls to Santy Claus
         because Santy Claus knew how to make beautiful doll clothes. And we
         didn't get new dolls, we'd get new hair or new head or new eyes, de
         pending on what the doll might need, but we couldn't have a new doll
         at Christmas. I only had one or two new dolls in my whole life, but
         I loved my old dolls. They would be renovated you see;by Santy Claus.
         And my poor mother, I didn't know it then, but she would sit up after
         weM gone to bed and fashion these beautiful doll clothes. Christmas
         morning we would get up- we could get up any time we'd wake up and
         there would be- the stocking would be full, and then here would be this
         newly dressed doll sticking out of the top. And that was the early
         day Christmas, but nothing was spent. An orange- every year we got an
         orange, that's the only orange I ever had was in the toe of my stocking.
         But they would buy an orange for each child and we'd get some hard can
         dy in a tarleton sack at the church program and sometimes they'd buy
         some candy for Christmas, but most of the candy was homemade. We would
         decorate the house lavishly with paper chains made out of the wallpaper
         any
         books andAcolored paper you could find. Paper chains, that took more
         paste. (Chuckles) The chains were fun to make and we'd string popcorn
         and the house was decorated all those hanging from the ceilings, great
         loops of all this. And we'd sing all the Christmas carols. We were
         a great singing family. My father - his father had come from Ireland
         and had been a singing school master- and Dad had done this, too; and
         he taught us all singing when we were very young. We would sit around
         this big table- this white oilcloth covered table before we had the or
         gan- later we got an organ, but he had a tuning fork and he would strike
         the tuning fork and he would get the tone and everybody around the tab
         le would get the tone and then we would sing. And he taught me to
         sing alto, because I had a natural low voice. I was a big girl. And
         he was an Irish tenor, and he liked an alto sitting next to him, so
         he taught me to sing alto. I didn't know it was alto at that time. He
         taught me how to sing the second part. And when I went to school we
         sang. We sang, you know, America and all those songs that you sing in
         school. And I was singing also, it was the only thing I knew how to
         sing. The teacher stopped, she says, "Martha, what are you doing?
         Why are you singing like that?" And I said, "That's the way I sing,
         because I sit next to Papa and Papa taught me to sing like that." She
         knew Papa, so she said, "Okay, you can sing like that." But she didn't
         understand why a child my age was singing alto. But anyway that's what
         I did.
         
         SS:  What was the kind of music that you sang at home? Was a lot of it re
         ligious pieces?
         
         MLL:  Well, gospel songs were popular, but all the old songs, old religious
         songs we knew. And then we always sang lots of fun songs, rounds, like
         oh, you know- what are some of the old rounds, I can't think of them.
         "Row Your Boat."
         
         MLL:  "Row, row, row your boat." Yes, and in a big family that was great fun
         because there were a lot of us. And we sang songs like The Bullfrog on
         the Bank 
         and the bullfrog in the pool." And Father could sing that real good
         where the high voices sing, "The bullfrog on the bank," and then the
         low voices sing, "The bullfrog in the pool!" you know- down low. And
         that was one of our fun songs. And then we sang- oh, there was one
         about, oh, my sister and I were talking about it this summer- McGint ywhat
         was the old song about Mc Ginty? I can't think of that. Yankee
         Doodle , was popular because my folks were New Englanders. They knew
         a lot of the New England songs. We knew all the old songs like "Home
         Sweet Home." And Coming Through the Rye, and Annie Laurie , and we
         had big song books that we sang from. And then later, when I was still
         a child, the folks in North Dakota sent us an organ. That was a big
         day and we all had to learn to play the organ. My mother could play
         and so she taught the girls. I never learned very much.. But we had
         lots of music. The four older ones became a quartet, and they sang as
         a quartet in church. The four older members of the family, when I was
         a child.
         
         SS:  Christmas, it sounds like, was really mostly family rather than a com
         munity celebration.
         
         MLL:  Well, it was both. It was both. There was a big celebration at the
         church where we spoke pieces, and had special dresses, you know, we
         had to dress up and had big pfcugrams at the church. And they had a
         big Christmas tree, and they gave out sacks of candy and an orange some
         times in the sacks and they were made out of colored tarleton- that's
         a stiff material that's kind of like cheesecloth, but it was cheap and
         stiff and it was pretty. And the women would get together and make
         these bags and fill them with hard candy and nuts. And everybody that
         came to the church program got one of those Christmas Eve. It was done
         on Christmas Eve. And some of the families took their gifts there. If
         they were going to give their children expensive dolls and nice things
         they liked to show them off, and of course, that was hard on my mother
         because we didn't have those kind and she would explain to us- this is
         how wise she was- that Santy Claus didn't bring our gifts to the church
         he brought them to our house and we were satisfied, we were never jea
         lous. It was fun to see those beautiful dolls and trains and things
         that were dis played there- they'd bring 'em and put 'em under the tree
         and then Santy Claus came and passed out the candy and gave these gifts
         to the children that had their names on them, but the poor little Lowery
         children never got any there. But we didn't care because we knew ours
         were at home. It was alright, but it was a bad custom, really, for
         poor families. Some poor families didn't have it explained that way
         to them. We had lots of reading at home; my mother liked to read and
         she read all the classics, you know, a lot of the good books to us.
         She liked Shakespeare, but she didn't read that to us as children.
         She read us poems and all the Mother Goose and the fairy stories, the
         Aesop Fables, and we knew all of those. And books were real important.
         Books were treasured. She wanted us to learn about money, but it was
         real hard because there wasn't much, and so one year she assigned us
         jobs, and we would be paid. My job was to hoe the weeds between two
         rows of trees in the orchard and I was to get a dollar if I kept the
         weeds out all summer. I wasn't a very good hoer but I was learning
         that if you worked hard that you would be rewarded, you knowjK And I
         got my dollar; it was a silver dollar. Then was the question what to
         do with it. And of course, she guided me there and made me want to
         buy books with it. I don't know, if she had let me alone I probably
         would have bought candy or something else, as children do, but I was
         influenced to pick out some books, because I thought books were great.
         And I bought two books with that dollar and I still have one of them.
         I bought Beautiful Joe, and the Hoosier Schoolboy. I didn't care
         much about the Hoosier Schoolboy. I bought it, but I liked Beautiful
         Joe. And we all cried. We used to all cry when we read these sad
         stories about Black Beauty and Beautiful Joe, and these mistreated animals;
         they made you cry. And Mother cried, and so I cried. Later I
         rebound that little book, but that was bought with my first dollar.
         
         SS:  Beautiful Joe is
         
         MLL:  Is a dog that was mistreated, you know, and it was a sad story. And
         children liked those sad stories. We all cried! (Chuckles) We cried
         a lot when Mother read to us because she cried over poems, all the
         sad poems, you know! But that's still a good educational way of get
         ting children interested in books, isn't it? I mean, children need
         to be interested in books and you have to start young.
         
         SS:  Seems like crying was a lot more common in those days, wasn't it?
         
         MLL:  Well, my mother was very emotional. Some people were and some weren't.
         But, I think maybe they did cry a lot. Not always sad, it was happy
         crying, too.
         
         SS:  Nowdays they take it so much more as weakness, you know, to cry.
         
         MLL:  Yes, um-huh, I guess so.
         
         SS:  Although it's always been that way for men.
         
         MLL:  Eye specialists say it's good for your eyes. Yeah, tears are good for
         your eyes; necessary.
         Let's see, what else did we recycle? I think I told you most every
         thing I thought of. Oh, the tin cans! We used every tin can and every
         bottle, except poisons. And they were thrown, you know where! They
         were thrown out in the outhouse! They couldn't be washed up, like car
         bolic acid. But all the other containers were reused in various ways
         for things. And some of the bottles were used to give the horses their
         medicine, you know. And some of the bottles were used to store things
         in, that you had. And Mother made eyewater, and it was put in a bot-
         tie. A lot of the medicines were homemade and they had to have a bot
         tle. And cans- baking powder cans had a tight lid. And the cover of
         the baking powder can was Mother's cookie cutter and biscuit cutter.
         That's all she ever had, was a lid. And the cans were used to store
         things in because there were no tight cupboards or places to store
         things; you had to have tight containers for everything.
         
         MARVIN L: Mice.
         
         MLL:  Yes, you had varmints of different kids; insects and mice and rats.
         And then the only can I can think of that couldn't be used that way
         was the milk can. And condensed milk was used by- when the cow went
         dry you had to have some condensed milk, you know. And sometimes it
         was used for baby formulas- there weren't any actual baby formulasbut
         if mother wasn't able to nurse the baby; then condensed milk-
         I don't mean canned milk like we have, although that was available,
         too, but condensed milk, which was sweeter was used and babies got real
         on it. It wasn't good but that's what they used. And they used it
         just straight, I mean, they just used it the way it was, they didn't
         mix it with other foods. And so there was the milk cans that we had
         then, and they were even recycled. And if you jammed 'em just right
         you could make 'em stick to your he^L and they were great fun to run
         around on, sort of like a little stilt. And we played games. And then
         they were used as a game like hockey with a stick, and you bat the can.
         You know, hit the can. Isn't that what it was called?
         
         MARVIN L: Shinny-on-your-own-side.
         
         MLL:  Yeah, shinny-on-your-own-side; now, that's it. I don't think we ever
         called it that, but we used to play that. And that's remarkable, you
         know, that people try to go to these old homesteads and dig up the dumps,
         Well, there weren't any. They didn't throw anything away except broken
         things. Broken glass and broken bottles and broken dishes were thrown
         away but no anything else.
         
         SS:  If there was sickness in the family, how ould you deal with it?
         
         MLL:  There were just a few home remedies that were drastic. There was al
         ways castor oil. And you didn't try to show you had a little stomach
         ache, because if you got it, you got a dose of castor oil! And it was
         drastic! And that was one of the common ones and everybody used it.
         And then for cuts and small inuries of that kind, there was turpentine,
         which was used in our family a great deal. That would heal up anything.
         Nowdays it won't, but it did then! And we had a few boughten things,
         we had Listerine when I was quite young. I remember Listerine, which
         was considered an antiseptic or a sort. And then there was carbolic
         acid for real severe injuries. We were a real lucky family, we never
         had any real serious illnesses. And then if you got a cold- colds were
         common- it wasn't called flu. Colds were Common and my mother had a
         drastic treatment for that. It was kind of like an Indian sweat bath
         in a way. She would take the big rocking chair and put a big quilt in
         it and then the blankets- the wash blankets- and put you in your night
         gown in that chair and take a five gallon oil can- we always had those they
         were salvage too, the ones that the kerosene came in. The top
         was cut out carefully so that it made a container. And you put your
         feet in that with hot water and mustard, and you soaked your feet in
         that, and you sat is this chair all wrapped up in this blanket and
         drank hot lemonades and then you would sweat. And that took everything
         out of you that you didn't have as well as what you did have! You never
         had a cold afterwards. And then as soon as you thought you'd been there
         long enough, and you'd sweat enough, why she would get the washtub out
         and have the room good and hot and give you a bath and put you in bed
         till you cooled off, because you know it's dangerous to get chilled.
         That was a standard remedy. And oh, a mustard plaster on your chest
         and one on your back. And they were hot and they blistered you. And
         they were homemade. Made out of the same mustard that you  jk 
         on your ham. And you made that by mixing it up and sometimes you put
         a little flour in that and that reduced the heat so it wasn't quite so
         bad. But she'd take a piece of an old sheet and stir up this mustard
         and water and lather it out on the sheet; fold it up and put that on
         you, put a flannel over it and that would sure cure a cold! (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  Did it work good?
         
         MLL:  We never had any, we were always healthy, so I guess it worked. We
         never died, either. That was a miracle. She was real careful of us.
         We never had anything but children's diseases. We got that kind of
         treatment quite often if she thought we had the sniffles.
         
         MARVIN L: We had to wear flannels.
         
         MLL:  We had to wear our rubbers, and it never rained there, but we had to
         have rubbers. You know what we used to do with them? I think my sisunder
         ter told that in that story. We used to hide 'em the sagebrush.
         And, oh, that was awful, guilt was worse than being punished, you know.
         And I was so scared she'd find out. I'd hide mine under the last fence
         before Ild go to school, I'd hide my rubbers. There wag ' t any rain,
         there was no need of wearing 'em, but you had to wear 'em! And the
         kids'd make fun of you if you wore your rubbers to school in dry weather
         you know. And then I'd worry all day for fear somebody'd steal 'em
         and they wouldn't be there for me to wear home again. (Chuckles) She
         was a stern mother, but she was a wonderful mother. She taught us the
         things that were good. Honesty and good language. She couldn't stand
         slang. There was no swearing in our family. But slang, even- one time
         I learned the word, 'dickens1 from one of my little girlfriends, and
         we were out hanging up clothes and I was holding the clothespin bag
         for her and I dropped a clothespin and I said, "The dickens!" Boy,
         she grabbed me just like that and in the house I went and had my mouth
         washed out with a bar of soap! And I never said that, and I felt guilty
         I was grown before I ever said that again. It wasn't swearing exactly,
         you know, but it was slang, and she wouldn't put up with it.
         
         MARVIN L: No wonder she's such an angel!
         
         MLL:  Yeah. Well, afterwards when I grew up it was fun to sa y that because
         I had been punished and I realized it wasn't really bad, it was just
         she was a real strict- you know, she liked the English language
         the way it ought to be said, and she taught us that.
         
         SS:  It seems to me that you kids did not do things that you knew were wrong
         that you would go ahead and do those things like the rubbers anyway?
         
         MLL:  Well, that we did. But I suffered from it because I was guilty -I
         felt guilty all day. I all day. So it wasn't good for us.
         We didn't defy her very often. It was easier to be guilty than to
         face the kids at school, because you know kids are rough on each other.
         Tell that story about the kids at school that spoke different languages.
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, we had- well, my folks were English, I guess you would say
         and Dad had come from Michigan- he was Irish but they spoke what they
         called English. And then there was one family of Bohemians and then
         there were a lot of these German families had moved into the Quincythat
         farmed, and they spoke German. Parents often couldn't speak Eng
         lish, and the children didn't learn English til they went to school,
         so that there was a lot of German spoken on the playground, you know.
         They had to speak English in school, they had to learn, but they would
         speak German. And then this one family that were Bohemian, they spoke
         Bohemian, I guess it would be, and then they would say, "What do you
         speak?" Well, I didn't speak anything, and I went home and I said to
         my mother, "What's wrong with us? These other children speak German
         and they speak Bohemian and we don't know anything? What are we?"
         My mother said- she was quite incensed to think that I'd bean attacked
         like that- andshe said, "Yes, you are, you're Irish." My grandparents
         had come from Ireland, my father's parents. She said, "You're Irish."
         She was proud of the Irish blood in our family.A Well, you know child
         ren- they want to be all alike. If one can do something, then why can't
         you do it? So, I said, "But I can't speak Irish." She said, "Well,
         noK tomorrow." And she went over to the corner of the kitchen where
         she cooked and got into the potato sack and took out a little potato,
         scrubbed it up and she said, "Now tomorrow you put this in your pocket
         and when you go to school, when they say that to you," Cause they would
         again, she saiid,"you say, I'm Irish." And they'll say, "Alright, talk
         some." And then you say, "I'm Irish, and if you don't believe it, I
         can show it to you, I have it in me pocket." And then you pull out th is
         Irish potato. And sure enough they asked me the next day and I showed
         them the potato and that quit the nagging, they didn't bother me any
         more. (Laughter) So, we're proud of being Irish. My dad could sing
         songs and things to us. He played the flute and he played the Jew's
         harp. And he could stand on his head and he entertained us that way.
         He was a real performer.
         
         SS:  He could stand on his head?
         
         MLL:  Yes, Dad could stand on his head, that was one of his accomplishments
         until he was quite old. He lived to be in his eighties.I don't remem
         ber when he quit doing it. But it scared Mother to death. None of us
         could do it, but he always could stand on his head, you know, he'd go
         down and p«-!^ o»yV* his hands and bring up his feet and stand straight up
         on his head. We thought that was great. Quite an accomplishment. He
         wasn't a heavy man. He was a tall man, but he was slim.
         
         MARVIN L: Danced to—
         
         MLL:  Danced the jig, but dancing wasn't allowed you know in our church or
         anything. My mother didn't believe in dancing, but she'd let Dad dance
         the jig, but he never got to teach it to us, I wish he had, but he
         didn't, because she didn't believe in dancing. But I guess maybe he
         did. He could sure dance the Irish jig.
         
         SS:  You said a little while ago that it was either one way or the other
         with families as far as religion goes; either they were strict or they
         just weren't strict at all.
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes. Well, these little towns all had saloons, you know. And there
         were people that didn't go to church that just lived a different life
         then we did. There was the other side of the street- there was a saloon.
         It wasn't discussed much in our family. My mother was such a temperance
         person. But coming home from school, there were boardwalks in this
         little town and this walk came up past the hotel, and there was a sa
         loon - apparently a saloon in that town in that hotel; I didn't know
         it at the time, but that's what it was, but this odor, I would notice
         odor, and later then I found out that was the odor of whiskey,
         but at the time I didn't know that's what it was, as I would come up
         the street I could smell this. I always wondered what it was but I
         never knew as a child that that's what it was. And then there were
         lots of bottles. In fact, my sister told about my mother's rollinpin
         being a beer bottle- round beer bottle. There were lots of liquor bot
         tles around. And sometimes they would use them for things, but there
         was never any liquor in the house. And no smoking, either. And no
         dancing. No card playing.
         
         MARVIN L: There was no liquor in our house, but the older brothers, they all
         drank.
         
         MLL:  Well, my brothers did too when they got older. It didnlt necessarily
         mean that they grew up that way, but that's the way they were brought
         up. That's the way it was. It wasn't necessarily a good way, but that's
         the way it was.
         
         SS:  But there were probably some people that would also qc 4c church ^u'
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, yes, that's right. Sure. Dickerson Hall that I mentioned
         was where they had dances, but I didn't know much about them, because
         we didn't go. Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  Was she at all active as a teetotler? Was there any opportunity
         
         MLL:  I don't think so, I don't think so at that time. No. No, women's or
         ganization or anything, it was just the way she— her folks had been
         that way. That is the way she'd been brought up. Lots of families
         were like that. Tell him about the cards on the train.
         
         MLL:  Yes, the playing cards. I'd never seen playing cards. We had Flinch
         and we played Muggins with the flinch cards. We played card games, we
         played old maid, and authors was great. But not playing cards, because
         playing cards were associated with the devil in the religious training
         in those early days. And gambling- you know, you couldn't play cards
         and not become a gambler, that was the supposition. So I'd never seen
         playing cards, I'd just seen these flinch cards which were- oh, they
         weren't bright colored, they were gray-green and white or brown-white
         or maybe sometimes of rosy and white. They were pretty designs
         on the cards that we had. And of course, old maid cards had pictures
         on them. Authors cards had pictures. When I was four years old my
         mother was to go back to North Dakota to see her folks and I went with
         her because a child that age could travel without any fare. The other
         children were in school and I was the youngest, so I went with my mother.
         And on the train in those days they had a table- they would bring you
         a table that was put up between the seats. The seats would- plush
         seats that faced each other, and there was a table between and you could
         eat your lunch; you carried your lunch in a shoe box and you could eat
         your lunch on that taM e or you could play games or whatever you wished.
         And so the people in the seat behind us were playing cards, and I stood
         up in the seat and looked over, and the whole thing was very exciting
         to me. I don't remember much when I was four, but I remembered this be
         cause it was all different you know, see, the train and the plush seats,
         red plush seats, and standing up and then we were going to see Grandpa
         and Grandma, besides, which was great excitement. And I stood up and
         these people were playing with these beautiful cards and I was so ex
         cited. And I said, "Mother, look, come and look." And she looked and
         she yanked me down, and boy, "No, you mustn't ever look at those, you
         must never play with those." She said. And I didn't know why and I
         didn't understand why. I just knew they were beautiful and those people
         were having fun, and it's too bad it couldn't have been explained bet
         ter. I didn't learn to play cards til I was through college and out in
         the world. My mother was gone by then, and she probably would have
         changed by then too, and I became a good card player.
         
         SS:  You pbObably danced, too.
         
         MLL:  Yes, I learned to dance in college. But I had to take lessons though
         because I was I was so old by that time that everybody else knew how.
         They learned, you know, along the way, like people are supposed to learn
         things, but I hadn't so I had to go to Saturday afternoon,- on the cam
         pus, they had a class because there were lots of college kids brought
         up just like I'd been that didn't know how to dance. And we learned to
         dance.
         
         SS:  What was the idea of socializing- the form of socializing if you were
         stricted with these cards and dancing and that sort of thing?
         
         MLL:  Oh, you played games. You had lots of games, all kinds of indoor games.
         
         SS:  For adults?
         
         SS:  Oh, yes. You had socials, you know. And then you had games like 
         checkers and those things that you played in between tw o or three or
         four people. Dominoes were great favorites. Families would go visiting
         and play games at each other's houses. Or you would have a social. I
         don't remember going to many of those in the town. The traveling was a
         little too difficult, but town families get together and have em.
         We played games like- oh, you could play games that were almost dancing
         like Farmer-in-the-Dell, and Skip-to-my-Lou. We played those even in
         my college days at church socials. At Pullman we played those games.
         And we played Spin-the-Platter ahd Winkum, and Post Office. My mother
         didn't approve of Post Office, but we did play it. That was a kissing
         game. But Winkum was okay. She'd let us play Winkum, but not Post Of
         fice. That was off the list!(Chuckles)
         
         MARVIN L: You played anyway though.
         
         MLL:  No.
         
         SS:  Those party songs, were they part of the-?
         
         ML1: Anything- Skip-to-my-Lou you had a partner, it was really dancing like
         folk dancing. You had a partner, you held ha nds and you
         skipped around the room. It was sort of folk dancing, those were al
         lowed but not social dancing.
         
         SS:  What was really the difference? Just that there wasn't any instruments?
         
         MLL:  Well, it was mostly that dancing and card playing went along with sa
         loons and the rough life that they were trying to protect us from.
         That was the reason. It wasn't the thing itself, there wasn't anything
         wrong with it. But it led to it; where it was done. There was drinking
         at public dances. And so, you would be led into this temptation, you
         see, and that's why it was prohibited, and we didn't do it.
         
         SS:  Like in Skip-to-my-Lou, would there be any musical accompaniment?
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, somebody played the piano. We played a lot of musical games.
         Famer-in-the-Dell. That was fun, because you chose you the farmer
         chose his wife, see. If you got to be his wife, that was a big night.
         You know, if it was your favorite boy. Those are kid games, but adults
         played 'em too. The whole family would play together, all kinds of
         games.
         
         MARVIN L: Did you ever play Skip-to-my-Lou?
         
         MLL:  And then Spin the Platter. You had a circle and then somebody was "It"
         and you spun the platter, and if you could grab it before it stopped,
         then you were "IT". Had a lot of games that were fun.
         
         MARVIN L: They still are.
         
         SS:  As far as socializing with other families; would it be mostly be your
         family visiting another families' house? And they visited you?
         
         MLL:  Yes, we did that a lot, and that was mostly in the daytime, because of
         travel, I think. And a lot of going to Sunday dinner. They were too
         busy during the week to do much. On holidays we'd get together. And
         Fourth of July was always celebrated with a big celebration and several
         families would get together.
         
         MARVIN L: Go to church and then you went home with somebody
         
         MLL:  Yes, and one home that we used to go home to dinner was 
         and they had more money than we did, and she had Vic torian furniture,
         that she kept stored and covered in one bedroom because of the dust
         and she didn't use it as she would have. And that was a papered house
         and it had big pink roses on the wallpaper and oh, I thought that was
         just the end. That beautiful pink roses patterned wallpaper! We
         didn't have any wallpaper on our walls. I thought to have a house like
         that they must be wealthy, just very wealthy. And she had an ostrich
         and she would give us feathers from the ostrich. They were great trea
         sures. And one time for Easter, she took an ostrich- not an ostrich-
         I'm sorry, I meant a peacock- she would give us the peacock feathers,
         they were so beautiful. And a peacock egg is quite large- not as
         large as an ostrich- well, she didn t have an ostrich- she had peacock .
         And one Easter she had-boiled a peacock egg and colored it and gave it
         to me for a present and I kept it. My mother let me keep it. I kept it
         upstairs in the loft. Of course, I suppose it finally dried up instead
         of- it rotted probably. It was one of my treasures I
         kept for a long time. To me it was huge but I don't think a peacock egg
         is actually so much bigger than a duck egg. Is it?
         
         Lee: I don't know, probably twice as big as a chicken egg.
         
         MLL:  It was a big egg compared to the chicken eggs that we colored for Easster.
         Well, you get an idea how we lived anyway, haven't you?
         Oh, there was another little fun thing that we got out of— anything
         you got free, you know, was made-fun. We used baking soda, lots of
         baking soda in cooking and then in it was also a home remedy for upset
         stomachs and bee stings and all kinds of things. It still is a good
         remedy. But in the baking soda package there was a little card- lit
         tle birds. And it was a little premium or a little gift with the pac
         kage. And then we collected those. And when we bought a new package
         of baking soda, which cost a nickel, this little card was attached to
         it, and it was someone's turn to have it that time. You know, you
         couldn't always get the card yourself, but you would save those and
         then you would have a collection of beautiful pictures of birds. And
         now, they would be an antique collection if anyone has any of those.
         You keep your eye out, because you might find them.
         
         MARVIN L: Baking soda was never less than a dime. Martha, baking soda was never
         less than a dime.
         
         MLL:  A dime? I thought it was a nickel. You sure? Well, you're the mer
         chant, so you'd know. But anyway, baking soda went a long ways. We
         had baking powder biscuits and it didn't take much to make a pan of
         biscuits. These men that went out to work on the roads did their own
         cooking and they made soda biscuits. And they learned to make awful
         good ones, and so when they came home then our treat was for the menmy
         brothers and Dad to make the biscuits for supper. They were crisp,
         had crust. Soda biscuit has a nice crust.
         
         MARVIN L: We generally had them of course for breakfast. Mother, toast, pancakes-
         
         MLL:  But you always had biscuits.
         
         MARVIN L: Always had biscuits.
         
         MLL:  But we didn't. My mother didn't think so much baking powder bread was
         good for you.
         
         MARVIN L: She always had biscuits. Dad had to have biscuits.
         
         MLL:  And see that was the difference between New England and Southern— his
         mother was a Southern cook, and she always made biscuits. My mother
         was New England and they were raised on yeast bread, and she didn't
         think so much baking powder bread was good for you, so we just had it
         sort of like emergency bread when you ran out of yeast bread, then you
         had baking powder bread.
         
         SS:  How hard do you feel that your parents had to work?
         
         MLL:  Oh, they worked hard. They got up early and there was tock to take
         care of, and the farming to do. Any everything had to be made. Clo
         thes had to be made. Butchering. The butchering, you know, was hard
         work. And everything was made and there was no refrigeration, so
         butchering was a problem to keep the meat. In the winter it wasn't
         any problem.
         
         MARVIN L: Lots of chores had to be done.
         
         MLL:  The children helped. Everybody worked.
         
         MARVIN L: Had to milk twice a day.
         
         MLL:  Yeah, you milked the cow twice a day, and then you put it in pans and
         you put it in the cellar and the cream rose and you skimmed off the
         cream and then the milk that was left was still real rich, but the cream
         was made into butter. We churned the butter in a dasher churn. The
         children had to help do that with the dasher churn. Took a long time to
         get the butter to come. Mother made the butter,
         
         Tell about the first churn- how you churned.
         
         MLL:  Well, to make things easier we were taught to sing. We sang a lot when
         we did chores like that. And we sang this, "Churn, butter, churn,-"
         I've forgotten the rest of it- "Peter's waiting at the gate, waiting
         for a buttered cake." And then you'd sing this little verse and that
         made the time go faster. And then we finally had the washing machineat
         first, of course, it was just a washboard, but then we got a washing
         machine that had a wheel that had to be turned. It didn't get the
         clothes very clean, but the boys and I had to turn it sometimes and
         we would sing or we would read stories while we turned this and of
         course if the story got too exciting you'd forget to turn. It wasn't
         a very good system, but the children had to help with all these chores.
         We gathered the eggs.
         
         SS:  Did you feel that you and your brothers and sisters were really close
         to each other?
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes! We were a close family, I should say!
         
         SS:  Not very much conflict among you?
         
         MLL:  Oh, no, there wasn't any. No, no, they were real close. There was no
         jealousy or anything.
         
         MARVIN L: All families were close. Closer than they are now, don't you think?
         
         SS:  Well, that's hard to say. I think that family life—
         
         MLL:  We did everything together.
         
         MARVIN L: Did everything together.
         
         MLL:  We read together. We read these exciting books. Swiss Family Robinson.
         My mother did the reading but we all sat around at all ages and listened.
         And we'd read one chapter before we went to bed at night and could hard
         ly wait for the next chapter to see what happened to the Swiss Family
         Robinson. Robinson Crusoe.
         
         MARVIN L: There was twenty years spread in our family.
         
         MLL:  My goodness, and then we'd go out in the sagebrush and play act these
         things, you know. And one time somebody sent us a box of books; I
         don't know. they came from, but they'd been carelessly put in this
         wooden box and in nailing it the nails went through some of the books.
         But the books in that box, one of them was about Perry's expedition to
         the North Pole, and that was really exciting. I was old enough, I
         couldn't read a lot of the books, but there was one about missionaries
         and it had pictures of cannibals in it, and that was quite impressive
         because it showed these colored, naked people with a fire and a big iron
         kettle acooking the missionaries over the fire, in this book. And so
         we went down in the sagebrush, my younger brother and sister and I
         and we play acted; we killed the cannibals, and these weeds were can
         nibals, and we acted, you know, like kids do, we acted this all out!
         
         SS:  You know, talking about the working; was there much leisure for either
         of them, say during the week? Was there a time that they
         could put aside to just sit down and relax and not do anything?
         
         MLL:  Well, I don't suppose there was much time. They read the Bible. They
         took time for that. There was always prayer at the table, and there
         was Bible reading, and then before we went to bed there was always this
         little family time of either reading stories- and then, of course,
         some of the work wasn't- there was lots of sewing and mending. Mending
         you know, was a big deal for mother and she'd sit in a rocking chair
         and so of course that wasn't as tiring as some of the other work was.
         But they worked hard, of course. And it took a lot of sewing because
         all of our she made clothes and she made over most of the clothes. A lot
         of clothes had to be made over- people would give her ol d clothes and
         she would rip them up and dye them and she made beautiful
         clothes out of old clothes. We were well dressed for not spending much
         money. We ordered our shoes and underwear and things she couldn't
         make out of the Sears Roebuck catalogue. Ordered the most of them.
         Well, that's the way it was. That's the way it was all true. People
         lived like that. All pioneer stories tell the same thing. Some peo
         ple had more money than others in some parts of the country, but it
         was the drought there that they didn't prosper. If they'd prospered
         we would have had- We had furniture; we never had homemade furnture.
         We had straw ticks one bed, but we had mattresses on our other beds.
         We had springs and bedsteads; they brought them from North Dakota with
         them.
         
         SS:  What was the difference with those few families- those families in the
         area that did well enough that they could get things- Christmas presents
         and that kind of thing?
         
         MLL:  Well, some of them were town people that were in business, see, and had
         stores- there were stores and banks. There was a bank and a store and
         a drugstore. And those people would make more money.
         
         SS:  Were they generally doing better than the country people, then?
         
         MLL:  Well, they depended of course on the country people for their economy
         but then, at the same time there was business and the y did make more.
         And some of them had more money when they came here. Some had better
         land. Some of the land produced better than ours did. That made a
         difference, too. I don't know. And then some of them- the teachers
         were paid; I don't know how they were paid, but they were paid. Tea
         chers got salaries so they could have better clothes. They didn't have
         to wear madeover clothes like we did.
         
         MARVIN L: What do you think our homestead was sold for, when Dad sold it?
         
         SS:  When did he sell it?
         
         MARVIN L: He sold it when we was- see, I was it was.
         We lived at the time. 
         They had a big family of German kids, I don't know how many. Big
         family. Some time in 1908. This guy just stomped in
         there one day with Dad, he was a German, an old German. He had five
         one hundred dollar bills, 
         
         SS:  He was willing to sell it for $500 at that time?
         
         MARVIN L: He'd used up his income. There was income as long as he stayed there
         and made these posts and shakes; that's what he made off of the homestead,
         and that's h ftl he raised us kids; his family. Posts
         and §hakes for these farmers down here on the Ridge,. Kept it all those
         years then sold it for $500.
         
         SS:  Did your parents start to despair after they hadn't been able to get
         crops for a few years, or did they really expect to
         
         MLL:  Well, the two oldest ones graduated from high school in 1914 and Mother
         was determined they were going to have an education. Well there was no
         ways, you see, there was no money. And so she just- there was no in
         come coming from the farm, so they couldn't pay the taxes; so they
         talked it over and it was a hard decision to make because it was kind
         the unknown like Columbus venturing out, you know. And they just loaded us all
         in the wagon and we went to Pullman because the agricultural college
         was there; WSC was there. And we knew one man there, and Dad went over
         first and visited him and he found a house and we drove in a wagon from
         Quincy to Pullman. And she was determined that they were going to go
         to college. And the house that he had chosen, we didn't stay very long
         there. The water wasn't good and it wasn't right. She got a house
         close to the college and took in boarders and Dad could get work and
         the two oldest ones started to- entered college and the rest of us went
         to school there. And that's how we got out of Quincy. We could have
         never made it there and then later the climate changed. The rains came
         to Quincy and some of those farmers that could hold onto their land made
         it with wheat. 
         
         And then, of course, irrigation came. Even in my day
         I can remember Dad coming home from town and talking about - they were
         talking about irrigation then. They knew the land would produce if
         they could get water. And they were talking about bringing it across
         the Columbia River from- we were pretty close to the- about twelve
         Crescent Bar 
         miles from the Columbia River- bringing it across in a flume- they were
         talking that. But they hadn't thought of Coulee Dam yet then. But it
         was talked around the stove in the country stores, you know, and he 'd
         come home and talk about it. They were qo'ifo entfio cL but they knew the
         land would produce if they could just get water, but they just couldn't
         get water in our day. We used to go down to this Crescent Bar. They
         had orchards down there. They raised peaches. And once a year we would
         go down in the wagon; put some straw in the back of the wagon and take
         our lunch- usually took someone with us- somebody that didn't have any
         horses. And drive doiflft. It's down quite a grade, if you can remember
         that country, you go down that Trinidad grade, down to Trinidad. Quite
         a little grade going down to Crescent Bar from Quincy, and we would
         drive down there. Start early in the morning and pick peaches. And if
         you picked your own you could get 'em quite cheap. And we'd have a
         pic nic, andtare could wade in the Columbia none of us could swim
         so we couldn't go swimming. Mother was scared to death of swimming, but
         she would let us wade in the edge of the river, and that was a great
         treat. And the peaches on the ground you could have for free, but it
         was a trick to get those home in any condition, because they were brui
         sed- to get them home in a wagon in any condition to use, but we alwaysshe
         always brought a lot of those, too and salvaged some from those and
         canned lots of peaches. But that was a yearly jaunt, was to go down
         to the Crescent Bar. But now Crescent Bar is covered with water, of
         course since the dam, it's gone. But it was quite an ifctteresting place
         in those days. There were big peach orchards, big growers down there.
         And it was fun. The whole trip was fun. 
         
         And then they used to go to
         Moses Coulee- that's a different direction. That was a longer trip
         and they used to go for prunes. There were prune orchards in the Moses
         Coulee. And I can only remember going once. It was too much for the
         family and Dad and the boys usually went. It was a real rough trip.
         The road went down over the bluff from the top; Quincy was on top and
         :f was down in the Coulee and it was a place called the Three Devils,
         it was kind of shale rock slides. I asked somebody if that
         was still there and think it's still there on the road, but it never
         did improve too much. I'd like to see it, but it was real rough to go
         over that with a wagon, and that was the hazardous part of the trip to
         get through the Three Devils on the road. But they would get down and
         they would have to stay all night to go to Moses Coulee. And one time
         we all went and took blankets. We didn't have any rattlesnakes at
         Quincy but there were rattlesnakes of course along the river and in
         the coulees. Mother was so scared of rattlesnakes. And so we sleptthey
         fixed sort of a tent. They had a big canvas they fixed kind of
         a tent. There were school seats out on this- it was in a schoolyard
         I guess and she made us sleep on these schoolseats. Well, if you re
         member the old school benches that you went up and sat on when you
         recited- they sort of tipped a little, and of course in the night we
         children all rolled off, She put a rope around, that was sup
         posed to keep the snakes out, you know, if you put a rope around the
         tent, that was a sure cure. Of course later that's been proven that
         snakes crawl over the rope just as easy as anyplace else! But my mother
         felt quite safe as long as that rope was there! But they would get a
         lot of prunes and then she'd can 'em in two-quart jars; the old style
         jars with a rubber and a zinc lid. She'd can lots of those and we had
         a cellar- dirt cellar- you know, an outdoor cellar where it didn't freeze
         where we stored those things. In the winter if it got real cold we
         would have to light a lantern and hang it in the cellar to keep the
         vegetables andt fruit from freezing. Most winters it wouldn't freeze.
         
         SS:  What year did the family arrive then?
         
         MLL:  Well, Dad went in 1901, I think, and Mother came in 1902 and then I
         was born in 1903.
         
         SS:  And you stayed until—?
         
         MLL:  We left in 19- the fall of 1914, I believe it was.
         
         SS:  Did he try to grow crops there at all, all time he was there?
         
         MLL:  The last years it was so dry, it was just hopeless and he gave up.
         And then, of course this land that he had broken went back to sagebrush.
         I guess that there in later years in the '30's when I was in thl?1 coun
         try, I went over there to see if I could possibly find our homseated.
         The house had been moved and that land was all grown up to sagebrush
         again.
         
         SS:  I wonder about how much he had cleared and planted then.
         
         MLL:  He hadn*t cleared the whole quarter section, I don't know. There was
         still some sagebrush on it. He cleared most of it though. And it was
         hard work clearing it. I don't know just how they did it. Kind of a
         dragging process, wasn't it? I think. They dragged it.
         it wasn't very big sagebrush. It was sort of sandy soil, so I don't
         think it was too hard, it wasn't like clearing timber. Some of it they'd
         have to out. I think they dragged it out.
         
         SS:  The weather pattern- the rain, such as it was, did it come in the spring?
         
         MLL:  Yes, we'd have some showers in the summer, but not very many. Winter,
         winter and spring and fall it would rain some, but not enough. And
         then there was this drought cycle, you know, that that whole Big Bend
         country suffered from, and then it came back, the rains came back. Now
         the country around Davenport always raised grain. Dad had a cousin
         that lived at Davenport and he always produced. They didn't get the
         drought that Quincy got and their soil was different. It wasn't- I
         guess it was sagebrush"originally, but it was- they always raised big
         ger crops. Quincy needed the water. Euphrata raised better crops than
         Quincy did.
         
         SS:  You know you read about the later Victorian women. A lot of them
         seemed to have been sort of fragile, frail, you know, somewhat protec
         ted, you know. It seems to me with your mother coming from the New
         England background that she wasn't like a- she wag really ready to
         pioneer.
         
         ML: No. no, her family had always worked, I think. They pioneered- her
         family had pioneered in North Dakota, I think. They had homesteaded
         possibly. My grandfather was a- had a store and had been a postmaster.
         
         SIDE D
         
         MLL:  —like funny papers, we didn't have 'em. We had somethings though.
         We took the Youths Companion , and the twice a week Spokesman and I
         think we took the Ladies Home Journal most of the time when I was a
         child. I remember the Ladies Home Journal, or Delineator, one of those.
         But we always took the twice a week Spokesman to get the news. And
         the Youths Companion and it had lots of things for children- pages for
         children in it, as well as stories and everything was read thoroughly.
         And the funny papers we weren't allowed to have but my grandfather would
         send them so then Mother had to let us have them. I think she thoug-,ht
         they would corrupt us! Because they played tricks, you know. You know
         the Katzenjammers played tricks and then there was Mutt and Jeff, and
         then there was Buster Brown and his dog Tige, and oh, we lVed all the
         characters in the old funny papers! It would be a treasure to find
         some of them - the old ones- now.
         
         MARVIN L: I guess you could find 'em.
         
         MLL:  They're probably are some around in somebody's attic. We saved 'em, we
         wore them out reading them. They were just like they look now, just
         the same size- colorful just like they are now, but different charac
         ters. Different stories. Happy Hooligan. Happy Hooligan was a great
         one. He wore this funny little hat that looked like a tin can, I guess
         it was a tin can, wasn't it? I don't know, it just sat up on the top of
         his head. He was one that we liked.
         
         MLL:  Oh, that is not a very nice one. Well, I was a big girl and my mother
         let me sleep and when the children went out- the older ones had to go
         out and help weed the garden in the morning, but she would let me sleep
         a little longer and then in the summer they would have breakfast and
         go and then when I got up I would just eat my own breakfast. And so
         this one morning- I was very fond of canned pears and pear juice was
         especially delicious- and she always canned pears in an Econimy 
         wide mouth jar- and pears could be fitted into nicely- and so one mor
         ning when I got up to eat breakfast there on the breakfast table was
         this jar and it had a little bit of pear juice left in it and I drank
         it. When I drank it I realized it wasn't pear juice, it was her yeast.
         She made yeast the night before and she d mixed up her bread that mor
         ning and left it and that was supposed to be one reason why I grew so
         tall! (Chuckles) That's a true story! It didn't taste like pear
         juice.
         
         SS:  Did she knead you when she came in?
         
         MLL:  I had to knead the bread because it was hard work and one of my sisters
         always had weak wrists, you know it's easy for children to complain
         about something when they want to get out of something. We alway s
         accused her of wanting to get out of some of the work, and so her wrists
         were weak and they probably were, because she wasn't as husky as I was.
         But I had nothing to complain about because I was just a big husky girl.
         So when I was quite young one of my jobs was to knead bread. It was in
         a big pan and you had to knead it along time, and I wasn't tall enough
         to do it on the table so mother would put it on the organ stool and
         then that was my job and I had to knead this bread. I don't remember
         any songs or poems that we used for that, should have had one, because —
         but I could turn the stool, I could give it a whirl and fortunately the
         bread never sailed off. That made it a little more fun, but I had to
         knead that bread until it was nice and satiny. So the bread would be
         good. I didn't mix it. I didn't know how to make bread. I did the
         labor because I had big husky hands and I was husky. I didn't mind
         doing it, it was kind of fun.
         
         SS:  Was there anything to stop you from being a tomboy?
         
         MLL:  I was a tomboy. Well, we didn't wear- I wore overalls. I wore the
         boys' left over overalls to play at home, but never in public. We
         wore dresses and petticoats and so forth and long stockings. But I
         did wear overalls at home to play in, because I played with the boys.
         And I was Dad's boy. And Mother allowed that. That was okay. The
         other girls, I don't remember them ever wearing them, but they stayed
         in the house; did the dishes and cooked and things. Probably didn't
         want to wear them. I loved to wear them. They were just left-overs.
         
         SS:  They didn't care that you didn't want to do the housework?
         
         MLL:  Well, Mother believed in children playing. She didn't believe in chil
         dren being made to work too hard. We had to have playtime; it was im
         portant; she knew that. And I don't know, I grew so fast maybe is one
         reason but I never had any tasks that were hard or that I hated, really,
         very much. And I did play a lot, and I was imaginative, I could make
         up- one of the things I loved was to find an old hoop. We didn't have
         many hoops, but sometimes you know, you'd have a barrel that it would
         come off and you'd find the hoop and then you could roll that. And it
         was a great way for children to play. It's very ancient, I guess. But
         we would make- the boys would help me- and we would take one stick and
         put another stick across and then you would- it's quite a trick to get
         the hoop started and then you could run after it and you could roll it
         all over the yard and it was great fun. And that was rolling the hoop.
         And that's one thing I liked and that was lots of exercise for a big
         husky girl like I was. You know, there was no one just near enough my
         age and I played by myself quite a bit. I had friends. 
         
         I had one lit
         tle friend that was a minister's daughter and I used to go- and my
         mother would let me because she was the minister's daughter and she's
         my age, and I would go to her house to play. And he had been a
         missionary in the North and he had a white polar bear skin, and oh,
         that was fun to get to go and we'd play on this big rug, polar bear
         rug. But my mother never knew this I don't think, but we would playtea
         parties were great fun for children, you know, and we always had
         tea parties at home. And so this little friend and I played tea par
         ties, but she was allowed to use the communion glasses to play tea
         parties and I am sure my mother wouldn't have approved of that if she
         had known, but I thought that was wonderful, because I never under
         stood what communion was. Children didn't take communion in churches
         in those days like they do now. But the little dainty glasses- our
         church didn't use the big cup, we always had individual glasses and
         we had our tea party with them! And she also played marbles for keeps,
         this girl did. And my mother didn't approve; marbles was the big deal
         before and after school, but my mother didn't approve of marble playing
         for keeps. We played marbles, alright, but not for keeps. That was
         gambling. And so this girl played for pencils. Boy, did she have a—
         she was a slick little marble player! And she played with all the boys
         at school, and she had the biggest collection of pencils of anybody I
         ever knew. 
         
         SS:  Did you play for keeps with her?
         
         MLL:  No, no, no I never played for keeps. Heavens no! My mother would
         have chastised me if I played for keeps. I knew I shouldn't, I didn't
         know why it would do something to me, but it would do something bad
         to me to play for keeps, so I didn't play for keeps, but I would play
         marbles just to win for the fun. You were supposed to do things for
         fun not for gambling.
         
         Well, between your parents in those days, were they- did they have a
         pretty equal relationship, or was your mother just kind of doing what
         your father said?
         
         MLL:  Well, no, it was sort of equal in it's way, but Mother was the dominant
         one, in that things had to be strict- well, my father approved of all
         this strictness, too. And I think that he had been raised that way,
         too, because he had a little Testament that his mother had given him
         when he left Michigan. Two - three of the boys left Michigan and went
         West, and she had given them each a Testament, so you know she was a
         religious woman. I never knew her. So he was brought up in a religious
         home, too, and he approved of all of this but for instance ,spanking,
         which wasn't done very much in our home, but we got a paddling occasion
         ally, and Mother was afraid Dad would hurt us, so she did the spanking.
         But there was great love between our parents. But I don't remember
         Dad ever spanking anybody, I don't think Mother would have let him,
         she was afraid he would hurt us.
         
         SS:  Would your father let her do whatever she wanted to, as far as the
         home and that, you know?
         
         MLL:  Oh, they did it together. Yes, I don't remember- there were no argu
         ments or fights. I don't ever remember any fights or anything.
         
         SS:  Do you think she wanted to go- to leave earlier than he did?
         
         MLL:  No, I don't think so, except- because of the school. They had good
         schools and she always got acquainted with the teachers and the teachers
         came home, took meals like the preachers did. She wanted us to
         know teachers and preachers and so we knew- they were friends, you
         know. And to take these two out of high school before they had finished
         wouldn't have been good. It was a small high school, but it would have
         been better to let them finish there. I think that's why they hung on,
         than to take them into a strange- the rest of us could adjust but when
         they were so near through high school it was better to stay. And we
         were able to stay. They managed. But that high school graduating class
         the two, they weren't the same age but they were in the same - they
         graduated together, my brother and sister- the oldest ones. Because
         when we came there she thought it was too far for the girl to start,
         for my sister, Esther, to start to school and so she had taught her
         at home, and so they were in the same class when they graduated. And
         my sister was the only girl, there were four boys, as I remember and
         my sister in the graduating class. And it was a big event- a family
         event, we all went to graduation at the school house. And the gradua
         ting class sat upon the little platform- or maybe it was in the church,
         I remember them sitting on a platform, the graduating class. And they
         were given their diplomas. And my sister had a white dress. Aunt 
         had sent her the dress. It was decorated with pink satin roses. And
         long skirts were still the style then, you know, and it had a fichu
         collar- that's kind of a ruffly collar that tied in the front, and the
         collar was sort of tucked up with a bunch of these pink satin rosebuds.
         Oh, it was a beautiful dress. And then the hem of the skirt- the skirt
         was tucked up with a bunch of these pink satin rosebuds, too, because
         that was just a bit of style, but that wouldn't do, my mother took those
         o^f and got that skirt down to cover those ankles quick! And those pink
         roses weren't wasted, they were put on the dress someplace, but my poor
         sister- I thought that was a shame! I thought thatk real stylish.
         That's the way they looked in the Ladies Home Journal pictures, you
         know! The skirts were tucked up a bit, not enough to be immodest,
         of course, but just an inch or two. But my mother couldn't have that
         when my sister was going to sit up on the stage for commencement.
         
         SS:  Where had she got the dress?
         
         MLL:  My Aunt fcella had made it. And she had her measurements and it fit her
         and it was a beautiful, white, cotton- I don't know what kind of mate
         rial it was. It was a soft- it wasn't organdy, it was a soft material,
         but it was beautifully made with ruffles and a pink sash.
         
         MLL:  North Dakota. Mother's only sister.
         
         SS:  That's where she left her relatives.
         
         MLL:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS:  You say she really felt that it was good for her to get away from her
         relatives?
         
         MLL:  Well, I don't know. Maybe it was because it was hard 
         there, too, and maybe he thought having a homestead would be a good
         life, because she was very lonesome for her family. But she thought
         too many relatives living close together would cause problems, and of
         course it does sometimes, too. But she was very lonesome and so far
         her folks
         that she didn't get to see . very often. They visited us and she
         visited them a few times. But we knew them well, but we didn't know
         them personally well. We didn't get to see them very often.
         
         SS:  You mentioned something abcut getting an organ.
         
         MLL:  Yes, they shipped out an organ as a present to us. The grandparents
         apparently were better off than we were. And Aunt 0ella and the grand
         parents shipped this organ; a reed organ to us. And Mother knew how
         to play somewhat and she taught Esther and then Esther played the or
         gan in church after that. It was hard on the organ in that dusty coun
         try because of the sand storms we had. But Mother knew how to clean
         the organ. The back comes off from an old organ and there are reeds
         and you pull these reeds out and she would tune them with a tuning fork
         and keep it in good tune that way. But she did that herself. Maybe
         with Dad's help, I don't know. Dad had a better ear for music than
         mother had, but Mother was good at it, too. She couldn't sing a second
         part, it always hurt her,'ctu se she couldn't but Dad taught the rest of
         us with him, so- we learned to sing with him .
         
         MLL:  No, she wanted to sing with Dad. She wanted to sing the second part,
         you know, and she couldn't, she could sing soprano alright, but she
         never could learn to sing alto, for some reason, I don't know why, be
         cause anybody that could sing ought to be able to learn. Seems that
         way to me because that's the way I learned, you know, early, but-
         
         SS:  Did you ever get caught out in a dust storm?
         
         MLL:  Well, they weren't that bad, I don't think. I don't remember any
         trouble that way; no.
         
         MARVIN L: We stayed home.
         
         MLL:  South of Quincy, that would have been possible in the sand- that was
         more sandy country south. Down around Beverly Hills- you know where
         that country is? But these sand storm were smaller than that. They
         just kept the house dusty all the time. But the big sand storms were
         south of Quincy through the- oh, Beverly Hills, they call it. There
         are some town down in now I think with irrigation, but in those
         days there wasn't much. There was a Catholic Church down there, I
         think. Mission.
         
         SS:  How important was education to your mother? Seems like she really
         wanted that for you.
         
         MLL:  Oh, education was the goal in life. You had to have an education in
         order to amount to anything. And no sacrifice was too great to get
         an education. And so even after we went to Pullman, we were still poor
         of course, and we all worked our way through college to get our edu
         cation. But it was really important. And it never occurred to any of
         us not to go; If you lived there it wasn't so expensive in those days.
         You could go to college. If you had $200 or $300 you could pay your
         expenses a semester you lived at home, you see. And we could
         earn that much money. I did different kids- I did anything. Ironing
         and baby sitting and jobs like that. And in the summer I got a job
         one year, cooking for harvesters with a friend of mine down in the
         La Crosse area. I earned $200- $240 that summer, cooking for harves
         ters. I was sixteen and this friend of mine was seventeen and we cooked
         for her brother. We did all the cooking on this ranch. She knew more
         about it than I did, but I knew how to cook. And that was enough money
         for a semester of college, you see in those days. Now that wouldn't
         go anywhere.
         
         MARVIN L: Do you know what she was doing when I picked her up?
         
         SS:  Extension work?
         
         MLL:  He knows. (Chuckles) Well then after I got then I could
         do things.
         
         MLL:  My mother had been a normal school graduate in Wisconsin. She had
         taught, but she had went to normal school. And my dad, I don't know
         what his education was. He didn't have any higher education.
         
         SS:  I was thinking if it would be okay, I'd really like to talk to you
         about the extension work, in the '30's. That seems to be very interes
         ting work.
         
         MLL:  Well, it was, yes. I don't know what you would want to know about that.
         I was home demonstration agent at Wenatchee and it was the first one
         that that county had and it was in that depression time.
         
         SS:  When did you first get the idea that you wanted to go into home ec?
         
         MLL:  I don't know exactly, but all four of us girls took home ec. It was a
         good course at Pullman at that time. And because my sisters took 
         I knew something about it. One time during my course I changed- I
         thought I wanted physical education, but I'm not an athlete; I'm not
         coordinated enough to be a good athlete, so it's lucky I didn't. But
         my dean, Dean Harrison, let me change and then before the year started changed back
         and stayed home economics. And we all taught.
         All four of us were home economics teachers.
         
         SS:  Were you interested in teaching before you went to college?
         
         MLL:  Well, that's my mother's influence again, you see. She had been a
         teacher and it was great to be a teacher. There weren't too many things
         girls could do in those days, you know. You could be a nurse, you
         could take nurse's training, which was real hard or you could teach or
         you could get jobs in stores; derk.^ in stores, which didn't pay very
         well, or you could be a telephone operator, but you know, there wasn'tor
         you could do housework. But there weren't too many kinds of work
         that women did, you know. But teachers were considered- that was con
         sidered a good job for a girl if she could get the education, and there
         was always a job. And then being a college graduate I could do high
         school teaching and I taught in high school first.
         
         SS:  You said that you couldn't teach if you were married.
         
         MLL:  Well, they didn't hire very many married teachers. There were some in
         those early schools that I taught in. There would have to be reasons
         why. There-would have to be a great need. If you got married, you
         just resigned right then during the school year. They didn't permit
         that. They told teachers what to do in those days. When I took my
         first teaching job at Culdesac down here in Idaho, it was understood
         that I would stay there weekends, that I would work in the community.
         That was part of your contract. I was used to that, I'd always worked
         in the church, and I worked in the church at Culdesac, I liked it.
         I was used to doing it; I wanted to do it. But a lot of teachers didn't
         they lived in Lewiston and they wanted to go home, don't you see?
         Made a problem. And they did go home and the school board didn't like
         it. They wanted them to stay there. You weren't hired just to teach
         you were hired to be a part of the community. And that's good; in a
         way it's good, because a teacher's influence is greater on the kids
         out of school than in, really.
         
         SS:  In the church and other activities?
         
         MLL:  Teachers were important people in those little towns. In little towns
         especially. Now I don't know that that was true- in my day, a teacher
         couldn't teach in those little towns if she smoked- if they knew she
         smoked- or if she- I don't know, what else? She couldn't get married.
         
         SS:  Maybe I'm not too smart, but I don't understand what marriage would
         have to do with it, one way or the other.
         
         MLL:  It wouldn't nowdays. Nowdays- they didn't get married til they got
         through college- it was partly the economics, they couldn't afford to.
         There was no way that a couple could get married and both go to college.
         It just couldn't be done. And the girls weren't trained so they
         could send the boys to college like they do now. Nobody got married in
         college like they do now. And they didn't get married as teachers.
         But we did have a few women that were teachers- there was one when I
         taught at Omak, who had taught there a long time and she was- her hus
         band had an orchard and they kept her on the faculty. She was a won
         derful Latin teacher; and I think it was because Latin teachers were so
         scarce and hard to get, probably. I don't know. But there had to be
         exceptions. There were plenty of unmarried teachers that needed jobs,
         was the reason, I think. They needed the jobs, and they just wouldn't
         hire married women.
         
         SS:  When you started going to WSC, what was it like? What was the program
         that they had for you?
         
         MLL:  Well, it was called home economics. Earlier it had been called domes
         tic science; not in my day. It had come a long ways by then. Dean
         Harrison was a wonderful woman and it was a small school; Pullman was
         a small town then. And the college was small compared to what it is
         now; that was in 1920, I graduated from high school in 1920 and I star
         ted college that fall. And there was nutrition, and there was cooking,
         still called cooking, and sewing. A lot of clothing work and some of
         it was actual sewing. You had to learn all the fundamentals of sewing
         and patterns and fitting and making clothes, because you still made
         clothes. We learned to make hats; still made hats. And there was
         tailoring; more advanced work. Then you had to take chemistry. There
         was a lot of science. It was considered one of the hardest courses
         that women took. Pharmacy was the hardest, I guess, that girls took.
         And home economics was one of the next because of the science. There
         was two years of chemistry, including organic and bacteriology and
         zoology. Those were all laboratory. There was lots of laboratory work
         to it, you see, as well as all your home economics classes had laborator. So it was
         hard in that respect. And there were very few electives.
         And the few electives that were- you had to take general courses
         of course, like English and, let's see- no mathematics. Didn't take
         any mathematics or history. Didn't have to have any of that, but you
         had to take English. And physical education was a requirement for
         everybody. There was no intramurals, it was just between classes; the
         games. But you played the games, basketball and hockey- girls' hockey.
         
         SS:  Most of the people that took the course, what were they planning to do?
         
         MML: Well, there was dietetics; that was a specialty. You could be a dieti
         cian and work in hospital. You could specialize in that. Or you
         could specialize in teaching, that's what I went into. And then, let's
         see, what else? In those days, those were two fields. There weren't
         as many as there are now.
         
         SS:  Were many of the women just planning to use it in the home?
         
         MLL:  Oh, yes, yes, lots of them^get married before they finished. That was
         beneficial, of course. But a lot of them became teachers and then this
         extension work was pretty well established then and they went into that.
         They usually went into that from teaching, though. They usually taught
         first to get experience. I don't know very many that went directly in
         to extension. That was teaching, of course, in a way. And then there
         buyers
         was some commercial fields. There was some in textiles. Textile
         and textile manufacturers hired home economic trained people. So they
         specialized in textile work if they were interested in that. There
         was quite a field opening up in the buying field for women trained in
         textiles. That was laboratory work in our course, too. It was a good
         course, interesting. And I don't know how I happened to get in
         extension. I was teaching. I taught six years three at Culdesac and
         three at Omak. And then the extension service held this big 4-H Club
         camp in the summers; it's changed a little now, but it was a big af
         fair on the campus. And they hired extra people to teach the classes.
         And because I lived in Pullman I was hired one summer to teach a cooking
         class for these 4-H girls. And I was supposed to teach them to can
         chicken. And the chickens were sent by the poultry department at the
         college and they were supposed to send me young, small chickens that
         could be Canned in a pint jar. 
         
         I was supposed to teach these girls to
         fit a chicken into a- I knew how to do it- I knew how to do that, but
         a big hen couldn't be fitted into- there was no way a big hen could be
         fitted into a pint jar. But we only had a certain amount of time for
         the class and it was held clear across town in the Pullman High School
         so the kids had to come from the campus, clear across town to Pullman
         High School laboratory where this- where I was teaching this class,
         and these chickens were supposed to be all cut up ready for us to can.
         The cutting was not supposed to be part of the lesson. And so that
         morning when I arrived and the chickens arrived from the poultry depar
         tment they were dressed but they weren't cut up and they were very large,
         And I only had a certain amount of time for this class; they had to
         be cut up; packed in the jars and processed and let those kids get back
         to the campus: it was an impossibility. So, we started in
         these big chickens; they couldn't get a whole chicken in a jar, which
         was what I had hoped to teach them, but we did the best we could, and
         we canned the chickens, and I spent the rest of the day finishing up
         that chicken. I had to stay in that laboratory all afternoon pressure
         cooking the rest of these chickens, because the girls didn't have time
         to finish. They each did a jar. We got through that. But all these
         great big old chickens were left and so there I was. And I was awful
         mad about it and I told the woman that had hired me, she was an exten
         sion woman and I wasn't interested in extension work at all. And I told
         her what had happened, and I said, "I just did the best I could do,
         and that chicken is all canned and its here and I hope it will keep."
         "But," I said, "I wouldn't guarantee that it'll keep." And she laughed.
         And later when I was teaching at Omak they arrived at my door one day
         and offered me a job in extension, and I don't know what else it was
         based on except that I got mad because I'd been given an impossible job
         and I'd done it. Now would you say that might have had some influence?
         Well, that was just an impossible job and I was awful mad about it!
         And she saw that I had- I think she saw that I had possibilities be
         cause that's what extension work vs^ like. You had to do impossible
         things, and we did 'em. You know, that's what it was, out working
         with rural people.
         
         SS:  Was the background very good for that at the University? I've heard
         people say -
         
         MLL:  No. Yes, we had practice teaching before we were sent
         out from Pullman. K We had an excellent woman in charge of practice
         teaching. We each had a six weeks session I think. We had an actual
         class that we were in charge of in Pullman. At the Pullman High School.
         They cooperated wifrfc the college in home economics and in commercial -
         they did that in commercial for years. Later they send these kids out
         like they do here, out to the neighboring towns and do it, you know,
         but we did ours right at Pullman High School. I did mine right at
         fullman High School. So, that's how I got into extension work,
         chickens, I think. I interested, but
         was, it sounded good, and I thought I would try it. So I'll tell you
         if you'd like me to.
         about that some day, It won't be as long as this. (Laughter)
         
         SS:  Is there anything from the early days that you can think of that we
         haven't touched on?
         
         MLL:  Most of what I've told him. Lee and I have always sat and visited and
         I never thought about putting it down. But it's fun to remember. We
         had wonderful parents. We're thankful for our wonderful parents. That's
         why we're what we are because of our parents.
         
         MARVIN L: husband. (Chuckles)
         
         MLL:  Because of what I was when I met you. I was already made then because
         a child has to be formed. Strictness doesn't hurt a child. But fun,
         they have to have fun; my mother believed in fun. And beauty; lots of
         beauty. Everything had to be beautiful. It was hard in those days.
         We planted- one time we got some tulips. Some way, I don't know how
         we got these tulips, we planted a bed of tulips. And everybody had one
         tulip. Mine was a pink striped one. That was the way she made things
         fun; it belonged to us. A tree-in the orchard; because they were so
         few, it belonged to us. The family shared the produce, but it was our
         tree! The crabapple tree was hers, but mine was a cherry tree, and this
         pink striped tulip was my tulip. We didn't have a lot of bulbs. They
         wouldn't grow; they wouldn't survive in that country. But it survived
         several years. 
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13669</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Long_F3</previous>
      <next>Long_Martha2</next>
      <disp_name>Long_Martha1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
