<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/27/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>F. Marvin Long, 1976-02-27, Interview #3 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:02:26</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Long, F. Marvin</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #3</intnum>
      <occupation>Operator of mercantile store</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894</birthyear>
      <residence>Kendrick, Cedar Creek, Leland</residence>
      <origin>Family moved from North Carolina (1888)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#factories"&gt;factories&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Kendrick"&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Leland"&gt;Leland&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Lee Magnuson</interviewer>
      <file_name>13668</file_name>
      <mp3>13669.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13669.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Phonograph made of Charlie Dale whistling; first telephone in Leland; other businesses
               and how boys made in town
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Charlie Dale of Leland: whistler, made phonograph record of
               whistling. Albert Lee's meat business; solo to NB Long, First telephone in Leland.
               Van Pelt's flour mill. Boys earned money doing jobs in town, cared for doctors' horses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Why NB long came west; having a fruit ranch and it's failure; moving to Kendrick and
               the businesses opened there; Marvin working as a clerk and what he made
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>NB Long's move west, 1889 to Crescent, Idaho. Sold cedar shakes and posts. Move to
               Fruit ranch. Apples. Failure. Albert Lee helped Longs start meat business. Mrs. Long
               ran hotel. Freight line to Pierce. Move to Kendrick, bought house, butcher shop, dray
               line. Marvin worked in store, 1909-10. Families buying for the winter. Marvin worked
               for $45.00 a month clerking.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Kendrick streets in 1908, mud and dust</title>
            <synopsis>Kendrick streets in 1908, mud and dust</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Not having any trees or water in 1908; Chinese-American laundries; Native Americans
               coming though in the summer
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>No trees in 1908. Locust trees planted. Trees from Martin Thomas. No water for yards,1908.
               Hulls. Flowers, Mrs. Long's flowers. Gene Chinaman, vegetable man. Gene sent back
               to China, but died on the way. Chinese laundries. Indians coming through in summer.
               Dry goods prices in early stores. Men's suits.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2820</time>
            <title>President Taft visits Kendrick; T. Roosevelt spoke in Moscow; Train service</title>
            <synopsis>President Taft visits Kendrick. T. Roosevelt spoke in Moscow. Train service. Seasonal
               shopping.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Being a blacksmith in town; different Methodist churches; rural post offices</title>
            <synopsis>Blacksmith, Mr. Hodges in Leland. Marvin made spoke wedges, Hodges made toys, loved
               children. Leland at its height. North and South Methodist churches. Rural post offices
               around Kendrick.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Leland as a thriving town. Failure of family fruit ranch. Starting business in
         Kendrick. Early Kendrick; Gene Chinaman. 2-27-76 1 hr Lee Magnuson
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This interview with MARVIN LONG took place at his home in Kendrick,Idaho on February
         27,1976. The interviewer is LEE MAGNUSON.
         
         LEE MAGNUSON: Tell about Charley Dale again.
         
         MARTHA LONG: Tell the story and then you can figure out the details.
         
         MARVIN LONG: There was a man by the name of Charley Dale,hauling freight from
         Leland and Kendrick to Leland. And he got the name of Whistling Charley.
         'Cause he whistled from Leland to Kendrick to get his load of freight and
         he whistled from Kendrick to Leland bringing the freight back. So he had
         acquired the name of Whistling Charley. That's that story.
         
         LM:  He made a record?
         
         MRS. LONG:  Phonograph record.
         
         ML:  Yeah. He had a phonograph record. Old style cylinder phonograph record thahe
         made, he make these records? Fixed these records by twisting 'em. And
         that's where Whistling Charley comes in.He to Kendrick, then he whistled
         back from Kendrick to Leland.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Then he went up here to Dry Creek.
         
         ML:  Yeah, us kids, we were just smali boys then and grew up at the house here
         and lived on Dry Creek then.The record started out, whistling by Charley
         The reason was so exciting, it was the first phonograph
         recording that was done in Leland.Us kids had never heard.
         
         LM:  Maybe you could tell about the hotel business in Leland that your mother
         ran.
         
         ML:  Well, let's see, let's get this in for historical...The reason Longs got
         into the meat business was my older brothers, Tom and Joe, worked for am
         man name of Albert Lee. And he owned a butcher shop in Leland. And Mr. Lee
         told our father he could buy off this meat business, 'caust,he had boys to
         run it. That's how we got into the meat business. Sold meat in thft territory
         from then, is there a date on when this started?
         
         LM:  No, it doesn't matter, what ever you remember about it.
         
         ML:  Well, we took over the meat business from Albert Lee and sold meat in this
         territory from then til 1868-(pause in tape) The first telephone line at
         Leland was a private line from Kendrick up to VanPelt's flour mill. And
         developed
         several years afterwards they put in a farmers lines all over the country.
         I don't know just what year that was.
         
         LM:  The first phone served the whole community?
         
         ML:  Yeah, it was the only phone up on the ridge. Was Kendrick-Southwick. There
         wasn't any people down here. It was just a small system. Just a few people
         I think. The warehouse over here had the first phone.Hadson \A/^rzJiouh..
         from Lewiston. It was a private line. There wasn't any long distance in here.
         It was all by telegraph.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Used to deliver the messages.
         
         ML:  Yeah, telegraph messages. Yep.
         
         LM:  What was it about Van Pelt's phone that you delivered the messages?
         
         ML:  The only phone from Kendrick to Leland was a man name of Van Pelt had a
         flour mill there. And he had the only phone in there, it was a private line.
         It was the only phone on that ridge.
         
         LM:  So everybody used it?
         
         ML:  Well they come up to Kendrick, yeah. Long distance.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Did you take the messages
         
         LM:  The kids did?
         
         ML:  did. I or Isd or some of us on the horse. We got paid for it.
         
         LM:  You'd take the message, or they'd come bqck with you and make another call?
         
         ML:  I don't remember. I guess they'd come back and call. I guess that was the
         way. There wasn't many 'em that did.We made all our spending money.
         Chores and messenger boys.
         
         LM:  What were some of the other things you did? Chores.
         
         ML:  Took care of the doctor's horses. Kept 'em hooked, harness ready to go.
         And the only way the doctor had, no cars, the only way the doctors got around
         was with horses. They didn't come after fem with a team. They all had
         teams,the doctors did. A team and a buggy or a hack. My brother Ed and I
         always had the job of taking care of the horses. Different doctors' horses.
         
         LM:  At his house?
         
         ML: Yeah, at his barn.They couldn't work with the horses and we had practice.
         
         LM:  What were the things your folks did before they moved to Leland?
         
         ML:  Have you ever put that in?
         
         LM:  Not the whole story.
         Let's put the whole story in. I'll start and see...My father, N.B. Long, 
         
         ML: come west 1889 and homesteaded what is known as Crescent now. Later it
         was ,Crescent. And dad sold th^e homestead to a fella name of Dorndorf
         for the big some of five hundred dollars.(laughs)
         
         LM:  How many acres?
         
         ML:  160.
         
         LM:  Do you know whose place it is now? 
         
         ML:  Sure, I think they call it the Dorndorf place.They sold it to I
         said five hundred dollars? Five hundred dollars.
         
         LM:  How much of that was farmland?
         
         ML:  It was farm and stump land. Whatever's cleared up. Made shakes and cedar
         posts. And peddled 'em out on Potlatch Ridge to the farmers. He'd take
         orders for these posts, fence posts and shakes. There was quite a demand,
         you know, for shakes.All the barns and all the sheds were covered with
         shakes.
         
         LM:  Those big long ones?
         
         ML:  Yeah.
         
         LM:  Longer than shingles.
         
         ML:  Yes, bigger shakes, regular shake length. We 've still got the froe, haven't
         we? Yep.
         
         LM:  what year did he sell the homestead?
         
         ML:  Well,Christ, I don't know.
         
         LM:  In the '90's maybe.
         
         ML:  Well '95. I was born up there in '94 and I was two years old when
         he come down. '96 I guess. We came to the ridge.
         
         LM:  Where did he go then?
         
         ML:  First place, we rented,farmed what is known, I don't know what it's known
         as now.Emmett Blackenem place. George Daggerman place. I don't know who
         owns it now.
         
         LM:  He went from there over to Cameron with the fruit?
         
         ML:  Yeah, he went down to a fruit ranch. 70 acre orchard.
         
         LM:  Apples or other things?
         
         ML:  Just apples. 70 acres of apples. He went broke on it. Lost everything he'd
         put into the orchard and four years of hard labor.
         
         LM:  What caused it? To fail?
         
         ML:  Everything. Kind of apples and no markets. Everybody went into the apple
         business and there was no market. Mostly no market, I'd say. Three kind of
         apples he raised were Jonathons, Roman Beauties and Ben Davis. Ben Davis is
         what broke him.(laughs) Good keepers the apple^ and never took on the market.
         
         LM:  What was it about having them ready to ship here? In town?
         
         ML:  They was hauled over here, and what do they call this old shed over here?
         The old...?
         
         LM:  Ben Cook's warehouse. I don't know what it would have been.
         
         ML:  Old packing plant. Fruit warehouse. That's what it was with it's basement
         in it. And they put the apples in the basement to keep. from freezing.
         In the winter. Yeah, this was quite a fruit country. Big orchards every
         where. Too much of one. Last one I remember is the Johnson prune orchard up
         here. Quite large prune orchard all over the country.
         
         LM:  Where was that?
         
         ML: The top of the hill up there. Right when you go up this grade, right up the
         top of that grade there. Nobody lives up there anymore, I don't think.
         
         LM:  Bear Ridge?
         
         ML:  Well just go up the grade right here.
         
         LM:  Up by Arnetts?
         
         ML:  No, you don't go up Arnetts. ^keep this way, that grade. Ever been up
         there?
         
         LM:  I know what you mean now.
         
         ML:  Goes up American Ridge.
         
         Ms. Long: Gentry Road 
         
         LM:  Most of those trees are gone now.
         
         ML:  Oh yes, they're afl gone.
         
         LM:  What did your father do when the apples broke him?
         
         ML:  Fella by the name of Albert Lee, after he went broke orchards, fella
         by the name of Albert Lee, Tom and Joe was working for him, and he backed
         him with, he's the one that backed him, financed him to get started.
         
         LM:  He started freighting?
         
         ML:  He had this shop, what?
         
         LM:  Shop?
         
         ML:  Orchard. I'm ahead of myself. On the ranch, orchard, we farmed on the side
         to make a living, but went broke. But this Albert Lee's the one that backed
         him on the meat business. Backed him with the shop and two teams of horses
         and two meat wagons and what else? That put us in the meat business.
         
         LM:  That was in Leland?
         
         ML:  Yeah.
         
         LM:  You went to Leland then. Your mother start the hotel at the same time?
         
         ML:  She was running the hotel.
         
         LM:  Is that when he freighted the meat over to Pierce?
         
         ML:  He didn't freight meat, he freighted groceries. Anything. There were no
         trains over there. Anybody, could-.come-down here and get a load of freight
         for the prairie over there. It would be stacked in this depot
         people who had teams, as far as freighting anything. Some of 'em had
         four and some had six.^Dad had a four horse team.
         
         LM:  How did you happen to come to Kendrick?
         
         ML:  Well, let's see.
         
         MRS. LONG:  You and Ed were graduating from the eighth grade that spring, weren't
         you?
         
         ML:  Yeah. Dad come to Kendrick to get work for four of us boys.(laughs) He told
         me the reason. And he come down here, how much money was it that I told you
         that before, didn't I? Mother wouldn't come unless he bought this house.
         And I think he cleaned up five hundred dollars, fifteen hundred dollars,
         and he put five hundred dollars payment on this house. And he went down
         town and he bought out a butcher shop for five hundred dollars. And he
         bought out a dray team and dray line for five hundred dollars. All good
         dealing. He come down there with us four boys and he had work for all of
         'em but me and he farmed me out.
         
         LM:  What did you do then?
         
         ML: I went into the store business. That's how I happened to be in the mercantile.
         
         LM:  You started in 1908? When you came to town?
         
         ML: No I didn't start, I helped 'em on dray line when we first come to town.
         Iwent to, I think it was about 1910 Iwent to the store. '09 or 10, I don't
         know exactly. It's where the hardware store is now.
         
         LM:  Is that where the gaslight system that you worked with was?
         
         ML:  I never worked...
         
         LM:  That acetelyne? I looked after it. I was in that store and I had to go in there
         and acetelyne 
         
         ML:  outfit and it'd get down but it wouldn't start up again. YOu had to go and...
         
         LM:  Was that just for their store?
         
         ML:  No, had 'em all, but as a store, he had two or three other stores. And no,
         that store, I was working there see, and that's how I happened to be looking
         after this plant. It was behind the store, father's store.
         
         LM:  What was his name that had that store?
         
         ML: Dameril Florence. I don't know if that. But I worked for
         Beckwith but they sold out to Dammeril Florence. I went along with the store.
         For some reason or other. Da d didn't have work for me.
         
         LM:  Who did you buy the house from?
         
         ML:  This house? Fella by the name of Wessils. dealer, wasn't it Martha?
         
         Ms Long: Uh huh.
         
         LM:  Do you know how much it cost all together?
         
         ML:  Which?
         
         LM:  The house? Five hundred dollars was the down...
         
         ML:  Fifteen hundred dollars.
         
         LM:  Fifteen hundred all together?
         
         ML:  We bought, if we had another fifteen hundred we would have went over and
         bought the other side of the street.We bought a drayline out for five hundred
         dollars, we bought thwpayment on this house for five hundred dollars, and
         he ...
         
         LM:  And the butcher shop.
         
         ML:  And the butcher shop.
         
         MS. Long: Where was the butcher shop?
         
         ML:  Between this hotel and the corner. In there where, isn't it Walter Cook's
         got his apartment in there?
         
         LM:  In the hotel building.
         
         ML: Yeah. That's where the butcher shop was. Until we, 0. C. Wilde, he died,
         fella by the name of Wilde had it down there where we had it, where we moved
         to. You remember when we had it there don't you?
         
         LM:  No, I can't. 
         
         ML: Well we sold it, no we moved it over to the main store there, used that for
         a warehouse, (break in tape)...and stock up for the winter for their clothes
         with their large families. And get abig box.
         
         MRS. LONG:  What sort of things did they buy?
         
         ML:  Everything for clothing. Their winter shoes and rubbers and underwear and
         socks, shirts, everything, everything they need for winter. He'd have these
         lists and these sticks to fit their shoes. Kids never got a chance to come
         in and pick out anything. We always did though. We had our own money and we
         done our own buying.
         
         LM:  You had connections at the store too.
         
         ML:  Well we didn't have any dry goods store then. We never had dry goods until
         1920. No, we had to go out and buy our stuff. Like body else. Course,
         I went to clerking awful young. I'm trying to think if I was 15.
         I wasn't any older than that.Beckwith wanted Ed, fella name of Beckwith
         run this general store. Said they couldn't have Ed, but they could have me.
         He wasn't very anxious to hire me. I worked the first month, I started work
         for thirty dollars a month. I think it was. I got a raise the first month,
         a five dollar raise, and I think that at the end of the year I was getting
         forty five. I stayed with that for, I don't know, that was top wages. Forty
         five dollars
         
         LM:  They thought you were doing good work.
         
         ML:  Well I'd a been going down the street. They wouldn't have kept me. They
         kept sale records and it was posted every morning back in a corner back
         there.All our records. You kept up your sales or you were going down the
         road. I didn't have any trouble though.A Married guy old Bob Shoemaker,
         he'd get so mad. I got the same money he was getting, same salary and
         selling more stuff and he was sore about it. I shouldn't have told him.
         He sure did kick.
         
         LM:  What was Kendrick like when you moved to town?
         
         ML: Well I'll give you an idea what the streets . like You could come
         down here on Main street with a load of freight and go down you had
         to unload the freight to get it out of them mudholes. It's before there
         was any gravel or anything you know. Get into one of them holes,
         Jack 'em up and put stuff under 'em. It was awful.
         
         LM:  And turn to dust in the summer.
         
         ML:  Well you had on awagon, sprinkler, and they sprinkled. They kept
         it down pretty good. You'd he surprised. They had to. Main street down there,
         that one block, .wasn't so bad. Even after the fire down there where the
         park is and that end of town was the main business part of town. And there
         were several, well, there was, after the fire they filled that street in with
         brick and stuff. It's pretty solid street. That's before it was paved or
         anything. It used to be afright. Spring of the year and the summer when
         you get...
         
         LM:  There wasn't any trees along the street when you first came.
         
         ML:  Not a tree. Not a tree.
         
         LM:  When did the locust trees get planted?
         
         ML:  I wouldn't know just exactly what year it was.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Must have had water.
         
         ML:  Probably in the late^early '20's I imagine. See, we come down here in 1908.
         
         Ms. Long: Where did they get those locust trees?
         
         ML:  Didn't you know the history of those locust trees?
         
         Ms. Long: I've forgotten.
         
         ML:  I thought I told you. Martin Thomas raised them.
         
         LM:  He lived next door here?
         
         ML:  He did but he raised them up in French, he owned that Cox place, you know.
         Owned all that. He had a grove up there. He raised...
         
         LM:  All kinds of trees.
         
         ML:  Not all kinds but that's where these locust trees raised. If I remember
         right. Ithink that's right. Ithink he's got agrove up there yet, ain't
         they?
         
         LM:  I'm not real familiar with it. The place.
         
         ML:  You know where it is, don't you?
         
         LM:  Yeah.
         
         ML:  Well if you ever, I think there's a grove up there yet. Coming up the grade
         from Juliaetta, up that old grade there. The road that goes across there
         to the other.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Did they have to water them to get them started?
         
         ML:  Sure they had to water 'em.
         
         MRS. LONG:  How did they do that?
         
         ML:  Done with water tank and barrel, and barrels. That was the days of water
         tanks.. That was the summer and I guess they got 'em for some of these
         fellas with threshing machines, I imagine. They could have, you know. At
         least that's how I think that's how they got 'em. I think he had, maybe he
         furnished the water tank. But he's the daddy of the locust trees, anyway.
         That's why they're all locust. Didn't cost him anything.
         
         LM:  And they grew fast.
         
         ML:  Oh yeah. It was alright, they're a good tree.Good tree yet, if they're
         trimmed once in a while.What was it cost us? A hundred dollars. Trim ours
         last years.
         
         MRS. LONG:  These are ash trees out here. They cost a hundred dollars.
         
         ML:  They cost that much.
         
         MRS. LONG:  And that was cheap. The bank, they lost more than that for theirs Those
         are maples, I guess.
         
         LM:  People couldn't water their yards when they first came?
         Fine, I forget how much the fine was^ five or ten dollars. For hitching
         on a hose. Hitching on a hose.
         
         LM:  There was a water system but you couldn't put an outside hose?
         
         ML:  Sure there wasn't any resevoirs, there wasn't anything.In
         
         LM:  Was it water from the springs in the hills?
         
         ML:  There was this one spring up here and them springs over there. But they
         play out in summertime. Wintertime it didn't bother. Summertime they get the
         hose on, they had an old lady down there where Frank Abrams lives,Hulls, he
         run kind of a Jew store here in town, novelty store. And she'd steal water
         and everything else and they'd have her on the carpet and fine her . That
         was the biggest distraction here in town. Mrs. Hull and the city councilmen,
         that water deal.
         
         MRS. LONG:  She loved flowers.
         
         ML:  Sure. Had a beautiful home.
         
         LM:  Did your mother have flowers in those early days?
         
         ML:  Sure. She watered with, saved her washwater and stuff to water em. Just
         like it was when we lived on the ridge. You couldn't cook on a hose, so
         use washwater.
         
         LM:  What kinds of things did she have, roses?
         
         ML:  Oh sure, she had roses and haji geraniums. Seeds were planted. She had a green
         finger, that girl did.
         
         LM:  Could you get a good dry land garden? Even without water?
         
         ML:  No. You always snitched a little water, water in a sprinkling can, you know.
         Get ahold of that hose before they could put the hose on it. That time it
         was fine to put the hose on the water.
         
         LM:  What was the story of Gene Chinaman?
         
         ML:  He furnished the town. I told you that story.
         
         LM:  We should put it on the tape.
         
         ML:  Well, the town, practically the whole town looked to him for the^ fresh
         vegetables . And he run a cart. Do you know where his gardens were, don't
         you?
         
         LM: Not exactly.
         
         ML:  It's where what's her name, Alice Curtendaw lives. Well from there up that
         other, that house, is that Nickoberg's house? This side of Alice's. Nickoberg's
         house, well that wasn't there then.That is where the Chinaman had his little
         shack and grew in that back there. He grew all the vegetables for the town
         pret near. Asparagus, rhubarb.
         
         LM:  Did  take his cart door to door?
         
         ML:  Yeah.Til he left town. He never come up on the hill or nothing. went to
         you know.
         
         LM:  People liked him.
         
         ML:  Oh sure. Old Gene Chinaman, you bet.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Wasn't celery a specialty of his?
         
         ML:  Yeah. Celery. Furnished the town with celery.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Celery was a luxury then, wasn't it?
         
         ML:  Yeah, oh sure. Tis yet.
         
         LM:  What happened to Gene?
         
         ML:  Well, them Chinamens, you know, have to go back to China and die. There's
         quite a few Chinamens in Lewiston, so they finally come up and got him,
         took him, I've heard different stories, different Chinamen I knew asked
         about him. I think he was right about it, tie died going across, so he
         got to be buried in China.
         
         LM:  Was he fairly old?
         
         ML:  Yeah, he was old. Gene Chinaman.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Didn't he go blind?
         
         ML:  Yeah, practically blind. Was he dead when you come here?
         
         MRS. LONG:  No, I didn't know him.
         
         ML:  wasn't here ? He come up there one day, oh, he was mad. used to
         run the store there , I was working for him. was growing early spuds in
         spring.
         
         MRS. LONG:  What kind?
         
         ML:  Early rose. Potatoes. So give him these early potatoes alright but
         they wasn't early rose. He come back up^the store with them potatoes he
         had in his hand. Oh he was mad."Him no early rose!Him no early rose!"
         (chuckles) He was mad.
         
         LM:  What kind do you think they were?
         
         ML:  They were an early potato. But they wasn't early rose.
         But he wanted early rose. He knew what he wanted, because he was
         a Chinaman, you couldn't fool him. "Him no early rose!" Called 'em a him.
         (chuckles) Us kids used to go down and visit him. Nobody ever teased him
         for anything. He was too nice to everybody. Everybody depended on him for
         his vegetables, anything fresh. I guess you don't see them any more. Do
         they come out to this country anymore?
         
         LM:  Not too many, I don't think.
         
         ML:  Probably got the quota of 'em, maybe.
         
         LM:  I don't know.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Produce business has changed for one thing, so they don't come to the
         little towns like they used to.
         
         ML:  Are they in the bigger places?
         
         Ms. Long: Chinatowns, you know. Lots of Chinese people that ...
         
         ML:  Even these little towns, lots of times we'd have a laundry here too- Oh yeah.
         They'd come up and come from Lewiston and come up to Gene's and they'd
         run a laundry. But they never seem to get that started and make that pay
         like Gene did with his garden. People, I guess there wasn't enough people
         had laundry work done.
         
         LM:  Were there many Indians around Kendrick? Did they just come through?
         
         ML:  They just come through to shop. They come up here to trade. When we seen
         the Indians most of the time was when the summertime when they going
         back in the woods for the huckleberry season. From then on we'd have quite
         a few coming through, going up before cars and horse and buggy days. And
         half the cars had the Indian business. Go to Lewiston, I guess. They ain't
         any Indians any more, is there? Not very many. They're all Americans, ain't
         they?
         
         LM:  Well sure.
         
         ML:  That's what Imean. They live like the Americans) This young
         generation, do the things I guess they do. We don't see !em any more. They
         used to come through, they come up here to trade because it was easier to
         come up with teams to Kendrick than it would to go to Lewiston. With their
         teams. I think that was the reason of it. Course, they got cars. You never
         see Indians anymore, for their trade territory. Only when they're going
         through to huckleberry. There psed to be quite a few Indian families between
         Juliaetta and there. Lot of Indians down there. They'd come up here and trade.
         That's rawhide, huh? I guess they hld better than rawhide don't they(the
         transcriber is not sure what this conversation concerns)
         
         LM:  What were prices when you first went into dry goods? What would clothes
         cost?
         
         ML:  When I  went in?
         
         LM:  What would a pair of boots cost?
         
         ML:  Well, you could buy a pretty good pair of shoes, when they got up past five
         dollars why, you were losing too much money. To sell 'em. We used to sell
         quite a few. Course, with the other stores, the dress shoes or cheaper ones
         were three and a half. But good shoes never got much below five dollars,
         like Florishiem and things like that, the better make of shoes. That is the
         lowest .What are they now, twenty five dollars?
         
         LM:  At least that. How about shirts and things like that?
         
         ML:  I don't think it's too much difference there. I don't know what a good shirt
         costs now.
         
         LM:  They're up eight and ten dollars now. Or more.
         
         ML:  Well I imagine shirts, a good shirt, we used to put out a pretty good shirt
         for a dollar ninety five cents. But they wasn't as good as the shirts made
         nowadays. People didn't have the money, they weren't after the high price
         merchandise . Gosh, I don't know. I'd hate to be running the store now.
         I don't see how Brayden makes it over there. That stock.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Didn't you sell lots of suits that you took orders for in those days?
         Men's suits?
         
         ML:  Well, we had clothing when I had Beckwith's store. When we used to work
         with them, First Kendrick Store Company. We carried about three hundred
         suits.
         
         LM:  Tell about the time President Taft came to town.
         
         ML:  (chuckles) Didn't I ever tell you that? Story?
         
         LM:  Tell it for the tape.
         
         ML:  Well, them days the trains always carried the, passenger trains, the last
         car was the, what do you call them?
         
         MRS. LONG:  Observation.
         
         ML:  Observation cars. And they had a platform in the back where you could go
         out and look at the country coming through or a train stop. When he come
         through, he come out the car onto this bleekends, rearend of this train.
         Start giving his speech and he was about half asleep, he sounded like it.
         He says,"When I come up through this beautiful valley of yours, this
         country, with all the fruit trees and everything." I don't think he ever
         looked out because there wouldn't be very many fruit trees between here and
         Lewiston. This time there was one big orchard right out of Lewiston. And ,
         north of Lewiston there, and he says,"It just made me feel like a big,red,
         apple." (laughs) He was a big pet gut belly , you've seen a picture of him
         haven't you? "I feel just like a big red apple". Speaking of presidents, what
         I remember most about seeing President Theodore Roosevelt come^to Moscow
         and of course, they let out anybody could go that could go. Up to cheer him.
         And we heard him speak on top of that, he had a great, big, that's the
         reason, it was fall, a great big stack of wheat in sacks. Sacked wheat. And
         I can remember that, piled in. That was the platform he spoke from this
         platform, Roosevelt did. That's what I remember about him.
         
         Ms. Long: That was Teddy Roosevelt.
         
         ML:  Yeah.
         
         LM:  Did you ride the train up?
         
         ML:  Yeah. Oh sure. We went to Moscow Lewiston because we could go up
         Moscow in the morning on the 9 o'clock and come back at night train. And
         you could have a whole day up there. Get back down here about 9 o'clock.
         9-10 o'clock. Come from Lewiston up here, you come up on the 9 o'clock, well
         quite a few people come and the Indians come trade, but unless they waited
         for the night train, theyA have to go back over here about 12 o'clock to
         catch the train going back. This one come up 4 o'clock in the evening.
         
         LM:  Would it cost very much? To ride to Moscow?
         
         ML:  I think it was a little less than a dollar, if I can remember right. Around
         a dollar, pretty close to a dollar.
         
         LM:  So you still didn't do it real often?
         
         ML:  You're darn right you didn't do it real often. You didn't have the money to
         do a lot of things real often.(laughs) But them days it's different. Now,
         you wait til you need a pair of shoes, you go and buy a pair of shoes- You
         wait til you need a shirt, you go and buy a shirt. But them days, you went
         and bought your two seasons, you bought up clothes. You fixed up
         for the fall and you fixed up for the summer, the spring. That was the end
         of our shopping. There wasn't any more shopping.Yep. Most people, kids I
         run with and everything, got all stuff from mail or Osburn. We never had any
         luck buying from a mailorder house. If we bought anything we'd have to send
         it back, wouldn't fit or something. I know one time mother couldn't get her
         own stuff the fall. She only tried it once. I don't think they do
         the mail order business they used to, do they?
         
         LM:  It's pretty big.
         
         ML:  It is? YOu couldn't tell it down at the post office.It ain't like it was
         in those days.
         
         LM:  You can't get as many different things.
         
         ML:  You can't?
         
         LM:  They sold a bunch of wagons down there, tools and everything then.
         
         ML:  They don't anymore, huh?
         
         LM: Not as much as that.
         
         ML:  They ain't sold, them things ain't sold.
         
         LM:  What was the stCiry about the blacksmith when you were a little boy?
         
         ML:  Fella name of Hodges, he was a widower. And boarded at our place. And I
         used to stick around, we was pretty good pals and I was just a kid. He give
         me a job, I'd make, them days there was a lot of wagon and hack work, you
         know. Tightening up wheels and they made wedges. I don't know what they
         called that. Wheel wedges, spoke wedges for . What they put spokes
         in on the rim, they put them wedges in there to tighten it. They put the,
         what do you call it?
         
         LM:  Tire?
         
         ML:  Tire, steel tire. And I used to go over there and make these hardwood wedges.
         By hand you know, we'd saw 'em off. You saw 'em in blocks. With a draw
         knife I'd make these wedges. He'd pay me by the hundred.
         
         LM:  How many would you make in a day?
         
         ML:  I don't know. I don't remember that. I made quite a few, I made 'em til I
         got tired. I imagine a hundred maybe. Maybe two hundred. I don't remember,
         
         LM:  You were still in Leland then?
         
         ML:  Yeah. I was in all kinds of business.
         
         MRS. LONG:  What about the toys that man made, that blacksmith?
         
         ML:  Oh yeah, he was a clown and he'd black himself up, you know, and he was
         really a clown. He was a good one too. He made this doll, wooden doll and
         jointed the legs and the arms and he put this thing on a board, after he
         made it. And he had an old board in back of it. And a handle put on him
         so he could hold this. He'd hold it with one hand out on this board and
         he'd kind of make it dance by hitting that board with a hammer or something
         maybe. Make that thing, oh boy, he'd really make that thing dance, It was
         cute, it was really showy. He was always clowning, he was. He was a character.
         
         LM:  He liked kids?
         
         ML:  Oh he loved 'em. They all loved him too. He didn't have any kids of his
         own.
         
         LM:  Was he older?
         
         ML:  Oh yeah, he was grown, married, he married one, finally, I don't know whether
         he was married before he come to Leland or not^ but then he married one of
         the Huffman girls. Up here on the hill. She died and then he never got
         married again after that. I think, there isn't any names or any people left
         up there anymore. All them people used to be around Leland. One or two farmers
         own it all.
         
         LM:  What all was in Leland when you lived there?
         
         ML:  Be easier to tell you what business wasn't there.
         
         LM:  Just everything.
         
         ML:  Well, there was a big general store and it was big as anything in Kendrick.
         And there was one time there was two hardwares up there,
         hut they was always a hardware store and they sold machinery. And there was
         a drugstore. And a butcher shop, we had the butcher shop.And a big general
         store. And sometimes there was another store, but the only one that 
         that had the business that made it there,
         pile of money there. And the flour mill made flour there. Van Pelt mill.
         You've probably heard of that.
         
         LM:  You told about his phone.
         
         ML:  Yeah, that's the reason he had this phone. To keep the market on the wheat.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Was there a barbershop?
         
         ML:  Yeah, at one time. I guess there was.
         
         MRS. LONG:  Doctors, dentist?
         
         ML:  Two saloons at one time.
         
         LM:  Churches?
         
         ML:  Three churches at one time. UB church never got started hardly. Never got
         going Democrats on one side of the street and Republicans on the other.
         That's a fact.
         
         LM:  Which one were you going to?
         
         ML:  What do you think? I'll let you set your mind on it. My dad would turn over
         in his grave. He was going over north Methodist church. See they were north
         and south. One was on the south side of the street, one was on the north.
         One catered to the niggers and the other didn't. Didn't
         nigger That's right though, they was all Republicans down there at
         the North Church, South Methodist was all Democrats. Well, just the same
         way it is yet, it, north and south is.
         
         LM:  I bet it's changing.
         
         ML:  Not in the south I bet it ain't changing.
         
         LM:  There's democrats in the south.
         
         ML:  They's democrats. Republicansjdon't see they're elected do you? What do
         you think of our president? Is he going to make it again?
         Kind of shaky.
         
         Who's going to run against him?
         I don't know. I'm waiting for Sen. Church.
         I know, but he won't, Church would be on the Democrat^ ticket. He won't have
         no trouble in the primary.
         
         LM: They're not sure about that.
         
         MRS. LONG:  It was pretty close in New Hampshire.(Break in tape)
         
         LM:  ...when you were a kid.
         
         ML:  When I was a kid, when I first come to Kendrick, there was a post office
         at Leland, one at Cameron, one at Southwick, one at Cavendish and one at
         Tekan. How many's that?
         
         MRS. LONG:  Five. And Teakan. And then there was Linden and Crescent and Park. There's
         three more. Is that eight. Them was all post offices.
         
         LM:  Were those little ones just in somebody's house?
         
         ML:  Yeah, they were all practically in the houseS. Some places had store in them
         places.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13668</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Long_F2</previous>
      <next>Long_Martha1</next>
      <disp_name>Long_F3</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
