<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">8/6/1973</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Carl Olson, 1973-08-06, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:31:30</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Olson, Carl</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Thresherman; operator of gas station and car dealership; sawmiller; miner; Troy
         councilman for 24 years
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1895</birthyear>
      <residence>Dry Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents emigrated from Sweden and homesteaded (1889)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mining"&gt;mining&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#forest fires"&gt;forest fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mining"&gt;mining&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Dry Ridge"&gt;Dry Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Park"&gt;Park&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13596</file_name>
      <mp3>13597.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13597.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Parents immigrated from Sweden; The course of history</title>
            <synopsis>Parents come from Sweden to escape "militarists, capitalism, and religion," Course
               of history from feudalism to monarchy to democracy. Capitalism failing because all
               land is taken, small business is dying, unions are striking. Inflation wipes out savings.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Parent's work in Sweden; Caring for the elderly</title>
            <synopsis>Parents farmed and logged in Sweden. Poor care for elderly in America. Poorhouses.
               The way to take care of the country is to take care of the people. Taxing homes.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Crossing the ocean in steerage; Homesteading in Idaho</title>
            <synopsis>Parents cross ocean in steerage. They choose Idaho over prairies. Locators help them
               find a homestead. Deadening trees to clear land.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Naming locations; Game hunting without wardens</title>
            <synopsis>People give names to places to identify them. Country reminds mother of Sweden. Shooting
               game with no wardens. Deer shot out, the meat sold in Moscow.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Timber industry ravaged the land; Controlling slope farming</title>
            <synopsis>Cutting of timber caused erosion, and drying-up of creeks. Farming on steep slopes
               must be controlled. The country close to being ruined.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Hiking to Troy from Dry Ridge barefoot</title>
            <synopsis>Carl doesn't get to Troy from Dry Ridge until he's 10. The long hike, barefooted,
               carrying butter. It never used to be windy.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Getting by on the homestead</title>
            <synopsis>Getting by on the homestead. Making clothes; growing food. Confusion when round nails
               replaced square nails. Brickmaking at home. Making sleds and skis; selling coyote
               hides.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>His brother Albert was nearly stumped</title>
            <synopsis>Albert, his brother, an expert mechanic, is nearly stumped.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Troy was a major shipping town in early days</title>
            <synopsis>Early Troy. People work at splitting ties, harvesting, sawmills, winter hauling, farming.
               Troy a major shipping town.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Accidents and deaths in Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Mean Marshall Hays killed mixing in a domestic scrap. Drunks celebrate his death.
               He arrests a man with a bad back and his own son. Other Troy killings.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3000</time>
            <title>Dealing with local criminals</title>
            <synopsis>A suspected pig stealer is threatened with hanging. Criminals were known locally.
               A homesteader disappears, and the kidnappers take his place.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Stories about "Big Anderson," the giant</title>
            <synopsis>Big Anderson, the giant. He whips his would-be kidnappers. He carries a huge log.
               Walks with two canes, because of a festering sore. Looks like an animal, scaring kids
               and dogs. His perpetual motion machine.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Exploits of the fool from Park</title>
            <synopsis>The fool from Park who mines where a tree points, He hauls his worthless rock back
               from Moscow. He thinks all guns have the same caliber.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3660</time>
            <title>Wild Bill is unmasked by a phoney cougar</title>
            <synopsis>Wild Bill, a phony hunter, is unmasked by a phony cougar.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3780</time>
            <title>Carls' father meets drunken Native Americans; Keeping the ridge clear of brush</title>
            <synopsis>Carl's aunt believes his father shot a dozen Indians to get citizenship. Father meets
               drunk Indians. They kept ridges clear of brush by burning. How Park got its name.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Word about Troy spreads to Swedes in Minnesota; Speaking Swedish</title>
            <synopsis>Per Johanson spreads word about Troy area to Swedes in Minnesota. Different Swedish
               dialects. Carl speaks only Swedish until he goes to school.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Playing barefoot in the snow; taking care of shoes in the winter</title>
            <synopsis>Olson kids play barefoot in the snow. Shoes get stiff, are greased with tar made from
               tamarack root.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4380</time>
            <title>Locals react to the 1910 fires; Timber from the fields was wasted</title>
            <synopsis>Local people not too worried by 1910 fires; few timber fires here. Timber cleared
               for fields largely wasted, other timber used.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Vollmer lends money at a high interest rate; Vollmer's legacy</title>
            <synopsis>Vollmer lends money at high interest, and towns don't like to be named after him.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Swedish women work milking cows and in fields</title>
            <synopsis>Swedish women work milking cows and in fields.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4920</time>
            <title>History of the Olson boys' mine; working the mine</title>
            <synopsis>Copper Chief, the Olson boys' mine. Its prior history: Cox, its first owner. "One
               day closer to the grave and I feel like greeting," another miner always tells them.
               Working the mine. Never hit pay dirt.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Legendary local characters. Why parents left Sweden; Varmlanders ;come to Troy.
         Getting by on the homestead. Family copper mine and brickmaking. Neighborhood criminals.
         Decline of opportunity; ruin of country by erosion. 8-6-73 1.5 hr 37p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: I think the first thing I was thinking of asking you, was why
         your parents decided to leave Sweden, and come to America?
         
         CARL OLSON: Oh. Well, I don't know if I should put that on the tape or not.
         
         SS:  Oh, its okay. No, do, do.
         
         CO:  Well, they come here for to get away from the militarists, capitalism, and
         religion. That sounds pretty bad, you know, in our country, don't it? Well,
         I'll tell you why religion is here. They run the country at that time. And
         the church had power over us, somethin' like the Catholics had, y'know. But
         they started breakin' away when they left, so now religion is just like it
         is here now, you know. Well, there was one kind there then. And you had
         to go to church, you had to do everything, y'know. They were boss, y'know.
         Practically run the country. And then the militarism. You didn't believe
         in wars, I guess—not very many fellers believes in that. But that's one
         reason. (He gets a picture.) See there, it was like it is here now, y'know—
         you're forced to go in the army. There my dad is. That'"was when he was
         in the army, see, in Sweden.
         
         SS:  Hm. So he had to serve?
         
         CO:  Yeh (chuckles). I don't know how, they went so two or three years, but
         it wasn't very long each year, I don't believe. I don't know for sure how
         long they had to, I think they had to spend a couple of years, anyway.
         
         SS:  What about the capitalism that you say?
         
         CO:  Well, you know, all the people were poor there, you know. They didn't
         have nothing. It was a pretty poor country, you know. Rocky, and just like
         goin' up in the mountains here maybe, y'know, about the same thing, where
         my folks come from. 'Course down there around Stockholm and down there, it
         was fairly good land, y'know. But that was all taken up. All the people
         owned that. And then, you know, the system was over there just like what
         they called it feudalism, if you ever know what that is. Well, if there was a
         family there, and when they died, the oldest boy got everything, see. The
         others didn't get nothing. And that's why it growed that way, you see, you
         got bigger and bigger and bigger estates. And that's the way it worked in
         Sweden at that time. But that isn't there no more, either. Feudalism died
         out, y'know, finally. They had slaves to do all their work, y'know. I
         think capitalism is on the way out too. Don't you?
         
         SS:  It wouldn't surprise me a bit.
         
         CO:  Well, here. If you go back in history, you know. First there was the real
         slaves, y'know. There was nothin' but slaves that worked for the people.
         Well, that come under the feudalism system, too. And that went on then, so
         long as there was room enough for the people, y'know, to live. And when that
         got too tough, then they got a rebellion, and they took it over. Then the
         kings come in and ruled, see, all over Europe—the kings ruled after that,
         after the feudalism did. And then the kings got taken out, so they went
         into democracy Row, you see, of course;-3 and it's capitalism here now, 100.
         And it can't last for these reasons. When they settled the United States,
         they settled on the East Coast, y'know. And when it got too tough for the
         people there, they kept moving west, see? They'd take a homestead and so
         forth, and they'd have a store, or a little sawmill. And all such, it was
         a future for them to go through, see. It's none here now, you know that.
         The small businesses are dying out all the time. The big chain store is
         takin' all the business, and big factories are takin' all the business there.
         And the big farms, you know where they're goin'—10,000 acres, you know, 2-
         3,000 acres. Where are you gonna go? It's just a job, that's all you got.
         And that's gettin1 so rotten, that the union are ruining that now, y'know.
         Sure, go on strike, strike, strike, that's what caused the inflation now.
         If there're anything you're gonna guide, it's to guide the wages. I believed
         in the~when I was young, y'know, I believed in the union awful, because when
         I went out and worked, I had to carry my own bed, and sleep in an old bunkhouse
         see? No baths or nothin', y'know. Dust lay there, and stunk in them
         from the sweaty feet, y'know, they'd hang the socks up (chuckles). You couldn't
         hardly sleep from the stink. So they cleaned that up, y'see, the union. But
         now there gettin' so big that they're startin' to ruin the country. Ruin
         ing it, for the strikes. You know just as well as I do, there is a saturation
         point on everything, isn't it? It costs so much to make somethin*, and then
         your price is set there. Well then, if they strike, then that thing is gonna
         cost more. So they don't gain anything! when they buy it back, their
         money goes back, see. And what to do then? So, all I heard around here,
         "Save your money, save your money, so you don't go in the poorhouse," and
         so forth. What's the use in saving money if it's gonna go like this, now?
         The money I saved when I was young, two years, be wiped out.
         
         SS:  What you're saying is that the way it is here, it reminds you of the way
         it used to be in Sweden, when it made your parents come over here.
         
         CO:  Yah. So you see how that is. And that's the way it was over there at
         that time, because that country was settled all over, y'know, full of people,
         see, and there was no other place to go.
         
         SS:  Did your parents have a farm of their own over there?
         
         CO:  Oh, they had a little bit, y'know. They didn't have many acres, y'know.
         They had a coupla cows, and they used the old scythe, y'know, to cut the hay
         with. They didn't do any thrashing or anything like that, because, what,
         they didn't have fields enough, most of them. And that's the way they lived
         there, you see.
         
         SS:  Do you know if he had to hire out and work for bigger farmers?
         
         CO:  Oh well, they worked up north. I don't know if my dad did, but he was
         pretty young, y'know. He was only 22 years old when he come here. But they
         went north and done some logging, y'know, in the winter, and worked. But
         then, that wasn't very big, very much for all of them to do, you know. And
         it was pretty tough, too, y'know, when you get up north there. It's colder,
         and the days are short, and you can't put in more than five, six hours and
         it's dark, y'know. So they used to tell about that a whole lot. They floated
         the logs down the creeks, y'know, to the mills, and so on.
         
         But now Sweden has got a pretty good government, y'know. It's pretty
         good. You're taken care of 100 there, 100. If you ain't got a home to
         live in when you get old, they got a home for you. You ain't no villas
         and stuff like they have here, that pokes in a whole lot of sick people.
         Everybody thought that was so darn good, y'know, here, but it's no good.
         It's good, better'n nothing, y'know. But when the people gets broke, or he
         gets so he can't work, he's got to live somewheres. Well, then they poke
         him into those big homes, you see. And there's half-crazy people in there,
         and there's everything in there. They can't, they don't want to live that
         way. You wouldn't want to either, if you have pretty good shape, y'know.
         Well, they poke 'em all in one bunch. They shouldn't do that. You should
         have a, they should have a little house for 'em. And then have a house
         like they got here, and then put the people in that's got to be taken care
         of. Then they can live the way they want to. But before they only had a
         poorhouse here. You don't remember that, I guess? They had an old building,
         y'know, and they'd poke 'em in there, and it was ragged, and half starved to
         death, and fighting and quarreling all the time.
         
         SS:  They had those out here too?
         
         CO:  Yeh. I talked to a feller that come from down South. They had a poor
         house there, he said (chuckles). They had one out in the desert, y'know.
         There they got all kinds of people in it, he said. They got miners and
         farmers. And they were quarreling and fighting all the time, he said.
         And they'd run away, and then they had to run and find them, you know—
         mix up, you see, like that. That ain't no way to take care of people. My
         way of taking care of a country is two things they have to do. One thing
         they have to do is take care of the people. And if you take care of the
         people, the people will take care of the country. You'll never have any
         trouble in the country. And that's the whole secret. 'Course they're gettin'
         there a little better now, than they used to be here. Now we got Social
         Security and all else, y'know, that's pretty good. If they wouldn't have
         Social Security, you'd have to build 15, 20 houses like they got in Moscow
         to take care of the people. You'd be all broke. Well, you can see it your
         self. The inflation'd took all their money, see. See? You got to regulate
         things, 'til you got somethin' to jo by, the people. And that's why the
         young people, they don't know what they want today. They run all over and
         they don't know what they're lookin' for, because there's no future, you
         see. Dob, that's all it is left. And then the old tax system they got here.
         Tax your home. If you don't own a home, you don't own nothin'. You don't
         own it now, you're just leasing it. Paying so much a year to live in it,
         don't you? Taxes, that's same as a lease. Now they're getting so, well,
         we're paying 525 on this little thing here, taxes alone. Then we get an
         empty building, what happens? You lose it, or else pay taxes on an empty
         thing that there's no income from. That's what happened in the last depression,
         that's before you were born. Big building in Moscow there, y'know, a feller
         had named David, y'know, four stories high. Lost it on taxes. Then it was
         4,000 taxes against it, and 4,000 then was same as 50,000 now, pretty near,
         y'know. So he couldn't pay it, and it sold on a tax sale. Pret' near
         everybody that had an apartment house in the '30's lost, lost 'em. Because
         the people that lived in the apartment houses couldn't pay the rent, see.
         And you couldn't kick 'em out. They had to keep 'em there. And they didn't
         get enough money to pay the rent on the damn thing, and keep it up. Rich
         people, millionaires went broke on having apartment houses. No, I'll tell
         ya, there's a lot of stuff here that's got to be corrected, if they ain't
         gonna lose the country.
         
         SS:  Let's go back and start with your parents coming over here...
         
         CO:  Well, they come over here in 1897. Come on a boat. They were six weeks
         on the ocean. And they had to come in what they called the steerage, that
         was the cheapest rate, y'know. And they lived way down in the boat then,
         you see. There's where she rocks. See, we get up here in the boat, on this,
         it doesn't rock so much there. Y'get way up, then it rocks again. So all
         the people that had money, they always took that place, you know. But that
         was a whole lot, co»st a whole lot. But they had to take steerage, way down
         the bottom. And they feed them, fed 'em, all right, but they had black coffee,
         my mother said, and a little bread, and that's about all. And the storm come
         up, and that old ship was goin' like that (tipping hand), and it laid over.
         They never thought they's goin' to make it across at all. And then when they
         got to Minnesota, my mother stayed there, and my dad come out here a year
         ahead, and took the homestead, y'know. And then when they come here, why
         it was no railroad here. It ended in Moscow. And he had to pack everything
         on his back from Moscow, that's 22 miles out to the ranch, and so forth.
         
         SS:  How did he happen to come to Idaho? Do you know?
         
         CO:  Well, it's because there was land to take here, you see. See, a lot of
         the Eastern stuff were taken. And it was some left on the prairie, just like
         Dakotas, ya know. But it's cold and windy, and no timber or no nothin', see.
         They couldn't even build themselves a home there, unless ya had money to buy
         lumber, see. But here you had the timber, see, and you could make a log
         cabin. That's what my folks did. They lived in that, y'see. And then you
         had firewood. So you see, it was whole lot of advantage to comin' out here,
         than go on the prairie in those days, unless you had the money, so you could
         build yourself a good home. And that's the reason they come out here, it
         was. They could've homesteaded in Nebraska, and Kansas, was quite a bit of
         land there, and in Montana, y'know, too. But prairie land, and cold winters,
         and blizzards so you couldn't see 50 feet, even. My mother said, when they
         stayed with their relatives there in Minneapolis—not- Minneapolis, but out of
         Minneapolis—the barn was about 150 feet away from the house, y'know. And
         they had to have a wire, and a rig to take ahold of, when they went out and
         fed the cattle in the winter, because if you didn't, you couldn't find your
         house. You had to take ahold of that thing and slide on the wire, to guide
         you (chuckles). Yeh. My mother said they done that when they stayed over
         there. They had to when a storm come up, they had to catch that rig and go
         out and milk your cows, and take ahold of it, and come back to the house.
         
         SS:  How did your father happen to find the homestead that he found? Do you
         know?
         
         CO:  Here?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         CO:  Well, they surveyed the country, you know, and then they had locators, they
         called 'em. See, you'd stay in Moscow, y'know. And maybe they wanted five
         or ten dollars to go out and find a place for you that isn't taken. That's
         the way they found them, see, they had a map then. Then they'd mark on the
         map this is taken, and this is taken. And when the next man come, they know
         where to go with him, you see. That's the way it worked out. I don't know
         if they paid those locators anything or not. Maybe the government had 'em,
         y'know, free of charge. I don't know about that for sure. But I guess they
         had 'em free all right, maybe, so that you could help 'em out, y'know, to
         find a homestead. 'Cause the country, at that time, they want to grow, you
         know, so they helped the people quite a bit, that way.
         
         SS:  Were there many farms around him when...
         
         CO:  Well, after you get to the divide here, they call't, between here and Mos
         cow, that's halfways between here and Moscow. On that side was quite a few
         farms, Genesee country and all that, because that was open country, so you
         could get field quite quick, y'know, was no timber there, you know—all open.
         But here, in here was timber all over, just like you see it there now. That
         took quite awhile, y'know, to get a piece of field. You had to cut the trees
         down and let *em...You ringed the trees, they called 'em, big yellow pines
         like that? You'd take the ax and they'd cut a ring around it, cut the bark
         off, y'know, and then they'd die. That's the way, and then they died. When
         they got dry, then they bored a hole in 'em, and set a fire in 'em, and burned
         'em down. That's the way they burned the tree up, too—all the way, a big
         tree down. They'd bore a hole this way, and then they'd bore one here, and
         they'd come together. And then they'd put some coals in there, and had the
         little bellow out here, see, to start the fire. And then when you got it
         started, it burned that log up, see. That hole here was the smokestack in
         other words, see. That's the way they cleared land. And then they used a
         lot o'timbers to make fences with, if you had a lot of it. They'd fall trees
         down, to keep the cows (chuckles) from running away. See, it was pret'near
         that high, and then the limbs, you know, and the cows couldn't get through.
         
         SS:  When did that area come by the name of Little Sweden?
         
         CO:  Well, there was so many Swedes here, that's why. They named it that, the
         people. You had names for everything in those days, y'know. You made 'em
         yourself, because the country wasn't settled. Now you say Moscow, and Troy
         road, and this road, and so forth, and Genesee country and that, y'see. And
         that's the way they had to name the stuff, so they'd know where they were,
         the people. See, we had names on everything on our farms. So when we talked
         to each other, we'd know where the folks were, or where they were goin'.
         Like the Big Point, the Little Point, the Mining Point, we had, that's our
         names now. East Around, North Hill, and North-up-in-the-Lane, we said—
         that's a road that runs there. If a man was comin*, we'd say, "There's a man
         comin', North-in-the-Lane," and all that. And named like that all over.
         That's the way they named. And the Mining Hill—where we had that mine, that
         was the Mining Hill. It was hills, y'know, that run out kinda ridgy, see.
         They named 'em Big Ridge, and Little Ridge, and all that stuff, so that they
         knew where they were. And that's the way all these other names were, y'know.
         Now, now we talk about people. Well, we had a neighbor August-by-the-Creek,
         see. See, he lived by the creek, and that's the way we'd know what or who
         they were talkin' about. So on, and all that kind of stuff.
         
         SS:  So what were the first years like for your parents out here?
         
         CO:  First years?
         
         SS:  First years.
         
         CO:  Oh, they were tough. Very tough. Because, well, it wasn't too bad after
         one year, because next year the railroad come, y'know. My dad worked on the
         railroad. So he made a little money that way, so he could buy a little stuff,
         But else it was pretty tough. I asked my mother why she didn't go back to
         Sweden? "Well," she said, "this country looks so much like Sweden, so we
         didn't get homesick." Because the living wasn't any better here then
         it was in Sweden, you see. 'Cause they had to start with nothing. Yuh.
         
         SS:  So it really reminded her of Sweden, this country?
         
         CO:  Yeh, it reminded her of the hills, you know, and the timber. Y'see, where
         we live out there, where we lived, it's pretty hilly country, you know. But
         it isn't sharp hills, it's big ones, you know, so they have big fields on all
         of it now. And canyons and draws, you know. And then there's a big creek
         run below our place, that we used to fish in all the time. then when
         we got enough money to get a gun, then we'd shoot a lot of grouse, y'know,
         to eat. We had a lot of blue grouse down there, canyon. We was huntin* all
         the time, y'know, fishing all the time, the creek too. No, no, no gamewarden
         to fool with you. You'd shoot all you could. My brother shot three birds
         with one shot one time, y'know. Three blue grouse. And then catch all the
         fish we could. Nobody to look at your basket like they do now. So that
         helped quite a bit. But the deer, they were shot out pretty fast. It was
         deer in here, y'know, but they bought the deer for 5 apiece, y'know. And
         those fellers had guns. They made a livin' that way so long as they could
         catch. They'd shoot 'em and take into Moscow and sell 'em for f5. So the
         deer was cleaned out pretty good when I grew up, there wasn't hardly any.
         But there's a lot of deer here now though, again.
         
         SS:  Yep.
         
         CO:  They move and go back, see, when they start loggin' in the mountains, then
         they scared 'em back. That's why they're here now. And then they a got limit
         on 'em, you know. You can't shoot more'n one.
         
         SS:  Tell roe how the country was different then in the woods then they are now.
         
         CO:  Different? How you mean?
         
         SS:  How it's changed. Well, when we were talking before, you were explaining
         to me why the creeks used to run, oh let's say year round?
         
         CO:  Well, that's because they didn't cut the timber off. See, the timber is
         cut off now all over. And the snow goes off right away, and the creeksJ  get
         way up, y'know, in the spring. Flows off. This creek here used to run all
         year, y'know. (Westfork Little Bear Creek, in Troy.) This isn't very big,
         y'know, but it'd be about this wide and this deep all year round. There was
         fish in it all the time. Now it isn't a drop of water in it, now. This year
         is awful dry anyway, but...That's what raised the hell, y'see. When the tim
         ber got cut off, and a little wind come, then the snow'd go just like that,
         y'know. Chinook wind will take it all off, y'know, 'cause there's nothin'
         to protect it but when the timber was there, then snow fell between the
         timber, and there was shade around them all the time. Up on Moscow Mountain
         there, the snow would lay off 'til Duly, y'know, before it was all gone.
         
         SS:  So the runoff was a lot more even.
         
         CO:  Yeh. Even all the time, see. Never got real, like it does now. You can
         see, in the spring when they get quite a bit of snow here, you go down and
         look at these creeks, and it's just pure mud comin' down. In those days the
         water was just as clear as a crystal. (Chuckles.) So now the country is go
         ing away too, y'know, on the top of it. You can imagine that this country
         isn't a hundred years old yet. And you go out and look and see what's happen
         ing to it. Go out in the fields in the spring, there'd be ditches this deep
         all over. Mud, topsoil is goin' away. That's somethin' they have to stop
         too; 'course they're workin' on that quite a bit now. I tell you they should
         change the way of farming. You take a steep side hill, y'know, you should
         plant grass on that, and hay. Don't put wheat on it, y'know. They put wheat
         on everything, the easiest way to farm, y'know. Well, we get a lot of rain,
         and, why heck, ditches this deep, and a foot apart maybe, just like the hill
         over here now, heck. All of it goes down in the creek. And it's only a
         hundred years old, so you know how fast it's deteriorating. Y'know, they had,
         when the farmers got so caught up here in the Depression days, you know, then
         they paid the farmer for not puttin' in any wheat, you know, 'cause they had
         too much. But then they didn't tell 'em what land to put out. So some fellers
         that had a little money, they went and bought land all over, no matter how
         it looked. And then they turned that in, you know, and drawed money on it,
         see. Instead of that, they shoulda told the farmers that, and paid 'em a
         little more money, and said, "Now this side hill, you take that out. Don't
         farm this, because here's where we lose the mud, you know." They had no
         regulation like that, see. It is the country they thought they never could
         ruin, but we are not far away from it, unless they change. We're running out
         of water everywheres too, now. Troy is pretty near out of water now, Lewiston,
         everywhere. No, I don't know.
         
         SS:  Let's go back to when you were a kid, and what you remember from then—
         from being a little boy on the farm, and what the life was like when it was
         just a homestead.
         
         CO:  Well, it ain't much to say there, because we didn't see much. I didn't see
         a town 'til I was 10 years old. I didn't know what a town was, 'cause we only
         had three horses on the place, and you couldn't get everybody to ride a horsethere
         wasn't enough. Ten, 12, kids, and three horses, y'know (chuckles).
         
         And it was nine miles, that's quite a hike. But when I got about 10 years
         old, we used to hike to town, y'know, and carry butter. And sell, y'know,
         sell the butter. And some days it was so hot, when we got to town, the butter
         was melted. Then we carried eggs, too. And then walk in dust this deep.
         There was no rock roads then, y'know. The farmers rode up and down with their
         wagons, y'know, and dust was this deep. Hot there, burn your feet off and
         go barefooted beside, because we didn't have enough shoes. So it wasn't any
         fun.
         
         SS:  Were the first winters really hard?
         
         CO:  No, they were pretty easy, it wasn't too bad. The winter was pretty good
         here. We never had any wind, y'know. And in Minnesota there, they had so
         much wind. They wrote back here and asked how the wind was. "Oh heck,"
         they wrote back and told them, "you can throw your hat on the roof, and it
         lay there all year!" But you can't do it now since the timber is cut off.
         Didn't blow at all hardly then, y'know, the timber stopped it in here. 'Course
         down around Moscow, they had a little breeze, I guess, but up here you didn't
         have any.
         
         (End of Side A.)
         
         SS:  Well, how was your father making a living?
         
         CO:  How he made a livin'? Well, it isn't so tough as it looks, because we
         live different now. There's a lot of kids in our family, y'see. So when
         one of them grew out of his clothes, the next kid wore it. So we had patches
         on everything, y'know, more before we throwed 'em away. They were real wore
         out, y'know. And the same with the shoes, see, the next one, next one. My
         mother, she made the clothes, she had a sewing machine, y'know. And she
         bought the cloth, and sewed our pants, and shirts, and everything. And you
         could buy cloth for15 cents a yard then, y'know, that is, shirt stuff. And
         for overalls I guess it was maybe 25 cents, maybe, a yard. So you could
         make a pair of pants for two bits, and you sewed it yourself, y'know. And
         then we raised our own food, spuds and everything, y'know, and had a little
         orchard down there, too. But then you had to wait two, three years before
         that would bear. And then we had chickens, and eggs to sell. We didn't get
         to eat too much eggs, because we had to sell them, for groceries, to get
         sugar and stuff like that. And they all were pret'near in the same pickle,
         y'know, with nobady that had any too much.
         
         SS:  What jobs was your father doing then?
         
         CO:  Oh, he worked out quite a bit. He was a carpenter, y'know, and a brick
         layer—not an expert bricklayer, but he laid the brick in the chimneys and
         stuff like that, see. And then we had a little brickyard home, so we made
         brick, and we sold them for a cent apiece. We didn't sell too many, but we
         sold quite a few to the neighbors, y'know, where they have the chimney in
         their house. Get the old stovepipe out, because that was a hazard to have
         a stovepipe, because you might burn up your house, y'know. So they all put
         in chimneys. And then he was pretty good with that broadax, y'know, cut
         your log and make it about that wide, y'know. And then he'd dovetail 'em
         together in the corners. And they'd cut and make their own shingles. Get
         a knife, you know, big, long, like this. And then they had a wooden club,
         they'd hit that, knock off a shingle, see.
         
         But the nails, you had to buy the nails, you couldn't make them.
         
         (Chuckles.) And I remember, the nails when they first come out, they were
         square, you know. I don't know if you ever seen any, have you? Yah. So my
         dad, he sent the older brother to get, buy some nails, y'know. So he gave them
         a sample of how big it should be, y'know, so they wouldn't forget. And they
         went down to the store. Then the round nails had come out. And the kids
         didn't buy any nails then. They come home, and told my dad that they didn't
         have any nails.. They told him they had the round ones only (chuckles). So
         they had to go back and get some round nails. They were made of cast iron,
         I believe, then. Square ones, most of them. They'd break easy. I don't
         how they made 'em, those days. They tapered all the way, you know, them
         square nails, they called 'em. But the round nails, they was sharp on the
         end a little, y'know.
         
         SS:  Did you say that you made your own bricks?
         
         CO:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  How did you do that?
         
         CO:  Well, we had, your rig was about this big square, see (about five feet).
         And then in the middle of it, run a pole down. And you took old iron rods
         and stuff, and drove in that pole, see, all over, see. And then they had a
         sweep on it here, and a horse out there. The horse walked around this thing,
         mixed the mud, y'see. One of us would throw the mud in, and the other one
         stand there and take it when it come out, and throw it in the mold, see.
         Catch it by your hand, and throw it in the mold. Five, I think it made five
         brick at a time in that mold. And then we had a stick to smooth it out with
         on the top. And then we'd carry it out to the dryer. We had a place where
         you dried 'em, you know, boards they laid on. And that's the way we made
         them. One guy was shoveling in there, in, dirt all the time. And then they'd
         throw in so much water to get the mud the right thickness. But they weren't
         number one brick, you know, because—well, some of them were good.
         Then we had a kiln, and we'd set the brick in the kiln, you know, leave
         'em about that much apart (about j inch). And then where the fireplace come
         in, come together like this, see, and then you'd put in more on the top. But
         in that fireplace there you put your wood in to burn 'em, to make 'em hard,
         y'know, see. And that's the way we burnt the brick. But they had to be reburnt
         too, you know. You'd have one kiln'd be about as big as this room
         here, and about that high (10 feet). And they'd set the brick all over there.
         And the top brick then, you see, and the one on the sides, they didn't get
         burnt enough. So that meant you had to throw the brick out, you picked out
         all the burnt brick, and reset it again, and then burnt 'em again. That's
         the way you had to get 'em hard enough. (Pause.)
         
         And then we made our own skis and own sleds, made 'em ourselves. My
         dad finally got a blacksmith shop, and there we'd make our sleds to ride on,
         for ourselves, y'know, small ones. And then we'd cut down a fir tree that
         was crooked in the bottom. And then we'd peel that off, and that's what we
         made the ski from. See, so you'd have that, up on the end. So we had to
         make everything that we wanted, couldn't buy nothin*. Then, when we go older,
         we trapped coyotes, and sold them, but you didn't get much for a hide then.
         50 cent, two dollar and a half, was all you got for a coyote hide. I guess
         I shewed you the picture here I had. Yah.
         
         SS:  Did he have to learn to do all of this for the first time, or did he
         learn a lot from his neighbors or did he know most of it?
         
         CO:  My dad?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         CO:  No, he musta learned that in the old country, because he done a lot of
         work here for them. I guess, y'know, some people, it's nature to some people
         to do things like that at all. Dust like my oldest, heck, not the oldest
         brother, but the third boy, Albert, he's still alive. He's an automobile
         mechanic, y'know. He knew everything about a car, he don't have to see it,
         even. That's no fooling. And they used to say that, that man Albert, he
         can fix a car with a plier when the other feller is looking for the tools,
         they say. He was that good, y'know. And I asked him one time if he ever got
         stuck on an automobile, so he didn't know what was wrong with it. "Pretty
         near, once," he said. A feller come up from Lewiston, and comin' up the
         grade, and he said, he turned to the right, the car would die. And so long
         as he went straight ahead, and to the left, it was all right. So Albert, he
         was in Moscow then, when this feller come up from Lewiston. So he tried it
         and took a look at everything he could think of, and he went out and tried
         it. When he turned to the left, why, yurop, or the right, either one, then
         she'd die. So he thought, and he didn't know what the hell to look. And
         then he said he took the carburetor apart, and he took the float out. And
         it was one of them hollow float, it wasn't a cork float, it was the other
         kind. Then he happened, he said, he took her up to his ear, and by God,
         there was something in there, it was leakin'. So it got water in it, or
         gas, see. And when you turned quick to one way, float went down, see, and
         choked the car. That's what happened. That's what's so funnft he said.
         He pret'near went stuck on that one though, he said (chuckles). Yeh, he was a
         good worker. And fast, Desus Christ he was fast. When I had the automobile
         business, he was my mechanic, you see. In those days it was so much for a
         job, you know. You'd put in the spindle so much, and everything, y'know.
         He could put them in so darn fast, could make good money on it.
         
         SS:  So, what was Troy like back then, in the old days?
         
         CO:  Well, you seen the picture here, didn't ya?
         
         SS:  Wasn't much in the picture.
         
         CO:  Well, it was a little better than that. It growed pretty fast though.
         There was a few people that come in here that had a little money, y'know,
         and they put a big store down there. So it was pretty good little town.
         And then, there's a lot of railroads built, y'see. And they cut a lot of
         ties here, the people—hand, hand. And they hauled 'em down here, and they
         shipped 'em from here. And then there were small sawmills goin' up all over.
         So people, it started gettin' work for 'em. And then they start gettin' fields.
         So you go out in the haying, and put in 10 days or somethin'. Then the
         harvest come, that was about 30 days, y'see. Then they had small sawmills,
         and they hauled the logs in on the sleds in the winter. And sometimes they'd
         have a half a million feet to saw, and that'd last about a month in the spring.
         And that's the way you got your work outside. I've worked on seven different
         sawmills in my time. Seven, seven, there isn't any left here now. They
         were all over in the canyons. They couldn't log in the summer any in those
         days, because you had to put the logs on a wagon, y'know. And you couldn't
         haul any logs on a wagon in that rough country, y'know, and uphill. Horses
         couldn't pull no load. But the sled is different, y'know. Put it on the
         sled it slides, and you could haul twice as, three times as much on the sled
         as you could on the wagon. And the wagon is so darn high, y'know. When
         you had wheels this high, you had to roll the logs way up there and the sled
         was down here, so that you could roll 'em right on, y'know. That's why they
         done all the logging in the winter. And there was a lot of mills around here.
         And then, take Genesee, now. They didn't have no timber, so they sold
         a lot of wood down there. And Lewiston didn't have any timber, so they sold
         a lot of wood down there. Was a heck of a wood town here, y'know. Gee
         whiz, y'know, 100 feet long, y'know—a wood pile laying by the railroad track
         to be loaded on the cars. Went to Spokane, some of it went to Moscow, and
         Genesee, and all that. It was the biggest shipping center between Spokane
         and Lewiston, Troy was. They called it "the biggest little town on earth,"
         was the nickname for Troy for a long time. Yeh, and that's why it got its
         name that way—for all the stuff they shipped out of here. Then they started
         gettin* fields, and then they had the wheat and oats and all that that come
         in here, and they shipped that out, y'see. So that's why it was such a ship
         ping town. (Pause.)
         
         Yeh, and it was a rough town, too, you know, there was a couple, three
         murders in this town. That's plenty for a small town, ain't it? (Chuckles.)
         And the sheriff to get shot, the policeman. And he was a mean guy anyway,
         so people up north here—they were pretty heavy drinkers, all of them, y'know.
         They said they celebrated for three weeks when they found out that they shot
         old Hays (chuckles).
         
         SS:  Did you hear about that when you were a boy?
         
         CO:  Yeah, I remember it. I was four years old when it happened. My dad come
         home from town and said, "They shot the policeman." And I talked to an old
         feller yesterday, he was here. He said he seen him, he seen him shoot the
         policeman. He lived right down where it happened. He was 84 years old, this
         guy. Yah, Corrin, a feller named Corrin. He lives in, out of that little
         Albion, Washington. That's above Colfax, y'know. Yah.
         
         SS:  How did your father say it had happened, do you remember what he said at
         the time?
         
         CO:  Well, he didn't know very much about it then, when he first told it. But
         he went out of town too, y'know. The town wasn't taken in then, so there
         was a few buildings on that side of the railroad track that was out of town.
         And he had no business goin' out there, y'know. And the old lady and the
         old man, I think, got in a quarrel, see. And they hollered for the police.
         So he got his old rifle out, and told him if he ever crossed this fence, I'll
         shoot you. But old Hays wouldn't stop. So he shot at him, shot him. He
         coulda shot somebody else, too—one of the bullets went through the hotel
         sign down here, on the corner.
         
         SS:  I guess Hays wasn't too well liked, huh?
         
         CO:  No, no. He got paid so much for each guy he throwed in. That's the way
         they paid him, too. That made it bad, y'know. He put one man in because he
         had a lame back, one day. Yeah, wagon, y'know, pretty high them wagons,
         y'know, and they had the seat way up. And then they had a step here. And
         this feller, he was gonna get up in the wagon, y'know, and he got a kink in
         his back, and he fell (chuckles)» fell back, and there was old Hays that grab
         bed him, and throwed him in jail. (Laughs.)
         
         SS:  For what reason?
         
         CO:  He told him he was drunk. (Laughs.) Yeh, he was mean. They said he went
         out and got 'em and he'd tie them, tie a rape on 'em and lead 'em in to town
         here, when he caught somebody that was drunk. And he put his own son in the
         jail, too. Yeh, he had two sons and they were twins. One was a barber, and
         the other one was a farmer. And I don't know what they done. There was some
         body else that had a blacksmith shop here. And his boy and the Hays boy done
         some damn thing, and he arrested both of them, y'know, his own boy and the
         other one. And one of the boys was sittin' in the jail there. He said, "The
         old man can't do this, can he?"
         
         "Well," he said, "he's already done it, hasn't he?" (Laughs.) And then,
         they were tricky, that Hays bunch was kind of a tough bunch, I guess, too.
         I don't know what he done, one of them. He was a barber, see, and they was
         twins, so you couldn't tell them apart. So when the sheriff come down to
         arrest them, they changed places. The barber went out in the country, (laughing)
         and he took the wrong guy!
         
         SS:  His own sons, huh?
         
         CO:  Yah.
         
         SS:  What was the other murders that you were thinking about?
         
         CO:  Well, there was a feller named Driscoll, he got stabbed in the stomach.
         He come from a dance down here in the hall. He got quarreling about somethin',
         he turned around, and stabbed in the stomach. His name was Driscoll. And
         then the other one was, he had a restaurant, he had a little restaurant, this
         guy. I forgot if he was a Negro or was a nigger or got killed, one of them
         anyway. He throwed him out on the sidewalk, y'know. I guess he was cuttin'
         up or somethin' too much. Then there was a spike in the wooden sidewalk, see,
         that stuck up about this far, and it hit him right there, and it killed him.
         He didn't want to kill him, y'know, but...
         
         SS:  Right in the forehead.
         
         CO:  Yeh, this spike stickin* up, y'know, went through his head here, in his
         brain. Then Hays shot that burgular, too. 'Course I guess he had the right
         to shoot at him, but he didn't have to shoot him. He died.
         
         SS:  What was this?
         
         CO:  It was downtown in the post office, upstairs of the post office. He laid
         behind the stump down there, waited for him. (Pause.) Yep. Oh, you know,
         it was a lot of the crimnals, too, y'know, that come from the old country,
         y'know. They skipped, get away, y'know, from crime. Two or three of them
         around here, I found out that they come to this country to get away from get
         tin' caught, y'know. I guess I told you about that feller that stole the pig,
         huh?
         
         SS:  Tell me that one again, 'cause I forget it already.
         
         G0: (Chuckles.) Well, a couple of farmers up there, they lived there, pretty
         close together. So they butchered a hog, and hung it up in the barn, y'know.
         And then they went to work, I guess—I don't know if they went to work or
         went to town. Anyway, they went away from it for awhile. And when they come
         back the hog was gone, you know. So all they done, they took a piece of rope
         with *em, and walked over to the neighbor, and he said, "You give us that
         hog or we'll hang you in that tree!" And here he come with the hog! So
         y'see, they didn't need any courts of stuff here, to penalize them, see. See
         how quick they got rid of that case? They got the hog back, and the other
         feller sent home, and that was all there was to it.(chuckles). Now they go
         to court and fight here for three months over a thing like that. That was
         a slick way, (laughs).
         
         SS:  You're saying that they knew, they could tell, who the guy was that would
         rob somebody.
         
         CO:  Oh yah, they knew every...Now you take here, all up here north where we
         lived. T'was only two people there that would steal and raise heck. And
         they all knew them, y'know, all, all around, they knew who done it. And
         that's what these people did, y'know. They knew right away who'd done it.
         And that's why they took the rope with 'em and went over there, and told him
         he'd hang him if he didn't come right out with it. But nowdays you don't
         know where the crimnal lives at all. No, you can't tell. Those days they
         did. They knew them all. Hell, and then there was other rough stuff goin'
         on here. A feller on Burnt Ridge, he took a homestead there, and at night
         they come and kidnapped him. They never found that guy anymore. So then
         they took the place, y'see. He hadn't proved up yet. But they found one man
         hangin' down in the canyon in the tree here, but I think that was after that
         happened, though. But they never found out who he was, either.
         
         SS:  Why was this guy...How do you know he was kidnapped?
         
         CO:  Well, he litfed there on this place in the cabin, see, to prove up, maybe
         he had a couple of years left. Then he'd go and get—oh, and I showed you—
         land paper, y'know. And he hadn't proved up yet. So they wanted to get rid
         of him, see? So they took the place.
         
         SS:  So did people suspect the people that took the place?
         
         CO:  Yeh. The people that took the place, they're the ones that kidnapped
         him, but nobody seen it. There was no proof what happened to him, y'know.
         See? But he disappeared anyway. And that was tried again on another place.
         But they got the wrong guy that time. His name was Big Anderson, they called
         him. He was so goddamn big, y'know, his arm was just that wide.
         
         SS:  As wide as both of your arms put together.
         
         CO:  Yah. Yah. Yah, just about. And big and tall, y'know. He had whiskers,
         and he walked with two canes this way, when I seen him. And he had a sore
         on his leg here. When he homesteaded, they tried theasame trick on him.
         They come up there—be lived on Big Bear Ridge, this Anderson. You know what
         he done? He just took one of them fellers by the legs and knocked the other
         feller to hell, and chased them off his place. Took one guy and used him for
         a whip. He was that big and strong. That's no fooling! (Laughs.) I seen
         the guy. He come home quite a few times. And he was a giant, believe me.
         He was out clearing land with one guy, y'know. And they had a log laying on
         the ground, as long as this room here. And one end was about that big, you
         know, and the other one was, y'know how they taper off. So Big Anderson said
         to this, was a guy about my size: "You take ahold of that end," he said,
         "I'll take this one, and we'll carry that log over on the logpile" where
         they burnt them up, they were clearing land. (Laughing.) Anderson picks up
         the log and the other feller, he was hanging up there! He took the log and
         the man and all, see, it's balanced!
         
         SS:  Geez, he must have been big.
         
         CO:  Oh, he was big. He was an old sailor. Old sailor. He had a sore on this
         leg that never healed here. And he washed it in the cold water in the winter,
         and he put this tar that come from the tamarack tree on it all the time.
         That's what he used for it. He was quite a character, too. He was going to
         make a machine that would run forever, y'know. He worked on that all the
         time. He lived in a little cabin, you know. When somebody»d come in there,
         he'd throw a blanket over it so nobody would see it. Then they'd ask him,
         "How is your machine comin'?"
         "Oh, it just lacks a little bit now," he said. "I just about got it."
         (Laughs.) But he never got it made.
         
         SS:  What was this machine supposed to do?
         
         CO:  Well, he said I have, y'know, a machine that would turn itself, so you
         don't need no power on it, you see. That's what he was workin on, see.
         See? That'd go itself.
         
         SS:  Nobody ever saw it, huh?
         
         CO:  No. No, well, it wasn't...I guess after he died, they seen it. He had
         a kind of a wheel there. I think it was kind of buckets on it, or water or
         somethin' that's run into, see. Some way like that he had it figured out.
         
         SS:  Did he walk with a cane usually?
         
         CO:  Oh, he had two of them. My brother, one of them—he met him. We hadn't
         seen him then yet, you know. We didn't know much about him. He met him.
         He had been to town, Troy, too, and he met this guy. My brother, he run and
         hid in the woods. He thought it was some kind of an animal. Oh, y'know, you
         can think—God, he was big, too, you know. His whiskers this way, and then
         he'd come like this...(chuckles.)
         
         SS:  All bent over.
         
         CO:  Dust like that he walked, see, he was bent over just like that. And he
         come home once, and we had a dog. And that dog ran and hid when he seen him.
         And when he left, the dog took after him and barked, and barked, and barked
         (laughs). He thought it was some big bear or somethin', I guess. Yeh, he
         made his own clothes. He had overalls. He made his shoes of overalls. He'd
         make 'em about that thick, and then he'd put a copper rivet through here on
         each side, and put 'em together. And then he had them big overalls, he made
         them about that big, big so he could pull 'em up easy. For his sore here,
         y'know. So, he was dressed funny, y'know, too. When you seen him, y'know,
         prenear scare you, all right.
         
         SS:  You mean he made shoes out of his overalls?
         
         CO:  Yah. He had about five, six thickness, see.
         
         SS:  Did he work?
         
         CO:  Well, I don't know how he lived, even. I can't figure that out yet. I
         don't know. I couldn't figure out if he ever worked. He sold his place.
         I guess he lived on that, when he sold his homestead, y'know. He took a
         homestead. That's the guy that took the other guy and hit him with, y'know,
         the same guy. So I guess he had that money, and that would last him a long
         time, y'know. Nope, he was a giant, all right. I don't know. He said—
         we asked him if he ever been married. "Oh, yes," he said "I've been married."
         "Did you have any kids?"
         
         "I don't know," he said (chuckles). Then he said he was on the boat,
         y'know, and the captain got mean. And he said he took and put a rope around
         the captain and throwed him in the ocean, and he held that rope until he beg
         ged for mercy, before he pulled him out. I suppose maybe he done that, too,
         I don't know (laughs). Yep.
         
         SS:  Did he say how he got the sore?
         
         CO:  No, I think it was a kind of a cancer, see. It was big, too. I seen it,
         y'know. It was about this big, right in here. It never did heal, see. It
         didn't seem to get much bigger, either. It was all meat, y'know, red.
         
         SS:  It was about eight inches or ten inches long?
         
         CO:  Yah, about that long. But he got pretty old before he died. I think he
         was up in the 80's when he died.
         
         SS:  Are there any other guys like, that were as eccentric as he was, that you
         knew when you were young?
         
         CO:  Well, there was another one that lived in Park. (Softly:) I don't know
         what we called him now. Well, he was a queer guy, anyway. He was always
         lookin' for mineral, y'know. Mineral, he was diggin' it. Had a mine there,
         he had a homestead down there in the Park country. Way in on the breaks,
         there's nothin' but rocks, he said, where he lived. Then he'd start mining,
         and he's just lookin' in the basalt, y'know, where there's no mineral at all.
         They asked him why he was diggin' there for? "Oh," he said, "that was a
         tree standing here," he said, "it was goin' like that, and there's where the
         mineral laid," he said. "So I started mining there,"
         
         SS:  The tree was pointing?
         
         CO:  Yeh, tree, the tree was bent over (chuckles), see? So he mined right under
         there. He said, "There's where ya find it." Then he'd take his rock to
         Moscow, y'know.
         
         (End of Side B)
         
         Then he'd take them rocks to Moscow, you see, so to see if it was any good.
         No, well they told him, "That's no good." You know what he done? He carried
         them back home. He thought they was cheatin' him. Yah. And then he had a
         gun, y'know. And it was a 45.70. And he thought all the guns were the same.
         So, if he seen a 22, he'd say, "That's a small 45.70, isn't it?" (Laughs.)
         Yeh, he was quite a character, that guy.
         
         SS:  And he really meant it?
         
         CO:  Yeh. Oh yeh, he didn't know any different. He was kind of a foolish,
         y'know too, you see.
         
         SS:  What did you say?
         
         CO:  Well, you know, kinda silly a little bit, in his mind, see. And then we
         had one they called Wild Bill, here. But he wasn't any silly, but he had a
         lot of dogs. He had four, five, six dogs with him all the time. Then he had
         a belt here, y'know, full of shells, and a gun. And long hair—he was in the
         same style as the young people are today. I seen him only once. And, he,
         oh he was a, he'd shoot all the time. He'd shot cougars and he had done all
         that stuff, y'know. And he never shot any shot. They said that his bullets
         were wore off on the end. He had worn them so damn long, y'know, on here,
         that they were wore off. So they thought they'd try him out over there at
         Boulder. He'd lived in Boulder Creek too, or Park. So they took a gunnysack
         and put it up in the tree, and make it look like a cougar? And then
         they had a guy below there, and he had a rope on it, so he'd jerk on that
         rope. And they told him, "There's a cougar down here now. You'd better go
         now and get it."
         
         "Ohhh, yesss," he said. Bang, bang. He didn't dare to look that way!
         (Laughing:) And they'd jerk on that rope, that thing would wiggle! He shot
         up all the shells, and the cougar was still there, alive. Those were wild
         days. Yup. I suppose you want to hear that story about my dad and the
         Indian, then, huh?
         
         SS:  Oh, yah that's a good one.
         
         CO:  Well, my aunt come out here from back East, and they were talkin' and talkin'
         about...She was kinda religious, y'know. So she thought everything was ter
         rible. She said, "I heard you'd killed an Indian."
         
         "An Indian?" my dad said. "Killed an Indian? I went down to Lewiston
         to get my citizen paper," he said, "and the first thing they asked me, he
         said, 'How many Indians have you killed?' And, I said, 'One.' 'Ho, you can't
         get no paper on one. You got to kill J_2 first.'" (Laughs.) I think she
         went home and believed that, too. Yah.
         
         SS:  Had he ever killed an Indian?
         
         CO:  No, hell, he never killed no Indian.
         
         SS:  I didn't think so.
         
         CO:  The way it started out, dad figured out afterwards, y'know. He's workin'
         for a farmer out there at Moscow, he's comin' down Paradise grade, y'know.
         And he had a wheat load, y'know, on the wagon. And it was steep grade too,
         y'know. He met two Indians there, and they were drunk. And they were swinoin'
         their guns and hollering and everything. And my dad said that, "If I
         had a gun, I believe I woulda shot those Indians. They scared me to death,"
         he said. "But I took the brake off," he said, "and used my whip, and the
         horses started off to beat hell, and then they all stopped," he said, "and
         seen that funny rig go down." They never seen a wagon, I guess, before, you
         know, or somethin*. And that's what saved him, he thought. And that's the
         way I think it started, from that. Because he said, "If I had a gun, I woulda
         shot those Indians," see. And I suppose that worked off that way, and got
         back East, y'see.
         
         SS:  Um-hm. Were there still Indians...
         
         CO:  No, the Indians didn't bother any people here. They were here around Lew
         iston and everywhere. They had trails up here. They didn't come here very
         much after they settled here, but it was trails all over. They come up here
         and hunted deer, y'know, and fished in these creeks, too, the Indians.
         
         SS:  They kept coming after people were homesteading?
         
         CO:  Yah, then they quit then, y'see. Then they stayed on the reservations,
         y'see. But before, y'know, in the summer...They're the ones that, they claim
         they're the ones that kept the ridges so clean and nice, y'know. You take
         a ridge here now, y'know, it's high, y'know, and dry. They kept grass fires
         a-running there all the time, so the brush never growed up. And that's the
         way the Park is got its name there. That's over in Boulder Creek, that's
         out of Deary. And it looked like a park in there to people when they come,
         y'know. It was big yellow pines and no underbrush at all, y'know. And they
         claim the Indians done that. They set fire to that long grass, y'see. And
         then in the draws, y'know, the timber was just thick, because it wouldn't burn
         there, y'know.
         
         SS:  Did sawmills pretty well handle the timber that was being cut off this
         country when people were starting farms? The sawmills around here, is that
         where the timber went?
         
         CO:  Yeh. You see, they homesteaded first, y'know. The sawmills didn't come
         in 'til it was homesteaded, because that was government land, y'know, all
         of it then. You couldn't take any timber off'n that. But when they settled
         here, the Swedes, a lot of Swedes stopped in Minnesota, because they got
         started there, y'know. And there's were they'd stop, when they come. And
         then they'd find out where to 0 from there, the Swedes. That's how they
         happened to get that way here. A feller named Per Dohanson, he found out
         that they had surveyed this land east of Troy here, y'know, ready for homestead,
         see. They had to survey the land, y'know. That was a lot of work,
         and when they got into timber, it took slow. But you take Genesee and Moscow
         in there, it was open country, and that was surveyed 10, 12 years earlier.
         So that was all homesteaded, y'know. And he come back here, and told the
         Swedes over there in Minnesota to go to Troy. It wasn't no Troy then, but
         he told *em where to go here, to Moscow. He said, "It's land open now, and
         if you go out there," he said—he had the sawmill back—"I'll bring my saw
         mill, too, and go with you;:" And that's how they got started, the Swedes,
         see. And that's what he done. He took a sawmill with him, and come down
         here too. And then whenever another Swede come from Sweden, they'd tell
         him to go here, you see. And that's how they got settled so quick, in that
         one spot.
         
         SS:  He found out about it back here. He was in Idaho when he found out about
         it.
         
         CO:  Yah, um-hm.
         
         SS:  Were a lot of the Swedes in Minnesota, had they come from the same places
         in Sweden?
         
         CO:  Oh, no. They were mixed. They were mixed. They had so many small countries
         in Sweden, you know, not bigger than Latah County, most of them, you know.
         Vermland was the name where my folks come. And then they had Smoland, 'small
         land," and several others—Smolanding, and all that, names like that, y'see.
         And they talked a little different, too. You could understand 'em all right,
         pretty good, but they had their little different language each, each one of
         them over there. And then the real Swede language, I didn*t understand that
         at all. See, I didn't talk English 'til I started goin' to school, I had to
         learn that there. There was nobody to learn from. They were all Swedes around,
         y'know, when you grew up. And I was in Elk River, and my brother was working,
         there then—this was about 1912, though, that's a long time after. We was
         standing out there in the street, and two guys was talking to beat hell. I
         said to my brother, "What kind of language are those people talking?"
         And he said, "That's Swede." (Chuckles.) That was the real Swede, you
         know. See, they come from Stockholm, y'know, where they had the schools a
         little different too, and that was the real Swede. But I didn't understand
         'em. And that's the way it was with the others, too. They had different
         words for, like flika they had for "a girl," y'know. And yenta. yenta is a
         "girl," too. That was in our language, yenta. and flika was Smolanding's,
         see, and so on. So they're different.
         
         SS:  Well, when you went to school here, there were mostly Swedish kids that
         you went to school with, right?
         
         CO:  Yeh.
         
         SS:  So, how did you learn English?
         
         CO:  Well, we had an English teacher.
         
         SS:  Did she teach all the kids English?
         
         CO:  Oh, yeh. They got her from Moscow and in there, y'know. 1'11 show you a
         picture of the first school here. Yah. Sroolandinq-a person from Smoland.
         
         SS:  But at home did you still speak Swedish?
         
         CO:  Oh yeh, my mother never learned English. She was home all the time. She
         never got the chance to learn English. But dad, 'course, was all over.
         (Break.)
         
         (Carl is saying that because the kids in his family had no shoes, they
         seldom went outside in the winter.) Well, I don't know how to start it again
         (chuckles). We didn't have no shoes, so we run barefooted between the house
         and barns. We run a race, races between the barn and the house, barefooted.
         Then, if we had any shoes, they'd get so hard as a rock, so we couldn't get
         'em on next morning, anyway, 'cause we didn*t have no overshoes for them.
         See? If you get that leather wet once, y*know. So we had a lot of problem
         with our shoes that way. And we got *em softened up a little bit, put tar
         on *em. We made our own tar from the roots of the stumps, y'know. Pitch.
         Put that in a kettle, y*know, and then you put a fire on the outside, and
         then the tar would come out, y*see. Then we mixed that with tallow, and that
         made pretty good shoe grease, y'know. And that*s the way we got our shoes
         greased up, if we had any (chuckles). Yah.
         
         SS:  Would you have to stay inside if you didn*t have *em?
         
         CO:  Huh? Oh yeh, we couldn't go out then. We run barefooted in the summer
         all the time, y*know. Yeh, only time we were afraid of anything was when
         we crossed the creek barefooted, when the crawfish was there. They'd bite
         ya, y'know. You know what a crawfish is? We had a lot of them in the creek
         down there. They were about that long, y'know, big claws on *em. They see
         anything white, y'know, they think it's food. So we had to watch ourselves
         going across the creek (chuckles). Yah.
         
         SS:  You started to talk about the winter of 1910, too.
         
         CO:  Yeh, well there isn*t much to it. It started at Buffalo Hump country, the
         way I understand it, and it kept goin* around and around *til it got over to
         Clarkia, and then those people got caught there in that canyon, y'know. See,
         the smoke got so they couldn't get out. I think it was 16 or somethin* that
         died there, if I ain't mistaken. It was quite a few of them killed, in that
         fire. And the crops, y'see, they didn*t have the machinery like they have
         now to farm with, y'know. They had horses, y'know, and the crops, they got
         in pretty late all the time. And it was dry and heck, some of the oats wasn't
         higher than that. So it was pretty near as bad as this year.
         
         SS:  Were people around here afraid that the fires were going to get all the
         way down here?
         
         CO:  Well, it didn't seem to scare them much in those days, for some reason. I
         don't think this timber here would burn like it does up in them countries.
         It wasn't thick enough, y'see. And then we had the creeks here, y'know,
         running too, you know, and pretty cold nights here too, at that time. So I
         don't know...But it never come this far anyway. It seemed like it followed
         that mountain range around there, y'know, and it went clean up to Coeur d 'Alene,
         I don*t see why we didn*t have more fires here, for all the land we had to
         clear, y*know. Cut them, and slashed the ground, then stick fire on it—
         I done that on the farm we had. And we had to do it when it was pretty dry
         so everything would burn up good, y*know. You*d slash trees about this big.
         *Course we watched them, too. But they never had any bad fires here at all,
         I dont think. I dont think there's a house burned up from a fire yet, that
         is, before grass fire, that I know of. It was kind of funny, all right.
         
         SS:  Do you think, most of thehamesteads that got cleared, did the lumber just
         get burned up, or did it go to the sawmills?
         
         CO:  Oh, it went to the sawmill, quite a bit of it. But I think there was more
         burned up then went to the sawmills. Because the sawmills, they didn't take
         so awfully much timber, you know, because they were small, and they had to
         log in the winter only, on the sleds, to get 'em in. And so up in our country,
         I know that there was more timber burnt up than there was any other place.
         But when you get up in the mountain here, you see, where there was no farm
         land, that timber was sawed up, pret'near all of it. But down on the ridges
         down here, that was wasted, most of it. And of course, in the bad canyon,
         now, where they couldn't farm then, that was finally sawed—like Bear Creek
         Canyon. Oh, we never figured that they could take the timber out of there,
         when we lived there, y'know. See, you didn*t have no riggins then. But
         the last war—or the first war—then they built a railroad down that canyon,
         and took pretty near all that timber out. There was a lot of yellow pine in
         that canyon, big trees, yknow. And they had a fire there too then, but it
         didn't do much damage. So I guess they sawed up more than theywasted, all
         right, when you figure it all out, yknow, in the mountains and the canyons.
         But it was a lot of wasted timber.
         
         SS:  About when would you say that these little sawmills started going out of
         business?
         
         CO:  Well, oh they been goin* out for the last...The last 10 years around here
         there hasn't hardly be any small sawmill. Used to be one up here in town,
         but that was bigger than they had in those days. But all those that sat up
         in the countries, they've been gone for about 20 years or more. Yup. But
         there were a lot of them, y'know.
         
         SS:  What did you know about this guy Vollmer?
         
         CO:  Vollmer?
         
         SS:  Vollmer.
         
         CO:  Well, he was here, y'know, and they named the town Vollmer after him all
         right. He had a lot of money, I guess. He was an Englishman, I believe.
         And then when they borrowed money, y'know, he'd charge about 12 on it or more,
         Then if you borrowed 100, y'know, you'd get only about 80, because he took
         the interest out, see? (Chuckles.) And the people didn't like him at all,
         y'know, so they lost the name. He lost his name here too, yknow, Vollmer—
         it was named Vollmer to start with. But they named it Troy. I don*t know
         how they happened to put Troy on, though, but they didn*t like Vollmer anyway.
         And then he went up on the Camas Prairie there, and there was a town named
         after him there, and he lost that too. He lost that name. They call it
         Cottonwood now, I believe. Yeh, the people didn't like him at all. 'Course
         a little jealousy there too, because he was rich, y'know (chuckles). Oh they
         didn't have much use for him.
         
         SS:  Was there a lot of helping out between the farms?
         
         CO:  Oh yeh, oh yeh. Yep. They done that, pret*near all of them, because they
         were all pretty poor, yknow, they didn't have anything. So they always worked
         together, helped each other, where they didn't have any boys. But the woman
         worked quit a bit those days too, you know. Take all the Swedish women, y'know,
         they done all the milking, y'know. That's what they done in the old country
         too, 100. The men never worked, never milked the cow in Sweden. So they
         done that, all these Swedes up here, the women done pretty near all the
         milking. And they worked in the field too, a lot of them, in the hay, hay
         business. My mother worked out in the field quite a bit. She'd even sow
         the wheat, by hand. Then my dad, he'd come behind with the harrow and harrow
         it down. They didn't have no seeders those days, y'know. So they didn't
         have much farm machinery, either.
         
         SS:  How did he harvest?
         
         CO:  Well, we had the thrash rigs come around, the old horse power come around.
         And then they had, after awhile they got the steam rig. But the first steam
         rigs they had here, they pulled the engine with horses. It wasn't self-propelled.
         Should have been here the other day downtown, there was a woman that stopped
         down on the bench there, and she had a whole boxfull of pictures. She
         wanted to know who this was, and this and that. And she had the picture of the
         thrasher, old thrash rig there and picnic picture. We used to have a picnic
         up here, this Nora Church, y*know. Every year the 24th of Dune, outside
         picnic, yknow. She had one of those pictures. And I pretty near forgot
         about that. But I dont know where she got all those pictures from, though.
         They were pretty old, a lot of them.
         
         SS:  You told me that the family had a mine when you were a kid.
         
         CO:  Oh, we done the mining, not him. We were the miners. Yeh, we done the
         mining. I showed you the picture of 'em here the other evening, didn't I?
         When we had that tunnel in the ground. Did I show you that?
         
         SS:  You showed me the picture. What I was wondering is if you'd tell me how
         the thing came about, and what you did with the mine?
         
         CO:  Well, you see that mine there was right next to our place pretty near, a
         half a mile away, see. A feller named Cox, he's the one that started it
         the first time. And he mined there, and nobody could take that land because
         there was mineral on it. See, you couldn't take a homestead then, if some
         body contested it for mineral. So there was 40 acres there, there's never
         been a homestead on it. It's still that way. So he mined and mined there,
         and he was a bachelor, and he had a shack. All he had for a stove was a
         whole lot of rocks, and he'd make a sourdough, and he'd put 'em in them hot
         rocks when they baked them (chuckles). And he was diggin' away there, and
         it was on the ridge like that, see. And they had to tunnel in here, A
         feller come down and asked him, "Well, have you found anything yet?"
         "No, no," he said, "if I don't find something pretty soon, I'll hit
         daylight," That meant he'll go through (chuckling). Well, he quit. I don't
         remember him very much. Then a bunch from Troy here took it over, and they
         drove a tunnel. And they had copper, a stringer of copper about that wide
         in it. And sank a shaft there, and then they connected Cox1 tunnel with this
         one, so you could go in one and then climb out through the other one. Well,
         they gave up. And then my brothers, they jumped the claim, and then we took
         it over in 1912. And we drove a tunnel about 300 feet ourselves. And then
         we drilled, core drilled it too, beside. But we didn't find nothin' either.
         
         SS:  What did you think you was going to find?
         
         CO:  Copper. It was copper stringers there all right, right on the top. But
         it wasn't big enough, y'know. They thought they'd widen out if they went
         down on them, you see. But they didn't, they seemed to hold the same. It
         was rich copper ore, but there wasn't enough. So we spent the winters there,
         you know, mining. In the summer we was thrashing, or doin' somethin' else.
         I was telling you about them two old fellers that said, "I never feel like
         greeting." Remember that?
         
         SS:  Tell it to me again.
         
         CO:  Well, there was two old guys there. They had a machine there, how to take
         the copper out of the ore, see. Leaching it, see. When you leach it, you
         got to burn it first, so the sulphur goes out, in the copper ore. And then
         they put it in the acid, and then they put iron in there, and the copper will
         stick on that, see. And they were experimenting with that machine. And they
         were halfway between our camp with that rig. And every time they come home
         from the mine they'd say, "One day closer to the grave, and I feel like greet
         ing," the old man would say. And we didn't know what in hell he meant by
         saying, "I feel like greeting," (Chuckles.) It sounded kind of funny, I
         thought. So he finally told us then. He said, "That's 'crying' on Scot.
         'Greeting,' that's 'crying,' you're crying. Well, I feel like crying," he
         said. "Because you're workin' so hard, and I'm afraid you're going to get
         hurt down in that mine, see." So that's what he meant (chuckles). Yeh.
         Well, you know mining is kind of unsafe work, and we were pretty young kids,
         most of us. Not kids, but 15, 16, years old, I guess, three of us. And we
         had to drill the holes, and then put the dynamite in, and light the fuses.
         And then we'd come back next day, we had to dig that out, and haul it out.
         But one of my brothers, he was ,left handed, so he worked pretty good that
         way, you see. You see, when you're down in the tunnel, you know. Like this,
         the tunnel? (He frames the tunnel in a doorway.)
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         CO:  See? Well I'd be up here drilling holes, see, and he was left handed, so
         he'd been on this side. And that worked out perfect. Then we'd drill a two
         holes here...
         
         SS:  You'd be each on one side.
         
         CO:  Yah. Then we'd drill the other holes here and they were uppers, drillin'
         this way. That was the easiest hole to drill. You stood and held your,
         you'd swing your handle there, and you'd drill them u. Do you know what they
         were for? The uppers?
         
         SS:  No.
         
         CO:  That's to break the rock out, so these holes would break out, and the lower
         ones would break. These holes go in straight.
         
         SS:  The high holes go in straight and the low holes go up?
         
         CO:  Yeh. The middle holes, not the lower ones. The ones on the bottom had
         to be straight, too.
         
         SS:  Ah, I see.
         
         CO:  See, we had six holes in it, see? And then when they light them with the
         fuse, and then run out of there, so we won't get caught. I think I've got
         a picture of that here, I'm lightin* fuses.
         
         SS:  You kids must*ve gotten a little tired of not finding, not hitting paydirt
         in there.
         
         CO:  Well, I never hit any paydirt in my life. I don't care what I tried (chuckles)
         I tried everything. We were in Montana and drilled for oil. Same thing
         there. You'd hit oil, there was oil there, but it wasn't enough. That's
         around Shelby, Montana. I never was lucky. Oh someday they might dig there.
         If they go down deep enough, it might be enough there, y'know, if they get
         down deep enough. And the copper mine, I don't know. But, it was fun. We
         done that in the winter. There was nothin' to do anyway in those days in
         the winter. Couldn't find no work then.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13596</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Nye</previous>
      <next>Olson_Carl2</next>
      <disp_name>Olson_Carl1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
