<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/16/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ruth Olson, 1976-06-16, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:33:34</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Olson, Ruth</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Teacher</occupation>
      <birthyear>1906</birthyear>
      <residence>Deary</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Minnesota and homesteaded (1907)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#games"&gt;games&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teaching"&gt;teaching&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teachers"&gt;teachers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rural schools"&gt;rural schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#transportation"&gt;transportation&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Texas Ridge"&gt;Texas Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13639</file_name>
      <mp3>13640.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13640.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>How parents came here</title>
            <synopsis>How parents came here.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Getting by with little on homesteads; kids' chores; father's work; school basketball;
               walking to high school to shower
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>People got by with little on homesteads. Mother used every twig at first. Kids had
               chores and made their own fun. Father's work. Evening play with the whole community.
               Run Sheep Run. Meeting girls from other towns through school basketball. Playing in
               the Legion Hall in Deary; walking to the high school for showers. Uncle injured in
               fall when building second story.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Banker Harsh helped their family and Deary</title>
            <synopsis>Banker Harsh helped their family and Deary.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1260</time>
            <title>Acceptance of Wells family; Chuck's wife ran the store at Helmer</title>
            <synopsis>Acceptance of Wells family. Billy didn't accept being called a "nigger". Mary was
               very hard working and kind. Chuck's wife Mildred ran the store at Helmer with her
               second husband.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1860</time>
            <title>Deary fire; work on the Deary paper</title>
            <synopsis>Deary fire. Margaret's work on the Deary paper while in school; the newspaper was
               marginal.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Entertainment for young people; basketball, party games and dancing</title>
            <synopsis>Entertainment for young people at homes - party games and dancing. Wink 'Em. Opposition
               to dances.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Ruth decided to teach; discipline problems with older students; interest in home economics;
               teacher's training in Cheney
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Ruth decided to teach because it seemed the best opportunity open to women, and because
               she admired some of her teachers. Discipline problems with older students who rebelled
               a little against what was expected of them. Margaret's interest in home economics
               came from helping her mother. Both got teacher's training at Cheney. No cars on campus.
               No smoking allowed in dorms.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Men got higher teaching salaries; women stopped working when they married; marriage
               kept a secret so women could keep teaching
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Men got higher teaching salaries than women because of coaching duties. Ruth would
               have preferred forestry if she had had the choice. Many women expected to marry and
               stop working; it was expected that their husbands would support them. Some kept marriage
               a secret so they could keep teaching until the end of the term. In those days married
               couples didn't expect as much money, so cone could work.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3360</time>
            <title>Margaret's first school; children learned from each other; quality of rural schools</title>
            <synopsis>Margaret's first school was at Applequist near Deary. The teacher was janitor. Kids
               drank out of the same dipper. Ruthfirst taught at Elwood School on Texas Ridge. There
               were many children because there were many families. Children learned from each other.
               Quality of rural schools. They taught fundamentals, not extras.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Giving children free play; what children were like; making an impression on children</title>
            <synopsis>Giving children free play. Getting to know them well. A child who swore because her
               parents did. What children were like. A child's memory of her teacher. It took little
               to make an impression on children then.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Authority of a teacher; respect for teachers; reading to the class</title>
            <synopsis>Authority of teacher in community. Questions of the teacher and respect for her. Ordering
               Ranger Rick for the school. Reading to the class.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4740</time>
            <title>Salaries and retirement better in Washington; one room schools near Deary</title>
            <synopsis>They taught in Washington because salaries and retirement were better. Names of one
               room schools near Deary.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4860</time>
            <title>No money during the Depression; flat tire in Troy; school was center of the community</title>
            <synopsis>No money during Depression. Their warrants for teaching couldn't be cashed. A flat
               tire caused them to open a checking account at Troy. The school was the center of
               the communities, and provided entertainment. Margaret had been to Kendrick twice when
               she graduated from high school. Taking away the local school took away the community.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Ease of transportation; Bovill lost its store</title>
            <synopsis>Ease of transportation has caused decline of Deary. Bovill has lost its store. Older
               people in Bovill have a bad need for transportation, while Moscow people want a bus
               to get to entertainment.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5520</time>
            <title>A dollar for a revival collection plate caused friction</title>
            <synopsis>A dollar for a revival collection plate caused friction.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Margaret Olson (sister) Teaching and teachers' authority in small
         communities. Choice of career and training. Entertainment for young. Play and chores
         on
         homestead. Decline of small towns. 6-16-76 1.5 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13278_lcoh_13278.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13639</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Olson_Oscar</previous>
      <next>Oslund</next>
      <disp_name>Olson_Ruth</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
