<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/21/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Carl Olson, 1975-02-21, Interview #4 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:27:38</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Olson, Carl</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #4</intnum>
      <occupation>Thresherman; operator of gas station and car dealership; sawmiller; miner; Troy
         councilman for 24 years
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1895</birthyear>
      <residence>Dry Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents emigrated from Sweden and homesteaded (1889)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#miners"&gt;miners&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farmers"&gt;farmers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#banks"&gt;banks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moonshine"&gt;moonshine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Dry Ridge"&gt;Dry Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13598</file_name>
      <mp3>13599.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13599.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Nils Nilson, the foolish miner from Park</title>
            <synopsis>Nils Nilson, the foolish miner from Park.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>120</time>
            <title>Olson's threshing operation on Little Bear and the surrounding ridges; Stacking vs.
               shocking grain
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Olson threshing operation. Threshing for 101 farmers on the ridges one wet fall, because
               they had mudhooks on the engine while the other operations didn't. The secret of pulling
               the engine out of deep holes with a plank and chain. Small farmers stacked grain instead
               of shocking. A bad job of stacking got the grain wet; Carl teases the farmer. Pleasures
               of threshing life. Going out of their way to thresh tiny amount of grain for farmers.
               Reasonable charge for threshing. Small size of most cleared farms on Little Bear and
               surrounding ridges.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Different jobs on a threshing crew; Smut fire on the machinery</title>
            <synopsis>Jobs on threshing crew of twelve. Most local jobs short term. Smut fire in the threshing
               machinery. Work of engineer and separator tender. Setting up the machine quickly to
               show people on Big Bear how fast it could be done.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Albert Olson's skill with the threshing machine; The variables that effect threshing
               technique
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Albert Olson could level the threshing machine while it was running; his gift for
               fixing machines. Deciding when the crop was ready to cut and thresh; effect of rain.
               Lateness of planting and harvesting. Old and new wheat varieties. A record day, 1142
               sacks in nine hours; the picture was published in the Case Company's magazine, American
               Thrasherman. Wearing down teeth on the chain. Number of grates used depended on difficulty
               of threshing the particular grain.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>The difficulties of raising and threshing beans</title>
            <synopsis>Threshing beans was difficult, dirty work. Problems with raising beans, and advantage
               of introducing another crop on summer fallow land. End of bean growing locally.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Meeting people while threshing; Stories about local families</title>
            <synopsis>Knowing the people in the country by threshing. Getting by on small farms. A rooster
               "cans" a man. A hook-nosed family said to be great cherry pickers.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>The right job for each worker</title>
            <synopsis>Finding the right job for each worker. The various jobs in small sawmills.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3420</time>
            <title>Working in a sawmill near the coast</title>
            <synopsis>Getting work in a sawmill near the coast. All workers had only two names: "Do more,
               see less," or "See more, do less."
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Differences working on the West coast; many locals moved to the coast</title>
            <synopsis>When the sun shined on the west coast, the men stopped working, went inside and played
               poker; it's the opposite in this country. Many early people moved from here to the
               coast.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Jobs in small sawmills; logging in winter; Employment changes when Potlatch arrived</title>
            <synopsis>Live rollers in the sawmills. More about small sawmill jobs. Location of small mills
               in draws surrounded by timber; logging to them in winter. Troy Lumber Company. Change
               of employment opportunities with coming of Potlatch.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>A cow dies after killing a sheep</title>
            <synopsis>A family cow lays down and dies after mistakenly killing a sheep who was a fast friend.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Drafted during WWI; Selling out of the threshing business as gas power replaced steam</title>
            <synopsis>Carl and brother both drafted for WWI during harvesting, not given extension as the
               farmers were. Cost of threshing machinery. Threshing was better money than farming.
               He sold out because gas combines were replacing steam engines.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Inflation during the depression; Responsibilities of the Government</title>
            <synopsis>Depression and inflation at the same time. Importance of every person; country should
               guarantee a good living income. Over time is a shuck. Advantage of manufacturing tax
               over income tax. Labor and taxes are what must run the country.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5160</time>
            <title>Borrowing from the Bank of Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Borrowing from the Bank of Troy to build the service station. Troubles with car dealerships
               in Moscow and Troy. No resale value on trade-in. Liberal policies of the Bank of Troy.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Difficulties for car dealerships and owners during the Great Depression</title>
            <synopsis>Bank of Troy policies. Most car dealers went broke in the Depression. Car dealers
               had to carry the papers on cars, and lost much money on repossessions and trade-ins.
               In '28 Chevrolet put out a car twice as good as '27, but they tried to make Carl buy
               the '27's first. Going broke on repossessions. Training people to drive in open fields.
               A man left his new car in his garage for two years, thinking he'd been cheated because
               he didn't know about clutches. Virtues of Model T's. Eastern roads better then local.
               Peterson and Carlson Tools used scrap steel from cars.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6180</time>
            <title>The Service station during the Depression; Banks going under</title>
            <synopsis>Getting by with the service station in the Depression, no real profit. No money in
               selling gas. Keeping his money in the store safe. Advance warning that banks would
               go broke from investments in timber and cattle.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6480</time>
            <title>On trial because a man had moonshine in Carl's car; Making cheap whiskey</title>
            <synopsis>Carl was arrested because a man in his car had moonshine; he got off, and listened
               to the man lie about him at the trial. Sam McKean sat on whiskey during a search.
               Everybody made whiskey because it was cheap.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6720</time>
            <title>Shoe grease and bare feet on the homestead in winter</title>
            <synopsis>Shoe grease and bare feet on the homestead in winter.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6840</time>
            <title>Stories about Victor Anderson; </title>
            <synopsis>Victor Anderson used to tell people he wasn't lonely because he had his woman (made
               with his fist and doll's eyes)in his pocket. Anderson's heaven and hell story (by
               folding one piece of paper in a certain way and cutting down the middle, it turns
               into a cross and parts of letters which spell "hell" see transcript). His love song,
               accompanied by jew's-harp and bark horn.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Homesteaders were the real pioneers; Packing everything on your back</title>
            <synopsis>Real story of pioneering the West is homesteading, not Buffalo Bill Cody. Toughness
               of homesteading with no towns, packing everything in on your back from Moscow. Family's
               first shelter a lean-to. Broadaxing cabins. Father's and Mother's work.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7740</time>
            <title>Lack of regulation caused problems with concentrated homestead farms</title>
            <synopsis>America in trouble with concentration of homesteads into huge farms, high food prices.
               Problem grew from lack of regulation. Too many products.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8040</time>
            <title>Mother and Father taught children to treat people right; Too many came to American
               to get rich
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother disagreed with father over marriage in the Bible, and was surprised to find
               he was right. They taught children to treat people right, though they weren't religious.
               Whenever you swear, you get a black spot on your heart. Too many people came to America
               just to get rich. If Carl got rich he was going to help people.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8340</time>
            <title>Leaving school at 14; Working from the age of 9</title>
            <synopsis>He didn't learn much in school, and left at fourteen. Working at his uncle's store
               in Helmer, where a man sold near-beer instead of beer. Warning him about revenues;
               fixing his wooden leg. Pulling out stakes for the railroad survey through his uncle's
               meadow at age of nine.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8760</time>
            <title>Stories about Per Johanneson's sawmill in Sweden</title>
            <synopsis>Per Johanneson burnt up his sawmill in Sweden and smuggled the insurance money to
               America. He paid his partner back in Sweden with confederate money.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Threshing on the ridges in the twenties. Difficulties selling cars. Service station
         during depression. Struggles of homesteaders. Work in small sawmills. 2-21-75 2.5
         hr
         67p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         Please note that the transcript is difficult to read; please see the PDF transcript
         for better translation.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER:He stayed at your place, Nilson?
         
         CAUL OLSON Well, he was on the way to the couldn't make it, I guess, so he stayed
         over night. That's when
         I got to know him most.
         
         SAM:  What was he like when you saw hirn there? Was he a friendly guy?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea, yea. There was nothin mean about him I don't think, but he
         had funny ideas, y'know. Y'see he had a prospect hole there y' know and
         was do you wine there;
         
         well "was a tree at was en a place over a he said," to dig.
         then he took some or that and went to Moscow University with It. md thfeaid,5fhat's
         no good—throw it sway." But he
         wouldn't throw it away. He put it in nis pa-KsacK ana toox j.c ucs-rv.
         -y'know
         
         Then he come over to "one place. He had a gun—45-70—x - was a pretty
         big gun. And he looked at his .22 and said, "You've got a small 45-70,
         haven't you?'
         Yea, he was quite a character, all right.  in Boulder Creek, -bey
         all talked about him, y'know.
         
         SAM:  Y'know Carl, I wanted to ask you about the thrashing because you never
         really told me about the operation that you had on the ridge, the harvest
         operation "ou never really have told me how you got goin at it and
         what it was like.
         
         CO:  Well I got " a job, y'know I worked for him for three to four years. He said,"I
         want you to come out and fire my engine for
         me and follow the harvest, and I'll give you two dollars a day." So
         I thought that was great, y'know to ma-e two dollars a day—I was only
         about fifteen years old then. And I went with him and when the harvest was over
         and he said, "YOu had steam every morning n't ya?" "Yes," I said.
         "Well," he said, "I'll give you two and a half like the pitchers get.
         And he hired me again and again, y'know. I worked for him for about three
         or four years. And then he wanted to sell the rig to my brother. So we
         bought him out. And then we- run that for about ten years. We thrashed
         all of Little Bear and up on Dry Creek and Nora country and clean up
         to Deary. We thrashed for a hundred and one farmers one year, y'know
         that's something. Now you only thrasn for one. are so big, y'know.
         
         SAM:  How could you do a hundred and one farmers in one season?
         
         CO:  One fifty-four days. And then we had the beans left, so we
         to go back and thrash them, and that took us eleven days; so we had sixtyfive
         days in . And it was the first of November when we got through.
         It was a rainy fall, see. And there was other thrash rigs around too, y'know.
         We grt such a long run because we had mud hooks on our engines. Mud hooks
         look like this and about six inches long and they were about that far apart
         y'know, SO you could go, and that's how we got around and got all that
         thrashing. And we thrashed between the showers. In those days, y'know in
         Little Bear we had to thrash most of it in shocks. We took it right from
         the field and thrashed it. And then the small farmers stacked all their
         grain, see, so they were in stacks. And that's why we'd keep agoina. If
         wheat all thv/'d been any . out there, it would have -rotten, y'know because
         it rained off and on.off and on off and on, see,, o then we kept
         a-goin that way. I didn't think we'd ever thrash the beans, but it
         happened to get a nice day on the. first of November, and it lasted about
         two weeks and we finished up on the eleventh. And goin home it started snowing.
         
         SAM:  What year about would that have been?
         
         CO: About 1920, I think. I'm pretty sure I'm right on that; it could be;
         '21 or '20, but it was either one of them days because I was in the army in
         see. 1919, so I missed that harvest. And then I come back and we thrashed one
         year, and the next year, it could have been '21 that was so wet But the
         first year I come out from the army,we made a lot of money that year. Maybe
         that was the big year, I guess so. And it could have been 1921. . .
         
         SAM:  Weren't there other thrashing crews around at the same time?
         
         CO:  Yea, but they couldn't move the machinery because they didn't have no
         mud hooks.. And there told you about that big plank we had. I'M.
         show you how it works about. And I figured that out . I was workiri on
         the road, y'know, pullin the grader, and we got stuck. Here's the engine
         now, we stuck a three by twel ve under the wheel here, and it was sixteen
         foot long, see, and then we wrapped the chain around here, 
         stiff locked it, they call it it was a' differential gear in it, y'know just
         like a car has.
         
         SAM:  Yea.
         
         CO: put that locu in it pull-. Well then the engine climb up that
         thing. It: tlimb up the pliant . And then we were out.
         
         CO:  And that's the. way we got out, y'know in the fields once in a while. 
         was so damn soft e,rcyou'd sink right down. Over here on this side of Deary
         we got on a flat field and doggone Uwe didn't stick that plank under it,
         and we went down four feet before it stopped. But then it hit solid
         ground there and then come right out. I thought, 'Here we are now-we're
         stuck for good!' Come right out.
         
         Now what did you putthe plank underneath? You put it underneath the engine.
         And under the wheel.
         
         SAM:  Yea. CO- And this is the spokes,
         a little bit, and the planks
         stood like this, hen we Lied" the chain here, and the chain come down,
         it wrapped around the bull wheel en
         and we tied
         Yea. And that was over on the GranlunJ placfrwhera it went down so deep.
         But the way I fund it cut, y'know "" ad that rigre than about a
         year, and we was grading the road, and we was following pretty close to
         we COme to a place where they'd blowed out a stump, tne edge,
         and they filled that in with loose dirt, y'know. And it looked like the
         v .„ti-«,vri a«H -" when we pot there , the bull
         road and it was wet tnen too, 
         wheel just dropped down in that hole anu tnere we sat
         grader behind it. So the Karo, ss s aiu
         name I had too-CarlOlson. "I'll go home," he said, "and get my team.
         TViprp waq no wav that wheel And we'll get out of here somewa Twa? just spinning,
         y'know, in there.
         telephone pole there, and I thought to myself, ''By god, I'll t
         here ha-t pe '
         it under the wheel, tied the this.1 I tooK the 
         arid up it went, just like that. And I was chain on and stiff locked ana
         the road boss he had the same
         sitting, waiting--he was gone aboutt an hour, y'know. He couldn't figure
         out how I got out of tliat hole, y'know. He just couldn't figure it.
         So I showed him how I out there after-wards. And that's how I happened
         to get wise to that thing, y'know. And that come out pretty handy in the
         harvest.
         
         SAM:  Well, this year, when did it start raining that fall?
         CO. Oh, it started about the last of August.
         
         SAM:  How much thrashing did you get in before that?
         
         CO:  Oh, about twenty days, fifteen, twenty days is all. We got through an
         Little Bear and we got up to ikrnott's place and I forgot who lives on it
         now, it's that old dam on it, it's about half-way down the ridge., ;nd
         1 said to the crew, nBy go -, it's goin to rain!" There were some clouds
         cornin up. And we were on the last shocking7 open field, he had a hundred
         acres of oats or sornethin there. I said, "We got to finish this now.
         It's goin to get rain and this "is the last shocks we got." And you know when
         it rain) on the shocks you ha to wait three or four days or maybe more
         before it dried out, ; Btttm it was stacks the rest of  finished up but
         we had to run an hour over time to get it through. And then all the other
         thrashing was stacked after that. So Arneber?'s place was stacked and Kelly
         place and the place you're on--all or. And we went straight
         ahead lo i.ora ane took all of ivora ana then over to Dry Creek.
         in And then from Dry Creek up to Deary. That's how we got such a long run.
         It was fifty-four days of grain and eleven days of beans—a hundred and
         one farmers wc thrashed for.
         
         SAM:  Why did some farmers stack it instead of shockin it?
         
         CO:  Well, they had so little it didn't pay to bring it together. They had
         to have eight bundle teams, y'know to keep the machine goin, and they had
         to go out in the field and haul it to the machine. But when they stacked
         you pulled your machine in between there, and I had the pitcher with me,
         four of them or five, and they pitched it in, and then we
         moved to another setting. . So long as it didn't rain we could thrash
         because the heads were dry. And the outside ones a little wet, if they
         were too we t sometimes we had to wait a day even,to et em
         dry off a little bit. We got to one place where they stacked the grain
         so poor, y'know, they had to know how to stack grain--that was an art
         then too.The bundles had to lean out this way so when the rain hit em it
         would run off. Instead of that, he got his bundles this way and the
         rain would run into the stack for him. "The kids stacked it," he said. He
         had kids to stack it, see; And we couiun't knock that grain cut a:... he
         run around there like he was crazy, that farmer. I said, "We can't thrash
         or nothin--we can't do nothin with it.?i It was Little Club too, and that
         the hardest wheat to knock out there ever was.
         
         SAM:  What? Little Club wheat?
         
         CO:  Yea. His son lives on the ridge there, Nelson--ha isn't far from where
         you live—Bill son. His dad, y'know, and he was runmin around there,
         if vou don't want em to thrash we'll quit."
         I throwed the belt off. No", he said, "you can't quit." And we finish
         him up too, y'know. And then when we come back that fall to thrash beans,
         why, we thrashed all around him, y'know,I just done that to tease him.
         n't We was goin to thrash it for him, I would leave nobody no matte:
         if I liked him or not. He called up when we was at Riersons. "When you
         go in to thrash my beans?" "Well, I don't know',' I saidv"I don't do any better
         job on beans than I do on wheat!" "Oh," he said, "you gotta come and thrash
         em,now." I figured on thrashin em all the time, but I just left him to the
         last guy.
         
         SAM:  How did you decide what order you were going to thrash the farms in?
         How did you decide who was goin to get it first?
         
         CO:  Oh, it come out pretty good so we didn't have much problem -there. The
         lower end of Little Bear ripened up .- faster than the woods did, y'see.
         And we taradown there somewheres, the ones that was readiest, see,
         there-' "so many kinds of grain. They had fall wheat, and the fall wheat
         come in two, three weeks alidad of the spring grain. So we thrashed the
         iall wiieat and sometimes we acta tu go dsck anu uiicu uus- udwa i.ui uj
         afterwards it wasn't ready. And that's the way we worked it, y'know.
         And then we boarded with the farmer didn't have no cook wagon or
         nothing. But I was so used to thrashing I could hardly ever miss. We'd be
         at your place for dinner, and so on, and I'd tell 1in . time 
         could have the food ready, "tit it happened when we thrashed beans once
         was hard to judge that. I told that next farmer that we'll be at your
         place for dinner, and by golly before I knew we was through with that guy,
         nd I took my car and run dwn there and told him that we', couldn't be'
         there for dinner.  And then the old lady got
         so excited she jumped in the bed and squealed andhollered. And the old
         man said, "Don't pay any attention to that. She does those things quite
         often," he said. (Laughs) It was old BeStencamp. he lived way down
         the end of the ridge.
         
         SAM:  What, she expected you for dinner and you weren't going to be there.
         You were ready to move.
         
         CO:  Yea, because uhe didn't have the dinner ready. But I hardly ever missed
         on that. I was so used to it you know. I knew how much field everybody
         had and I knew the braggers--y'know some of ikmibrrg they've got so much
         and all that, so you fool here.
         
         SAM:  You mean they said they had more to trash than they had.
         
         CO:  Yea.
         
         SAM:  The yield was so good, huh? What was the food like in the farms? Did
         they cook real good for you?
         
         CO:  It was just like goimto a picnic every day. One fella asked me once,
         he said,"What would you do if you had a chance to do something?" "Well,
         I'd be a thrasherman if I could," I said,"that's the best job I ever had.
         It didn't last too long, so you didn't get tired of it, and the good eats
         we got all the time, y'know and everything. And we slept in the straw stack,
         and we were all together all the time, and we had a good time and 
         And on Saturday night we'd all km in the .- --P wagonr~they called th,
         a Wagon that the forks and other stuff and the beds and
         everything---and we all drov
         com" back on Sunday--Sundav evening." No it was pretty good: I liked it
         because you got to know people and everything else y'know. And we wasn't
         out:"to make money only, y'know. And that's one thing--we were well liked,
         y'know, they wanted us if they could get us, Because just think of it—I
         We lost money on that.
         pulled one, pretty near whole mile to thrash nine sacks of wheat.  I didn't
         charge him any extra either. And the smallest hern thrashing--that was ! wee
         sacks. i\ . (laughs) I didn't like that very good, \e were ready
         to quit, y'know, we was through.6nd he come over, he only lived about a
         mile from us and he wanted his beans thrashed. Gol, y'know we had to fill
         uo the boiler with water and steam up and pull over there and everytl :w so I
         .didn't like it. anyway-- our (V-Fe kept on, oh I thought I'd better go- he's neighbor.
         And when we got up to his barn up there, it was a bunch of boards about
         that high from the ground "' " over, and he Tun and me where to go.
         at? figure it out.
         
         "Where in the hell is the bean stack " I couldn't So
         under there,(laughs)
         
         I got off and I looked and I seen the beans, .nd he got three sacks.
         out there , , TT ,. , atwas the place right next to the cemetery where it happened.
         We lived
         (his brother) down there where Emil lives, you can see his place from the cemetery.
         
         SAM:  How did you work out the charge, hew much it would cost them to thrash?
         
         CO:  Well, we had so much a bushel, so much a sack. We got eight cents a sack
         for oats and ten cents for wheat, ten cents a sack. Y'see they sacked all
         to  It you had" sack sewers with you to sew 'em up and piaiSU'em up z 1no the grain
         and but that was pretty reasonable. Most or rnem
         had two cents more than we did all the time too. And then when they went
         down to "Genesee country, then they had the cock wagons with em.
         Then they got about twenty cents a sack, I guess. But up in the woods here,
         there .. so many small jobs that7 Ucouldn't afford it. And then another
         (This was wheat farming )
         thing, y'know that book you give me. you could see there, it tnose teiias
         were on a small farm there wouldn't be anything to thrash—the horses would
         eat up everything. They even worried about that a lot of places a long time
         tcoiae. in. there ago up here y'know, Tf they had too many horses, they'd eat up all
         the damn
         grain. Well a man got a hundred sacks of wheat, that was a-big j-oh-in those
         days. And;oItsatoo, y'know. But that's the way it was small fields,
         they 
         fifty and sixty acres had cleared up in the woods up here, y see. it
         was timber all over y'know, and they had to get their fields wherever they
         could, Amd it was quite a job to clear off the land, y'know. If it wasn't
         big timber on it, it was small black pine, they called it. It'd get about
         this big, just as thick as it could grow.
         
         SAM:  It was like sticks.
         
         CO:  Yea. So they didn't have very big fields, y'know. Now Little Bear was
         pretty good because that was a ridge, and they claimed the Indians set
         grass fires on those ridges ,and they kept the small stuff down, but it was
         yellow pines here and the all right, but they can can fields pretty
         quick that way, between the trees even.
         
         SAM:  Was Dry Ridge like that too, where you grew up?
         
         CO:  Yea, there was nothin but timber fere. And my dad didn't have sixty
         acres of field I don't think for a long, long, long time. So he had
         nothin to sell. All we got was enough feed for the horses and the cows.
         What we sold didn't amount to anything for a long time. Maybe sell for
         a hundred dollars a year—a big sale that would be in those days, y'see.
         The wheat was only worth about sixty cents a bushel. You'd get a dollar
         and twenty cents for a sack then. It's , different now, y'know.
         
         SAM:  So in 1920, when you were thrashing, each farmer would only maybe
         fifty, sixty acres. . .
         
         CO:  Yea, lots of them, they didn't have any more,a lot of them. Some of them iu
         only ten, fifteen acres. There was a feller up on this end of Little
         Bear, let me see, what the hell was his name? He lived on the forty there.
         y'know—we didn't charge him anything, we just thrashed it for him freeall
         the time.
         he was so hard up- lie only had about ten acres of field. So we never
         did charge him anything for his job. We donated that
         
         SAM:  Wil you tell me who was on the crew? How big was your crew, and what
         did the different men do?
         
         CO:  About twelve people, you can figure out—we had six bundle pitchers and
         two sack. Se"esometimes we had three, that'd be nine, and then we had a man
         .to haul water, that's ten, and then engineer is eleven and the separator
         man is twelve—about a twelve man crew is all we had. But my brother,
         he took care of the separator, and I took care of the engine , so we
         took the big jobs that they paid more for. Engineer, he'd get four or
         five dollars a day?; and the separator tender, he got about the same as the
         engineer did. So we held those two jobs ourselves and that's why we
         could make it fairly good, y'know, nothing big.
         
         SAM:  Would that be how much you'd make when you were done dividing up the. . .
         
         CO:  Yea.
         
         SAM:  Money. You'd have four or five dollars a day for yourself
         
         CO:  No we never figured that—we figured what was left and then we cut it
         in two--so we took half and half, my brother. Except in 19. . ., well
         that big year we had, I told you, we made money then. We made seven
         thousand dollars that year. We got thirty-five hundred a piece. But
         that was more than we made in three or four season-before. But the
         war had been on and thing were up, y'know. We paid seven dollars a day
         for pitchers too then, see and seven dollars a day for sack sewers.
         
         SAM:  Whet did you pay before that?
         
         CO:  Two and a half for pitchers and the sack sewers got three and a half, I
         believe. Two of them, that'd be seven dollars a day there.
         
         SAM: So there was a real shortage of labor after the war then?
         
         CO: No, it was no shortage of labor. Well, it never was any big jobs you
         go out and
         had, you know. Just when I was young I'd work a sawmill—get in
         thirty days, maybe. And then you go out in the haying--I never went
         out in the haying that was too hard work for me. Tien they got in maybe
         ten days. And then when the harvest come days about. And
         that was all the work there was, seelhesawmills, they were all
         over the country, but they were small, and there only way they could get
         any logs in was in the winter. You couldn't log in the summer—you
         couldn't haul them on the wagons, you couldn't get no load on, y'know.So they ha
         a good winter,they'd Set more lo§s- In a poor winter they wouldn't
         have a big run. So it would hardly last over thirty days on the sawmills,
         then you were through there. So an all around job was something we
         didn't know anything about hardly. And the harvest was the best pay
         and it was the easiest to get people there, y'know. And as it said in
         that book, they come from way back in Kansas, here. Because the crop UXtS
         earlier there, so they got another thirty days inland they made pretty
         good that way, in those days.
         
         SAM:  Were your crew, were they local men?
         
         CO:  Yea, they were all local, yea. There was quite a few people here then
         because a hundred and sixty acres is what they owned—most of thera was
         and all homesteader, y'see," that's all you could take. You could take 320
         if you paid so much an acre, but very few people had any money to do that.
         And they called that the pre-emption. Now like Flodin 's place, he took
         pre-emption and homestead both, so he was the big farmer up there—he had
         320 acres, but they didn't have too awfully much field anyway because
         there was timber all over, y'see. In order to get ahold of $150 then, that's
         just as hard to get as a thousand now, or easier. It's easier to get a
         thousand now then it was 150 then—that's what it took on a pre-emption
         I believe, so much an acre anyway. So my dad,he filed pre-emption to
         start with, y'know. And then you could live so long and then you had to
         pay up or lose it. So he shifted . over to homestead then, instead.
         That's the way he got on it—he didn't have that much money. There was
         no pre-emption to take around there anyway, then they'dtook up practically
         all the land.
         
         SAM:  Was this on his original homeplace? Was it a pre-emption to start with?
         
         CO:  Yea. I got the paper here yet on that. I showed you the pre-emption
         and the deed.
         
         SAM:  Yea. Well, did you have trouble with the machinery, the thrashing
         machinery? Did it break down at all?
         
         CO:  No, we didn't have much trouble other than we had the fire the first year.
         We burnt out the first year, and that was tough for us, y'know. A smut
         fire burnt everything inside the separator and the blower fell off. We
         was out on Hupp's place, that -was the last place on Little Bear way down.
         we was in a hell of a. So we thought fix, out we were going in two days ate. that.
         We called up the Case people in Spokane and they shipped it down on the
         night train. come here at eleven o'clock at night. And then we had to
         put in all that stuff, y'see. So in two days, we was goin again. And they
         thought that the IWW set fire on it, y'know.
         
         SAM:  Oh yea, you told me about that—it wwasn't them at all—they didn't
         do it. 
         
         CO:  No, it was nothin. We had the explosion the day before, y'know, and it
         was awful smutty grain, too. But it was the black smut. So we didn't think
         the guarding ourselves down on this place because - see the
         big head here and there in the bundle. It was that brown smut and that was
         just right, the right mixture, y'know. And what started it was electricity,
         You could go around the machines certain days and stick your finger up
         tc ' the belt, and you could see the sparks fly, y'know. And that's
         what set if off there—electricity. And then something went through the
         cylinders, what made the spark, y'know and that set It off too—a rock
         or something, or a piece of iron happened to go through the machine. And
         it poof, fire all ovet it at once. No, I liked that job, thrashing,
         I thought that was pretty good.
         
         SAM:  As the engineer what did you do? What did you do to take care of the
         engine as the engineer? What was your job?
         
         CO:  My job was to run the engine keep steam in the boiler, pokin wood
         in it all the time. The farmers furnished the wood, y'know—they hauled out
         wood for you, and you''steam er up with that, y'know. Then get up in the
         morning about four, so you'd have steam by seven. See, you always had
         to start over in the morning again. So we put in long days all right.
         The engineer, he put in the. longest day, from four to about eight, y'know.
         
         SAM:  What about the separator tender? What did he do?
         
         CO:  Well, he took care of the machine. It was always somethin to fix—not
         o r all the time, but y'know, somethin shaked loose, belt break and had to lace
         it, and have all that ready and check up you? y'know. So he worked
         overtime quite a  So that's what count, y'know, if you had the machinee
         shape so you could run steady without having any breakdowns. And how to
         set your machine, I told you about that too. One of theftlson boys, I
         don't know if it was Bill or not, but one of them boys, he went over on
         Big Bear y'know, and worked. And the fellow named Fairfield v- run the
         machine there,and hd smoke a pine and somethin happened to the machine,
         histewbacco and he
         oh gol dumit,"he'd feel fotm fill his pipe up, and then went down and
         fix it afterwards. And it took them so long to set the macnine, y'know,
         Nelson said to Vtn, "Now tbe-m Olson boys on Little Bear it takes th em
         five minutes to set the machine mey laughed and
         "you're a real braggart,IheShade fun of him, y'know. And he told me this. So we
         happened to quit Little Bear because the small machines start comin in,
         y'know, and combines. So we thought we'd try Big Bear for awhile, so we
         got the job down there. And I knew all about it so I told the crew,we had
         anice level spot down on the flat there and the farmer said %vl can set
         thera "
         down there on the. flat,that level So I told them, "Be ready now, we're
         going to show those people on Big Bear how long it takes to set a machine!
         It was level so we didn't have to dig for nothin, y'knowsee had to dig for
         the wheels to get the machine level, y'know. And the same with the engine,1
         it was rough ground, but it was level as the floor. So I told em,
         pull the belt out,"get it goin when you pull it out,
         The ones that too run out with it." And you know how long it took us? Three minutes!
         And here the bundle wagons was-sittin up above,  about five-hundred
         feet away from the machine lookin at us when we were settin,y'know. I
         the engine ed $ lined never stopped I just unhooked it, turn it around, and it up,
         and they were there/and throwed the belt on; I. backed up and throwed off
         the clutch and I never stopped it. And the fell "sat there till I had to wave
         at' em to come on down, come on down. Yea.
         
         SAM:  That's funny.
         
         CO:  That oldest brother Albert, y'know, he was a real mechanic. He worked wth
         us the first two years and helped us out, y'know. Of course, he'd had
         a job like that before, y'know. He was fast too.
         
         (End of Side A)
         
         CO:  Settin was just a little bit off, y'know. See it had to be level so the
         wheat wouldn't flow to one side and this and that. Well put a jack
         under there, and told them, and pitch in." And they used to talk about
         my brother. They'd say, "Well, I've never seen a fellow like that. He
         can fix.a machine with a pliers when the others are lookin for the tools."
         And that was the truth all right..fast, y'know. And then he seemed to
         know everything ; . about the machine. He could sit on
         the s ack pile and first thing you see him jump off and start running down
         there to fix somethin. How did he know? I didn't know there was anything
         something
         wrong, but the sound of the machine didn't sound right to him-- A was chokin
         up or somethin, so he'd be right there. So they donU have to shut her
         down even. See the blower would choke up sometimes ,straw in there, y'know,
         and all that. If you're there in time you can poke in there alittle bitit
         won't getyur whole machine choked up, y'know. If the blower should
         choke up,there'd be straw all the way through, y'know. And that's the way
         hfe was-he taught us all that stuff. That's why we had good luck.
         
         SAM:  So you learned it from Albert.
         
         CO:  Yea.
         
         SAM:  Y'know I've heard it said that they used to say about you and your crew
         there that if anybody could thrash it, you guys could do it—if it could
         be thrashed,you'd be the ones to do it.
         
         CO:  Yup. Well that's the way it should be, everything, but if they run the
         country like we run the thrashing machine there wouldn't be no depression.
         
         SAM:  (laughs)Carl, how could you tell when you could thrash it? When it was
         just dry enough or. . .
         
         CO:  We, we'd go out and test it, y'know. We'd walk out in the field and then
         in the middle of the bundle
         we'd stick a hand into the bundle and pull out a head and see if it was
         tough or-not-, y'see. If it wasn't tough, why. it was ready to thrash. And
         with rain.thafd be a little different, but that'd be the outside heads
         only that got wet, y'see, then we'd jus'ttest them,see. If it gota ll"temp
         you couldn't knock the chaff off the wheat y'know, and then it'd' go out
         in the straw pile. So you had to know that too. It didn't take much rain
         y'know in shocking, -Jtien you thrashed shocks. Just
         a good shower would lay you off half aday. Areal rain'lay you off a
         whole week even.
         
         SAM:  Did that happen to you very often?
         
         CO:  No, not'olten because,y»see, we done most of that thrashing in August
         After that and very little rain come in August, i'hey was all stacked, y'see, and
         the,
         were all ripe then , see, so we didn't lose much time- once in a while
         though we had to lay off. I think it was only one harvest that we put
         in that we didn't have to lay off for rain, or else you have to lay off
         two or three days or so on if' it was a kind of a rainy weather. Especially
         when it was shocks, But ifjlt was stacked then you didn't have to wait too
         much if it was a good rain, then you head to wait a couple of days, maybe.
         
         SAM:  For what they were growing then, was it mostly wheat that you thrashed.-
         
         CO:  Wheat and oats, practically all of it. Hardly any barley at all. TheY didn't
         raise any barley up here—hardly at all. And y'see they didn't have the
         machinery to farm like they do now, y'know. We got some awful late grain
         in y'knov/. If you'd get a spring that was wet, y'know, they only had horses
         to plow with,and they couldn't get it in in time and it'd be late, awful
         late. One place on Little Bear, a fella named Harris was farming, and we
         come up there and we were about through on the ridge, too. And you know
         what he 'was doin? He was cuttin the grain; and we was thrashing it, yea,
         it was so late. He was an awful poor farmer anyway.
         
         SAM:  How long did the grain usually 1after it was cut between then and when it
         was thrashed? How long did it take for it to get aged and be ready?
         
         CO:  When it was wet, you mean?
         
         SAM:  No, when they cut? How long would it take after they cut it to season?
         
         CO:  Oh, t'd take about a week sometimes before it was good enough, see.
         They cut it when it was pretty tough—you couldn't wait till it was ripe
         because then the binder would knock the grain out for you. You couldn't
         cut grain, it had to be tough yet—it took about a week out in the shocks.
         And sometimes they even had to turn the shocks,y'know, to get the inside
         dry, set the bundles this!way if it was kind of a damp fall. But they had
         a wheat here they called the forty-fold we thrashed quite a bit of.
         That was so damn ripc If you wait till that got real ripe before you
         cut if, you wouldn't have more than half of it. You know that kicker in
         in the binder, you just kept kickin that straw all the time, we just
         thrashed it right there.
         
         SAM:  What was the name of this wheat?
         
         CO:  Forty-fold.
         
         SAM:  Forty-fold?
         
         CO:  Yep. It had some damn long straw in if j_t ad stuff was that tall ..
         out it was good wheat and ripened early. That's why they put it in so
         much, y'know. It ripened a whole lot earlier than the Club wheat did.
         
         SAM:  Was most of the wheat fall wheat, or was most of the wheat winter wheat or
         spring planted wheat?
         
         CO:  Well, you could pretty near seed any wheat for fall if you want to. See,
         they didn't have no special wheat for ihat. The reason they planted in the
         fail was that it'd ripe early, y'know. If you was to put in all spring
         wheat it would never rinen up heardlv in some years—it would be Standing
         green, y'know, especially that Slub wheat. That was pretty late, all
         that Club wheat. And I think the Forty-fold had to be seeded in the fall —
         it was a real fall wheat, jt was a bred wheat, y'knov;. The reason they
         called it Forty-fold was because it created forty times as much as the
         seed. But they don't raise that anymore at all. Hell, so much
         straw  wheat they got now, I'd like to thyash that, jesus. We could
         thrash a thousand to fifteen- lundred sacks  About this tall, and
         to Emil's
         heads that long on it, no straw, y'know. I was out one time and
         looked at his wheat. "Jesus, do you expect to get any crop from this?"
         "Yes, I'll get about forty bushels." It looked like ten to me according
         to the old wheat, see. It was that thin when we'd get about ten bushels
         acre.
         
         SAM: What was the yield in those days when you were thrashing?
         
         
         CO:  Oh, if you thrashed a field and made forty bushels, they'd talk
         about it all the time. Twenty bushels was good; now they get as high
         as a hundred. So you see the difference on the wheat too.
         
         SAM:  What was the most you ever did in a day, do you know? Did you ever have
         any big record days?
         
         CO:  Well, that's the one, the big picture that we had there, that we had
         1,142 sacks in nine hours time—that's the biggest record wehad. You
         never had any big job anytime, you had to move so much, y'know, You lost
         there
         so much time movin from one field to the other one, and v was no big
         job. But this fella had a hundred acres of oats-Vnd I knew that the thrashing
         I told them to set the machine in the center of the field.
         "We're going to thrash it all in one pile," I said, " and then I'll go on
         down to get the photographer." And I went down and got him, and we finished
         it in rine hours all right. It was 1,142 sneks,and that was about, fourthousand
         bushels in that setting. That "was on Big Bear. And Case, got
         ahold of that picture--we had a Case machine, y'know—and they sure wanted
         that picture.
         
         SAM:  What did they do with it?
         
         CO:  They took it back East, and they had a magazine out, what in the hell
         was the name? Thrasherman, they called it Thrasherman, so the picture got
         in that. I got a few letters from back East, they had read it y'know.
         them .
         One fella wrote-- I told how many out in one season"- and I
         You wear out
         got a letter from one guy, he said,"How can that be? teeth
         like that?" He couldn't understand. So he wasn't no thrasherman, I know
         that. Teeth was the main thing in the thrash machine. If the teeth got
         too dull, it would chop the straw too, y'know, the bundle wouldn't go in
         fast enough, so it'd break it up and you'd get alot of chaff, y'know in
         the sacks, you couldn't, blow it all off—if you did you'd blow
         wheat too. So they had them made, and they had a little curl on the
         end like that—well, if that wore off, then it wouldn't take it , y'see.
         And the bundles won't go into the cylinder and they could raise hell with
         your feeder, break the chain or somethin because they wouldn't go in fastenough,
         see.
         
         SAM:  Coula you sharpen it, sharpen em up?
         
         CO:  No, some turn em around, but then the hook was the other way and
         they jerked the tooth so fast so it didn't kncsk it out. And that's
         what I wrote and told this guy. But I said, "There's one way you can use
         thevfrV longer without taking them out and that is to bend them forward."
         So we had a rig like that, the bar about that long, we had to put it over
         teeth and then bend the teeth fofward, and you'd get the right curve,
         but if it wore so much then you had to throw tu away, y'see, and you couldn't
         turn em around because then the straw went in too fast.
         
         SAM:  How long did one of the chains last, the teeth?
         
         CO: Oh, that depends on the grain a lot. If it was easy thrashing, why it'd
         last you the whole season pretty near. You'd put in a new set and thrash
         for thirty days, something like that, it'd last you all season. But had
         that bar with us all the time so if they wore down too fast we'd bend them
         forward a little bit, y'see, we didn't have to take cm out,and get the curl
         
         SAM:  Could you bend them quite a few times with. . .
         
         CO: Well, about one time would be about enough, then they'd get down so
         narrow--you had to have it wide this way too, because the teeth in the
         grates, there were teeth there and these went between like this, see.
         
         SAM:  Yea, they went in bee ween each other, yea.
         
         CO: And then if they wear off on the sides, then the heads would
         go through so you couldn't run the teeth on the grates, they wore on
         the sides all the time. They got thin as a knife pretty near. And you
         had to put in new teeth there..'Aid thtre was six rows f you had a bad
         thrashing.There was two rows in each grate, see? And good thrashing like
         used one grate only, and you get into a little Club, you had to
         have em all in—six rows to knock it out. And then it took a lot of powersteam too
         v'know, because it pulled hard. But /', that wheat pretty
         near fall out itself. So it was easy to thrash, byt then it had some damn
         long straw, y'know.
         
         SAM:  What about the oats and beans? Were they very different from the wheat
         to thrash?
         
         CO:  Oh, oats was no different at all. Oats was easy to thrash- you had no
         shell; there, y'see, they just hung on, knock em off is all. But "
         you had to be an expert to thrash, you'd crack em ail to pieces else.
         You got to have a slow motion on your cylinders, and it was double cylinder
         in machine—one back of the other one. So it went through two cylinders,see'
         But they thrashed it once later on, but they cut the speed down, but
         then they didn't knock em all out. Then you had to thrash dirt. It
         wore the machine out so damn fast, y'know, because you got dirt on the
         roots. And it was just dust around the machine, and you just wore out
         everything. It didn't last no time at all—the bean thrasher. And
         then we had to have two rubber rollers, so all the beans had to go through
         the rollers to bust the dirt chunks, see. They were just as heavy as
         the beans, so they'd go in the sack. So it went through them rollers
         and busted the dirt,so you didn't get it in the sack.Or else you get
         about twenty-five per rent dirt in there, chunks like the end of your
         finger, y'know. Mo, that bean thrashing, I didn't like that very good--
         it was too dirty. And then it was hard to pitch that, yknow, there
         was no bundles there, you had to tear them loose in the stack you know,
         and dust and everything else.
         
         SAM:  So thrashing beans was a lot dustier and dirtier than the others, eh?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea.
         
         SAM:  That's funny, it mafces sense.
         
         CO:  See when they harvest them there, they had a cutter ., you know they went
         and cut the roots . You couldn't cut em on the top, y'know, then you couldn't
         get em together-pieces. And they were ripe, y'know, some pods
         ripen faster thantothers, y'know. Then they had to let em lay a long time
         in the field even to let em dry out before "could stack it. And they
         come in late, y'know, it was hard to say;. They lost besn crops every once
         that wray
         in a whle, y'know—they didn't get em in in time. But they got wise—they
         waited too long before they planted em, y'know. If you plant them reai
         early when the ground was warm they'd grow up pretty fast, but if you
         waited too long—they froze so easy, y'know, they were afraid of an early
         frost, see. So they planted em pretty late. But there was pretty good money
         in beans then. The way they farmed Little Bear, they made good because
         y'know theysummer fallowjjhey don't do that anymore, y'know—leave a field
         out, y'know, and put nothin on it. It's what they call summer fallow.
         And then when the bean business come in they put beans on the summer
         fallow, and then they'd plant fall wheat on the sane ground,see? So they
         made good, y'see, they got two crops that way, y'know. But they don't raise
         any more beans at all around here.
         
         SAM:  What happened?
         
         CO:  Well, the prices didn't come up fast enough, I guess. The price was
         pretty good then. They made pretty good on beans. But they start irrigatm;
         down south and all over, and raise'beans, see, and they could do it
         cheaper and better—so we quit altogether.
         
         SAM:  Well now, Carl, when you're talkin about enjoying it, having a good
         time in the harvest crew, you say it's because you got a chance to
         spend time with people and get to know em better.
         
         CO:  Yea. Well, that's what you did—it was something new everyday, y'know,
         especialfyfor us, that had small farmers. We could thrash for three, four
         farmers in a day_ sometimes—small jobs, y'know, and all that. Now
         Ganesee was a little different—they had a different set-up there. They
         had thcook wagore, and it was the big_ farmers there, y'know. So that was
         a whole lot more, you had to have cooks and roustabout, and you had to hve Your
         own bundle teams too—they had a heck of crew to pay, y'know. They had
         about twenty-five, thiy men when we had twelve.
         
         SAM:  Is that how you gotnow a lot of the people around the country?
         
         CO:  Oh, yes. I knew pretty near everybody east of town here, y'know, clean
         on Big Bear and Deary and Dry Creek and Nora and Little Bear—all of them.
         Yea.
         
         SAM:  When you were goin around and thrashin for different people, v/ere most
         people in about the same shape, I mean as far as how well off they
         were?
         
         CO:  Well, ' a farmer'had, say, up to a hundred acres of field or eighty acres, the
         1 were pretty well fixed, them were- y'know, but it wasn't too many of em.
         But the small farmers—they didn't make much, but they worked out a
         whole lot of them people too, y'know. They workC in the woods, and when they
         went and
         started the woods business up here, they'worked
         out too,when they had small farms.
         
         SAM:  Would you say that many of the families were just barely making it
         or were most families gettin by so that they were doin 0K.?
         
         CO:  Well, theymaSe a livin. There was nothin to buy much those days, y'know
         like our family—we didn't buy much stuff. We raised all our food
         and it was a little game in the country. We shot a lot of grouse to
         eat and fish in theBear' Creek and stuff like that. And sell butter, eggs,
         trade for groceries, so you used very little cash, very little. If
         the average farmer had around ahundred dollars income, he was sittin
         pretty good. Yea. And most of the women made the clothes for the kidsth-
         v had sewing machines and they'd buy the cloth, y'know, buy the
         overalls, and make. ..And/lne kid growed "'''and the other one would
         wear it, y'see and so on. So they wore out everything, there was nothin
         thrown away. To find atin car, when Iwas akid was ahelluva job because
         we wanted them to play with.
         
         SAM:  The story about the rooster tannin the man?
         
         CO: Oh yea, that was pretty good. Chat's the only man Iever canned, the rooster
         had to do it
         
         SAM:  Will you tell me what happened there?
         
         CO:  Well, he was kind of aqueer duck, this guy, y'know. So it was in the
         bean thrashing, so we took one man with us extra, in case theWere short
         handed, the farmer »ey furnished the pitchers and everything-all
         we furnished was the sack-sewer and the engineer, about four or five men
         when we went out thrashing beans. So we thought we better hire aman with
         us in case they was short handedr-then he ccdd get up and help them. So
         we hired this guy for that, and I said, "You don't maybe have to work at
         all because if they got a full crew, why you don't have to do anything,
         but if they're short handed then you gotta get out and help them." So
         got over there on the ri'y'know,  was 
         in the barn. I guess we'd been out about aweek maybe and he started
         cussing and swearing up there about 4 o'clock in the morning. He .was
         rolling his bed roil up, and we couldn't figure out what in the hell was
         goin on. So he went, y'know, and I asked the fella; that slept close by
         TV to him, I said,"What in the hell is the matter with Charlie, quittin away?
         And he said, "That rooster crowed ail morning and he got mad about that!"
         So he left. Yea.
         
         SAM:  Hey, what's that story about the hooked noses? Will you tell me that one
         again?
         
         CO:  Well, that a.family around here, they all got such big noses, y'know.
         When i 8een them the first time they lived on Little Bear, then the old man
         and the kids wereen, twelve, fifteen years old, I guess. And somebody in
         the crew said, "That's the best cherry pickers I ever seen." And one
         fella said,"What do you mean by that?" "Don't you see that nose?"he said,
         "they hook that on the limb and they Pick with both hands!" (laughs)
         
         CO:  you don!t nave to tell their name.
         They're living here now, y'know-three of them in town here. And when the
         come and ask me about that one day, and he laughed aboutV Charlie
         Spencer was the one, one of the Spencers married to that family, see?. . .
         Hewas kind of a funny duck all right, that way. You know
         other people told me,"You can never tell when he qiits. If something hits
         him he don't like, he just quit the job and walk off." Yea.
         
         SAM:  Was there much difference among the VW that worked for you? Did some
         of them work a lot better than others? Were some of them a lot more skilled?
         
         CO:  Oh yea, you always find that. And there's a little trick in that too.
         I didn't have to hire too much men, but I founef'a lot about people. If you
         put em on the right job, he's good, and you put him on another job, he's
         just worthless-there's that much difference in people. But people don't
         understand that. That's why they have so much trouble. Some people seem
         to be worthless-you put him on the right spot, maybe he's_reaJL good, y'see.
         And I found that out when 1 worked on the sawmill down there. I was
         kind of a half a boss there, I was millwright, y'know. I straightened
         em up1 kn$t\e feller- he was a funny guy—he was kinda helpless, y'know.
         And Mead said to me, "Well, I guess we'll lay off that feller." They
         bought the sawmill out, and then they were goin to start new, y'know, new
         he people. So I guess we'll weed-our crew out" and said, "We'll let that
         feller go over there,"and this and that. So they started up and they had
         a tail sawyer is what they calleu him, he standi behind the saw and takes
         the lumber away, and that's what this feller done. And my god, he had two,
         three guys there, and none of them knew how to do it, y'know, good workers
         too. So I said, "You, better go back and get Anderson that used to be here—
         he's an expert at that. And 'hej went and hired him back. He knew just
         what to do, y'know. See, there's a trick there, y'know. If you take the
         slab away and let the slab fall the wrong way, you can't push it down on
         the rollers because you got limbs on it too, maybe, and it was round, y'know.
         But you turn the flat side down, and then the boards when you take em }
         you gotta pull this way and get the narrow side up so the edgermen know
         how big a piece of board they can get out of that thing, y'know. And
         that man was an expert there- But you put him in some other place,
         he didn't seem to know how to work at all, see? And that's the difference
         on people. So if you line up your crew right, y'know, why you can get
         along with pretty near anybody, unless it's a feller that absolutely
         know nothing, but you don't find many of them.
         
         SAM:  Would you tell me about what the set-up was in those little sawmills?
         Take the one that you were millwright in. How many men would work in
         the mill? And what were their different jobs?
         
         CO:  Oh, well when I was millwright down here at Kendrick, why that was a small
         mill, it had about twelve, thirteen men only. One was aratchet
         setter, he put up the log y'know, whether it was one inch board or
         two inch board, y'know—he'd pull the lever and push the log up.
         And then the sawyer, he was the guy that done the sawing, running the
         lever. And then they had a turndown man—he turned the log with a
         cant hook on the carriage, y'know, turned the log over. When they
         got so far in, and then they'd turn it three, four times, y'know. And
         then they had the liptender, but we never called him that, the pond duck
         The Walled him here. that's what I done when Iwas a young kid.
         
         SAM:  What was that job?
         
         CO:  That's to pull the logs out of the pond,y'see, up on the deck. Then you
         had the trimmer man. He trimmed the lumber off on the ends, cut off
         the barky end- ,and so forth. And the edgerman—hes the guy that put the
         lumber through the edger and took the edgingsoff, y'know. Like you'd make
         an eight inch board or a ten inch board, you'd move the saws back and forth,
         y'know,see? And then you had aman behind there, throwed cm
         away, y'know, when they come through the edger. And then you had the lumber
         pilers, they piled the lumber out in the yard, and so forth. And then you
         had the engineer to- run the engines, and that's about all of them.
         
         SAM:  What did you use to pull the lumber out of the pond with?
         
         CO:  Well, Ihad acable that went cut, and you laid acable across the chute.
         The chute was like this, see? And the water was up here and the logs ,
         you pull em up on the chute with pike pole... .Then you wrap the cable
         around them andhook them on the main cableand then you had- the drum
         lever, and pulled
         up there and the friction, ipu went and pulled the logs up, y'see-pull
         up three or four or five of them-it depends on the size, sometimes you
         only puirone log up-M ones. Iused to do that, nd that was the
         pond duck, but they call that the Slip tender, and there's where Igot
         when I went on the coast that time here, I told you about when I. . .
         
         SAM:  Hum uh. You didn't—what time was that?
         
         CO:  1917. I took a hundred and sixty dollars and said,"I want to see the
         country now—I don't care if I get a job or not!" Because I was gonna
         be drafted next year. I knew that the war was on, y'know. So I went to
         Portland and I looked through the window, and there was a sign there
         that said they wanted a single jack hammer—four dollars a day—eight hours.
         I looked at it and I said, "I wonder if I should take that job." That's
         what I'd been doing was, mining, y'know. That's where the single jack
         hammer Is, when you hold the bit yourself and then hammer it with the other
         end. So I said, "Well, I guess, no I don't think I want that job. Outside
         work too much, and it's in the fall of the year." So I/went a little farther
         up the street and there was a sign in the window, "A sliptender." Four
         dollars a day, too. So I thought I better go in and find out what that
         feller docs anyway. "What is a sliptender?" And he told me, and that's
         what I'd been doing on the small mills here when I was a kid. So I took
         the job then. And I went to Alma, Washington, they had a shingle mill
         there. And the fella come up, I told him that Iwanted to be a sliptender
         here, and he looked at rne. "You .a slip tender?.' he says," a small guy
         like you? 'I don't think you can make it. I had a man here who weighed
         two hundred pounds and he quit. We'll let you try it anyway." Heck, that
         was nothing for me, that was a different way of pulling up the timber-rit
         was easier because the man that sawed the log off, they sawed if off in
         the length of a shingle, y'know. So you pulled the log—all I done
         —four logs,
         was to hook it on. And one day I only had to pull up four logs They was
         so big—the cedars—that there was enough for two days. So I worked
         there about'month outside there. r bo9S it's gettin too damn wet
         out here—I don't want It rained all the time y'know.
         
         "No," he said, "You can't quit. I got ajob for you. You go up and
         sit above the boiler and drop some extra fuel down .... "they don't get
         enough sawdust to heat the boiler, so you got to throw out slabs for them.
         I sat in the chair like this, and the elevator went right by you.and all
         I'd do is touch em and it'd fall down to the fire men, y'know. So I sat
         there—I think it was only two days. I went back to the boss and I said,
         "No, Idon't want to sit there—I'll go craz sittin there ail alone'doin
         nothrg." "No, you can't quit," he said. "You go out and help .the carpenters."
         They were building the mill bigger, and so I stayed there for about three
         or four months. So you can see, And there's where I found out about they
         had two names only, the people there. I come there and he said,"Hello
         there Mr. Do-more-see-less." I said,"My name ain't that." "Well," he said,
         only use two names out here." He said, "When you lrwwve now, your n.-e
         fre ilfeee more and do leas? but now when you're workin?you» 'see less and
         do morel1 (laughs)
         
         SAM:  What did you think of that country? That country on the coast?
         
         CO:  Oh, Ididn't like it. I was on the, what do they call that? The wettest
         place on the coast, anyway, GraY- Harbor. A little town name Alma there.
         And the Saginaw Timber Company was a big outfit, y'know, they put the
         mill. . .
         
         (End of Side B)
         
         so they kept you fairly busy when you had to pull
         up them sliver8 all the time.
         
         SAM:  What did you think of that country as compared to this country?
         CO; Oh I wouldn't want to live there- it1 too wet. And the funn? DartT
         of it, the sun shone only two chays when Iwas there. Thtm  stayed in
         that' 8 i_ and played poker, the crew-no foolln—not the mil crew, but the ones
         that worked in the woods. And that was just opposite than it was here.
         When it rained we stayed inplayed poker. We wouldn't work in the rain
         at all in the8™1118 out here.
         
         SAM:  It's funny. Why would they do that on a sunny day?
         
         CO:  I don't know. "It was too nice to work," they said, or something.
         That was the funniest thing-- that kind of tickled me too because it was
         just opposite here. See, we got,;irfree board and everything in the sawmills f
         80. we didn't care if we had to lay off a day—we never worked when it
         rained hard. We did a lot of our workin outside, y'know, and get wet all
         over. We didnt havano clothes for rainy weather here—we stayed in.
         re The  when the sun—they stayed in.
         
         SAM:  What did you think on your travels? Did you see much country over there?
         
         CO:  No, I didn't travel too much. 1 stayed there and then I went to Spokane
         and I went to automobile school for a little while and learned how to
         run a car or fix em mostly.
         
         SAM:  Did you learn much at that, school?
         
         CO:  Oh, I learned a little. In those days we could take care of our :car, y'know.
         In those days nobody knew anything about a car, y'know, so you pretty near
         I had to laugh at there. He
         had to do it yourself. They was just comin out, y'know. "the teacher was
         telling us how the car works,and all this and everything, d then he
         said, "If everything is a 11 right and the car won't start, what's wrong
         with it?" Nobody got it right. And you know what was wrong with it? "The
         man on the crank," he said. Y'see they didn't have no self starters then,
         (laughs)
         
         SAM:  Hey, were those people on the coast, did they seem a lot like the people
         out here?
         
         CO:  Oh yea, it ain-t much difference. .... They were about the same. You
         one from another.A can't tell : We haa a lot of people that lived here went to the
         coast too, y'know, and stayed there, and then there isn't too many that
         comes this way from the coast, though, I don't think. But a lot of
         these early people, they went to the coast, y'know, because it started
         boom there, y'know. A lot of them sold their homestead rights
         and went on the coast irkhe early days, there was one homesteader that
         lived close to us , he went to the. coast, and then a fella ,that
         homesteader right close to where you are, he went to the coast too. But I
         think he hadproved up all right, so he sold it. He sold his place to
         somebody because it was startin to boom there then y'know. Building the
         cities and. . .
         
         SAM:  Well, there was one more thing about the sawmills I was wondering about.
         What do those rollers do?
         
         CO:  Oh the rollers? Well, that's where you,suppose the saw is over here now,
         y'see, and the logs sr rollc along there, and then it comes out here.
         And then you take the board, then they got rollers that push it down to the
         trimmer men andtthe edj|er men, and the slabs, they got to go down in the sla
         from the rollers, and that's the ones that I and Carmen put in.
         
         SAM:  Yea, you told me about that, yea .
         
         CO:  And the people they looked and looked to see them—I'll never forget that.
         
         SAM:  What was it that you had to do to make em live rollers?
         
         CO: Well, y'see they were wooden rollers—they sat in the bench and they pinned
         in the end, y'know—they swirled around. Well, the line shaft, y'know
         they had steam engines and then they had%ig line shaft run through the
         mill that they took the power to the edger, y'see? And power to the
         trimmer. And that line shaft happened to run right under the bench.
         
         SAM: Uh huh.
         
         CO:  So we took an old belt and cut em this wide--two inches. And we put em
         on thefshaftVrp to this roller,see? And then 6nom this roller we had another
         one. And from that one this one. So we didn't have em all rollingryJei
         we had to do was just push it alittle
         bit and the live roller would take it, see? And that's the way we made
         it easier for the people. And in those days they didn't saw any timber
         that big. Hell, all the logs were from this size up to that
         size, but now they saw stuff like this all the time.aSo then when they
         squared a log on the carriage in those days, they made one by twel-ryes,
         because that was the popular lumber then tc build barns with, y'know—
         'twelve inches wide and an inch thick. Well vou SqUared that log up and
         sawed all the one by twelves on the carriage, didn't send that lumber
         the edger at all, y'see turn the logs until got it squared up,see?
         And two by twelves, when sawed them did the same thing, and two by
         make that on the big saw, so the.edger man didn't have to do that.
         All the edgerraan got was outside stuff for the log, y'know. See, when you
         cut the bark off and then the next one be maybe be four inches wide, and the next
         one eight, and six—finally they had the log squared up and .'they'd
         saw it all on the big saw. And then you pushed maybe that many stack of
         lumber out on them rollers, and that's where the live rollers come in, y'see.
         You'd push em a little bit, and they'd catch em and way down they go to
         the trimmer man. He'd trimmed em off on the ends, y'see. No, I worked
         on seven different mills here, and there are none of them left.(laughs)
         
         SAM:  How long would those mills work after they got the lumber?
         
         CO:  Well, they run, like I said, about thirty days.
         
         SAM:  That's all.
         
         CO:  For thirty, forty days, that's all.
         
         SAM:  How much would they put out in that time?
         
         CO:  Well, if they had a million feet that was a big run, y'know. But most
         of them had maybe 500,000 or less than that even,because they couldn't
         move the timber veryfar then. They had to have the mills where the
         timber was, y'see, because you had no - trucks-nd they'd haul it in on
         the sleds in the winter, because you couldn't do much loggin with a big
         wagon with wheels that, high on, and it'd be mud holes and they'd sink down
         and get stuck. Very few logged with awagon unless it was right close to
         the roac already. That was tough goin anyway. Y'know the wheel went down
         in the hole- it'd stick the teem, y'know- you couldn't get out even. But
         on the sled, y'know, it was smooth, just like the ice is here. And they
         could take quite a load on the sleds in those days.
         
         SAM:  Did they just cut the trees down in the winter? Or did they let em season?
         
         CO:  No, they cut em in the winter. And snaked em down and then they rolVeii
         on the sleds and haul em in.
         
         SAM:  Snake em down with horses?
         
         CO:  Yea. You only need a coupla horses only. On the sled too, because they
         went up adraw,y'see, mostly. They put amill where there's adraw and
         then they'd log everything downhill, y'know. So they didn't have no
         hills to pull hardly. Unless it was somebody like a farmer—hed had cut
         acoupla thousand feet—he might haul it over there y'know. It'd take
         time Just somethin for it, lit the real timber—they/set the mills
         where there was alot of timber, y'see.
         
         SAM:  So most of the timber came from right around the mills and it was owned
         by the own er of the mill.
         
         CO:  Yea, that or else he'd buy some from the ones that had land there too,
         y see. le'd buy from them- so much athousand. Andthey'd log it. See,
         you could buy logs for about fifty cents athousand—up to adollar and
         ahalf. Of course, the timber was all over and they wanted to get rid
         of it. They wanted to get field on their land, y'see, and all that.
         But like our homeplace--we never logged a log—there was no mill. It
         was one there we could have logged to once, but it come so late that all
         our timber was down in the ear creek canyon, y'know.
         
         SAM:  Was there species that you preferred in the mill? That they wanted to
         have to log?
         
         CO:  Yellow pine and fir. They took tamarack, too, but not so much. Yellow pine—
         they made one inch stuff from that. And the fir was two inch stuff—
         two by fours and stuff like that. And then when the yellow pines got
         gettin scarcer, then they took more fir. Some of them wouldn't log anything
         but pine—pine logs, that's all. Because this old lumber around here, y'know,
         was pretty close, most of it too, then.
         
         SAM:  I heard the Troy Lumber Company was quite a big operation.
         
         CO:  Oh, yea. I worked for them too.They had the first mill up here—the
         White Pine Mill—that was a band mill, they put that in. That was the
         biggest one they had, or ehe they had a lot of small ones—three or four
         small ones around the country. And then they had a factory down here—
         they made sash and tWs and all kids of building material here then too.
         And then they moved down to Lewiston and Clarkston. So they haven't
         got any sawmills anymore. hcy just retail lumber, I guess.
         But they were pretty big then, for those days, I mean. See, the Potlatch
         mill, that come in in 1906, I think.. And then it changed the lumber
         business quite a bit, yknow»-that big mill up there. And then the Elk
         RiveH'mill come in 1912. So then things started kinda booming around here.
         There was a lot of work then. You could go to Potlatch sawmill and get
         a job, And ' . like I said, it was no year round jobs to start with, but
         then when those big mills come in they run year round, y'see. So a lot
         of people went and got work there.
         
         SAM:  So I imagine then that the little mills started falling off about then.
         
         CO:  Oh yea, they were going pretty fast, yea. And then when the Second
         World War broke out,that's how they happened to get a mill down in
         Kendrick andJuliaet layknow, it was such ademand for lumber,Cut
         they was small mills. They bought stuff here and there and put em in.
         
         SAM:  You know there's a story Iwant to ask you to tell me about. You told
         me it was about a cow dying because his friend the sheep. . .
         
         CO: Yea, I've never figured that one out yeb. It's no humbug about it.
         It's absolutely the truth—everything that happened. I don't know why
         the cow died, unless he happened to get sick, but I don't believe so.
         I think it was because he killed the sheep. No those two animals be
         together all the time, no matter where they were. We had five or six more
         cows, y'know. And this sheep and the cow,they'd be out in the field in
         the fall, and they'd be together all the time—ail the time. And then
         when fall come we used to throw the hay out on the snow, y'know, so we
         didn't have to feed em inside, Add we done that, and we had the hay
         scattered here and there, y'know, for the cows, And then this cow
         and her sheep—they were eating at one pile. And two other sheep come
         running from the other one down to that pile. And the old cow done and
         grabbed her and tore her whole stomach open right there. We had to
         butcher her right there. And then x got through eatin we put @m in
         the barn like we always did. , My brother Oscar and I, we date the feeding, and
         tied em up— we didn't have no stanchions, y'know. And
         next morning "come, '' that old cow standing up in the manger and
         trying to push herself out against awoo ien log barn, y'know, you couldn't
         push the wall down. And she stood there and chewed foam, y'know and
         grunted. And you couldn't do nothin with her. She stood up in the
         manger and wanted to go forward, forward. And in about two or three
         days we come down and she lay dead in the barHhere. And that all happened
         from the time when she killed her friend. I don't if they got instincts
         like that or not.
         
         SAM:  You mean that now the sheep came down to get some of the hay.
         
         CO:  The other two come. See, this cow and the sheep were eatin from, and
         when them two come theCow didnt want them around her sheep. And she
         wrong and ripped her open
         hit the one with her horn, see. And that's what done it. My mother, she
         didn't know what to think about It. She thought maybe it was something
         in that too. There was nothing wrong with the cow--we milked her all the
         time and fed her in the barn. We called her Redsiie because she was a
         white cow with two red r pScomiti down on the sides here, y'know. But
         I never did talk to any animal doctor about thatso I don't know
         what he'd say.
         
         SAM:  But they'd been friends for a long time before that?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea. Ayearl they were together like that—they wouldn't part at
         all Isn't that somethin?, Now if it'd been i animals with the
         same kind of a fur or skin—but the sheep had wool and she had hair. And
         how they could be so friendly is the funny part of it. They never was
         apart—no time. No matter where they went. Went down the pasture in the
         woods—they'd be together there. No, that's somethin I never could figure
         out really.
         
         SAM:  How did It come about that you had to go into the World War I? What
         happened there?
         
         CO:  Well, they drafted em. I was that age—I was twenty-three years old
         then and I tried to get an extension so we could finish up the harvest,
         y'know. Mel1, we didn't get no extension. They give farmers extensions
         all right, but it wasjust as important to thrash the wheat as to raise
         it I guess. So I didn't get any. I was out two days with the machine and
         I had to go. And then about twenty days after that my brother was drafted).
         that was with me in the thrashing business. But then we had to
         turn it over to Albert—Albert and Bob, they thrashed for on this ridge here, so
         Albert took over, no, Bob took over the machine from then on. And that
         was a good harvest too, y'know. We got a poor treatment there.
         
         SAM:  Did you not want to go at all anyway? Or did you. . .
         
         CO:  Oh, no, I didn't want to go anyway, but you ccddn't stop it. But they
         should have give us the same extension as the farmers got to get
         their crops in. And taking both of us too, that was the worst part of
         it. It was a big bean harvest that year, too. I 'forgot how many
         bearfaCufcre wasfonyfltle Beat—the bluest crop they ever had.
         And we just had our new machine only one year then. We owed seven-hundred
         dollars on it I guess, on the bean machine too.
         
         SAM:  How much did it cost you when you bought it from Hawkinson?
         bean machine—we bought that
         after, that cost 1?00 dollars, I believe. It was a wooden machine; it wasn't
         no good anyway. It fell to piece in two years. Yea, 2500 ,A riq like
         that cost about 3J500 dollars new then—the steam engine, twenty
         horse C engitf and thirty-two inch machine, and awater tank with it and
         wagon.
         
         SAM:  When you say a thirty-two inch, what do you mean?
         
         CO:  Wide. And there was thirty-two inches this way too—the cylinder. That's
         the way that they figured} the machine was twenty-eight inch or twenty-four
         inch, y'see and thicty-two, and they made em up to thirty-six, I believe,
         the biggest.
         
         SAM:  Well, that was a pretty good business when you were doin it for you then?
         
         CO:  Oh, yes, that was awful good business. Everybody wanted to be thrashermen
         y'know—they made a little money there in those days. That's about the only
         thing there was any money in, y'knowexcept workin for a dollar a
         day, and there was nothin in it.
         
         SAM:  You mean it was better money than farming was?
         
         CO:  Oh, yes. If you had a good fall, you'd make pretty good. Yu had something
         that paid you a thousand dollars a year—that was a big income then.
         
         SAM:  Well, why did you sell?
         
         CO:  Well, I sold because steam thrashing was goin out. Combines was comin
         in, and gasoline power,o the farmers,, buy a gas rig together, two or
         three of them and thrash- . their own grain, y'see. I bought a gas rig
         afterwards, but I only used that two years and I got rid of it. it was
         he'd have a gas rig himself Andyou had to go wa off to get another job
         and it was scattered out—there was nothing usre. So I quit that and I
         went into the automobile business down here, but that was worse yet.
         Depression comin on—so Ilived through two of them now. The 1933
         depression, that was abad one, closed the banks up and everything else.
         I don't know what they'll do yet. Maybe they'll close up the whole
         country, huh? What do you think about it?
         
         SAM:  It doesn't look too good to rne. I think there's a good chance we're
         headed for a depression.
         
         CO:  Yea, we got both at one time. We got inflation and depression, but the
         then 1930s they had the depression only—no inflation. So you could do
         do eomethin''now it, something. Orthat one hand that would help if you 
         again. Awww, the people are asleep. They don't know how to run nothing
         when it comes right down to it. Don't you know that every man that's
         walkin is just as important as the other oneJ They can't get that in
         their noodle, y'know. They want to pay one man $100,000 dollars a year
         and another $1,000.. If it wouldn't be for ou and me and that, there
         would be no houses—there! be nothing. Aren reportant. Here
         these politicians they get sixty, seventy thousand dollars a year and
         they raise their salaries anyway. No, we can't run a nation like that,
         that'll never work. YouHhat everybody gets a joband there's where
         They with the people. I think we should have a thirty
         hour week now myself. And they should be paid enough so that ire)live
         according to our country. And no overtime, that's another e Because
         then the people can't work and make a few dollars extra anymore because
         they don't want to pay that, see? And it's the same thing, if you have
         a contract somewheres, and yo8move a whole lot of machinery in there
         and you got a job to finish before winteryou can't pay them time
         and a half to finish jobs, so they have to quit and go back next spring.
         That nuts the cost uo. You have to re-start, y'know. And waiters are
         the ones that get hooked worse.They can't work over eight hours, y'know,
         is, and y'know Whaa restaurant those eight hours a day may not have a gol
         damn person there. Should let em work twelve if they want to, but no
         overtime,see?
         
         SAM:  Do you think everybody could be given the same amount of money? Everybody
         could make the same?
         
         CO:  Well, I don't say it should be exactly the same-that wouldn't work either
         I don't think , but I mean thyshould have it pay_ according to how we live
         in this country, what it takes for a family of four or something, and-pay
         that kind of a wage, see . And then theyshould get away from this income
         tax business, taking your money away from you before you can use it. That's
         work, so you can the dirtiest law we have. When you go out and work, yoil want toYget
         some
         money so you can buy your car or home or clothes or stuff. Then they take
         that money before you can use it. They should tax it at the factorymanufacting
         tax, that's where it should be. Then if you got a bad year,
         say, well, I'll wear these shoes twice as long now$and I wonlt buy
         me no pants,add that way you can get back «, see? That's adjusted itself--
         that tax system. If a man's get a lot of money, he'll buy just the
         same anyway. And how simple it be to collect It. Just one man, one
         person, you might say,at the factory,owns it and does the business, and
         he sends a check to the government and that's all there's to it. Here
         they got income tax where tfiygfattct for this, djuct for that and
         deduct for this, and fuss  it up,so It costs them twenty-five per
         cent to collect the taxes. Yes, it doe Manufacturing tax'it wouldn't
         cost them anything. Y'know, you make so many yards of cloth or automobiles
         or whatever it is, but then the politician will come around,
         or other people -"- they're queer, y'know. They don't
         savvy how , stuff works. You' t0 have labor, don't you ,to make
         something nd you gotta have taxes ta run the country. Those two thin
         are with us forever,see? But then they'll say, "Well, if you make a
         that material, he'll have „ manufacturing tax ,then the man that bu to pay the tax.
         Well, don't they pay for tabor? Isn't that more than the tax? They don't
         kick on that. So if you get somlhin left in the store that you can't sell,
         it s you have paid for the lebopSj.o there you", same thing, ' here. It's
         got to have the taxes to run the nation with .and you got to have the labor
         the things. And if they don't sell that part, they're out the
         labor, aren't they? They're but the taxes too. It's nothin wrong with
         it at all. But that's what they'll use, y'know. They won''Well now .when
         I buy something 1 have to pay taxes on this and have it in the .belli' Well,
         why don't they say''ve got to pay labor and leave it on the shelf too?
         Because taxes and the labor,we go to have.
         
         SAM:  Carl, did yo"borrow money fr0m the Bank of Troy when you went in to
         business? Did you have to borrow? Or hcw'd you get started?
         
         CO:  No, I never borrowed any. Well 1 did too. I owed the bank 
         I think, when they closed it. But I had that much on the account too.
         And I asked them afterwards—"I wouldn't have lost anything then," I said.
         "You bet you would have lost, you wouldn't get paid for that money you
         had there-you had to pay the bill anyway." So you see the ws are 
         
         SAM:  So you didn't use the sank at Troy.
         
         CO:  Well, I did for a while there. I wanted to sell the farm y'know, and then
         I'd get money and the banker said,"No, you don't have to sell the farm
         for that. You can come in here and borrow some money if you want it. " But
         I was just about ready to pay up there wTiat I owed". I'd been buying a whole lot
         cf cars end stuff.-it wag  and j had that much in the checking
         but I would have lost the whole business the way the law was.
         
         SAM:  Were they good to ycu ss far as giving you what you needed? The bank?
         
         CO:  Oh yea, I cculd get anything I wanted. The banker even, when I built the
         service station, y'know, I had a son with me when we went to Moscow and
         it didn't pay good the so I sold out. We didn't make no money, we were runnin behin
         to beat the banker, he come over to me and said, "You build
         a service station." And I said, "No, I can't afford it now, broke."
         "No," he said,'you go ahead and build and you go out to the lumber yard and
         get your stuff and charge it and build it!" So I did.
         
         SAM:  This was Ole, Ole. So first you started in Moscow and then you came to Troy
         with the business
         
         CO:  Well, I first started here. I sold Oldsmobiles here, y'know, and things
         was going pretty good so kid, he come around and he said, "I want
         to go in with you. How much will it cost?" "$5,000," I said.
         And he done that, y'know. And then the big outfit in Spokane we
         dealtthr?u§ney had a garage in Moscow, the fella wanted to quit, so
         we bought them out,see, up there. And then we moved across the street
         and took the Chevrolet afterwards, But then started getting so
         bum we ' couldn't sell nothin.And then the trade-ins were bad those
         days, y'know, cause all the cars you trade1 in, you couldn't hardly
         sell em,because they were out of date ahundred per cent. Just like" the
         Model T now, and that Chevrolet, first to come out, they fell to
         pieces y,know in a hundred miles. And you couldn't sell that stuff,
         And you couldn't hardly make a deal without takin a trade in, y'know. And
         the profit wasn't too much on the Chevrolet, either.
         
         SAM:  About when was this?
         
         CO:  1927-and'23 when I was up there. And then in '29 I went down here and
         built this service station.
         
         SAM:  Did the bank change much from BeW to Brocke,or were they much the same
         in their way of philosophy, way of dealing with people?
         
         CO:  Well, they were both good that way. there were a lot of Swedes
         here and he was a Swede, and a lot of them come from the same part, so
         he got a lot of help from 
         
         CO:  Yea.
         
         SAM:  The same part what, of Sweden? Where?
         there too.
         
         CO:  Oh farmland they call it, and right around nd Brocke, he learned
         a lot from him, y'know,, W the bank was run. They run this bank
         just like it belonged to everybody, the way it should be run, y'know. If
         they knew aman was good, why they gave him money he didn't have to
         put up any mortgage,"yriSw. And that's what kicked Brocke out. He was
         running in on the old liberal way. And they got new bank laws now, y'know.
         And that's the trouble there. And there's so many people banking now, too
         so you have to runthebank- different, y'know ,too. Such a thing as
         writing a bad check those days, it was never heard of anything like
         that hardly, nd being in the red, and all such things.
         
         SAM:  But I heard that Broke was real good at being able to decide if a person
         could be trusted or not—he was a real good judge of people.
         
         CO: Yea, he did, see,he was born and raised around here and he mingled with
         the people so he knew them. 
         
         (End of Side C)
         
         And that's trgs way a lot of them got started here, y'know- didn't have to
         put up any collateral at all. Just like when I went down there and I
         talked to Qev\rMb 1 said I wanted to sell my place ,I guess. He said,"
         You don't need to do that. You can borrow the money if you want, if you need
         any." So things are different y'see.
         
         SAM:  Well, when you started selling cars were they just pretty new in the
         country still
         
         CO:  Well, they wasn't real new because they'd been selling a lot of Fords and
         Chevrolets then, y'know. In 1920 is when the car business started to
         boom, y'know. Then everybody started owning them, in the twenties.
         And I was down here in '26 and '27 and '28 and »29, y'see, so it was goin
         up pretty fast. But then we got that depression y'see, and set back things.
         Pretty near all the people that was dealing in automobiles .went broke,
         every one of them. Two, three in Lewiston and Spokane and here,down in
         Pullman. It was just like I said, you had to take in po trades. And
         then.you had to guarantee the paper. The banks wouldn't look at anything
         when you sold a car--they wouldn't take it at all. Then if you had to
         repossess it, then you had to pay it OUt yourself—even anew car, y'know.
         If you bought a new car you had to pay so much down, and then there was
         interest to pay, and then there was insurance to .pay and all that. So
         if you got a third down on it and put it on the paper, he hadn't paid anything
         that guy--he still owed just as much as the car did. And then we 
         stuck with that, y'see it would put us in, we could buy a new car for
         that money, less money than the old. And they had one finance company
         were that would take it and guarantee it, but the rates so high that
         you couldn't sell a car if you used that So you had to use that other
         one, and when you signed it.
         
         SAM:  Why wouldn't the banks tke it. . .I don't know.
         
         CO:  They wouldn't take any automobiles at all. Oh, thy might take come rich
         feller, but he didn't need the money, he wouldn't buy one unless he had
         the moaey anyway, bigger people.
         
         SAM:  Did you have many contracts fall through?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea, werepossess . quite a bit. And that's what made it so tough
         y'know. And then those old cars, y'know, that you took in, they were
         outmoded anyway.Therewas one car that the Chevrolet had—they gave $35
         to smash it upYea, WciSfse they didn«t want to make parts for em anymore,
         see? And when you ffade, maybe you have to give fifty or a hundred ifor
         that. Well, that was your profit right there, see? So it was pretty tough
         sleddin. They'd come down, yknow, and then they changed the models from
         '27 to '28--the '28 was twice the car the '27 was, see?
         
         SAM:  Twice the car?
         
         CO:  Yea, twice as good built, everything in it. The '27, that fell to pieces
         all the time, y'know. I they come down and said, "We got four carloads
         of '27 cars you gotta take." I said, "We won't take a Rocramn one-"
         "Well," he sad,"then you lose your franchise." I said,"What's the difference.
         J.f we take the cars we broke and we lose it anyway." So we finally
         agreed then e had a truck sold ,and there was a truck on one of them,
         so we took one of the carloads because we had that truck on it. But then
         we had three '27's anyway there. And we had some on the floor, and you
         would have made ninety dollars profit on those damn things, y'know.
         And the new Chevrolet didn't cost any more and they were worth $200
         more at least, just even the looks on em—they were a little bigger
         and nicer and better built all over. So you see what a pickle that was.
         No, one went and we repossessed , the big finance man come out,and
         "We got to go down and repossess it. Yea,a Model-T on Texas Ridge, you
         better go with me." So we went and there it stood way on the rimrock.
         I said, "Leave it there. Let's go home—it's goin to cost us more to
         take it home than it's worth."
         
         SAM:  What had they done? They'd thrown it over the side? How had they gotten
         it down there?
         
         CO:  I don't know, somebody that couldn't pay for it, he didn't give a damn,
         I guess he drove it down there and left it there. Then I talked to a
         dealer from North Dakota after I was in the service on how he come
         out. "Oh," he said, I went plumb busted. They come around, the finance
         company around and said yOU gotta go out and repossess the cars. Well,"if
         I do I'm broke. There's no use—I can't do it."'Well," the finance man
         said, e'11 let it go for six weeks and then we'll go out and see what we
         can do." And when they went there wasn't a goddamn tire on the cars or
         nothing—they'd stole all the tires, broke the windshields and everything--
         ruined them. He lost everything, see? And it won't much better now,
         if it gets really bad. I think ninety per cent of the cars, not ninety
         fifty per cent of the cars. maybe more than that. Who are
         they gonna sell era to? Most families got two cars already,or three. And
         there's no opening for a used car. If you have to take them back, why gee
         whiz, what a pickle that would be. You'd never come out—they couldn't
         heres
         sell em anyw , because they already got cars.
         
         SAM:  When you were selling cars were most of the cars the first one that the
         person had owned?
         
         CO:  Yea, a lot of them. I had to train people how to drivp, yknowi too.
         Quite a few of them. But he said,"Never train your wife to drive because
         that don't work. Let somebody else do that. Because they get so nervous
         and funny. The best place is to go out on a field somewheres where there's
         open ground ,and they learn quickest there, y'know. Because if you get
         on the road they get nervous—seeing anothe"- car comin. And if you get
         on the field, you can drive any old direction, stop and start." So I
         done thot a little bit, all right. Took em out on an opening somewheres.
         
         SAM:  Who is this he you're talking about.
         around and
         
         CO:  Well, it was one of the territory men that comes and checks see if
         everything is all right.
         
         SAM:  So you took people out and taught em how to drive?
         
         CO: Yea.
         
         SAM:  Was that hard?
         
         CO:  Oh no, it was pretty easy,because they were pretty simple then.The only thing
         when they jumped from the Model-f to the gear shift, y'know ,then they was
         a little ' Put for a drive we were all right, y'know. But I guess
         I told you about that man who come around and the fella told him,
         "i traded cars up here two years ago and I got beat,"he said,"and I didn't
         want anybody to know about it.
         
         SAM:  No.
         
         CO:  He told the Chevrolet guy "Well, what's the matter with it?" he said.
         "Well, it makes a helluva noise in there," he said,"when back up.ar
         it in the garage, y'know." So he said," I'll go with you home and see."
         There stood a car, two years old, brand new--he just drove it home, that
         guy. And there was nothing wrong with it—he was gonna back out he
         didn't push the clutch in—he pulled on the lever. And it rattled when
         the gears started goin together. And this fella said, "Why you
         go back and tell him or. . . " "Oh, I d%n»t know, I thought somebody had
         beat me," he said, "and I don't want anybody to know that I gct beat."
         And that was true, that story, it was the Chevrolet man himself that told
         it.
         
         SAM:  So he left it sittin in his garage for two years?
         
         CO:  Yea. Never moved it. /ftlust drove it lorne. He traded off a Model-T, y'see,
         and he thought the outfit beat him, sold him a rattletrap, see?
         
         SAM:  I heard stories about how when they first came in with the cars that
         people would try to stop em by yellin "Whoa."
         
         CO:  Yea, they done that too, all right. Yea, they done that all right, Sut take
         a Model-T was pretty easy to learn to drive. If you c6Ld steer that's about
         all you had to do. You had your pedais there,you'know. Pedal' for back
         up, pedal fr srake, nd Pea for second gear and all that. So it was
         a pretty good little car?Because they had,poor roads then too, you know
         oles so ymi fcad to carry a stick with you to see if you could get
         across or not. One fella went back East in a Model" T, he said he drove that
         car about forty miles an hour all the way there, on the highway, see? It
         never hardly ever broke down, yfknow-Model"T»s--they were tough. You
         had to do a lot of upkeep on em like the ignition system, y'know, Ihey had
         them coils in there, you had to file them so they'd cut the electricity
         off right, y'know--that's about all pu had to do in em, and then put brake
         linings in, 0 nothin else broke'era—hardly ever. And they were handled
         pretty rough, too, y'know on these kind of roads we had,
         w where you'd have to back UP and take a run at lt
         to make it over the hill and all that. But they had the best steel in
         them, Model'T's was ever made, y'know, pretty near all of t was Swedish
         steel in all the shafts and axels. ; Peterson and
         Carlson stated there, a wrench factory? they bought Model-T
         axels and braces}and that's what they made them good tools from.
         Even the fender brace, y'know, that come out to hold up the fender,
         a little rod 'bout like your finger, but it tapered, kind of. And you know
         what they made of them? Tiicy just took em in there and cut em off and
         made punches—best punches in the world.
         
         SAM:  What factory is this?
         
         CO:  That's Model T--Ford.
         
         SAM:  Oh, you said Peterson and.  
         
         CO:  Yea, Peterson and Carlson, they used to come around and sell tools when
         I was in business, y'know,sockets and all kinds . And they started from
         that, buying up old Model~T wrecks and stuff, and took all that good stuff,
         the axels out and braces ,and made tools from them. And they guaranteed their
         tools, that's why they got uch a good name. Pretty hard to beat that
         Swedish steel, y'know. And they put that in the axels and stuff, y'know too,
         something that had to carry anyUoad, they always put the best steel in there.
         
         CO:  Where was the money in the business for you? Did you get it from sellin
         the cars?
         
         CO:  Well, I never made any money, never made any money there. Made more
         workin, thrashing and workin out. No, and the damn gas ,1 didn't
         make no money there. I was right through the depression with the whole
         works. I jsst had the station finished in 1930, and it was depression after
         that. But I was single and I lived upstairs and had a bed up there—it
         didn't cost me anything to live. So I didn't lose it. 'But I got a good
         break when I got through building that station and the shop back there too,
         y'know. And the fella wio was hauling oil to me from Deary, he bought it.
         And I got $8,500 for it and that's what. I paid for the whole works. So I
         had the shpp left, so I come out there, y'see or else I'd been broke.
         And then leasedit back from him, y'know, so I run it then for about
         eight, ten years "But didn't make any money though. I was sittin in
         em there watching the other day, three cars come in there and bought gas.
         You know how many trips I had to make out when I was there to sell that
         much gas? Twenty trips! Well, they bought two gallons, three gaiona ,and
         four gallons was abig sale—that was two bits a gallon—one dollar, see?
         And they come in and bought six, seven, eight, ten dollars worth of gas—
         those three cars. And there's ten times as many cars oat as there was then.
         
         SAM:  Yea, that's right.
         
         CO:  Sure. We only got three cents a gallon profit.
         
         SAM:  That's i?hat you got then? Three cents a gallon?
         
         CO:  Yea. Well, hell/you'd go out there and sell adollars worth, four gallons,
         you'd make twelve cents. And then you had to wipe the windshields for em
         and put the chains on for nothin and.
         
         SAM:  Put the what on?You had to put chains on?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea. We never charged for that because the other service station
         didn't. So you had to do what they did. Now they charge you a dollar and
         a half, I believe,to put chains on. So there was no profit.
         
         SAM:  What about on repairs? Did you make money fixing up cars?
         
         CO:  No,we never done any, I leased the shop out back there It was different
         people run that. I got thirty dollars amonth rent from it, y'see, and
         that's what kept me goin, see. I slept upstairs and went across the
         street and got ahamburger and aglass of milkmen1 went UP and Slept
         upstairs. Then I had six-hundred dollars in the safe. Ihad a safe down
         there—I didn't deposit any money there for three or four months, y'know.
         Ijust put the cash in the safe and deposited the checks only. So I had
         a little money in the depression. That helped me collect some bills that
         way too, y'know. They come in there and want to pay with acheck, y'see.
         And I got squared up and the banker said, "Where in the hell did that
         fella get all the money from, anyway That's the only bank in Troy that's
         any good,"
         
         Ole Bohman said. No, I didn't want to quit depositing all together
         because that would hurt the bank, y'know. I knew that they was goin under.
         A fella from Spokane told me that. And then I told that
         fella in Deary1 H/sVrvLce station, I said," If you got any money in
         the Deary bank you better pull her out." "No, no," he said, "the big bank
         on Spokane is behind it," he said. "Well," I said, "that's why it's goin
         under." lie didn't take it out either, and they lost quite a bit up there.
         "No," he said, "the reason they're goin broke, they got so much money loaned
         on timber." Ana you couldn't sell a board in the depression, y'know—the
         timber was worthless . And if you had it on cattle, then you were finished
         right. You couldn't aell the cattle—you had to feed em and that cost
         moftsy, y'see. But that was poor loans, y'see, and thats what this fella
         said, he was a government man, I think. And he said/'They're goin broke
         all them banks.
         
         SAM:  But not the Bank of Troy—the Bank of Troy made it.
         
         CO:  Yea. It made it. It was the only one around the country that made it too.
         
         SAM:  Oh, I wanted to ask you about prohibition.
         
         CO:  Prohibition? (chuckles) 
         
         SAM:  Yea. I was goin to ask you about what you remember about that? You
         told me once that you got arrested but you didn't do anything.
         
         CO:  Yea. I took a guy home then. I was workin in the service station down
         there,that Dinsmore, he had the first one, I worked for him. And we
         were open till eleven o'clock, y'know, and I closed the doors, and had
         this money in my pocket and everything,and then a fella said, "I want to
         take me home.to far to walk-"
         And that was a fella that owed me some money- thrash bill—he owed
         me a thrash bill. I thought I'd better be on the good side with him and
         took him home. Then I went to drive up to his house he said, "No, it's
         a rough road, stop here by the road." We stopped there and here comes the
         policeman. And he had a pop bottle full of whiskey, and he sat that in
         the car and jumped out and said, "I want to see who they are." And then
         I found out they were policeman and I was 8ointo throw it out, y'know,
         and they grabbed it before I got rid of it. So we got arrested for
         havin liquor, But I didn't get anything for that. I pr it there, but
         they wouldn't take ray word, I said, "lookee here, I'm no bootlegger
         or anything. I'm workin for a station down here, there's the checks in
         heard it the here and everything." So Axel Bohman.he next day,and he come
         right up to Moscow and turned me loose. He told em the whole story.
         But he got a little fine and thirty days or sometiiin,! forgot, twenty
         days or somethin.  
         
         SAM: So they believed you after.  .
         had nothin to do with that. I
         
         CO: Well, I had the proof, I But I went up to thettial
         when they had it, this guy, y'know.
         And I learned a whole lot there. The people on the witness stand lies only-,
         they never tell the truth. And he didn't tell one thing the truth. Here's
         what he said about me: "He reached down here, he said, 'Do you want a night
         cap?' andhanded it to me." And that's what he_ did. He's the one
         that had it here. And everything they asked him, pretty neai ,it was the
         same story—it was all lies, (cackles) Yea.
         
         SAM:  Did you ever hear about Sam BcKeon's moonshinin?
         
         CO:  Oh yea, he was ne of" thlxpert? here. He's the one that sat on the box
         and had a whole gallon under it when they come out to search him. They
         never lift/the box up,and there was his whiskey sittin out on the lawn, see
         He knew they was cornin, uess,so he put the whiskey under the box and
         sat down on it. And then they searched his house and didn't find nothin.
         Yea. Everybody made whiskey pretty near then, after learn how to make
         it.It was pay thirty dollars a gallon for moonshine when you can
         make it for fifty cents. (Breaks)We wcnt barefooted In the smw, that's
         true, but I'll tell you how it happened mostly. See, we didn't have no
         overshoes those days, we only had leather shoes ,and we used them in the
         winter--they pet wet. And then they got so hard you couldn't get em
         on your feet, y'know, you had to grease em up when they dried out. So
         we'd run to the barn and back and fed the cattle baref- We didn't
         thTou ch run out the snow or anything like that, y'know. And that's the way
         that happened. So we madefown shoe grease, y'know. We got ahold
         of a bin cast iron kettle aid then cut a whole lot of chips, y'know, it
         was pitchy, end then we built a fire outside and got the tar out. The
         tar, you know what that is. And then we mix that with lard—tallow.
         our shoes And boilHt, and that's what we greased- with. And we didn't have
         any grease then so we couldn't get our shoes on.
         
         SAM:  So then you had to run barefooted?
         
         CO:  Yea, we had to run out and feed the cattle, y'know. Y0U could put somebody
         else's shoes on if you wanted to, but we just done-that for fun to see
         how we'd like it,about a hundred and fifty feet to the barn and back, so
         it get s pretty cold. We got kind of a kick out of it, y'know, too. But
         with we couldn't get o«t in the winter very much leather shoes only, y'know.
         
         SAM: I don't know how your feet could stand it?
         
         CO:  Well, the only time we could stand it was when the snow was real frozen
         hard so we could run on the top of it. Then leather shoes would do pretty
         well, y'know.
         
         SAM:  No,I mean in barefeet, horyou could stand.  .
         
         CO:  Oh, well, you had to run fast, y'know. It got pretty cold all right.
         
         SAM:  So everything you told me is true.
         
         CO:  Everything. And I could mayDe tel1 You more too» but 1 don't know.
         did you, Yea. You didn't make your second lady and show your wife that I showed you
         here?
         
         SAM:  What?
         
         CO:  VictfAnderson, the clown
         
         SAM:  What was that again?
         homes,
         
         CO:  He played the Jew's harp, this guy, and he went between the house, he
         lived there right close to us and played for you for fun. He made a
         horn;bark and you could hear him for a quarter mile.
         
         SAM:  He made a horn of bark?
         
         CO:  Yen. And sang in it. And then he played the Jew's harp. And then they
         always ask him, "Are you single?" "No1}0! got my wife with me all the tine."
         Then he'd take that out of his box and put them two eyes here and a little
         hair and"11 are she is--'She's with me all the time,"he said, "don't you see
         her?" 
         
         SAM:  (laughs) I showed you that here,didn't I?
         
         SAM:  Were the two eyes little buttons?
         
         CO:  What he usedf had regular dolls eyes, y'know, those that tip back and
         they fit food here.,
         forth. That's what he got ahold of, and iut I made me a pair
         of
         here for fun. Maybe I lost them too—here—just a couple beads. See,
         (Carl clinches his fist.)
         
         put that there, see? That's the eyes, see? Like this. And then you wrap
         your handkerchief around there and then you got a real person there. See?
         And you see ther16 altoo, it moves. -. (laughs)
         
         SAM:  Carl,what's the story that goes along with the heaven and hell that. . .
         What's the story that goes along with that?
         
         CO:  Oh, you can use any story you want. If I wa3 goin to show it to you now
         I'd use it between Nixon and Agnew.
         
         SAM:  What was the story that he used to tell.
         
         CO:  Well, he used the presidents all the time, this fella that told it, but
         they were dead then. But-Nixon, and if you want to make a good story
         about it, what I'd do, I'd say, "Well, here is Nixon and Agnew goin to
         Heaven. And then Nixon says, 'What did you do with my passport?" Oh, don't
         you remember,'Agnew said, 'you told me to sell that for $50,000 and we
         split the money. Oh and don't worry—you can haveihalf of mine, we'll get
         in anyway.' That's the story I'm gonna use on it.
         
         SAM: He said, "ou give him half of mine, we'll get in anyway,"and then he
         gives him the bad half.
         
         CO:  Yea, he gives the bad half to him. And St. Peter said, "You go down
         there- you don't belong up here." When the one that gets across he says,
         "Come on in, come on in."
         
         SAM:  And what was the song that Victor Anderson used to sing?
         
         CO:  He used to sin- a Swede song. Did you understand it?
         
         SAM:  Come on, you know I don't.'"May I put a ring on your little white hand,
         and a crown in your hair, and you shall be my maiden so long as we're
         here on the world." That's the way the song goes in English. It's
         a nice song, y'know. "May I put a ring on your little white hand," see
         he's singin to his girl. "And a crown in your hair, and you can be my
         maiden so long as we're here on this world." That's what he used to sing.
         But his hoofnrt see....
         
         SAM:  With the Jew's harp and the. . .
         
         CO:  Yea, Jew's harp—he played that all the time. He was a real clown. They
         haven't got any clown as good on T. V. as he was. He's kind of funny
         lookin too, y'know, so he could put on. That's old Vic Anderson.
         His brother lives in Clarkston, the oldest one, he's ninety-three years
         old, I believe.
         
         SAM:  Is that Art Anderson?
         
         CO:  Yea. And Victor he was the oldest in that family, well they had three
         or four girls too.
         
         (End of Side D)
         
         SAM:  You know, there's one thing I want to ask you about end that was. . .It
         seems to me that it's hard to find what the true story is of the early
         days, y'know, in the West. It seems Like you always hear about Buffalo
         Bill and that sort of stuff and you don't hear about the homesteading
         and the way that it was.
         
         CO:  I read en article in, I don't know if it was Reader's Digest over
         three or four years ago,and they said that they didnrt give the right
         people the honor for building the West. They wrote about Cody
         and them that didn't do nothing but shoot one buffalo, ,'IT said. It's the
         homesteaders—they're the ones that built the West and raised the families
         And they never give them anything at all—it was a big article about it.
         Hw they can throw everything on one man, y'know. And Bill Cody, he was
         nothin but a crook, pretty near like the rest of the politicians are.
         He didn't do nothin, but he'd ride around. And that's the way everything
         is—one of them got all the honor,and the others nothing. No, it was
         quite an article I read about that.
         
         SAM:  I can't figure that out. I mean do you feel'that the story hasn't been
         told yet?
         
         CO:  Well, in one way it hasn't, so people understand--they just th'nk
         that all you had to do was go out here and take a homestead and
         everything flew up. It wasn't even a road--it wasn«tVjntown--it wasn't
         a norse even« There was one team of horses here for the longest time
         before anybody else had a team of horses even. Now they got three,
         four cars to jump in and go and they just think things are that way,
         was that way the" I guess, but it wasn't. You had to walk, carry your stuff on your
         back like my dad did. He carried everything from Moscow
         out twenty miles except the stove. He couldn't carry it—it was too
         big. So he got old Osterterg with his team to haul his stove out for
         him. And there was no roads, you had to go through the trees, and it
         was no roads or nothin, not even a town rfre—rail wasn't here even, see?
         I don't see how they made it myself. I can't figure it out. Just think
         i.f you arid I should start out like that, and go way back and there isn-'t
         a heme or house or nothin to go into. That's what they had here—it was
         no houses, no roads, no nothing. And they couldn't build a house very
         fast either because them trees were too big to handle and everything.
         And you couldn't find anything to make a roof of hardly.
         
         SAM:  What was the first place that your father built? Was it just a. . .
         
         CO:  Well, he had a lean-to then. They just put up some poles—like this—
         and it leans. And they slept under that. And then they cooked out on
         a fire. They used to call that, they had a name on that canyon, I
         don't know what the name was now—it wasn't much of a canyon, but there
         was a Swede name for it—Lean-to anyway, they called it. Call that canyon
         cows after that lean-to they had there. And then the come, in and they wrecked
         all the food one time. They had one cow, and he got in andtrornperi' everything
         to pieces. 'Course it wasn't too bad, because had neighbors pretty close
         all over,y'see—half a mile or so, quarter mile. So you got a little
         help that way. No, people don't see those things. They go into town—
         you drive to town, nine, ten miles and you got nine, ten miles back,
         you got a twenty mile trip just to go to town. So goin to town—that's
         something that didn't happen very often. They couldn't afford unless
         they were hauling wheat or something like that. And they hauled that In
         the winter always. But the only thing that helped them at all, thssy just
         happened to get the railroad in here next year, y'see. My dad worked on the
         railroad here and made a few dollars that way. So he had a little to buy
         then vfith, yknow. And that helped quite a bit. And later on they started farmin
         in Genessee because that was open country there, y'know. They plowed
         there and seeded and he used to work in the harvest there. But then he
         could never come home—he had to stay until the harvest was over. It
         was thirty, forty mile trip, y'know. He had to ride with somebody down fcere
         to get tc the job, and then you sV ayed there until it was finished. And
         she, my mother, was sittin up here in a lean-to with a couple of kids, but
         nt her dad homesteaded right by so it was too bad. He was home—the old man.
         But her brother, he lived there top but he had to go to work like the
         rest of them.
         
         SAM:  How many years was it before he built the house?
         
         CO:  Oh, I don't know for sure. He ™.t first a small cabin, I think and
         then he added on to it. They were all logs, y'know—"ewed logs and
         dovetailed together. Not the regular—you know what the dovetail looks
         like? I don't see how he could do all that and get it to fit like that.
         I t old my brother to leave otvof those buildings but he tore all down.
         So you couldn't see how the dovetailing was. And then the house had to
         burn up on top of it. And then after they got the houses built, then
         they went out with the big broad—axe and smoothed the walls down, see,
         so they got smooth, and then they put lumber on the outside
         to make em look better, y'see. But the house I was born in was a log
         cabin. But when you see the picture of it, there's boards all over, but
         the logs are still in there. And then they had the sSffolding, y'know,
         and that was quite a job . They called then broad-axes- }bu had
         a big broad axe. ' , about that wide, y'know, and then
         they'd have a scaffold and then they'd go like this. And smootif-the
         wall even all the way down, see? There was one man up here, Johnson, he
         was an expert in that broad-axing. They hired him sometimes to come and
         do the broad-axing for us. So they were pretty good on woodwork , the
         Swedes. They come from a wood country, y'know, in Sweden was. . . Dad 
         was twenty-two -years old when he homesteaded here, y'know and how can he
         learn all that stuff that way? I can't figure out—he was a carpenter
         and he laid bricks, and all that, so that's helped him. It isn't very
         many houses aroundthey're tore down now, lots of em— ori the Dry Creek
         Rige that he wasn't along and built. He was with pretty near everyone.
         They come and got him all the time to do any carpenter work. And then
         when we made the brick out there, he laid the brick in the chimneys for
         them too. So he worked out quite a bit.
         
         SAM:  When did you have this fire at the house?
         
         CO:  Well, that's when Emil lived there alone—no, they wasn't alone. And
         no, they wasn't alone, they were both home. I don't know—it caught
         from the chimney. It?ettled sorae way and made open a crack like that
         in it, see? And they had fire in the stove and it caught upstairs, y'know
         and there was no chance to get up there either. It was way up in the
         attic.
         
         SAM:  What aboutfyour mother—the kind of work that she had to do with all the kids.
         
         CO:  Oh, there was a lot of work. She did all thesee ing by hand,
         when they farmed,y'know. And my dad, he run the harrow and harrowed it
         down, see. The seed was on the ground and then they'd harrow over it,
         I used to watch her. She
         to cover up the seed, so" he done all that work. held this bag
         here full of and then she'd go like this.
         
         SAM:  From side to. . . one hrnd to the other hand.
         
         CO:  No, she was quite a worker. She was a pretty husky woman too. And
         then she milked cows and took care of the cows pretty near all the
         time. All those kids in the family.
         
         SAM:  I You had so many bothers and sisters.
         
         CO:  Yea, eight boys and four girls. That was quite a family. But to start
         with would be the worst anyway, because when people have their first
         kids and they're all small, y'know. But after the other ones start growin
         up, then they got help, see. They'd help then, y'know, but till the kid; got
         about eight, ten years old, y'know, then they can start helpin a little.
         But to have kids that's just born and only a year or two old, another one
         about three and four andso on, that makes a lot of work. So that
         was quite a thing, but after they grew up then they got help frojn the
         bigger ones. Yea, so you see this country isn't very old. It isn't
         more than a hundred years old about. So you see how fast things have
         moved the last fifty years, and this country's goin to ruin theirself
         if they don't change it, she'd goinall the pieces. Well hell goddamn it,
         they're takin,all the big farmers taking all the land now. And now they're
         tryin get em back on. I seen in Canada, they're workin that now. The
         government buys up land and he sells it to get the people back on the
         land. Well, you keep drivin everybody to the big cities, crime there and
         fighting stealing and everything else. When they made the law, the
         law was a hundred and sixty acres was all you could take of land.
         Why don't they make a law now that you can have about three-hundred acres
         only. And then split it up and get the people out and everything,will
         help the whole nation.Because all these smaller farmers, they got two
         or three cows, they got some pigs, they got some chickens, and then there
         wouldn't be a trusk all this stuff you're buying.7" 'made butter and
         sold it, see? Now they have to come "6rem a big outfit and they raise
         the price just control the food, practically. And now it'd be worse
         than ever, And then when they raise this five dollar wheat, that was a
         real land killer, because if you and I sat here and wanted to buy a
         hundred and sixty acres of land, and five dollar wheat, them big on es
         would bid a thousand dollars an acre. And we could never pay it off if
         we bought it .because we didn't have enough. See, we do things so crazy
         here I don't know what to think about this country anymore. It's no
         sense in it.
         
         SAM:  Do you have much of a feeling about when things started going haywire?
         Or who the president or when?
         
         CO:  Well, I don't know what started it a-goin—it was too free, I guess.
         They didn't regulate the right things. That's the way I got it figured
         out. And the big guy took over everythingpractically. He took over the
         mill and he took over the farmland he took over all the factories, he
         took over all the small stores—they're goin out of business all over
         because of these big chain stores, and they control the prices,see? So
         it's no good. And another thing, we make too much stuff that we don't
         need and sell to people. Yea, I talk to people down in the grocery store,
         and they said, "By god it's gettin so I can't even buy anything anymore,
         because I don't know what to buy, it's so goddamn many things here, I don't
         know what I want!" (laughs) Here he'll have a dozen kinds of cereal
         maybe, made from the same thing ,only one is rolled this way and the
         other is rolled that way. (laughs) That makes it hard on the dealers
         because they carry so much stock—it takes money for that, y'see. Now
         when wg went to the store when we was kids, there was about five or six
         articles was all we had to buy and went home. BuY some coffee, sugar,
         and had their own milk—never had to buy milk,
         ' d But thev butter to those stores for people that din't have any
         farms, so they could buy the butter there, y'see and theggs, and stuff like
         that. And the coffee would come in big barrels y'know, and they'd scoop
         a couple of scoops in the package and wrap it up; and you took it home and
         put it in the old grinder and ground it yourself. You had better coffee
         too. That's why they seal the cans so tight because they lose the flavor
         when yu break it up, see?
         
         SAM:  I grind my own coffee.
         
         CO:  Yea, do you? Well, that's what you should do--it's better flavor isn't
         it? 
         
         SAM:  Yea. 
         
         CO:  But it's one thing you can do that I don't think about,
         that's if you got ground coffeeput it in the Frigidaire after you open
         it once, see. It don't steam off then when it's warm, y'see, it steams
         it off and you lose a lot of the flavor.
         
         SAM:  I wanted to ask you about t|.@ family, too. You said that they weren't
         religious—your father, he wasn't religious, but your mother, she was.
         Is that right?
         
         CO:  Well, she wasn't very religious at all-she never went to church at all,
         but sheWbrougKE in Sweden, I guess. Religion had, the big power over
         there then. That's why they left the countryfor the bankers and religion
         and militarlsm,You had to go to the army and spend four years there all
         the time.
         
         SAM:  But you said that your father and she, they used to disagree about
         the Bible?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea, but she didn't read much. My dad, he read all the time. He
         was posted and everything. He'd read all the time. And lots of them,
         they don't read, y'know they just hear a few good things,
         but they read the whole thing out- you can find out yourself.
         
         SAM: So what would they disagree about?
         
         CO:  Oh, it was something about, oh, I don't know, marriage or somethin. Pa
         said somethin and Ma was against it. So Pa said, "You go and read it in
         your Bible yourself then." And she did, and then she told me, "I never
         thought anything like that was in the Bible" (laughs)So you see, here
         afew preachers tel1 ousomethin. They just take the high spots
         
         SAM:  Well, the thing 1 was wondering about that, and I asked you this a little
         before was that if? hey didn't teach you religion very much, they taught
         you though to be good to other people?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea, that was the main thing, Honesty. If there was any crooks
         around our neighborhood we could never associate with em. She wouldn't
         allow us to be close to em, see? So when I went in the business, I got
         fooled. 1 didn't know there was that many crooks in the world as they
         was. They wouldn't pay their bills or nothin. I lost ovec fourthousand
         dollars the time I was there on gas. So you see how much you lose then.
         Because it was such a small profit in gas,and four thousand is just pretty
         near like taking it out of your pocket. But if you're selling something
         you double your money on and lose four thousand, then you don't lose so
         much. But on gas, it was such a small margin, y'know--awful loss.
         
         SAM:  Well, what did your parents teach you then? As far as dealing with
         other people—gettin along with people?
         
         CO:  Well, they just told us to be honest and do the right thingand help
         people if they need help and stuff like that. And everyday life that
         '11 you live is simple if you do those things, why you have no problems.
         
         SAM:  You mentioned to me about getting a black spot on your heart?
         
         CO:  Oh, yea they told us that, if we swear too much. Everytime you swear
         you get ablack spot on the heart?Mi used to tell us. And when that
         gets black all over, you die. (laughs). Well, that maybe was pretty good
         teaching for akid so he wouldn't get too rough, huh? (chuckleslea,
         I '11 tell you what's wrong with the caintry too, y'know. A lot of
         people, they were poor that come to the country—but that's so old
         nowlthat should have died It locks like. And always ..., rcadin
         about rich people, y'know—how nice they have U. And they come here
         to get rjch, see, that's on their mind and that's all they seem to give
         adamn for. There's more than riches that counts, y'know.. But that's
         the ones th talk about-that rich man he got everything, he got everything,
         , blame him for that. But I rich—I wanted to
         get rich all right,but I had adifferent idea in my head. If I got
         rich I was gonna help the poor because I know what it was to be poor.
         
         SAM:  Did you really feel that way?
         
         CO:  Yea. That's why I invested a lot of money but never hit anything.
         Iwas infl fields in Montana, mining, mining several places, bought
         stock in a lot of different mines—never hit a darn thing. The only
         thing I hit at all was the brick yard here—I had stock in that, but
         that didn't have much—I doubled my money there, that's all.
         
         SAM:  But how were you going to help the poor if you had money?
         
         CO:  Well, if I seen somebody that needed a better house fix It
         up for them. Not keep donating to them all the time—that don't
         help anything. Do something for them that does some good. Some
         people live in shacks, y'know and they got kids and they got nothing
         and they never get ahold of nothin. Some people you can't help too,
         but that ain't very big per centage. Put them on their feet so they
         can make it. See, if you get behind one time, you get so hard up
         that they have to pay debts all their life—you never get anywheres,
         you're workin for somebody else aiil the time.
         
         SAM:  Oh, yea there was one more thing I was thinking of too. That was
         when you quit school. Now what was the story on that—why did you
         quit?
         
         CO: Well, It was many reasons. I didn't like the teacher very good and
         they didn't teach anything that done me any good. I was so darn good
         at arithmetic that I beat him hll the time. And I wanted to go out and
         earn some money so I could buy me some better clothes and stuff like
         that. And that's what done it. But I didn't know, I stood there and
         I looked at the schoolhouse and I looked at where we lived,and finally
         I come pretty near _ ,
         I turned and went home. goin back again. But they
         didn't teach you much helpeyou much in school in those days. We
         didn't have much schooling anyway—three months a year, I started
         with: Then it went to six finally. Then they had the teacher--she got
         thirty dollars a month. And then they raised it to sixty. When I
         quit the teacher got sixty dollars a month, I believe.
         
         SAM:  Did you come to blows with this teacher when you left? Did this
         teacher hit you?
         
         CO:  No, no, I never was hfet. I never had any trouble with teachers hardly,
         It was something I said or something that he didn't like—1 forgot
         what it was, out jjlavim, with the other kids, I believe. No, I
         was good in school--I never started any trouble. Never stood in the
         corner, never had to sit in afterwards like to punish thern—you had to
         stay in school after it was over, yknow. one of that—never. I went
         back and seen one teacher I hadn't seen for a long time and I said,
         "You know who I am?" "No, I don't know." I said,"I used to go to school
         for you.""Oh, you1re Albert," she said. "No, I'm the younger one, Carl."
         "How in the dickens could I ever forget you? You were my get in school 1"
         she said. She is still alive too. She lives in Boise now. She must
         be eight-five ninety years old now.
         
         SAM:  How old were you when you quit school?
         
         CO:  About fourteen. 1909 is when I quit.
         
         SAM:  When you quit then did you go to wor right away2
         
         CO: Well, not right away, but I got a job from my uncle then to be a clerk
         in a store in Helmer. There was a little town there then—he had a little
         store there. So I was there in 1909 and '10 when Haley's Comet was on.
         
         SAM:  What do yotfmean—you saw Haley's Comet then?
         
         CO:  Yea, and the fella was ray partner, he was a barber—he had one
         wooden leg and he dot a little bootlegging—he sold beer, y'know
         
         SAM:  Yea?
         
         CO:  See they come out with two beer—one with no alcohol in and then the
         real beer. You could get that yet, but it was against the law to sell
         it in Idaho. So when they come in and bought beer he gave them the
         good beer and then when they went home he gave them the near beer. And
         they come back with a dozen bottles and what do you do with them? "I
         throwed em in the gol damn gutter," one fella said. "Give me the good
         beer—that's what I wantl" (laughs) And then they were searching down
         in Deary and I come home late—I ent down with a couple of boys
         and we missed the train  8 we had to walk
         back. So I come home about midnight up to Helmer and I told that bootlegger
         there ,"The revenue mann Deary, searching all the beer parlors and
         everything. You better get your beer hidden." So he had the barrel
         upstairs, y'know, he had to roll it down the stairway and'roll'it
         out in the chicken house. But nobody ever come though. Morton Low, his
         name was. I had to fix on that wooden leg every once in while, too,
         so it would work.
         
         SAM: What went wrong with it?
         
         CO:  Well, he lost it, he had the wooden leg.
         
         SAM:  No, I mean.
         
         CO:  And the joints here y'know would get so they'd wiggle too much. And
         you had to tighten it up and screws come loose.
         
         SAM:  So you went down and warned him that the . . .
         
         CO:  Well, we slept upstairs in the same building that it was in, so I
         woke him up and told him, "By god those beer fellas, they're liable to
         search you too." Yea.
         
         SAM:  Now was that your same uncle when they were building the railroad
         through, you pulled out some of the stakes?
         
         CO:  Yea, that's tie one I stayed with on the meadow up there.
         
         SAM:  What did you do that time?
         
         CO:  Well, he had a nice meadow there, y'know, and what we looked for was
         bigger field. It was timber all over and I didn't want
         em to ruin the »meadow. So I pulled the stakes out and hid em. But
         they built the railroad anyway, (laughs) I didn't pull out very many though,
         I was only about nine years old then, I guess. But I was down to
         the surveyors when they were there, y'know and talked to them and
         everything, y'know ,yea.
         
         SAM:  Were there a lot of foreign workers, Italians and people like that?
         here
         
         CO:  Yea, there was a lot of Italian?, a lot of Italians at that time. When
         they built the Elk River Mill and that, twenty-five per cent of them
         I believe was Italians. They couldn't talk English hardly at all. But
         most of them, they went back, y'know. They come here to make a little
         money and then go back to Italy. But , they were pretty fair to
         work, but they had to have a boss over about every four or five of them,
         they said to show them how and stuff like that. Yea, there was a lot of
         them in Elk River. Yea.
         
         SAM:  Did you tell me, Carl, that Johansen, the man that started up Nora, the
         mill there. . . You told me that he made some money, that he was sort of
         a tricky guy.
         
         CO:  Yea, he was a tricky guy.He burnt Up the sawmill they said, and he took
         all the insurance money and his partner didn't get any. Then he had
         a kid to carry it for him when he come over here so they wouldn't search
         him. But he was kind of smart too, y'know, fe started the brickyard
         up here.
         
         SAM:  Was there something about him using Confederate money? Did you tell
         me something about that?
         
         CO:  Yea, Axel Behte he told him, "You better pay up that guy now that
         you swindled back in.  ." Course they were neighbors back there in
         Sweden. "Yes,"he said, "I'll send him the money." He sent Confederate
         money to him Yea.
         
         SAM:  Oh, I should really get goin, Carl.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13598</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Olson_Carl3</previous>
      <next>Olson_Carl5</next>
      <disp_name>Olson_Carl4</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
