<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">1/6/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Lillian Woodworth Otness, 1975-01-06, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:30:37</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Otness, Lillian Woodworth</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Teacher of English and physical education in college and high school;
         homemaker;
         
         
      </occupation>
      <birthyear>1908</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow</residence>
      <origin>Grandfather was an original founder of Moscow, moving from eastern Oregon (1871);
         father
         came from Montana (1877)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#banks"&gt;banks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#California"&gt;California&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Oregon"&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13602</file_name>
      <mp3>13603.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13603.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Why grandfather came to Moscow; raising cattle; The men who owned property in downtown
               Moscow
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Grandfather A.A. Lieuallen came to Moscow from the
               Athena, Oregon area (1871), because the land looked
               good for cattle raising. In the severe winter of
               1873 he lost $40,000 in cattle. Then he bought
               Moscow's first store (at First and Main) from Samuel
               Neff. Lieuallen, Russell, MacGregor and Deakin owned
               adjoining property at Sixth and Main, Lieuallen's
               being the northwest part. His civic-mindedness.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Native Americans playing with grandmother's hair; Memories of Moscow fort</title>
            <synopsis>Mrs. Otness's mother (Llily Lieuallen Woodworth) said
               that Indian women loved to play with her red hair in
               the store. Her memories of the Indian scare of 1877
               and Moscow's fort.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>How and why Moscow was named; Rejected names for Moscow</title>
            <synopsis>Reasons for naming of Moscow. Name selected by consensus. Rejection of Hog Heaven
               and Paradise as names. Moscow was not named for Russians or for Lieuallen's beard.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Goods sold at family store; Not banking in Moscow; selling the store and developing
               the town
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Goods sold at Lieuallen store. He traded for farm
               produce. He rode horseback to St. John to bank, and
               kept his going a secret to avoid getting waylaid.
               A man absconded with money and records from Moscow's
               first bank, so Lieuallen lost the notes he was owed.
               He then decided to sell his store and work on developing the town. He gave people
               free lots for building on them. His concern for innovation in the town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Mother going to school in Portland but then getting married before graduation; women
               rarely went to college
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother went to school at St. Helens Hall in Portland,
               She married before graduating from high school. She
               played mandolin in a local group. Married women rarely went to college, but were expected
               to raise a family. The university's prep school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Mother had siblings who died young; brother Jack was outstanding college athlete</title>
            <synopsis>Mother had a brother and sister who died very young.
               Her brother Jack was an outstanding college athlete,
               especially in track.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Carrie McConnell overheard the David boys saying the worst words they could think
               of
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Carrie McConnell overheard the David boys saying the
               worst words they could think of.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1980</time>
            <title>Jack being expelled from college; mother knowing everybody from first graduating class</title>
            <synopsis>Jack was expelled from college by President Gault
               when he refused to stop winning track events against
               Washington Agricultural College "in the interest of
               good relations". Her mother knew all the students
               in the first graduating classes at the university.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Family moving to Wallace and Lewiston; Father was frustrated with farming</title>
            <synopsis>Family moved to Wallace and Lewiston for short periods.
               Father was a frustrated farmer who farmed for Dr. Gritman in Alberta and in Saskatchewan
               for himself.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2580</time>
            <title>Family moving to California and New Mexico; leaving after a rancher had been shot</title>
            <synopsis>Family went to California for mother's health, and
               father decided to homestead near Playas, New Mexico.
               The week they arrived Pancho Villa's band shot the
               postmasters from Playas and other towns at a- postal
               meeting. Mother finally insisted they leave, after
               hearing that a rancher and his wife had been shot by
               their hired hands.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2820</time>
            <title>Family returns to Moscow and father converts a house into first apartments in Moscow</title>
            <synopsis>Family returned to Moscow when father decided to
               convert a house they owned into Moscow's first
               apartments, such as those he had seen in California.
               They had all the modern conveniences, and were in
               high demand among professional people.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Mother given gold to play with as a child; family's legacy in Moscow street names</title>
            <synopsis>Her mother was given twenty dollar gold pieces to play
               with as a child, and planted one, hoping it would grow.
               Almon, Asbury and Lieuallen streets were named for
               A.A. Lieuallen, Lilly for mother.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Father knowing early Moscow leaders; Father was very conservative and a fan of big
               business
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father knew the early Moscow leaders. He caused his
               father much sorrow by becoming a Republican. Mrs.
               Otness teased him about his highly conservative convictions. He was entirely in favor
               of big business.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>A.A. Lieuallen's move to Moscow area. Loss of cattle in winter of 1873. His
         operation of Moscow's first store. Naming Moscow. Early town events. Closeness of
         university and town. Family experiences. 1-6-75 1 hr 20p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SS: SCHRAGER: The first thing I was going to ask you about Grandfather
         Lieuallen. And I thought I'd ask you first off if you know how he
         happened to come to Idaho?
         
         LILLIAN WOOPWORTH OTNESS:  I don't know very much about it. I know that he
         belonged to a family that had moved west and had settled around Athena
         and Weston, Oregon. And several of them came up here, according to
         family tradition at least, to look over the location. And the others
         were farmers, he didn't care for that, he liked the cattle ranching.
         And they came up here, and of course you've heard all the stories about
         how the grass was nigh and all over the hills and so on, and he thought
         that this would be a wonderful place to raise cattle. And so he came up
         and first, I guess, was on a tract out near what I know as Munson farm
         out in the Robinson Lake area. And brought a herd of cattle up here, and
         in one of the hard winters, what was it. . .
         
         SS:  I'm not sure, I think it was around '73 or '74.
         
         LO:  Something like that. I think maybe that's about right. And they had
         heavy snows and the ground froze, and the cattle couldn't get to the feed
         and he lost forty-thousand dollars worth of cattle, which was a goodly sum
         in those days. And apparently it was about that time that he decided
         to try something else—the store and that sort of thing.
         
         SS:  So he was probably one of the main stockmen in the country, if not the
         main one, when he came that herd.
         
         LO:  That might be, I just don't know.
         
         SS:  You know when they say that in the History of Ndrth Idaho that he was the
         first man to settle in the valley, Paradise Valley, do you know if that's
         so or not?
         
         LO:  I really don't.
         
         SS:  The summer of 1871. . .
         
         LO:  Yea, that1 was the time that my mother always said that the family came.
         But I really don't know, he was one of the early ones, certainly. And at
         one time he and Russell and McGregor and Deakin owned property that adjoined
         at Sixth and Main Street—it was a four corner place. And he had the
         property west of ^ain and north of Sixth at that time. Now I suppose that
         was a homestead that he took over from somebody.
         
         SS:  Did neafor, was it Neff that he got it from? This is what I've heard, I
         don't.
         
         LO:  I don't Rnow whether he got all that land from Neff or not,or whether it
         was just the store. I thought from what mother had told me that it was the
         store he acquired from Neff and the post office went along with it. But
         I don't know whether Neff had the homestead or not.
         
         SS:  But do you think the reason that he went into town and started a store
         was because of that hard winter, probably?
         
         LO:  I think so, that's what I've understood from my mother as the reason. And
         apparently he was very public spirited and civic-minded and interested in
         developing the town. And was busy in whatever was going on that way.
         
         SS:  Well, I wonder if the town was just his store to start with?
         
         LO:  I think it was a little more than that oh, maybe to start with, but later
         on the store was located at First and Main, y'know where the Bank of Idaho
         is now, and White's Drug Store was across the way—you've seen those
         pictures with that. Dr.  had his dental office in that same block
         too, north of First Street. I heard my mother tell about how she used to
         play with Margaret McP alley. They lived there within about a half block
         of each other. This was while my mother was still living there, on First
         before they built the house on Almon Street. Before that, she told me once
         they'd been in a house that was located where the old post office is
         now.
         
         SS:  Wheny had the store, did they live right by it? Or was it a cabin?
         
         LO:  Well, I had the impression that it was very close there, and Mother used
         to be in the store quite a bit, I guess, as a little girl, and she told Me
         about how the Indian women would come in and they'd be so fascinated with
         her red hair. They'd want to hold her and play with her because she
         had red hair, and she was pretty small at that time, must have been.
         
         SS:  Do you remember anything else that she said about what the store was like?
         
         LO:  No, she didn't say a great deal about what the store was like. This also
         was during the time when they had the Indian scare and they had Fort
         Russell, y'know, but I think she was only about three years old then. Wasn't
         that in '77?
         
         SS:  That's what Homer David says too, that she was in the fort.
         
         LO:  Yes,well she has told me about that—about how people in general would
         go and work their farms during the daytime and then go hole up in the
         fort at night. She would go with her mother, now I don't know whether,
         oh yes by that time they must have been in town, I don't think they
         were on that farm any longer. And her mother would hitch up the wagon
         at the end of the day and take the children up to the fort. They'd go
         in there and stay overnight. But that didn't seem to last very long.
         
         SS:  So they spent their days on the farm—the women and children did too.
         
         LO:  Un hum.
         
         SS:  Did she remember at all what it was like in the fort? Wh± she did in
         the fort?
         
         LO:  Not very much. She didn't remember very much of that. Somebody from
         Spokane wanted to come down and interview her about that and she discouraged
         because she said she was just too young to have remembered very much
         about it.
         
         SS:  Three or four is probably about the threshold of memory.
         
         LO:  Um hum, urn hum. No, she didn't seem to have very clear recollections of
         that and I can certahly understand it .
         
         SS:  What about this question of the naming of Moscow as you understand it?
         I actually read in that History of North Idaho, I was looking at the other
         day, they gave the credit for deciding to name the town Moscow.
         
         LO:  Well, it seems to have been the object of considerable specdation, and so
         on. I think Grandfather probably was very influential, was right in the
         business of planning on that. Mother sort of changed her stories as the
         years went by. For years she told me that the reason they chose Moscow
         was that they wanted a name that no other towns in the United States 
         Or maybe I misunderstood it—maybe they just didn't want one that was very
         close because apparently Neff had come from near Moscow, Pennsylvania.Then
         later on Mother told me that they also wanted something that sounded citified
         and glamourous, and that Moscow, Russia filled the bill as far as that
         was concerned.
         
         SS:  Did she have any opinion about the question of Neff's flaming the town
         after his hometown.when she talked about it?
         
         LO:  I'm trying to remember. It seems the way she used to tell it, they reached
         a consensus on it, and of course they had called it Hog Heaven beforehand
         and the women objected to that because they ttought that was not a very
         dignified name for a beautiful valley like this. So they discarded Hog
         Heaven and they wanted to call it Paradise, but I think the post office wouldn't
         approve that because there were ether towns that had that same name. She
         was very definite about the fact that it had nothing to do with Russians
         among the population. Somebody had written a book—Mother said when he
         was old and senile and said that that was the reason that there were
         Russians that justwould come down out of the hills occasionally and then
         disappear back into the hills, and that they were responsible for naming
         it Moscow. She was very positive about that fact that that wasn't true.
         And my father, when he was county auditor, did a good deal of checking
         with the county records. And he said there just were no Russian names
         around Moscow. Mother always felt that the reason that theory got
         accepted was because it appeared in print, and that it wasn't reliable at
         all.
         
         SS:  I don't know why there's such a controversy over the naming of Moscow,
         but there really seems to be.
         
         LO:  Well,and so many theories. I have a clipping some place that somebody
         had given to Mother and she just pooh-poohed the whole thing. It had
         to do with somebody pointing to my grandfather's beard and saying,
         "You look like a Russian with that long long beard, why don't we name
         it Moscow" And my mother thought that was perfectly ridiculous—there
         was just nothing to that.
         
         SS:  Y'know on this Hog Heaven, was that supposed to be because they ran hogs
         in the valley. 
         
         LO:  Well, hogs liked to dig the camas, has been my understanding of the
         tradition and grew very fat on the camas root. And of course, there
         no question that there was camas around here. The men called it Hog
         Heaven because it was so good for the stock.
         
         SS:  What about the Indians that used to camp here in the early days? Did
         you ever hear about them from your mother?
         
         LO:  Not very much, she used to mention the Indains coming into the store, and
         of course she was aware of the fact that the Indian trails had run
         through here, but she didn't have very much to say about it. In fact,
         I can't remember her mentioning them particularly except in regard to her
         red hair.
         
         SS:  What about what Mr.Lieuallen sold mostly and the kind of business that
         he had in those days? Have you gleaned anything from looking at those
         ledgers that he had?
         
         LO:  Well, yes, I think it was pretty generalfwhat you'd expect of a country
         store. You know, tools that were commonly used, and produce, and staples 
         4nd apparently he was taking produce in trade, taking eggs and vegetables
         that people bought in and they got credit for and so on. Oh, fabrics,
         and hats, and shoes, and just the whole gamut of what you'd supply if
         you were running a store in a little frontier town.
         
         SS:  I read that he had to go to Walla Walla to get the first stock that he
         laid in, but I'm curious about where he would have continued to get his
         stock after that time. I wonder if he had to keep going back to Walla Walla
         since it was before the railroad came in?
         
         LO:  He probably did. I don't remember hearing Mother talk about that very
         much. She did talk about how he banked up at St. John because there
         wasn't a bank here in Moscow. And he would ride horseback up to St. John,
         and when he was going was rather carefully guarded secret because he'd
         be carrying gold and didn't want to get waylaid. But I don't remember
         that she ever said very much about where he got his stock.
         
         SS:  Have you heard the story that when the mail first came, it was left
         deposited there in a shoe box in the store. I guess I read that someplace.
         He started with a shoebox.
         
         LO:  Yes, I think I have. Of course most of the early post offices were some
         thing similar to that. Mail would be left in somebody's home or in a
         business, something like that, that may well be true about the shoe box.
         
         SS:  And then he sold his store and turned to selling land and platted
         the town of Moscow?
         
         LO:  Yes, that was it. He had financial reverses. Somebody absconded with
         money from a local bank and with a lot of records, a lot of things that
         had been left there for safe keeping, including a great meny notes that my
         from
         grandfather had taken people who owed him money. And without the notes
         he couldn't collect. So that, according to family tradition, he lost a
         good deal of money that way add was forced to make a choice between trying
         to maintain the store and trying to sell real estate and do that. And
         because he was so interested in building up the town he chose to do
         that and gave up the store.
         
         SS:  Have you heard anything about this business of him platting the town and
         then selling land?
         
         LO:  No, but I imagine that that is true because Lieuallen's addition
         is one of the sections of Moscow, and Mrs. Lieuallen, I think
         whether
         he was involved in the early platjfcing of the town. Now it extended to
         other parts of the town besides what he owned I don't know.
         
         SS:  I don't know, but I thought the book said actually he platted the town
         of Moscow in 1880.
         
         LO:  He may have.
         
         SS:  Did you tell me there was something about him giving free lots to people?
         
         LO:  That's what my mother told me—that he would give lots free to people
         if they would build houses on them. This was a device for promoting
         building up the town. Of course at that time lots weren't very expensive
         anyhow. Lots down along Asbury and Lieuallen street probably sold for
         thirty-five dollars, but he was interested in getting people to stay here
         and build homes for themselves.
         
         SS:  Do you know anything about his political convictions?
         
         LO:  No, I don't. I think Mother told me he was a Democrat. And having
         come from Tennessee, that could well be. But I don't know whether
         his convictions were very strong.
         
         SS:  Was it he that you told me that didn't care for his Black Republican
         cherries ?
         
         LO:  No, that was my other grandfather—that was my grandfather Woodworth who
         was a very strong Democrat. And he had this cherry tree in his orchard
         and he loved everything about the cherries except the name—Black Republican,
         
         SS:  Can you tell m e overall what you understand your grandfather's being like?
         What kind of person he was that's come down through history anyway as '
         the founding father of the town?
         
         LO:  Only that he seemed to be mixed up in everything that was goingpn. He
         seemed to be involved in everything that was developmental or innovative
         in the town. But beyond that I don't have any very strong impressions
         because I never knew either one of my Lieuallen grandparents.
         
         SS:  Are there other things that your mother told you about growing up in
         Moscow when she was a young person, that you remember?
         
         LO: She went to Portland to school before there was a high school here. She
         went to St. Helen's Hall in Portland, and I suppose she must have gone
         on the train—by that time the railroad would have been in here, wouldn't
         it? She was born in '74.
         
         SS:  She'd be eleven.
         
         LO:  Uh huh. And I don't know how many years she went down there,
         but I know that she did go down there to boarding
         school. And then when the high school was started here, she attended the
         high school. And I thought for years that she had graduated from high
         school here, but it turned out that she had married my father in January
         before she was due to graduate in May, so she didn't actually finish
         high school. Oh, I think there was a lot of activity with the young
         people—that is, Mother belonged to a mandolin club, and she played the
         piano and the mandolin club apparently had quite a membership. £ have
         pictures of the members of the mandolin club—there must have been, oh,
         maybe ten, twelve mandolin players. They used to play around for various
         social events. I think like any small town, they made their own fun,
         their social life.
         
         SS:  She didn't go to college then?
         
         LO:  No, in those days married women didn't go to college. They didn't even
         go to college when I was in schoolj It was unusual for any married women
         to be in college, and the ones that were, we thought were sort of odd. I
         suppose when I was in college, I knew maybe half a dozen. And this was just.
         
         SS:  What would you think would be odd about it?
         
         LO:  Well, married women stayed home and took care of their families. It seems
         ridiculous now that it would be odd, but even the ones that I knew in
         college mostly were wives of staff members who somehow or another hadn't
         completed their education. And I knew two or three that finished up here.
         
         SS:  Single women though—it was completely acceptable for them to go to college
         in you mother's day?
         
         LO:  Oh, I don't know about that. Yes, it was acceptable, but there just
         weren't very many of them that did. There weren't very many men that
         did either. When they first started the University, they ran a preparatory
         school because the students that came were not really high school graduates
         a lot of them. And there was a lot of talk when I was a child about
         the prep school. It was discontinued after a while, when they started
         getting enough students that were prepared, but when it first started out
         the prep school was an important part of it.
         
         SS:  Was the prep school actually a high school?
         
         LO:  No, but I think it was sort of remedial courses for those who hadn't
         
         SS: -
         finished high school and who needed more background. And people came
         from other parts of the state to go to that before going to the university?
         
         LO:  That's my understanding. They'd do prep school work and then go on and
         finish their college. I don't know how long that went on. But it was a
         common term in the community.
         
         SS:  Do you think they were taught by the college teachers or had a separate
         faculty of their own, do you know that?
         
         The prep school? I don't know, I just don't know abut that.
         Now, your uncle, that was your mother's brother, he went to the college?
         Uh huh, uh huh. He was enrolled—the one that was the athlete.
         Yea.
         Yes he was a student in college, but not for very long because he died
         very young. And he would have been the only one of my mother's family.
         She had a brother and sister who died very young.
         
         SS:  Was that sickness?
         
         LO:  Oh, I think it was probably the diphtheria epidemic. I don't know how
         old they lived to be—I'd have to lo«k up the family records on that not old. And she
         and this brother were the only ones that grew up at ail.
         
         SS:  What- did you hear about his prowess as an athlete?
         
         LO:  Well, apparently he was a very good athlete. He was a baseball player,
         and he was very good in track. He got lots of medals in track meets, and
         so on. I doubt if he was around when they started having football.
         I don't know just when that was, but I don't think he was involved in
         that—but lots of baseball. I have medals that he won in intercollegiate
         track meets.
         
         LO:  You know Mrs. Bush was one of Governor McConnell's daughters. And she
         lived up on the hill there, kind of yards back to back with the Davids,
         the Homer Davids, and the Davids had four hoys. One time she was out
         in her back yard and she heard some of the David boys, I don't know which
         ones, talking on the other side of the fence. And they were trying to
         say the dirtiest words that they knew. And one of them said, "Oh, I know
         a good one—maure, manure!" And after a while another one said, "Oh, I know
         a better one—corset coverI" Now you remember that Sam, when you want something
         really pornographic
         
         SS:  Yea. (laughs) Things sure must have been different for that to be the
         dirtiest word they could think of.
         
         LO:  (laughs) Do you know what corset covers were? It was a kind of camisole
         that women wore under their dresses—well, it was the top to the petticoats,
         except petticoats in those days were probably separate. And the corset
         covers would tuck in under them and sometimes oh you know they had lace
         and insertion and ribbon and that sort of thing.
         
         SS:  You know I have to think about it—I really don't know what corset covers
         are, I mean I figured what they'd be but. . .
         
         LO:  Well, camisole is another name for it, but it was really going a long way
         to find a dirty word. Even'manure.'
         
         SS:  Did you know the McConnell daughters?
         
         LO:  Yea, I knew Carrie, well slightly. They were of my mother's generation.
         I knew Carrie quite well because she lived here all her life, I guess,
         and was a friend of my mother's for a long, long time. And Lived within
         a block of Mother during Mother's last fifteen, twenty years that she
         lived here in town. The others, Mamie Borah and Ollie Lu«ldbman, I met
         occasionally but I didn't knaw them well at all.
         
         SS:  Did you ever hear much about what the social life used to be like around
         the mansion when they were girls? I've heard that it was really quite
         something from Lola Clyde,that.
         
         LO:  No, I don't think I'd ever heard very much about that.
         
         SS:  I guess maybe it was more that the Mcfbnnell daughters were sort of the
         center of Moscow society when they were young.
         
         LO:  That may well be.
         
         SS:  0. K. now what's the story about your brother Jack's run in with the
         president of the university?
         
         LO:  My Uncle Jack.
         
         SS:  That's right, I mean your uncle.
         
         LO:  According to Mother he had been competing in these track meets and he was
         one of the successful ones, and the University of Idaho had a track meet
         scheduled with Washington Agricultural College at Pullman. And the rivalry
         was quite strong, and Idaho had been beating the ag college. President
         Gault called my uncle in and said that in the interest of good relations
         between the two colleges he didn't want the University of Idaho to win
         so big. So he wanted my uncle to see that he didn't win too many events.
         And my uncle said he didn't play that way—he played to win and he would
         feel he had to do his best and win or lose as he could. President Gault
         said that if he disobeyed him he would expell him from school. And
         he called, according to Mother's story, he called my grandfather and told
         him that if Jack didn't agree to do this that he would expell him from
         school. Jack refused to agree to do it and he did expell him from school.
         
         SS:  think Jack got to run the races? (laughs)
         
         LO:  I don't think he got to take part In that meet—I could be wrong about
         that, but I think he was not allowed to compete.
         
         SS:  Now that's something that wouldn't get very far these days either. I mean
         his father would probably be down there right now talking to the president
         of the university.
         
         LO:  Urn hum, probably. But in those days of course administrators had a
         good deal more power over individuals than they do now—that is it was
         a kind of dictatrship—you either shaped up or you couldn't stay in school.
         
         SS:  I'm really curious about what the university was like back
         in the early days. I guess there weren't very many students at all when
         your uncle was going there.
         
         LO:  Oh, I don't imagine so. I don't imagine there would have been very many.
         And for many years my mother knew all the students at the university
         because there were so few of them and they were fairly well integrated
         into the life of the town apparently. Being in musical circles as she was,
         she just knew everybody out of the first few graduating classesr- I don't
         imagine there*d be anybody she didn't know.
         
         SS:  There were some events then where they'd get together for music and that
         sort of thing.
         
         LO:  I think so. I think that was quite common.
         
         SS:  Do you know how she met your father?
         
         LO:  No, I really don't. She was very young, that is she must have been,
         well she was not quite eighteen when she was married, and I don't know
         how long she had known Dad, but he probably was working here in town
         and the town was probably small enough that everybody knew everybody
         else. I don't know beyond that.
         
         SS:  Then after they got married they stayed here for some time?
         
         LO:  Yes, they lived here for quite some time, then I think Father went up
         to Wallace and they lived there for a little while. And then they lived
         in Lewiston for a short time when my brother was a baby, when he was
         very young, and then came back here. Dad was kind of the auditor at one
         time—I don't know exactly when, and he'd been in the abstract business.
         I think that's what he was doing in Wallace and also in Lewiston. And
         then they lived here. I was born here,apparently by that time they were
         settled down here.
         
         SS:  Then your father had this s»rt of wanderlust for farming?
         
         LO:  Yea, I think he was a frustrated farmer because he went up to Canada
         later on and farmed a big ranch up there for Dr. Gritman. Dr. Gritman,
         I guess, was making quite a bit of money and wanted to put it to work and
         this was one of his ventures, was this farming in Canada. He had quite
         a big ranch up there near Champion in Alberta. Dad went up there several
         years and farmed for him. I suppose by that time I was in high school—
         maybe not—yea, proably I was in high school by that time.
         
         SS:  Well, so he would go up and farm part of the year and then come back down.
         
         LO:  Yes, that was it. Then later he farm^for himself in Saskatchewan for
         several seasons. I think that he sold out up in there about 1926, as
         I remember, that was about the time—'25 or '26.
         
         SS:  Funny, his family seemed to kave moved around a lot too,as I read some of
         the materials that he dictated to you, they seemed to have been in a lot
         of places.
         
         LO:  Um hum. Yes his father had farmed near Genes ee, and then he had a
         store at Uniontown, and then he had a farm down on the breaks of the
         Snake near Uniontown, and then moved back to Moscow. And he had come from
         Montana in 1876. They had moved from Montana—they went down through, oh
         by Henry's Lake and down through south Idaho and around and up to get to
         Moscow, to get to this part of the country So that was quite a little trek
         in itself.
         
         SS:  Were you here when you were a kid in Moscow? Most of your growing up. . .
         
         LO:  Um hum. Except for the couple of years that we spent in California I spent
         all my life here until I was out of college.
         
         SS:: tell me about that trip when you went down to California and Mexico?
         
         LO:  Well, we went to California because of my mother's health, and while he
         was down there somebody sold him on the idea that he could, I suppose, homestead
         and raise wheat in New Mexico. So we all went off to a little place called
         Playas in New Mexico which was right down near the Mexican border. It was
         just, oh such a very small place. There wasn't anything there but a store.
         I don't even remember a gas station—maybe there was one, but the main line
         of the Southern Pacific came through there, it didn't stop at Plafcs unless
         you telegraphed ahead that you were going to flag it, and then it would
         stop and pick up passengers or it would let off paying passengers, but
         it picked up the mail by hooking it off a pole and tossed off mailbags.
         We were down there only a few months because it was at the time of the
         Mexican border trouble, and the week that we arrived there the postal
         service had held some kind of meeting of postmasters in that area, and
         they had gone into a town called Columbus, New Mexico. Pancho Vi'a's
         bandits had crossed the border and raided the town and had taken some of
         conventioneering postmasters out and lined them up and shot them. And
         this was all the talk just about the time we arrived. And the postmaster
         -from Plias had been there and was killed. Then later, after what I think
         probably was three or four months only, we left there very hurriedly because
         someone came riding in to our yard one day and said that a young fellow
         and his wife who were ranching about, oh I think maybe it was about thirty
         miles away from us had been killed by their Mexican farmhands who had then
         taken off across the border into Mexico. And my mother decided that was
         no place for her children. So we left.
         
         SS:  Fast?
         
         LO:  We left the very next day, and Father left in about a week or two. So
         that was the end of that. But of course that was much earlier than Father
         was in Canada because this was about the time I was
         starting to school. I think I had been part of a year to school in Los
         Angeles before this, then we went back to California and I went to first
         grade again there.
         
         SS: But he decided to come back from California too?
         
         LO:  The reason that we decided to come back from California was that the
         house on Almon Street that father Lieuallen had built had been rented
         while we were in California to the Kappa Sigma Fraternity for a fraternity
         house, and while we were gone they decided to build their own house on
         the campus. And so Dad in the meantime had gotten the idea from observing
         apartment houses in California, he had decided that he could convert that
         house on Almon Street into an apartment house. So when the Kappa Sigs
         gave it up, we came back here and Dad spent, oh what must have been six
         months or so anyhow, remodeling it into apartments, and that was really
         the first apartment house in Moscow. It was, I think, the first one to
         have electric ranges and to have shower-baths and folding beds—beds that
         folded down out of the wall. This was quite the thing. The waiting list
         to get apartments there—there was always a waiting list in the early
         times, up until the time of the depression.
         
         SS:  Who were the people that wanted to stay there?
         
         LO:  Oh, we had bankers and physicians and university professors.
         
         SS:  Was this supposed to be the newest thing in living?
         
         LO:  Well yes. It was innovative; this was just new for Moscow.
         
         SS:  You mentioned to me before about the built-in kitchen that he had. Besides
         the stove were there other thijgs that he added?
         
         LO:  Well, a kitchen cabinet. And this was a combination cupboard, and it
         was a free-standing piece of furniture—it wasn't really built in, but it
         was a combination cupboard and breakfast table. It was a compact
         of unit. There was a place for supplies and dishes and the counter pulled
         out to make a place that you could eat, you know, like a breakfast
         table. And had a built in flour storage place with a sifter right at the
         bottom so that you could load a sack of flour into it and 'sift it right on
         out of there--you didn't have to scoop it out. And it had, oh, bread
         drawer, silverware drawer, all this sort of thing.
         
         SS:  Did he do the remodeling himself on these places?
         
         LO:  Oh, he did quite a bit of it. He hired carpenters and plumbers—he was
         quite good atthat sort of thing—he was good with his hands. And I'm sure
         that he did the designing of it, but he hired carpenters to work on it.
         
         SS: Do you have any idea of what kind of rent he was gettting in those days?
         
         LO:  Oh, I suppose, well I think the most expensive apartment was the ground
         floor apartment. We lived on the ground floor and there was one other
         ground floor apartment, and I think that rented for fifty dollars. And I'm
         sure that was the most expensive one.
         SS: You know there's a story about your mother that I remember you telling
         her
         before and that was about playing with the gold.
         
         LO:  Oh yes, about playing with the sack of twenty dollar gold pieces.
         She didn't have very toys, I suppose, and so at least once, maybe only
         once, she was given this sack of twenty dollar gold pieces to play with.
         And at the end of the day when they checked up they found that one was
         missing. And they asked her about it and she said, "Yes." And she took
         them out and showed them where she had planted it. She knew about planting
         seeds and growing more, and so she planted this twenty dollar gold piece
         in the hope of getting more. So they dug up the twenty dollar gold piece.
         I suppose you know that the streets Almon, Asbury and Lieuallen are
         named for my grandfather—that was his name—Almon Asbury Lieuallen 
         And Lilly is named for my mother, but through some error the streets were
         supposed to be in order—Almon, Asbury, Lieuallen and then Lilly, but
         somehow in drawing up the plat they got them in the wrong order, so they
         run Almon, Asbury, Lilly, and then Lieuallen —in that order.
         
         SS:  Well, that's not too bad if it's Almon, Asbury and Lilly Lieuallen.
         That's really quite nice.
         
         LO:  Yes, I thought that was kind of interesting.
         
         SS:  Do you know anything about Noah Lieuallen.
         
         LO:  No, I don't, not anything like firsthand. I know that he was a schoolteacher
         here and that he was probably related to Mother. He probably could have
         been an uncle—I just don't know. But there was a big family of the
         Lieuallens down around Athena and Weston and quite a few of them
         came up here too. And I know that Mother had Lieuallen cousins and so on,
         but I just don't about Noah Lieuallen.
         
         SS:  What about how your father got to know so many of the oldtimers and
         the old happenings, like he seemed to know,from what you told me, quite a
         bit about about how the university got started—he personally knew Willis
         Sweet and those people?
         
         LO: Well, I think that he was just here early, he and his family must have
         come in about '76 or '7 and he grew up in the area and then became a
         young businessman and interested in politics and so on. And I think he
         just knew everybody that there was locally. And he knew Willis Sweet, and
         he knew oh a lot of the prominent early men like that. After all, Moscow
         was pretty small and I think that a man in business like my father probably
         did know all the other businessmen and all the politicians.
         
         SS:  You told me he was a staunch Republican?
         
         LO:  He was raised a Democrat—he was raised by the grandfather that didn't like
         the Black Republican cherry . And it was a great source of sorrow to my
         grandfather when Dad turned out to be a backsliding Democrat. And when he
         from
         converted being a Democrat to a Republican, he became one of the
         most reactionary conservative. Republicans that you could hope to find anywhere.
         We used to tease him about belonging to the Neanderthal wing of the
         Republican party. And I asked my mother at one time if there ever was a
         president of either party that Dad approved of and she said, "No, none of
         them suited him."They all did most things wrong." No, he was really very,
         very conservative, once he quit being a Democrat.
         
         SS:  What would that mean? I mean can you think of any particulars that he
         felt very conservative about?
         
         LO:  Well, I think he was kind of all for big business. He felt that business
         was what had built this country, and thatpusinessmen deserved quite a bit
         of credit and consideration and so on. And he used to get quite upset when
         my brother and I would advance the idea that we didn't think that business
         was that much entitled to special privileges and so on. He just was not
         a man who had liberal ideas.
         
         SS:  Well, I guess you and your brother picked up some when you were young.
         Those ideas that business wasn't entitled to special privilege were
         ideas that you absorbed then.
         
         LO:  Well, yes. I think that we, maybe when we grew up and got away from
         Father's influence and had little chance to look around for ourselves that
         we saw things a little bit differently. Maybe it was the generation gap,
         but. . .
         
         SS:  Well, if he hated all the presidents do you think that was mostly 'cause
         he didn't like the federal government?
         
         LO:  No, I don't think he hated them all, but I think he just felt that they
         could have done things differently. And I think : he probably felt
         that Hoover was one of the better presidents that we had. He disliked
         Roosevelt very much. He just thought Roosevelt was terrible.
         
         SS:  It's funny fron what I've heard, it seems like a number of Democrats
         became Republicans during Cleveland's time. I think that 1893 depression
         turned quite a few.
         
         LO:  That might have had something to do with it. I never did know what it
         was particularly that caused him to change.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13602</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Oslund</previous>
      <next>Otness2</next>
      <disp_name>Otness1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
