<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/21/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Pete Paolini, 1976-10-21, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:25:51</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Paolini, Pete</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Sawmiller; lumberjack</occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Elk River, Lewiston</residence>
      <origin>Came from Italy in 1920</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumberjacks"&gt;lumberjacks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mills"&gt;mills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farms"&gt;farms&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bootlegging"&gt;bootlegging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#unions"&gt;unions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#students"&gt;students&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#strikes"&gt;strikes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gambling"&gt;gambling&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Lewiston"&gt;Lewiston&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13566</file_name>
      <mp3>13567.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13567.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Growing up in Italy with little farmland; family who was here already; why he came
               to America; getting out of army duty; where he lived.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He grew up forty miles west of Florence on a little acreage. Half of what they grew
               went to the landlord. His brother got a false passport to get to America. His siblings
               settled in Wilson Creek, a division point a hundred miles west of Spokane. He came
               to America
               because he wanted work and didn't want to go in the army. He got out of physical by
               making his heart beat fast. He crossed the ocean in 1920 with his brother's fiancée.
               She didn't like it in America and went back with her
               husband; her daughter returned when she was grown. Most men "toughed it out" working
               on railroad section. He boarded with brother and wife.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>840</time>
            <title>Working as a lumberjack in Elk River; blowing money in Spokane</title>
            <synopsis>Lumberjacks were a great group of men. IWWs brought the better conditions. Lumberjacks
               stuck together, while many sawmillers were scabs. Lumberjacks gave their own money
               for drink; they always paid back the conductor on the
               line to Elk River. He only left woods for mill because of short season. Blowing in
               in Spokane - girls took the men's money. How lumberjacks stuck together. Unlike lumberjacks,
               sawmillers were family men.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Working on a strip in the woods; wasn't asked to join the IWWs</title>
            <synopsis>Working on a strip in the woods. Two Frenchmen fought and one left, so the three men
               managed the strip themselves by working extra after supper. Wasn't asked to join IWWs.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Working on railroad sections because he didn't speak English</title>
            <synopsis>A railroad pass to come West to Spokane. Railroad section work was all he could do because he
               didn't speak English, and the instructions were simple.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Brother forcing him to read the Spokesman Review; dating in Elk River at 25; unhappy
               first marriage, tearing down his house in Elk River and rebuilding in Lewiston
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Section work was hard. His brother made him read the Spokesman Review when he wanted
               an Italian paper. Foreigners were "up against it." Dating at Elk River when he was
               25 - movies, not many dances. Unhappy first marriage. Tearing down his house at Elk
               River, he rebuilt on a lot in Lewiston.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Brother losing his job due to strike; coming to Elk River and availability of jobs;
               working in the orchards in Lewiston; who raised his children after wife left
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Brother lost job in car inspector's strike, so they came to Elk River. Availability
               of jobs in Elk River. Preference at Lewiston for ex-Elk River workers in 1933 - little
               work and lots of walking. He worked on orchards farms for free produce and wood. Housekeeper
               and neighbors
               helped raise his children after wife was gone.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2820</time>
            <title>How he got superintendent's job; how Weyerhaeuser got more timber</title>
            <synopsis>Bloom ran Elk River as "one horse town" as well as mill. He got superintendent's job
               by helping Weyerhaeuser steal timber. Weyerhaeuser got more timber cutting access
               roads than the timber he bought. Old Weyerhaeuser
               felt sorry for the horses working in the rain.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Other Italian-Americans in Elk River; going to dances</title>
            <synopsis>Other Italians in Elk River; some married. An Elk River boy who became a multi-millionaire
               in Spokane by trucking. They went to dances together, because Pete had a dollar in
               his pocket.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Loading lumber in Elk River; forced to join four L's at Elk River and Lewiston; not
               getting promoted
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Loading lumber at Elk River mill. Sawmillers were family men so they didn't support
               each other like lumberjacks. Forced to join 4L union at Elk River and Lewiston. When
               the boss's relatives got promoted over him, the union
               representatives (who were company bosses) told him he was free to quit.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3780</time>
            <title>College students getting men's jobs; favoritism in promotion in the company; how Potlatch
               got around company union outlaw
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>College students got men's jobs for extra work after the men trained them. Favoritism
               in promotion. After Roosevelt outlawed company unions, Potlatch came through the back
               door with IEU. His commitment to unionism - as
               soon as they got organized, he went to the top. Changing from AFL to CIO - Billings
               failed to live up to promise to raise wages when they raised on the coast. Chauncey
               Afoll, the head of the (cut off)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>Elk River never had a strike; was told to vote Republican; strike in Lewiston</title>
            <synopsis>There was never a strike at Elk River. Whenever there was an election, they shut the
               plant down and told all the men to vote Republican. In the Lewiston strike there were
               scabs bought off by the company. Nixon's long standing
               crookedness.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Not interacting with other Italian-Americans; selling bootleg whiskey; no drinking
               at the mill; being fearless
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He had little to do with Italians, whose dialects he couldn't understand. Discovering
               and selling a cache of bootleg whiskey. No drinking in mill, but some came in sick
               Monday morning. Little heavy gambling. Harry Adams' joke about his bald head and another
               man's wife; his fearlessness.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>How he lost his hearing; getting a better assignment after being passed over</title>
            <synopsis>He lost hearing grading lumber in the planer. Passed over for a raise in the planer,
               he complained to the steward, and got a better short-term assignment.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Company pressures; importance of union. Lumberjack unity and woods life. Elk River
         in the twenties. Depression hardships. Life near Florence. First years in America.
         10-21-76
         1.4 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This conversation with Pete Paolini took place at his home in Lewiston, Idaho
         on October 21, 1976. The interviewer was Sam Schrager.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: What was it like there where you grew up in Florence that made
         you want to leave? 
         
         PETE PAOLINI: I didn't grow up in the city, it was forty miles west of Florence.
         About half way between Florence and the west coast. Just exactly half
         way. Nice little town, they called it. We live amile
         and a quarter out of town in a little acreage there. ^probably
         eight or ten acres I would say. But we had the landlord then and that
         was rough. You know, half went to the landlord. Everything we raise
         and probably more sometimes.
         
         SS:  So you couldn't even make a living.
         
         PP:  No. No. It was really rough, and that's why my oldest brother,
         soon as he get out of the army, he came over. And then a sister and
         a brother follow him two year- no, I think the brother, he's over
         here in Wenatehee now, next to me, he left home, fourteen and a half
         years old. He came over to- what would you call a passport that
         wasn't his?
         
         Forged passport.
         
         Well, would it been somebody else? The guy was old enough and small
         so he took his name and passport and he came over. So when he apply
         for citizenship why he had to tell them the whole thing what happened,
         because he was anxious to come over but he couldn't; too young, you
         see, but^well developed and strong in you know.
         So they didn't punish him for that?
         
         Oh, no, no, no, they just made him go through the regular-
         Yeah, like anybody else. Take out the first paper. I think he was
         in Alaska when he became a citizen. He went to Alaska when the sawmill up in Elk River
         shut down and no hope of a steady job so he went
         to Alaska.
         
         SS:  So when these brothers and your sister came over, where did they go,
         when they first came to the states?
         
         PP:  Wilson Creek.
         
         SS:  Wilson Creek.
         
         PP:  Wilson Creek was a railroad town; lively little town; lot of work.
         It was a division point on the railroad. You know what I mean, you
         understand what I mean?
         
         SS:  Yes.
         
         PP:  Freight, not passengers. A division point for freight. All the freight
         in those days, they only travel fifteen, twenty miles an hour and lots
         of traffic on the railroad then. And when they got 110 miles out of
         Spokane they had their eight hours in.
         
         SS:  What did they do on the railroad? What were they doing?
         
         PP:  Some of they on the section. This brother I got over here now, he
         was a car inspector right in Wilson Creek. He pass on the freightthey
         all inspected, they wouldn't go by Wilson Creefyuntil all thewhat
         do you call the car? They call 'em hotboxes, you know when they
         start to get too hot, you know, they have to change the oil and then
         sometimes they change the plate. They don't make the freight car like
         they do now.
         
         SS: Well, after the war there in Italy it was pretty rough, wasn't it?
         
         It was rough during the war, too. There ain't no question about it.
         Too much everything was rationed, you know. And even though
         we out there on an acreage, why, the landlord took his share
         first- (Chuckles)
         
         What did that mean, then, what did you eat mostly?
         
         PP:  Mostly what we call a pasta. You know it's made of such as
         macaroni and spaghetti and beans, lentil beans and greens.
         
         SS:  Did you have to go in the army there?
         
         PP: Well, that's why I'm over here. Not only looking for work, but I was
         due to go in the army within eight or nine months. But, ah, boy, I
         didn't like that, I seen enough of I just didn't want to go into
         the army.
         
         SS:  I heard a lot of people that were going in were just going up to the
         lines and getting shot and—
         
         PP:  Well, what the hell, the army- just some ruler decided to go to war,
         why, that's all there is to it. In those days dis country you didn't
         have no draft, you know, just a volunteer army. It was late to go
         to get a passport, but I had a cousin that work for the county in the
         office, and he said, "I think I can get you through." And he told me
         just what to do, you know and sure enough they send me to the city
         twenty-five miles west- and you go to Spokane to pass the physical
         for the army. Well, over there was a city and he got me some paper ,
         got me started and I went and got a physical examination to see if I
         was fit to go to the army, before I was twenty-five I would come back,
         I signed an affidavit. And I passed the examination with kind of a
         doubt, guy told me what to do and fool the doctor; my
         heart.
         
         SS:  What did you do to do that?
         
         PP:  You know (breathes hard and fast).
         
         SS:  What did you do, jump around, run around?
         
         PP:  Yeah, and then if you started- breathes hard and fast again- your
         start beating faster, see. (Chuckles) Okay, you sign an affidavit
         before you're twenty-five you'd come back in and pass another examina
         tion, and see whether they let you stay over there. But I had a sis
         ter and three brothers by then over here, you see, and it made it a
         little easier. But unless I had this cousin working at the county,
         I wouldn't know what to do.
         
         SS:  So what year was this?
         
         PP: 1920. In 1920 in April, yeah because by Easter we were out there in
         the middle of the ocean; Easter Sunday.
         
         SS:  Did you go with friends? Or by yourself?
         
         
         PP:  No, there were a few friends. Not only friends there was a girl,there
         that one of my brothers had gone with her, but he came out of the army
         too, and boy, he beat it! And then send for her and she was along..
         
         SS:  She was coming to marry him?
         
         PP:  Yeah, yeah. They got married the first day she got over here, got
         married in Ephrata. They had a nice little girl, you know, gee, I
         played with her a lot. But his wife didn't like it over here. After
         three years he had to go back over. The kid, it bother me to see that
         little baby go back. But when she was twenty, she married a guy and
         he had some relation in Pittsburgh and she decided to come over. And
         at twenty or twenty-one, I couldn't tell you which, but one of the two,
         either twenty or twenty-one, she had a decision to make whether she
         wanted to stay there and become an Italian citizen or come back here
         and be an American citizen. So, she come back and the immigration
         people wrote me quite a few times, they want lot information and I
         couldn't tell them too much, you know, after all my knowledge limited
         but finally I happened to think this kid was baptised in Ephrata. So
         I wrote to them and told them to write at the Ephrata County, you know
         and the record was still there.
         
         SS:  And it was okay then
         
         PP:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  Why didn't the mother like it here?
         
         PP:  Well, she couldn't talk. She didn't know anybody, just got disgusted
         right away. And it is kind of rough for a young
         hen you are young, you want to chase around and that was out.
         
         SS:  Were there other Italian women there that she could ... ?
         
         PP:  Yeah, my sister was there, you know, but that's all.
         
         SS:  That was it. Ive heard that most people that come over they left
         their wives behind or they were bachelors. Isn't that true?
         
         PP:  Well, of course, in those days, that was before your time, but there
         was a time when a guy could come over and work at least seven or eight
         months on the railroad and you had to tough her out. The railroad
         was kind of a rough business especially, you had some relation at
         the town, you live in a bunkhouse on a railroad car and do your own
         cook and your own washing and it's not very pleasant. But a lot of
         then those guys that did come over, and they either send their wife over
         to America, see.
         
         SS:  This living in a bunkhouse; that's what you did when you came over
         here.
         
         PP:  No, I didn't because I had a sister; she was well established and
         her husband had a pretty good job, too. And they had a nice home
         right in town, right in Wilson Creek, nice home, so I stayed there
         and she done the washing and I slept there and I ate there and paid
         room and board to them. But it was more like a home than live in a
         bunkhouse on the railroad. You never get to talk to anybody
         and you don't know anybody and no entertainment of any kind. You
         can't go and do anything. You know , yourself when you were twenty
         years old and live that kind of a life for two or three years, you'd
         get disgusted, wouldn't you?
         
         SS:  Yeah. That would be tough.
         
         PP:  Yeah, it would be.
         
         SS:  To be doing that- not to have anybody to cook for 'em. Like in the
         logging camps they always had a good cook.
         
         PP:  Logging camp, that's a different, I spent a year in the logging
         camp. I'm glad you mentioned that. They " the best, those
         lumberjack- I don't know about now, but in those days, the real lum
         berjack, they were good people. And play cards every night and cribbage-
         you know what that is, don't you? Play cribbage every night
         and talk. Everybody have a -some story you tell. Time went fast in
         a logging camp. the time I got into the logging camp- those
         camps, they was clean. You had the clean sheets every week, company
         furnished sheets, you know. You had the hot and cold water for shower.
         But two years before that, (Chuckles)the Wobblies got the woods on
         strike. And if it wasn't for the Wobblies -
         
         SS:  That's right, the Wobblies did-
         
         PP:  The Wobblies did- In fact, I have a neighbor over here, one of the
         best of friends over here, he's been a vice-president for the PFI,
         you know, this outfit here, he's one of my best friends. And he ad
         mits, you know. (Chuckles) The Wobblies is what made them clean out
         the camps. They were full of lice and everything else.
         
         SS:  That's what I've heard. I've heard the Wobblies did a good job.
         
         PP:  Oh, it was the Wobblies, it was the Wobblies that done it. No ques
         tion about it.
         
         SS:  What kind of a strike was it? In this area where you were, what was
         the camp that you were in?
         
         SS:  Elk River.
         
         PP:  Camp A up in Elk River. You know, out of Elk River.
         
         SS:  When they talked about that strike, did they say they shut everything
         down?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah. Oh, you bet, you bet. The lumberjack usually they stick
         pretty much together. It isn't like- when we went on strike over here
         in the sawmill, you had so goddamn many scabs, that they finaly lost
         the strike. But thadlumberjacks— I've seen those guys- in those days
         I used to- you know, single, went to Spokane once in a while. Go
         down used to call^the skidway, Wobblies and all this, you know, but they would stop
         a guy, "I need a drink."
         And nobody ever refused them. Everybody would give 'em fifty cents.
         They were that kind of people.
         
         SS:  They took care of their own.
         
         PP:  You bet, you bet they did. In fact they were pretty well 
         In order to get into Elk River you had to go to St. Maries on the Mil
         waukee, you know, and then from St. Maries, you took the little branch
         line or the passenger train that went into Elk River, I think right
         around sixty-five, seventy miles, I don't know. They made a run into
         Elk River and . But that conductor there, the only conductor I
         know, and the lumberjacks come in from Spokane going up to Elk River
         or stop at Bovill or Clarkia. They knew each other from a hundred
         miles around. And they didn't have any , no money, but up there
         the conductor would never throw 'em out. But he said h e never lost
         a cent. You bet, and something else. I put a year in there
         and the trouble was that when I got ready to go back to work, to the
         camps, they were still shut down and I wasn't used to loafing around
         so I went to work in the sawmill. But otherwise, I want to go back
         in the woods so bad. You get so that you like that kind of work. You
         like the people.
         
         SS:  The camps were shut down because of the weather or because of the
         strike?
         
         PP:  Yeah. I've seen in those days, course in those days you had a horse.
         You didn t have  you have today. Everything was a crosscut and
         a horse to skid your logs, you know, and it got too soft. I've seen
         the time that you went into Spokane looking for a skiner, they used
         to call him; two sawyers; four sawyers job to do after the Fourth.
         Yes, many, many places it was still wet up til the Fourth.
         
         SS:  Short season.
         
         PP:  Yeah, it was season work, that's what it was. That's why the lumber
         jack, you never found one that had a wife, you know, they were all
         single guys. They went to Spokane with a couple hundred bucks-two
         hundred bucks in day was a lot of money, two three hundred bucks,
         in about a week or two week's time come back broke.
         
         SS:  And drink. Drink, right?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah. Moonshine! In those days nothing but moonshine. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  And then there were all the prostitutes.
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah, right. Oh, yeah. And some of those smart gals they would
         get ahold of guy they'd stay with him, you know, and probably took
         his money away and say,. because he'll get drunk. And some of those
         prostitutes they'd be honest enough, you know, to, not to gyp him too
         much. But they got pretty well paid.
         
         SS:  These guys though- it's a funny thing about- One thing, you look back
         at it, you know- It seems that when you blow in- it meant a guy'd
         make a lot of money and then it's all gone. Right? Then start from
         scratch again.
         
         PP:  You don't have a wife, you don't have a family, no responsibility, no
         nothin', and it gets so you've been broke once or twice, but you
         never suffer because somebody carry you along. See. You done the
         same thing for somebody else. It's unbelieveable. But the lumber
         jack, they stuck together and they understood it. If a guy was
         drunk they knew how he went broke, see.
         
         SS:  Did you have to know the guy very good?
         
         PP:  A lumberjack—»You could spot a lumberjack a mile away.(Laughs)
         
         SS:  How was that?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:  How can you spot 'em? They way he was dressed?
         
         PP:  They way they talk, you know. They all had that dirty word in their
         mouth, you know. Never open their mouth unless they said, "Dammit!"
         or, "Fuck you." Or nonsense like that! That's the way they talk.
         It was no place for a lady to be around. See.
         
         SS:  Did you really like the class of people that were lumberjacks better
         then the guys that were at the sawmills?
         
         PP:  Yes, I did, I did. There's no question about it. I could tell you
         that I've been beat out of a few hundred, quite a few, too, but never
         from a lumberjack.
         
         SS:  What's the difference like between those guys and the sawmillers?
         The guys in the sawmill at Elk River?
         
         PP:  Well, the sawmill, it's different. It's a different breed of a people,
         The sawmill; you have a family. You go home, you know, to your family
         every day, but the lumberjack's a different guy, see. He didn't have
         responsibility. And that's why they live different. But they
         were honest.
         
         SS:  What did you do when you were working in the woods as a lumberjack?
         
         PP:  When I went in the woods I saw. Saw, gyppo, see. So much a thousand.
         
         SS:  That was you and your brother?
         
         PP:  And my brother, yeah. Then you see in those days, what we do, we
         went to any camp, if they didn't have a job right then, they'll
         hold you to stay in and they find somebody, you know. And most of
         the time it take two or four guys to what they call a strip of
         timber to log that off. Bring them down to the railroad. In those
         days, like I say, they logged different. They built the railroad
         into the woods. Like I said, when we went up in the woods, you
         know, we went in there and the foreman said they wait a day or two
         We ate in there. And sure enough it was only a day and
         a half or so and here comes a couple guys. So the four would go to
         gether. One was what they call a swamper, and one the skinner, see,
         and I and my brother were the sawyers. We saw the logs in teen
         foot length. And the swamper would see that the guy with the team,
         have a load ready for him to take along. When we got half way through
         this- our job, those guys, they were both Frenchmen, and they " a
         fight among themselves, so one pull off and went. And we had so
         damn much money accumulated- because we were getting just the wage,
         I think it was $3.40, $3.50 a day-
         
         SS:  And you get a bonus.
         
         PP:  And the bonus. That was cash you see, but we had to finish our job
         in order to collect that. The strip was. so much a thousand.
         
         SS:  And you get the bonus on every thousand, right?
         
         PP:  Bonus on every thousand at the end of the job. The end of the job
         the foreman would come out and look the strip over and see if it was
         okay, and then they pay you off.
         
         SS:  So what happened when they left?
         
         PP:  Then we handle between the three of us, you see. If they get some
         body else in probably that guy would have give him $150- 200 bucks.
         So we done it ourselves.
         
         SS:  You handled it, the three of you?
         
         PP:  The three of us, yeah.
         
         SS:  Could you handle it?
         
         PP:  Well, we did this way In order to fix the road, the skid road,
         sometime we go out after supper, see, and do the little bit of a jobs.
         Because they won't let you keep any team out, you know, after eight
         hours. But you could go out and fix your trail. Or if you had a
         bad tree that was leaning in a different way and it took you a long
         time to do just what you wanted.
         
         SS:  You'd do that after supper?
         
         PP:  Yeah..
         
         SS:  So did you have to work really hard on that strip?
         
         PP:  It was hard until you got onto it. I was new. Just a young punk of
         a kid, you know. But stayed with it and we done it, in fact we
         built a little reputation for doing it.
         
         SS:  You mean for doing it- just the three of you doing it?
         
         PP:  Um-huh.
         
         SS:  Did you join the IWW when you came there?
         
         PP:  No, no. In fact. They didn't bother you too much then, either. If
         it had come around, But by then they didn't bother you. The IWW, they
         pulled that strike then that was it. And I don't know, I couldn't
         tell you too much about that because, just like I said, they didn't
         bother us. And I kind of think they left you alone for a year or so.
         Join the IWW, they want to be sure that you meant it. You know and
         stay with it. I kind of think, that's the way I got it.
         
         SS:  Now what year was it that you were in the woods there?
         
         PP:  '24.
         
         SS:  Okay, well, going back a little before that; when you first came
         When you first came here from Italy; when you first got out there,
         how did you go, did you take the train all the way out?
         
         PP:  Yes, I did. In fact I stopped in Chicago. Course, you know by that
         time I was told just what to do, writing to my brother, and he had
         grown kids- he had a widow. And he told me what to do, so
         I stopped in Chicago and some people there and they found a guy
         that was coming into Spokane. So I went into St. Paul with this guy
         and the railroad give me a pass to come out West. That was pretty nice
         but they done it right along.. They did want to build the West anyhow.
         Beside I knew I couldn't go out and do anything else by railroad, see.
         And I did. I went out on the railroad.
         
         SS:  How come you knew railroad was the only job you could do?
         
         PP:  Well, what else could you do when you can't talk? And who would hire
         you? See, even in the sawmill, unless you know, you know, can talk
         a little bit so the foreman can But on the railroad,
         just one job and after one day or two you're on your own.
         
         SS:  But you'd never done that back in Italy? Railroads?
         
         PP:  Oh, no, no.
         
         SS:  So what was it like with the language? To not know English. Was
         that hard at first?
         
         PP:  Well, yeah. But what I mean, but not to work, because like I said,
         it's a job that you learn it so quick, you see, that most particular
         job was it-
         
         SS:  What was it? What was it that you did on that job?
         
         PP:  he marked the bad one to pull out and you placed th e new
         one. See, the track you know what you do there.
         
         SS:  Were most of the guys on that crew Italian?
         
         PP:  No. NO.
         
         SS:  Just you?
         
         SS:  What do you mean, you couldn't buy your own cigarettes?
         
         PP:  Well, gosh dammit, I finally got so that I listened to them guys, you
         know, And and so, cigarrette, cigarrette. (Chuckles)
         But they would say, "What kind?" Well, I had an idea what they said,
         and in those days, it was Camel, Chesterfield and Lucky Strike; you
         very seldom see any other brand.
         
         SS:  What about the work itself? Was it hard? Was it real hard work?
         
         PP:  Well, its not easy work, no. It's plenty hard, you bet. It's pick
         and shovel, you know. It's not for a sissy! But, what the hell!
         You. over here to work! But when a guy is twenty, you know nine-
         in
         teen and twenty, afte^ you once get. on the job, it's not too
         bad.
         
         SS:  How was your brother coming along, your other brothers and the sis
         ter that were here; were they learning the language fast?
         
         PP:  Well, just about like I did, but the^had the 1 anguage pretty good,
         except they- this one over here at Wenatchee he talk pretty good be
         cause he came over, I told you, when he was thirteen and a half years
         old. But, you learn. Jrrom Wilson Creek- I had a brotherthe
         oldest brother he was in Montana, east of Libby, thirty miles,
         and he wanted me to go over there, work for him. He was a forman.
         And once in a while I'd go over there and then I stay there.
         
         SS:  What kind of foreman?
         
         PP:  He was a section foreman. I told him once, I said, "is there any
         in order
         place that I can get a newspaper, that I can read?" And he point
         to the Spokesman Review. I said, I can't- and he said, "Keep on
         looking at it. You can look at it, if you can't read it, forget it."
         He said, "You got to learn the English sometime."
         
         SS:  You spent most of your time with the family. You'd be speaking Italian,
         you wouldn't be speaking English.
         
         PP:  Well, not only that, otherwise, what the hell could you do? Go out
         Don't like that. to the goddamn bunkhouse and So, I stay with my
         brother he was married and had family there, and pay board and room
         with her.
         
         SS:  Do you remember when you were first here and like over there, ever
         having a hard time because you were a foreigner? Because you didn't
         speak English? People held it against you because-
         
         PP:  Why sure, no question about it, you kind of up against it all the time.
         You are handicap. You bet.
         
         SS:  Did you ever get in fights over that? Somebody give yo u a hard time?
         
         PP:  No. No. I know it, even when I first started talking, you know, some
         times they kind of laugh. You know, let 'em laugh. You'd be surprised
         how many time I laugh at some of those guys trying to say something *
         (Chuckles) No, I didn't let that bother me too much. You see
         I was right around twenty-five years old before I even started going
         out with any girls, you see.
         
         SS:  Where was that, in Elk River?
         
         PP:  Elk River.
         
         SS:  When you started going out with girls at Elk River, who were they?
         Were they girls whose parents were—
         
         PP:  No, they were English. They were born over here. But, you know, to
         a show here and there, you know. Those days I didn't go to dances
         much. You don't speak the language good, you know, you kind of holdi^
         yourself back.
         
         SS:  Well, those local girls, you know, they were kind of like the Elk
         River girls.—
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah, some of 'em. This Ilk here is one. ^ retireshe
         retire over here. Went to a show quite a few times with her.
         I see her few times, nothing serious. When I finally got serious
         with one, she was from Deary, married her, Jesus Christ she turn
         out to be not so good. Give me a couple kids and then I had to kick
         her out. That was rough. You bet. And that was in the '30's, the
         early '30's.
         
         SS:  In the Depression.
         
         PP:  But I this place, I had bought a piece of land over here, you
         know, two bits down, two bits month, you know. Tore down the old
         bath and everything house up in Elk River. I bought five room house for $100 and tore
         it
         down and try to rebuild it over here, but soon as I got the roof on
         and move it in- Those days they were bad ones.
         
         SS:  What happened? Didn't the house come back together right?
         
         PP:  Well, just tore it down piece by piece, but all the windows and doors
         and bathroom fixtures and lot of that stuff you know-
         
         SS:  You could use that?
         
         PP:  Oh, yes, I could use that.
         
         SS:  Didn't some people move the whole house out?
         
         PP:  Well, no, it's pretty hard to do that, you know, in those days special
         ly. Now they have the means of moving them so lot of house was moved
         alright, but just like I did. This big house, we can see it from here,
         now we got the biggest story houseA here , move it, too. There you
         can see part of the garage and the window
         
         SS:  When you decided to leave and to come to Elk River area with your
         brother, what kind of strike was that? Had you gone on strike, too,
         on the section?
         
         PP:  No, this wasn't on the section. He was a-
         
         SS:  Car inspector.
         
         PP:  Car inspector, yeah, and the car inspector they went on strike and
         they lost out in the strike. And it probably was a good move
         for me to go with him then, see. And I finally ended up over here.
         
         SS:  Did he lose his job in that strike?
         
         PP:  Uh-huh.
         
         SS:  What was the union I wonder at that time.
         
         PP:  Well, the union, of course they still got it now, too. Under this
         kind of a system you had the engineer, you had the fireman, you had
         the conductor, you had the brakeman, you had the sectionman, you had
         the car inspector. You had so many different branches into that
         union.
         
         SS:  Oh, they were all different?
         
         PP:  You see, what they call the Craft Union.
         
         SS:  Craft Union, yeah.
         
         PP:  Yeah, sure, that's what we had over here in the sawmill under the
         AF of L and finally we organized the CIO.
         
         SS:  The CIO is an industrial union, it's everybody.
         
         PP:  That's right, that's right it's everybody belong to the same union.
         
         SS:  That works better.
         
         PP:  Well, it sure worked better, you bet. Yeah, he lost out. As I say,
         that was probably for the best because I ended up with a pretty fair
         job over here. I got to be a pretty good grader, lumber grader.
         
         SS:  How did you get into the mill? Was there a lot of jobs at the time?
         Openings in the mill?
         
         PP: No-
         
         SS:  Elk River.
         
         PP:  Elk River of course in those days was at the end of the line and help,
         good help especially was hard to get. So there was no problem going
         and get a job in the sawmill. So, then when the sawmill
         shut down, of course, by that time I was married, family. And it shut
         down, the doggone thing, and never started anymore. There was a superin
         tendent down here,' and he knew that there were a lot of people up in
         Elk River yet, you know work in the sawmill and they udnerstood
         lumber, knew what they were doing and rather than hire a new guy they
         would call those guys, not only it was kind of an obligation for the
         company too to get some of those guys because it's in the company, see.
         
         SS:  They'd laid them all off.
         
         PP:  Yes. So, it was on the Fourth of July- on the fifth of July in '33
         why- in the meantime there was quite a few guys over here already from
         Elk River and this guy had told him about me and another guy, so they
         called us to come down. We come down and get a job alright. Anyway,
         six hours a day, two days a week.
         
         SS:  Doing what? What were you doing?
         
         PP:  Well, lumber; just anything.
         
         SS:  What year was that?
         
         PP:  In '33.
         
         SS:  Two days a week, huh?
         
         PP:  Two days a week- three days a week- you go to work eight o'clock,
         sometime eleven o'clock, well, that's all for the day. One department
         shut down. When we come back- who called you?
         
         somebody else, some neighbor. And then try to catch a ride with some
         body all the time. There's was five- one guy would pick us up, you
         know, there'd be four and the driver. Many time lose our
         ride. The driver he was a MoAMtal driver,maybe get to work til five
         that day or maybe sometime it was his turn to go home early and we
         had to work another hour.
         
         SS:  What did you do then? You didn't have a ride home.
         
         PP:  Walk. Iwent two years withQut an automobile. Walk from the sawmill over here.
         
         SS:  How far would that be?
         
         PP:  About six mile- six, seven.
         
         SS:  Each way?
         
         PP:  Yes.
         
         SS:  For how much money?
         
         PP:  I was making right on an average of twenty, twenty-one, two dollars
         for two weeks work. Every payday.
         
         SS:  Did you live on that?
         
         PP:  No. But I got acquaint with lot of those guys. One guy still up here
         now, Harry Eisman, Most of 'em are dead now. But they had big gar
         dens, they were raising gardens and they all produced to sell, fruit,
         cherry, peaches, anything, you know. Whenever I didn't have nothing
         else to do, I was home, I used to go over and help those guys and I
         would get produce, fruit for free. And any time they had a cherry
         tree that was dying out, I could have it if I dug it by the roots for
         my winter wood.
         
         SS:  Rough.
         
         PP:  Don't tell me it was rough! It was rough. No question about it. But
         some of those guys, they don't believe it. But I made it, I paid my
         bills. Took a long time to do it.
         
         SS:  Is that when you and your wife split up?
         
         PP:  Yeah, I had it pretty rough because you see then I have to have a
         housekeeper, pay a housekeeper.
         
         SS:  Did you keep the kids?
         
         PP:  Yeah, I kept the kids. Yes, you bet. Oh, yeah, the neighbors would
         if I hadn't.
         
         SS:  The neighbors?
         
         PP:  Yeah, oh, yeah, all the neighbors stuck up for me. They help me out
         that way, you know.
         
         SS:  She must not have been much of a mother then for the kids.
         
         PP:  No. No, In those days, the youngest kid wasn't quite five and the
         other one six they thought it was a mean daddy
         that they had, see.
         
         SS:  So, you kind of raised the kids yourself?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah, sure. You bet. And then finally I married this gal over
         here, We've been married almost thirty
         years now and we have a girl twenty-five years old. She got married
         after she a good job,
         
         SS:  Was it - for you to kind of take care of the kids- was that hard to
         kind of be a mother to themttod?
         
         PP:  Well, sure, course. Course, it is like I say, I had pretty good neigh
         bors. One neighbor live in this double house over here, both are dead
         now, they were wonderful people to me.
         
         SS:  They took care of them?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah, they- between them and the housekeeper. But it was rough.
         I had the debts to pay, you see.
         
         SS:  You had the hosuekeeper right during the Depression, then? '33?
         
         PP:  Oh, yes, sure, sure.
         
         SS:  Well, Elk River, when you were there; what was the town like in the
         '20's? Was it a booming town?
         
         PP:  It was. It was. Just like I said, it was a wonderful little town.
         Everybody had money because everybody work. There wasn't a guy that
         didn't have a job. The bums, they didn't even show up. You know those
         days, on the mainline railroad, bums seemed to go by by the hundreds,
         you know, but not at Elk River. Everybody worked there, everybody
         had money. Everybody happy. Saturday night they would have a dance
         a picture show.A In the wintertime you couldn't go out of town with
         the car. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  So that meant-during the winter was there a lot of social life in the
         town, right in the town?
         
         PP:  Well, yes.
         
         SS:  I heard that they shut down the picture show on Sundays in Elk River.
         Pp: Yes, once in a while they get what you call one/horse town, a guy that
         run the sawmill, the big boss, you know, he wants to be elected the
         mayor of the town. He wants to run the schoolboard, he wants to run
         it, not only the sawmill, he wants to run the town, too. (Chuckles)
         You've heard of a one-horse town, haven't you? That was one-horse
         town. Just like I say, nobody minded.
         
         SS:  Was that Bloom?
         
         PP:  Bloom.
         
         SS:  Was that his idea to shut down the movies? I've heard that it was
         some of the church people —
         
         PP:  He was a religious man, too, see. Angie Bloom.
         
         SS:  What kind of boss was he?
         
         PP:  Well, of course, he didn't have nothing to do with the men. He was
         the general superintendent. He couldn't talk English any better
         than I can now. Well, I don't know what I should say- but he was a
         timber cruiser. He made a living as a timber cruiser. In those days
         everybody, they could steal from Uncle Sam, that had done it, see what
         I mean? This old cruiser got to know how many million feet of the
         timber went into the Potlatch for nothing, so he got a job out of it,
         see. Not that he knew how to run a sawmill. Don't repeat this now!
         
         SS:  So he helped 'em set up.
         
         SS:  Well, I've heard the same thing about Deary in Potlatch.
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah. Well, it was just as much to work then as it is today.
         Politics, what have you.
         
         SS:  And there was all that timber just sitting there, and nobody had used
         it or nothing.
         
         PP:  Well, this people over here that I told you got to be my best friend
         during the Depression? The old man, he was- he run the firs t camp
         for the original Weyerhaeusers. He ran the first camp. And he said,
         "Boy, did we get the timber." Weyerhaeusr in those days- the Forest
         Service was different; A guy would go in there and say, "I want a
         strip of a timber'.'And he'd buy a section of timber. But he don't buy
         it over here handy, he'd go two, three miles back over here. "That's
         the timber I want." And then he gets to cut a right-of-way for nothing
         He got to get into it. (Chuckles) And this guy, is his
         name. He said, "We got more timber for free than what Weyerhaeuser
         bought.
         
         SS:  Was that in Idaho?
         
         PP:  No, no, no, Cloquet.
         
         SS:  Oh, Minnesota, yeah. Cloquet, Minnesota.
         
         PP:  Yeah, Yeah. 
         But he had he  story. When they first opened up this camp
         and Johan Neil supposed to run it, and one day it was raining. Here
         comes the Old Man Weyerhaeuser himself up to the camp. They said he
         got inside and looking out and he said, "Jo, what a day for horses!
         What a day for the horses!" And he kept it up for about an hour.
         Finally said, "Jo, go tell those guys to bring in the horses."
         Well, I shouldn't talk, I shouldn't tell those things! (Laughter)
         
         SS:  It*s okay.
         
         PP:  Don't repeat it!
         
         SS:  Well, that kind of story- I heard stories about Old Man Weyerhaeuser
         before.
         
         PP:  Well, that's the way he got started by stealing.
         
         SS:  That's what everybody said. That's nothing new. (Chuckles)
         Well, in Elk River when you were there; were there many other guys
         that were Italian working in the sawmill?
         
         PP:  No. Well, I would say, there was quite a bunch at that. There was
         one bunch - they came right from the border between Austria and Italy
         there and I couldn't tell whether they were Italian, they talked both
         languages.
         
         SS:  Italian and German, too?
         
         PP:  Austrian, yeah, they were Austrian. And they talked bot h the language,
         And there's one up here now still alive, he's been sick a lot he was
         from Venice. There was two, three families from Venice. And then there
         was probably, oh, five, six or seven of those guys from way up north.
         Right up on the line.
         
         SS:  How many families were there? There was some with families, some—
         
         PP:  Yes, they had some family, just five, six, seven.
         
         SS:  Didn't have families?
         
         PP:  Uh-huh, yeah.
         
         SS:  And then there were just more guys just by themselves?
         
         PP:  Yeah, single guys. There was a boardinghouse- a woman ran a boardinghouse-
         she had lost her husband and she had two kids; one was name
         John, the other was Louie. And John finally went to Spokane just be
         fore sawmill shut down up at Elk River and he went into the freight
         business. Started in with an old beat up truck and he ended up with
         owning the United Freight Line and in no time at all got to be a multi
         millionaire. And I have seen the day that I loan him four bits to go
         to a dance! See how it goes.
         
         SS:  Is that luck?
         
         PP:  Well, there was luck and he had guts, too. He had the guts and he
         had the mama to back him up. The mama- even the Depression didn't
         hurt too much because she kept her money, so she had enough moneythe
         way he started out with a service station, Spokane, and finally
         bought himself an old beat up truck and he got to running from- Seattle,
         Portland to Spokane. But he got one of those big outfits - Monkey
         Ward or Sears or some of those big chain stores, you know, do all the
         hauling. And the first thing you know he got himself a fleet of trucks
         finally spread out
         clear to Alaska. And finally it was sold to United Buckingham. You
         ever see that United Buckingham.
         
         SS:  Trucks.
         
         PP:  For a while it was just United, J was ;and I think now
         it is run by Buckingham. But to me, I remember many times, he say,
         "Come on, fellow," because he always had an automobile up there, and
         money, Mama, see. He worked just like I did, you know, down
         in the sawmill; the check went to mama and then mama
         Bought the car alright, but check him down, you see. So he invited me
         to go to Moscow.or someplace, you know, because he knew that I had
         a dollar in my pocket. Yeah, and then, first thing you know, the guy's
         a multimillionaire and I'm a poor guy trying to make a living!
         
         SS:  That's the way most of us are. Well, when you started in the mill,
         what did you start doing?What was your first job?
         
         PP:  Loading lumber. In those days we had lots of handwork you know, hand
         lumber, you know. Handling lumber. Especially at Elk River, most of
         the lumber was dried out in the yard. And I and my brother went out
         to gyppo work; it was all glyppo work then.
         
         SS:  Was that pretty good money?
         
         PP:  Well, we made a wage, you know, doubled our wage, see. In those
         days I think, wage was forty cents an hour.
         
         SS:  But you could make eighty cents an hour loading?
         
         PP:  Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:  And you would just work eight hours?
         
         PP:  Yeah. Well, course, just about eight hours and maybe any more than
         that. We ate probably lunch and go right back work, but then we quit-
         
         SS:  What was it like with the guys in the mill? How did they get along?
         Did they tease each other a lot, joking?
         
         PP:  Well, yeah, but of course, you couldn't talk to the guy in the sawmill
         Right in the sawmill they never would. Mostly fin the h side. In
         the dry lumber side. And finally in the sawmill I went and pulled
         lumber on the greenchain one year. And that was a pretty fair job,
         it paid, I think it was fifty cents an hour in those days.
         
         SS:  But these guys in the sawmill, they weren't as close as the guys were
         in the camps?
         
         PP:  Oh, no, no, no. Because I told you that they're a different breed
         of a people. Family people, see.
         
         SS:  You mean like maybe they had other ties so they weren't- they didn't
         care about the-
         
         PP:  No, everybody for themself, you know. In other words, sure somebody
         down-and-out they took up a collection anytime; a guy throw in two
         bits, you see, but a lumberjack if he was down-and-out, still he was
         drinking and he wants another drink, he didn't make any bones about
         it, he asked you for a drink; the price for a drink, and he got it.
         
         SS:  Okay. But in the mill, why weren't these guys the same way?
         
         PP:  They were friendly. But if you ever was drunk and you spend all your
         money, "To hell with you, I got kids to feed," See. But the lum
         berjack, he was single guy, he didn't have any kids, he share his last
         dollar.
         
         SS:  Okay. What about say, the union with these guys in the sawmill?
         Did they care about the union?
         
         PP:  They didn't have any union. Finally came, the company union came.
         
         SS:  Oh, is that the Four L?
         
         PP:  The Four L. And I and a little young Swede, we were working on the
         greenchain and we decided, goddamn, we wasn't going to join it. And
         finally the boss come out, said, "I'm sorry, I don't want to see
         you go, I don't want to let you go, both of you guys pretty good men,
         but you got to join the union." Forced us into it. Then when we came
         down over here, they didn't even ask us to join, just started taking
         the money from the payroll to pay for the Four L.
         
         SS:  Did the Four L do anything for the men that you could see? Did they
         do good?
         
         PP:  Oh, yes. Yeah, yeah, they did because I- I didn't lost my job, but
         I lost my advancement three or four times to the boss's son to the
         boss's son-in-law to the boss's cousin; and if it were not for the
         union, "Oh, boy," he said, "one nice thing about belong to the union
         over here," he said, "a guy don't have to. job. If he don't
         like it, he can go." That's what they told you.
         
         SS:  Do you mean that they protected your job?
         
         PP:  Protection one way,you had better like it or you could quit.
         
         SS:  That's no protection, is it?
         
         PP:  Because, they told me it was. You see, in other word, this was in
         Russia, they didn't hold me over here, like I was free to go. The
         business agent and timekeeper for the union was a Jerry Johnston
         was the timekeeper. 
         
         PP:  find and then the company started to having what they
         called the students, you know, those college guys from Moscow, they
         come in sometime and they would have 'em in bunches, they'd bring in
         eight or ten, some of the top guy, you know. Then they put one with
         me, one with somebody else, one with somebody else, you know, to train
         'em, so they would learn the trick with the lumber. Well, okay. I'd
         train 'em, show them the grade and then once in a while the guy would
         say, "How do you scale lumber?" Well, showed them how to scale lumber.
         I didn't have to, but I told 'em. Here comes the first of the year
         take an inventory, shut the whole thing down; those guys they got to
         work and I stay to home. And I want to work so damn bad because we
         wasn't working enough. After I taught those guys, they was the ones
         that got that extra work and not me.
         
         SS:  Were they working regular during that time or were they just bringing
         them out from Moscow-
         
         PP:  Bringing them from Moscow and they spend four, five, six- it depends
         from here
         whatever the supervisor thought, then they send them.to another sawmill
         out on the coast, you know and made a salesman out of them. See.
         That's what they were doing. And that's why - when I finally joined
         the CIO I stayed with the union, and boy, I never missed a meeting. .
         
         SS:  Wait a minute; one more thing about this Four L. They didn't stop,
         say, the boss from giving a job to his son over you? I mean, what
         happened? Did you lose?
         
         PP: They advance, especially in grading or
         almost anything, there's always a job that pay from two and a half to
         five cents an hour more, you know, a better job. Okay, who gets that
         advance? The boss's son, the boss's son of a bitch or- you know what
         I mean. Or maybe the guy bought him a drink or bought him a bottle
         of whiskey.
         
         SS:  And that's the Four L?
         
         PP:  That was the Four L, yes. Then when Roosevelt come along and out
         lawed the company union, they come back from the backdoor. IEU, they
         called it a different name.
         
         SS:  It was the same union.
         
         PP:  Yeah, yeah, it was the same
         
         SS:  Did most of the men feel the same way you did?
         
         PP:  Sure. But what can you do about it?
         
         SS:  But you did get better jobs when you were there, right?
         
         PP:  After we got organized, yes. After we got organized.
         
         SS:  So this lumber grading you did after—
         
         PP:  Well, I was big even before the CIO, but never got any place, stayed
         on that job, never got to advance. But soon as we got organized I
         get up to the top in no time. And I want to tell you something else,
         lose
         the company didn't a goddamned thing by advancing me rather than
         advance-a guy that they didn't know anything- just because he was the
         boss's friend.
         
         SS:  Sure. Now, look when that started; that organizing- when did it
         start?
         
         PP:  I wouldn't know.
         
         SS:  It was down here, right?
         
         PP:  It was down here, oh, yes..We went in with the AF of L, and that was
         okay in one way, fairly good, but then, again, C. L. Billings told us
         "Boy,"he said,"today we have a war on," he say, "I don't want any
         strike, I don't want any wildcat strike or nothing," he said, "whehever
         thetoast have a raise, I'll see that you guys get a raise, too."
         Once, the coast, they got seven and a half cents raise and we didn't
         get nothing. And^we changed to the CIO.
         
         SS:  Is that what did it?
         
         PP:  He brought the leader of the AF of L, he got him in the main o-Md.*. S^
         So when a guy from Clarkston, Chauncey Noll- he was a radical guy,
         was smart- of course, they called him communist and everything else,
         but he was honest, I don't give a damn what he was, he was honest,
         and we organized.
         
         SS:  Was he the main organizer?
         Pi: Well, he was a no- course, they came from outside to organize to
         help and organize.
         
         SS:  Well, what was this guy? What was his name?
         
         PP:  Chauncey Noll.
         
         SS:  Chauncey Noll.
         
         PP:  Yeah, he died, too a couple of years ago.
         
         SS:  But what did he do? Was he the leader?
         
         PP:  He was just a working , the same as anybody else.
         
         SS:  But he was kind of a leader, I know that.
         
         PP:  But, boy, when he started in, he'd go to hell anytime for a guy, you
         know. If he had a grievance, boy, he had the guts to open it up to
         the top man, if he had to. He wasn't afraid to fight.
         
         SS:  Did he become the head of the local; Chauncey Noll?
         
         PP:  Yeah, um-huh.
         
         So, he really believed in the men? I mean, he was on your side?
         
         Yes, no question about it. He was for 4A.
         
         Did he talk much about unionism? You say, they called him a radical.
         He must have been pretty outspoken then.
         
         He was, he was. The guy's still alive. He's a lawyer, but they made
         him a vice president 
         
         Him and two other guys, but he was doing all the talking. He was re
         presenting the company all the time, you know, and boy, him and this
         Noll lock horn many times, even when it was this. But when Chauncey
         Noll died, this . was a pallbearer. And come out in the paper,
         and said, how did he say? Said, "The guy called me a son of a bitch
         once," and he said, "and "I was a pallbearer to his funeral." Yeah,
         he admitted that the guy was a radical and all that a a son of a
         bitch even, but the guy said that you couldn't buy him out.
         
         SS:  Was it hard to beat the AF of L and get the new union in?
         
         PP:  No, to beat them it was nothing but a vote and when all the members
         found out what they had done, you see, the labor voted to come in and
         held a election and we got the CIO and that's all there was to it.
         And then, of course, the people from Portland or some of
         them place, they come in and started us out.
         
         SS:  When there was a strike- the first strike that you were in herewas
         there ever a strike at Elk River? In the mill when you were
         there?
         
         PP:  No. No. What the hell— How can you strike up there? I want to tell
         you this story: We had the Hoover- Hoover, you know, you heard about
         Hoover?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         PP:  Okay, okay. They shut the goddamn plant down and the superintendent
         come out saying to be sure to vote for Hoover. We want the sawmill
         to run^ And one guy said, " shit!" One guy heard him say that,
         "Say," he said, "you hear what he said?" He said, "You better vote
         for Hoover, I bought a house in this town, and I want this goddamn
         sawmill to run.
         
         Over here, too, Roosevelt that  you Couldn't
         The strike here, was that in '36 that they had that strike?
         
         PP:  I don't remember.
         
         SS:  Didn't they shut the mill down here?
         
         PP:  They called the strike and the company locked the gate, see for two
         weeks or something like that and it was in the fall of the year. And
         then they got I don't know what would you call them- the company
         brought them out-
         
         SS:  The strike breakers.
         
         PP:  — and going back to work and all that stuff. Well, hell, they lost
         the strike.
         
         SS:  Didn't they somebody like- the name was Potlatch Rose or somebody like
         that?
         
         PP:  I called that gal an old bitch so damn many times she got to know me.
         Oh, probably, oh, maybe, eight or ten years after she was down there
         night, you know,any time something, you have to go to her, or if you^re
         lay off or get sick. One night, by gosh, I got a kink in my back;
         I went over to see her,and slept til time to come home
         and got paid for working and say, she treated me just like-(chuckles)
         Didn't they kind of bring her in to try to get the men to go back to
         work? Wasn't that why?
         
         PP:  Well, I told you, that bunch of those guys just like her a
         few of the leader, and few more of those guys, you know. They got
         em in give em free pop and a free lunch, a free show and all that.
         
         SS:  To get 'em to go back to work.
         
         PP:  Well, I tell you, money, money, look what fkxon- not with the money,
         with the people that want to elect him. him crooked,
         the first time he ran with Eisenhower, he was supposed to be impeach.
         Pictures in the paper and all the magazine in the country and then
         get elected. Why? They bought votes. Hundred and seventy-eight mil
         lion dollars.
         
         SS:  Yes, crooked as the day is long.
         
         PP:  They never told us, but Ifinally got it 
         He ended up with seven homes. Two in California and five in Florida.
         He sold two already.
         
         SS:  I want to ask a little more about Elk River when you were there. Most
         of your friends, the people that you spent your time with; were they
         Italian or were they—?
         
         PP:  No, no, no, I didn't have any Italian friends any more than— I made
         friends with other people; Swedes and what have you, Norwegians— see
         my first wife was Norwegian, and I know quite a few. No, plain Ameri
         can people. I got away from Italian people.
         
         SS:  Any reason?
         
         PP:  Reason enough. I told you five or six family, most of them they come
         from way up on the border and they were hard to understand and then
         there were four, five family from the South, the same way. So nobody
         talked my language, and I thought I might as well talk the English
         then.
         
         SS:  What about the bootlegging in those days? Wasn't there a lot?
         
         PP:  Lot of bootlegging.
         
         SS:  And drinking and boozing?
         
         PP:  Yeah. (Chuckles) One Monday morning I and my brother was coming home
         for lunch; we jumped the fence and we had probably half a mile walking
         the railroad, good to walk in the railroad they kept it plowed out,
         snow bank that high both side, and all at once we seen something
         sticking out, that was a bottle, pop bottle full of moonshine, goddamit
         we was picking up probably fifteen or twenty. They were put in there
         on Saturday night for the dance, you see, and the guy probably got
         drunk and forgot 'em or couldn't find 'em, so we went back in there
         with a gunny sack and got 'em and we sold 'em. And that's how much
         bootlegging I done. In those day I didn't drink, I didn't touch it.
         I would like to drink some beer, oh, yeah, beer or wine, but not the
         whiskey. Now I drink whiskey, the doctor won't let me.
         
         SS:  Was there much drinking around the mill?
         
         PP:  No, not in the mill because they can you. They can you. But there
         was a few of those guys they would start drink Saturday night, drink
         until Sunday night, and sometime they would come on the job not drunk
         but sick. Yeah, I ve seen that a lot. In fact there was guy there
         now, he d been having a hell of a time, operation and doctor. '
         older than I am and he just had one foot in the grave long time.
         Abuse himself, you know.
         
         SS:  So there was some guys that did that? Maybe married men too, it
         wouldn't matter.
         
         PP:  Uh-huh. Oh, yes.
         
         SS:  What about the gambling? Was there much of that?
         
         PP:  Well, the gambling, it was not- say few friends get to gether, there
         was nobody 
         
         SS:  Then like there's a lot of guys played pool, didn't they in downtown
         Elk River? Poolhalls and that kind of—?
         
         PP:  Uh-huh. But there was no money bet on pool. Up there, just like I
         say, there was two or three poolhalls in there to go to, and cardplay
         card, you know.
         
         SS:  Who was that guy? Harry Adams had one of those poolhalls?
         
         PP:  Yes, I knew him so well. His son is the mayor of 
         
         SS:  Yeah, that's right. I heard Harry was quite a- really knew how to
         tell stories. Great liar, huh?
         
         PP:  Once, you know- he was baldheaded. The year before I came to Elk
         River, he had a poolhall right on the corner and everybody going to
         work would stop in there, you know and old Harry had this bald head.
         And one guy came along, he was going to work, felt his head, "By God
         it feel like my wife's ass." Old Harry, said, "It does, doesn't it?"
         Jesus christ the guy got mad, call him out. "I'll kill you son of a
         old 
         bitch!" (Laughter) When the thing got rough, you know, "I'm not afraid
         of any damn man."
         I like him, he's a nice fellow.
         
         PP:  supposed to eat my lunch, if you want some more information, I'll
         be over here in ten minutes.
         
         SS:  Well, maybe I should get going, I'm supposed to see somebody this af
         ternoon. But maybe I'll try to stop by again another time when I
         come down.
         
         PP:  Fine, I'll be around.
         
         SS:  If I can, I will. The only thing I was going to ask you was; the
         difference when you got up to get up, you know, you got to move up,
         was it in the lumber grading?
         
         PP:  Yeah, yeah, um-huh.
         
         SS:  What was the difference- at Elk River you had a low job-
         
         PP:  No, no. I didn't grade in Elk River. I started grading over here.
         And it was so- I got to be one of the top- that's why I don't
         hear any more, run one of the biggest machine they had, run 
         big board that wide and that thick-
         
         SS:  The planer? Was it in the planer?
         
         PP:  In the planer, oh, yeah. Right next to the planer there, see, grading
         it. But you know, even then, the boss  And
         once I was supposed to go up again another nickle an hour- what they
         call a replane, and he passa me up, never say nothing, and I could
         a holler, but I didn't. I thought, well, I'm okay over here, it's
         okay. So something came up two, three months afterwards and I don't
         remember just exactly what went- finally then I nail him down. I said,
         "How come you pass me up two, three months ago?" Said, "I don't know,
         why?" So, I went over to the union right away. I said- you know,
         told the union what he'd done, told the steward and right away the
         boss said, "Well, I'll fix it up." So a job came up here to another
         sawmill four miles from here, they were buying all the lumber that
         the sawmill will cut, he send me up there to check out this lumber,
         and grading it and I would get a nickel an hour more and a
         half hour overtimeA making out my tally sheet.
         
         SS:  So that's what a union does for you?
         
         PP:  That right. That's right. If the union wasn't any good how come the
         lawyer, the dentist, the undertaker, the preachers, how come they be
         long to the union?
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13566</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Otness2</previous>
      <next>Parker</next>
      <disp_name>Paolini</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
