<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">8/2/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Selina Smith Pierce, 1974-08-02 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:02:11</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Pierce, Selina Smith</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker; operated grocery store</occupation>
      <birthyear>1893</birthyear>
      <residence>Deary</residence>
      <origin>Came from New York after marriage to Albert Pierce (1920)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#boardinghouses"&gt;boardinghouses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Texas Ridge"&gt;Texas Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13571</file_name>
      <mp3>13572.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13572.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Getting married in New York and moving to Texas Ridge; buying the grocery store in
               Deary; didn't like farming
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Married her husband in New York and they came out to his farm on Texas Ridge after
               a few years. Bought the
               grocery store in Deary after a year. The switch to a farm was terrible. Didn't like
               the custom of feeding
               neighbors during threshing. Farming: hard work and
               earned nothing.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>420</time>
            <title>Buying out grocery store and dry goods; testing cream for Hazelwood Dairy</title>
            <synopsis>Bought out grocery store and added dry goods. Tested
               cream for Hazelwood Dairy. Store not too much of a
               paying proposition.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Reasons why the fire may have been set; almost didn't save her son; fire burning buildings
               in Deary; getting carried out by Mr. Wade
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Reasons why she felt the fire was set. Went outside to
               help put out the fire and had a hard time to get back
               in to save her son. The fire burned down 8 buildings
               on Main Street in Deary. Stayed in too long trying to
               get some things out by the light of the fire, then the
               streamers caught fire and Mr. Wade physically carried
               her out.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Rebuilding after the fire; still has nightmares about the fire; who paid the minister's
               salary
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Owners of the store quickly rebuilt a brick building.
               The second store was smaller because they didn't have
               the money. Got shoes just before the fire. She still
               wakes up and fears she smells smoke. Church's Ladies
               Aid made the minister's salary.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Taking in teachers and telephone crew for room and board</title>
            <synopsis>Took teachers to board in their new house for $30 per
               month. Men more easily pleased than women. Boarded
               telephone crew in summer.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Other businesses in Deary and what she saved during the fire</title>
            <synopsis>Recalls other businesses on Main Street: Sam Anderson's
               grocery, Gorey Drug Store, Mrs. Devoine's confectionery
               store, Curtis Hardware, Buren grocery. Eight buildings
               burned. During the fire she saved worthless things and
               forgot the valuables.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Curtis and Evoine selling out; Deary not recovering from the fire</title>
            <synopsis>Curtis and Devoine sell out. The town didn't recover from
               the fire. In the fire she busted the door to the store
               down with a chair.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Raising strawberries and selling them in Moscow; first store to sell produce; other
               products that they sold
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Raised strawberries out on Texas Ridge and sold them
               in Moscow. Their orders for the grocery store were
               shipped down from Spokane and men came through to pick
               up their orders. They were the first store to sell
               produce. Had smoked meat and whole cheese that they
               cut up.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3420</time>
            <title>Credit can be bad for business; Lou Wells funeral in Moscow</title>
            <synopsis>Credit kills a person. When burnt out many people
               didn't pay their bills. Albert's sister refused credit
               to someone who owed quite a bit. Her husband wouldn't
               refuse anybody. Went to Lou Wells' funeral in Moscow.
               Mary King belonged to Ladies Aid and was one of us.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Town fire (1923). Problems of running store. Dislike of farm living. Boarding
         people. 8-2-74 1 hr LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13284_lcoh_13284.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13571</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Pierce_Albert</previous>
      <next>Platt</next>
      <disp_name>Pierce_Selina</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
