<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">12/3/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Tom &amp; William Hickma Platt, 1974-12-03, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:33:00</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Platt, Tom</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Livestock operator</occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Genesee, Salmon River</residence>
      <origin>Father's family came from Wisonsin (1881), mother's from Kansas
         (1894)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#liveries"&gt;liveries&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rodeos"&gt;rodeos&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#railroads"&gt;railroads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moonshine"&gt;moonshine&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Salmon River"&gt;Salmon River&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13568</file_name>
      <mp3>13569.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13569.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Genesee businesses; rodeo largest community event; Sundown Jackson</title>
            <synopsis>Early day Genesee was busy with businesses. Genesee's
               three day horse show and rodeo. Sundown Jackson had
               Dave exercise his "wild" horse. Quality of the working
               stock. The rodeo attracted good riders. The biggest
               community event of the year.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>960</time>
            <title>Hickman livery barn, 1914-1915</title>
            <synopsis>Dave Hickman's father's livery barn. Because railroad
               ended at Genesee, they conveyed salesmen down to Lewiston. About 1914 his father put
               two automobiles on the line. In 1915 there was only about a mile of rock road in the
               country, and it was hard to use. He rented teams, stabled horses overnight, kept stallions
               at stud, but didn't freight. There was room for fifty head of horses in the stable,
               and fifty more in the corral.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Two towns of Genesee (old and new); Rosenstein store; winter</title>
            <synopsis>There are two towns of Genesee: the "old town" was abandoned when an effort was made
               to charge the railroad for the depot, and the road simply relocated the town. The
               Rosenstein store: Max Rosenstein cut the Chinese laundryman's clothesline. Morgan
               the telephone man had to pull his car up the hill to his house with a pair of mules
               in the winter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Native Americans traded goods in Genesee</title>
            <synopsis>With Genesee only three miles from the Nez Perce reservation
               boundary, Indians traded there, but own little land in the
               area now. (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Native Americans near Genesee; no homesteading land left in 1881</title>
            <synopsis>Indian families in the Genesee area. When the Platts came
               in 1881, there was no homestead land left. Dave's father
               came in 1889 with a ticket to the end of the railroad line.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Marketing grain; importance of horses; stage routes and railroad.</title>
            <synopsis>Problem with marketing grain in the early days. The change in
               climate made it possible to grow wheat on the flats starting
               in 1917. Tunneling under the snowpack across the street in
               Genesee. Driving stock from Cottonwood and Grangeville
               to Genesee, because it was the end of the line. "Tame"
               horses were shipped from Genesee for the French Cavalry.
               Importance of horses in early farming. Hay and fruit
               warehouses. Driving pigs from Lenville to Colfax. Stage
               routes un the grade from Lewiston. Going to Palouse from Genesee to the flour mill.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2880</time>
            <title>Harris was Methodist minister</title>
            <synopsis>Great-grandfather Harris, a Methodist minister, watched
               the Sunday ball games and complained.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3000</time>
            <title>Platt cattle  operation; </title>
            <synopsis>The Platt operation comprised owned and rented land around
               Genesee and homestead and range on the Salmon River. In
               1915 John Platt brought in a big stock of Hereford
               cattle from Iowa and Nebraska. ; the first in Idaho.
               The enterprise failed when the livestock investors demanded
               their money at a difficult time. Their stock built up from
               20 purebreds to over 200. Fluctuation of cattle market.
               Demand for purebred bulls was mainly in range areas.
               Genesee tied to the development of other areas, (cont.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Genesee as strategic location</title>
            <synopsis>Genesee's strategic location in early years. Specialization
               in use of horses, home delivery of purchases.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Platt cattle known as best around; Salmon River operation</title>
            <synopsis>The Platts first bought three purebred Herefords in LaGrande
               in 1896 and introduced them to the Salmon River range herd.
               At first they were laughed at because of the small size of
               the bulls, but soon they were known as the best cattle in the
               country. The Salmon River cattle operation described.
               Located due south of Winchester, it was squatter's land
               not surveyed until 1910, then homesteaded.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>Tom in charge</title>
            <synopsis>Tom got a saddle horse at five and ran the place in his
               father's absence by nine or ten.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>Purebred cattle; drowned cattle while fording</title>
            <synopsis>The purebreds were raised at Genesee, then taken down to
               the range. In early years range cattle were fed at Genesee.
               Platt^partner in the butcher shop absconded with money.
               A drowning on the Clearwater at Spalding while fording
               cattle. The family operation was a natural combination of
               resources.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4860</time>
            <title>Salmon River country had rough weather, land</title>
            <synopsis>The Salmon River was rough country. Rumors of stock
               stealing. Country too steep for a Texan. Tough winters:
               people expected to be holed up for three to five months.
               Winter diet. Pigs too much trouble to raise there.
               Homestead social life.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Effects of winter on cattle operation, hay; post WWI depression difficult</title>
            <synopsis>Private school at the Platt homestead during the winter. The
               severe winter conditions of 1919-20. A 60% shortage of
               feed forced them to drive the cattle across the frozen Salmon
               River. Hay prices went from $7 to $50 a ton, and beef
               fell from $36 to $9. Effects of that winter cold on the cattle.
               After selling off almost all of their herd, John and Bill
               Platt started up again. The post World War I Depression
               was hard on the stockman.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5460</time>
            <title>Post WWI depression prices, farmland as tax write-off</title>
            <synopsis>Farmers had speculated on more land with high wheat
               prices, and were caught short after the war with the
               falling market. Williamson of Moscow invested in new land
               as soon as he could borrow on his other holdings, and lost
               almost all of it. Farmland is now being bought by non-farm
               interests at inflated prices and used a s a tax write-off.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5760</time>
            <title>Settlement of Genesee; railroad</title>
            <synopsis>The Genesee area was early settled by people and groups who
               intended to stay and found more opportunity than where they'd
               come from. Speculation in towns which hoped the railroad
               would pass through them. It commonly takes three generations
               of investors in a place to realize profit; expansion of farms
               from an inherited base isn't hard.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Winter 1919 was awful; no work, low wages, bodies froze</title>
            <synopsis>During the bad winter of 1919 the cows tails and even their
               bodies froze to the ground. Wages were low after the war,
               though there was much work. Some ranch hands were not
               competent.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Turteling Brothers</title>
            <synopsis>Turteling brothers started as a one tent construction
               operation in the country and became big.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7320</time>
            <title>Driving cattle across the Salmon</title>
            <synopsis>Tom describes driving cattle across the Salmon; using
               a calf to lead the rest.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7500</time>
            <title>Local support for WWI</title>
            <synopsis>Local effort to support World War I; selling the family's
               unwanted Plymouth Rock, rooster. An Idaho company was
               early involved in the war.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7680</time>
            <title>IWW accusing; fires in Big Bend; smut explosion</title>
            <synopsis>Dave was accused of being an IWW when he complained about
               dusty conditions while thrashing. Several fires in Big
               Bend country were never solved. Quick action in a smut
               explusion. How smut grows on wheat. Headers were
               replaced because the delay before thrashing caused some
               wheat to shatter. Thrashing outfits were a big business.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8280</time>
            <title>Growing wheat good on flat and in the hills</title>
            <synopsis>Reasons for growing wheat on the flat as well as in the hills
               include the high price of wheat during the war. The climate
               has moderated; and the water table has appreciably dropped
               one reason being the intense cropping of the soil.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8640</time>
            <title>Scandinavians; anti-German pranks; moonshine</title>
            <synopsis>Scandinavian hospitality. Anti-German prank-during
               World War I. Most moonshine around Genesee was
               made for home use.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With William Hickman (cousin), Kenneth Piatt (brother) Introduction of purebred
         Herefords by Piatt brothers (1896). Livestock operation at Genesee and Salmon Rivers;
         hardship
         in winter of 1919. Salmon homesteading. Settlement of Genesee area. Horse show and
         rodeo.
         Livery business. 12-3-74 2.5 hr p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         TOM PLATT: Well, if you'd give us some idea what you're looking for or what
         you're thinking about. Kenny said something about the town.
         SAM SCHRAGER: I think your early recollections of the town would be a good
         place to start.
         DAVID HICKMAN: I was born and raised right in Genesee. Tom came there when?
         
         
         SS: Oh, I was born there, but of course, we went back to the Salmon
         River and stayed there. I never got back to stay there until
         1909 when I started to school; the fall of 1909. And I was there
         during the school term for three years and then wasn't back until
         I started high school.
         
         
         SS: Your family had a place on the Salmon, too?
         
         
         SS: Yes.
         
         
         SS: Were they ranching there?
         
         
         SS: Cattle. Dave lived there all the time. He knows a great deal
         more about it than I do.
         
         
         SS: What was this town like when you were just a kid?
         DAVID HICKMAN: Oh, every business house was filled up. Every place along
         the line had something in it. My dad ran a livery stable there
         and that was just about the east end of town as far as any business
         was concerned. But across from us was a creamery, up the line a
         little ways was a hardware store, furniture store and then just
         keep right on going through town, every place was filled up. Every
         thing was lively. There were two or three blacksmith shops. Later,
         of course, some of those turned - a couple of them turned into
         garages. But at that time they were blacksmith shops for shoeing
         
         
         
         SS:
         
         
         SS:
         horses and fixing farm equipment. I don't have any idea how many
         places there were that were actually places of business, but I can
         remember when there were a couple of grocery stores and two or
         three- two merchandise stores. Mercantile stores where they hand
         led dry goods and this type of thing. And my recollection of the
         thing that I like to remember about it is that where we lived
         down on the flat was right in the area where they had the old
         ball field at one time. And the city ball field was right close
         there. But it was also the place where the Indians came,A moved
         into town, or came in for a celebration they came down and stayed
         right down on that flat close to us. And they would go back and
         forth across there from town. Seemed like the recollections that
         I have mostly of Genesee is the old horse?shows. Three days a horse
         show every spring, and usually two days of rain, so they were always
         assured of a good crop. „Lots of big horses; lots of draft
         horses and quite a few head of Herfords and big cattle of some kind
         there that they were raising, and lots of big, old Percheron and
         Belgianshire horses. And of course, there at the livery stable
         there was always two or three stud horses that were standing there
         during the season to take care of the mares. But I can remember
         especially those horse shows because you were always assured of
         at least two days of rain out of the three, was in June.
         It sounds like it was a three day affair and that was quite a big
         celebration for the town. Is that right?
         Well, yes, it was three days of the horse show and rodeo. It was
         a horse show and rodeo combined. And I can remember one time of
         Old Sundown Jackson, Nez Perce Indian that was world^ champion rider
         being there at the fair and I was just a kid around the livery
         stable, but he gave me the job of excersiSing his horse for him.
         And I took the horse out for a little ride in the morning then
         that afternoon he would take the horse and " him down and put
         a hackamore on him and throw the saddle on him and that thing would
         just buck and bawl till you would think he was an outlaw, but he
         was just as tame as could be if he wanted him (to be) and then af
         ter it was all over he'd put the saddle back on him and away they'd
         go again.
         
         
         SS: Do you remember the horse shows, too?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes.
         
         
         SS: I'd like for you guys to describe some more about what it was like
         and what they did there and just what the celebration was. Were
         they local stock horses?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes, I think most of it was local stock. I think most of the
         farmers had good stock and this stock was bred to good stallions
         that were kept around there locally.
         As I remember it, it was simply a showing of horses, not so
         much saddle horses, although there were some saddle horses, but
         mostly draft horses with a few cattle. And the prizes, I don't
         have any idea now what the prizes were that were offered, but I
         suppose they weren't very much in cash now compared to what they
         would have now.
         
         
         SS: Was this a Genesee specialty?
         
         
         SS: Yes.
         
         
         SS: It wasn't something that they did all over?
         
         
         SS: Oh, no, it was a one year thing and as far as I know, Genesee's
         horse show was Genesee's.
         
         
         SS: And I doubt if anyboelyfurther away than Colton came down, or ever
         got in there, did they?
         
         
         SS: I don*t suppose. Not many people would get to it, anyway.
         
         
         SS: Didn't have any trucks in those days. (Chuckles)
         
         
         SS: Did a lot of folks come in from the country for those days and stay
         in town?
         
         
         SS: Oh, they had real big crowds, as I remember it 
         
         
         SS: Yeah, the Indians would come up from the Reservation and stay down
         there on the flats and of course, they took part in the rodeo and
         also in the fair.
         
         
         SS: They were quite a piece of the parade, too. There was quite a stfxic*
         parade, all these horses and stock and cowboys and 
         
         
         SS: A little different than-
         
         
         SS: Community Day now? That they have.
         Oh, yes.
         Community Day is just something for people to come back to and get
         acquainted again where this was strictly a stock show. They were
         showing horses, that's all there was.
         
         
         SS: What about the other livestock?
         
         
         SS: I remember some cattle, but I don't remember very many cattle and
         I think it was mostly horses.
         
         
         SS: Paraded a few herfords and a few shorthorns, you might say that
         was about it, I don't remember any dairy cattle ever being in it.
         
         
         SS: What about the horses that were show horses? Were there certain
         guys that had certain kind of horses that they used? And other
         guys had other kinds?
         
         
         SS: I think this is right; some farmers just prided themselves on their
         livestock that they had and it was mostly working stock, that is,
         they worked them on the ranch, they had some mares that they
         kept for breeding stock. Some of the farmers, of course, just used
         mixtures of cayuse and Morgan, and Belgian or anything they could
         get hold of. But these things that were shown on horse show day
         were good stock. Probably all had IDrbbons on rem.
         
         
         SS: I would imagine that all the stallions that came up the street
         were registered.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes, I'm sure they were.
         
         
         SS: And they were real good animals. They were, I suppose you'd say,
         a good deal more proud of those animals that they worked those days
         than the farmer out here today is of his D6 or whatever he happens
         to have.
         
         
         SS: Some of those fellows were pretty proud of their livestock and the
         ancestry and the breeding and so forth that they had mixed up in
         'em.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes. And they knew about it, too.
         
         
         SS: Were there breeds of horses that were agreed on as being the best
         for work horses? Were there any outstanding?
         
         
         SS: I think you run into the same thing that you do with beef cattle
         or dairy cattle now; the individual. A man^likes a certain indivi
         dual type of animal will treat it better and he'll get along better
         with it, and naturally, he likes it better. One man may like a
         Shire and another man a Percheron.
         
         
         SS: Percherons, Belgians, Shires, Morgans.
         Oh, any number of lem. Of course, the Morgan was more or less of
         a coach horse that was introduced in order to make better driving^
         Lighter horses. But as Tom says, the Shires and the Belgians this
         type of thing, the Percherons were the ones that they really liked.
         
         
         SS: Did they race at all, in the horse show? Were there races?
         
         
         SS: I don't remember anything, except maybe there was saddle horse
         races.
         
         
         SS: If there were, it was in conjunction with the rodeo. First time
         I said something about it, I was talking about the old flat down
         where we lived, then when these horse shows were on they were
         on a flat closer to town on the south side of town, the same place
         now that they have the ball field today. And this is where they
         used to have their rodeos.
         
         
         SS: Was the rodeo anything like it is today? With the roping and- ?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes.
         
         
         SS: It's about the same thing except that they didn't saddle in the
         chutes, they saddled out on the grounds.
         
         
         SS: Geared 'em down and a couple of guys snubbed 'em up. And 
         Kenned Did they have bulldogging?
         
         
         SS: Well, we didn't at that rodeo that I remember. Rode some steers.
         
         
         SS: Wild horses, and broncs and that stuff?
         
         
         SS: I don't remember 'em turning loose wild horses to be roped out
         there on the grounds.
         
         
         SS: No, I don't either. But they had lots of things going on all the
         time. It wasn't a three ring circus like they have now with all
         the things going on, but they attracted some good people. For in
         stance this Sundown Jackson was the world's champion in that Pendleton,
         and it was a good enough show that he was attracted, now whe
         ther it was the prizes or whether it was close to home, I don't know
         which, but he was there and riding.
         
         
         SS: There were other good riders there.
         
         
         SS: Pruitt. J£~Wo*
         
         
         SS: Yeah, Pruitt was up there,and White. Bills and Weeks and I don't
         know who else,
         (few lines obliterated by the popping of the fire in the fireplace)
         SS
         
         
         SS:
         
         
         SS:
         
         
         SS:
         SS
         
         
         SS:
         These were all guys that were in the rodeo?
         Yes.
         Did you say that this was the greatest event of the year?
         Oh, yes, there is no question about it, because it was the only
         real event that they had at that time. And, as Tom says, the In
         dians made up a good share of the show because they were in the
         parades, taking part, and then they took part in the rodeo, too,
         some of 'em. The ones that wanted to.
         Could you describe about your father's livery and blacksmithing
         operation there? What he did? What you remember.
         Well, he had a livery stable, but not blacksmithing, no. There
         were at least two blacksmiths in town at the time, but he didn't
         have one.
         The earliest memory I have of it was probably after it was
         going downhill a little bit because I only remember him having about
         twelve or fourteen horses} Six teams or seven teams.
         And they had teams that were hired out for people to drive and
         then other teams that they furnished drivers with. At one time,
         this was in the early days, Genesee was the end of the railroad
         long before the railroad got into Moscow, and so anyone wanting to
         go to Lewiston came to Genesee and worked the town there, the drygoods
         part of it, the drygoods salesmen, and then they took *"
         hack and went from there on down to Lewiston. And this was the
         regular run every so often for the livery stable to take two or
         three drummers down to Lewiston with their suitcases and sample
         bags and so forth. And it was only about twenty miles, so this
         wasn't so awfully to travel. And later, oh, about 1914, '15,
         somewhere along there Dad bought a couple of automobiles. A 1912
         Velie and a 1913 Reo. Ran a taxi service then for the next
         three or four years. And I'm not just sure which year it was or
         where it comes in, but, oh, about 1917, '18, somewhere along about
         wartime, why then, Dad went to work for Tom and Kenny's Dad. And then he farmed for
         them for a couple years and
         then went out on his own later and bought a farming outfit. But
         that was the end of the livery stable, about the first of the World
         War.
         
         
         SS: Do you think that it had to do with the change over to automobiles
         that made him decide to 
         
         
         SS: I am sure this was part of it. Of course, at that time there was-
         In the early days there were no roads. There still weren't any
         roads in 1915, '16; they were still all dirt roads, except that one
         stretch of road east of Genesee which had been put in somewhere
         around 1910, probably. They put in a mile or a little over of
         rock road there, and this was the only rock road in the country,
         the rest of it was all dirt. So automobiles weren't very popular
         in the wintertime for quite sometime. And eventually they could
         get graveled roads in the country.
         
         
         SS: Would you happen to knowNv thevj streets in Genesee before they
         rocked that road, which came first?
         
         
         SS: I don't know. I always thought that the road out there by the old
         east end warehouse was one of the first ones put in. It was put
         in on that Tory ranch.
         
         
         SS: I'm sure it was the first road, outside of town, but I just kind
         of wondered whether they rocked Main Street there before they
         rocked that.
         
         
         SS: Your dad, Kenny, talks about that in his book. Do you remember
         what the reference was?
         I remember reading part of that; one of the references he said
         was^tney built it out of such heavy rock, just very little crush
         ing if any, to it that the farmers when they came in they'd drive
         on the side of the road instead of driving on top of the rock.
         They stayed off of it until it finally got enough dirt mixed in
         it that the rock didn't stick up quite so bad. I don't know
         whether he gives the date in there when this was built or not.
         
         
         SS: Let me just ask you how they used the teams for taking the sales
         men- Did he freight very much, was that part of the livery business?
         
         
         SS: No.
         
         
         SS: Did he always rent teams?
         
         
         SS: Just rented teams or horses coming in, of course, to be stabled
         over a day or a night or for a meal or two or whatever part that
         people wanted to stay. This way, there were always some animals
         in fed and to keep a few stallions, this type of thing, were
         always kept there the year around. But there was no freight, no
         actual hauling out of there.
         
         
         SS: Did farmers rent teams to do their farm work, or was that taken
         care of by their own teams?
         
         
         SS: They owned their own horses. And mostly the renting of the teams
         was to people from town or drummers traveling through.
         "JAP: Do you have any recollection of how many horses there were in the
         A
         stable at the time?
         
         
         SS: I'd have to make an awful guess. I suppose in the neighborhood of
         forty-five, fifty head they could put up inside the barn without-
         And there was quite a corral there,
         Would
         too, put mangers around the outside; I imagine he could have put
         up 100 head or horses there without stretching things too far,
         KP: Did he take over that stuff from 
         
         
         SS: He bought Shelton out.
         KP: Pop mentions housing a comany of cavalry there one time.J always
         it was that stable.
         
         
         SS: It was before my time then, because that would i to have beenwell,
         I don't know the time it would have been- I was going to
         say, that probably was when the fort was still there, or was this
         militia there?
         KP: It was when he was a boy.
         
         
         SS: Would have been a little while before my time.
         
         
         SS: When he was a boy it was Old Town, anyway.
         
         
         SS: Yeah.
         
         
         SS: ^Genesee as it's known today.
         
         
         SS: What do you mean? That was the oldest town?
         4fa: There was two Genesees. Genesee originally was on the corner out
         beyond the east end of the warehouse, if you're acquainted in
         Genesee at all. And it went around thatcorner and over toward
         the cemetery, and it was on both sides of the road. Then when the
         railroad built in there, somebody tried to hold em up and instead
         of coming on clear into what was the town at that time, they stopped
         where Genesee is now and said, "Build your town over here." So
         this is what happened.
         
         
         SS: How much of that town had to be moved then? Was there much there
         at the time the railroad came in?
         0ft: I don't think they moved very much of it. They just built a new
         town. NThere was a stage stop and a couple of stores out there.
         Levi's. I think it just mostly just went a block out there and
         t—
         they just left it. I don't think they ever moved very much of it
         into town.
         
         
         SS: Was there still much trace when you were there; the old town?
         ypft: Oh, yes.
         There must have been close to a dozen buildings out there when we
         were kids.
         Now it's all farmland. AThey're all gone now, there's nothing there,
         
         
         SS: And the story that I read that Vo^Lmer said that it was Jake Rosen
         stein was holding up that railroad. That is what Volmer said.
         
         
         SS: Well, this could be. There's one name that I keep kicking around,
         and I don't know where he fits in, but this Levi had a store at
         one time there in the early days, and of course, Rosenstein had a
         store in rtw , and then after him, his son, Mttc Rosenstein
         ran a store there until they finally went out of business.
         
         
         SS: Do you remember what the Rosenstein store was like? It was a drygoods
         store there in Genesee.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes. It was quite a store, had a little of everything in it
         and they were good people to run a store. They wouldn't let you
         get out without buying something .J* You came in there to buy some
         thing, you're just about going to buy it! The only thing I re
         member much about the Rosensteins was that there were two girls,
         as far as I know they're still alive.
         
         
         SS: No, one of 'em died about six or eight months ago in Los Angeles.
         
         
         SS: Oh, is that right?
         
         
         SS: No, wait a minute now, I'm thinking of
         
         
         SS: And they were Jewish?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes.
         
         
         SS: Did he take a very active part in the community? The community
         life?
         
         
         SS: I just don't remember.
         
         I remember my Dad 3 in that book about Max 4uttmg the
         Chinaman's clothesline down. (Chuckles)
         
         
         SS: Max did what?
         
         
         SS: Chinaman's clothesline down. Had a Chinese laundry and Max cut the
         clothesline. And got caught at it.
         
         
         SS: I don't remember that they had any active part in the affairs of
         the town at all, even who was the mayor or the council or anything
         else in those days.
         Well, my dad,,for a while after he quit the stable was street
         A
         man and policeman and water superintendent and everything I suppose
         a jobjjat the present time takes about two or three people to
         do the same thing. But in those days that's all there was to it.
         One of the things I remember a long time back is a fellow named
         Morgan who was head of the telephone company and he lived way up
         on the north hill, and he would drive in with this old car of his,
         and I don't remember what make it was, two or three cylin
         der car; two cylinder maybe, and he'd get just about fifty yards
         up this first hill, if it was the least bit slick, why, that's as
         far as he ever went. And then he'd go home and get a pair of mules
         and take the car on home.
         Now, I don't know why at that time he always went up that
         hillVby the old HermannFurniture store, but now there's a pretty
         good road up the draw, where he could have gone, or looks like
         he could have gone. Maybe in those days it would have bogged him
         down, too, maybe it would have been so wet he couldn't got through.
         
         
         SS: Do you remember about when that telephone came into Genesee? I
         don't really mean the year, but were you kids at the time that tele
         phone service came in?
         it was there as long as I can remember.A Dad had his phone there
         in the barn, so it had to have been in there after 1910, '12,
         somewhere along'there that they put it in. The farmers had it, I
         guess, in the country, although I can't remember anything about
         the service or anything like that. Maybe it's like they tell about
         the old phones that were hooked up on the barbed wire fences,
         because they had lots of barbed wire fences.
         See, Genesee is only three miles actually from the Nez Perce
         Indian Reservation, the north boundary of the reservation,
         although it's all practically owned now by white men. There's no
         Indian land left at all that I know of, although there probably
         is some. But, at that time they traveled back and forth to Gene
         see right along to do some of their trading.
         
         
         SS: He has all that stuff that Gamble's used to have in there and
         had and Sweeney's.
         
         
         SS: What do you guys remember about any particular Indians that you
         knew when you were young?
         I can remember going with that uncle of mine, Eli Eichman at
         Spalding. One old Indian up there that he was quite good friends
         with, and that was Pio Ptalek but outside of Sundown Jack
         son or some of those fellows, I really didn't can't remember any
         names.
         
         
         SS: Did you know any of the Indians?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes, there were a number of Indian kids in school there when
         I went to high school. And then this one family that moved in
         each fall to send the kids to school, they lived on their own ranch
         up there. And there was one boy that stayed with them one winter
         is
         
         Presbyterian minister now, him real well. Who was it we went
         to see, Kenny, at Spalding? Oh, yeah, Dan Arthur and his kids.
         J$: I remember the Arthurs.
         
         
         SS: When you were young there were still a number of Indians around
         Genesee?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes. Lots of them further down on the Reservation. When I
         worked for Neil Sweeney that eighty^belonged to an Indian named
         Cook, and he used to farm it and come up and work on threshing
         machines there. Apparently he sold that or something, I don't
         know what.
         KP: -^scattered pieces of land, in that Of course, you have to remember-when we were
         kids there was some
         one living on every eighty acres or every 160 at least. Now,
         there's someone living on every half section, probably or maybe
         even not that much. Average size farm is 
         
         
         SS: Was this land originally part of the reservation before- what lar
         gely happened that Indians sold the land?
         
         
         SS: No. The land right around Genesee, well, the land that we still
         have there, the Hickman family, still has was Piatt brothers at
         one time, or was Piatt's. It was homesteaded by a man named Hanson
         and then it was bought by Platts. Our grandfather. And then this
         is the land that we still have there, but you'd have to go about
         two miles or two and a half miles south before you'd get into the
         reservation, but the land right around Genesee was all homesteaded.
         The story is that our folks came here in, I believe '79-
         
         
         SS: '81.
         "tt: '81? Well, that's when Mother was born, wasi in '81? But
         and went to school there, Dave Miles, who was a teacher and a
         at that time the land around Genesee was all taken up, so they had
         to buy land. They could have come on farther up toward Moscow
         Mountain and got land, but around Genesee it was all taken up at
         that time.
         
         
         SS: Do you have any idea why they picked that place? Why Genesee?
         
         
         SS: Well, the story wasAthey came to Uniontown and stayed with a sis
         ter, wasn't that it? Granddad's sister, stayed over winter with
         them, and they were about five or six miles south of Uniontown.
         Apparently they had in mind coming to this Genesee Valley all the
         time, because^the next year they moved on up into the Genesee
         Valley. And the way I understand it, they lived out on the old
         Perkins place for some time, and then finally bought this place
         from Hanson; still have it.. My dad didn't come there till
         '89, and he came from North Carolina and just bought him a ticket
         to the end of the railroad and that was the end of the railroad.
         So, that's how he landed there.
         
         
         SS: Do you know how he started in?
         
         
         SS: Well, he started in working on orchards down in the Snake River
         and worked on a ranch there for a year or two before he finally
         bought in- bought this livery stable. But he worked there a lit
         tle while, anyway, on some of these farms.
         
         
         SS: When Mr. Piatt came in '81; do you know how developed the land
         was? Was it very much under the plow already? Was there much of
         it producing crops?
         I would doubt that. They had no great place to send a crop. No
         way to get rid of it. They had to send it to Walla Walla, they
         had to feed it, if they had the grain they had to feed it to the
         pigs and drive the pigs somewhere. And hay, they had to feed the
         
         cattle or horses or something of that sort. And there is another
         factor in there, there's been a big climate change, because it
         was years before they could raise wheat on Genesee Flats.
         
         
         SS: 1917. The first war is when it started.
         ^P: Before that, at the time we're talking about in the 18^0's those
         flats were in timothy and clover, hay. Course, there was a big
         demand for hay then; all this work was horses, all transportation
         was horses.^ So, the whole climate has changed, and we have some
         pictures around someplace, one of them is with your dad and it's
         taken in front of Follett's store and you can just see his head
         over the snowbanks where they shoveled snow off.
         That was in 1912 or '13, wasn't it?
         Tunnelled through in order to get from one side of the street to
         the other.
         
         
         SS: I don't know, there's been a tremendous change.
         
         
         SS: So stock was much more important in the early days than it was
         after the war?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes. And it continued to be important for a long time because
         they drove stock from over around Grangeville, even drove hogs
         from over in there; Cottonwood and Grangeville to Genesee because
         Genesee was the end of the railroad. The only place they could go,
         that's what made Genesee for a long time.
         W: During the war they came in there with horses for the French Cava
         lry, before we got mixed up in the war. And they brought those.
         Salmon River and Grangeville and over in that country; brought
         them across the Indian Reservation and probably picked up a pony
         or two as they came along. Anyway, they sold them out then toand
         the idea there was that they had to ride 'em through the gates
         in order to show that they were broken. Some of 'em hadn't even
         had a saddle on 'em before, but they rode 'em through the gate, any-
         Away. I can remember that.
         
         
         SS: Who raised the horses?
         
         
         SS: They came off of Salmon River, I'm not sure where the horses
         came from in the first place, but they came off of the Salmon River
         breaks down there someplace. Somebody was in the horse business.
         
         
         SS: Just about everybody over there had a few horses.
         
         
         SS: That's funny, because I'm thinking that it was so completely farming
         country; you don't think of it much as being horse country.
         fj$: Yes, but if every farmland, or every piece of land, say 160 acres
         had to have- well, we had eight or ten horses there when we farmed
         that 160 there at home, 170 acres, and if every piece of land had
         that many horses, there was an enormous amount of that land that
         was going right back into feed-.and, grain to feed those horses.
         Well, take Hampton and Driscoll out there with theAbig outfits
         they had, and they had a bunch of mules-
         
         
         SS: Thirty, forty mules 
         I don't know how many mules they would have to farm a layout like
         they had, but ~ was a good many of 'em. Took seven horses,
         usually, on a gangplow, two-bottom plow, and now they start out
         with a six or eight-bottom plow behind one cf these tractors.
         
         
         SS: What about the marketing problems? Do you remember much about
         what that was like, or what they used to say it was like, in the
         early days?
         : Well, when you got the point where you had transportation and
         could sell grain and stuff like that for cash it was the same as
         it is today, as far as I know. And of course, the big packing
         companies were not long in establishing packing houses in Spokane
         
         and Seattle. Cudahy and 
         
         
         SS: And you can remember, Tom, when they had the hay warehouse there
         at Genesee?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes, sure.
         
         
         SS: Had apple packing house there. One time, I don't remember it,
         necessarily, but they must have had prune dryers, because there
         were prune orchards scattered all over that area.
         Did the Genesee slaughterhouse slaughter for outshipments, or just
         local? That was still operating.
         
         
         SS: In my time old Wi WL and Raders and so forth, they were just
         doing their own butchering or butchering for people, local people,
         I don ft know that they were hutching for anybody out of town at
         all.
         
         
         SS: I was thinking more about the time before 1900, when you were saying
         that there wasn't much of a market. I would imagine it would be
         a lot more difficult.
         Now, Tom mentioned driving pigs. Now, I can't imagine driving pigs
         but this was one of Mildred's dad's stories that he used to tell;
         how they used to raise pigs out here in this Lenville country
         where they lived, the Armstrongs, and then when they got 'em ready
         for market they'd drive them to Colfax, across country. Well, I
         
         imagine driving pigs. (Chuckles) KIt don't seem possible,
         but I guess they did it!
         I know my dad said the first time he saw Obergs, they were coming
         the with a drive of pigs.
         
         
         SS: What was it like down to Lewiston? From Genesee, in the early days?
         
         
         SS: What was it like to get down?
         
         
         SS: Was that grade pretty tough?
         
         
         SS: Well, the grade's been improved time after time, but the old cen^
         tral grade, and there was a grade that came up through by Archibalds,
         came that central grade and then the old Uniontown grade
         was- they've been there, well, I guess ever since there were peo
         ple up on these hills. Just here a while back they made this
         Collins place a historical site, the house and the granery. And
         that was right on the old stage road. And then, of course, there
         was another stage road that came out of Lewiston and came up through
         Genesee, when Genesee was down at the old town, and went right on
         through past the fort and came up through Moscow and Farmington.
         I believe Farmington was the end of the route, and then they turned
         around there; went on back.
         
         
         SS: If you were trading, would you be more likely to trade in Lewiston
         or Moscow in Genesee?
         
         
         SS: I don't know, I would suspect that at that time you would be
         apt to stay in Genesee, because I think they had the transportation
         and the goods in the stores.
         
         
         SS: I was thinking of if you had to go to a bigger town, which was the
         town that Genesee would feel closer to?
         
         
         SS: Gee, I don't know.
         
         
         SS: I would imagine Lewiston, because Lewiston in those days was what
         A.
         they called the seaport. They were bringing boats in there in
         the early days. In fact, they tell the story that when they were
         building, later, building that railroad up the river, Orofino up
         in there, one railroad ran a boat with a high mast up there
         A
         and put in drawbridges all the way to Kooskia, while the other
         railroad was building in there, so that whole area is drawbridges.
         They knocked the bottom out of the boat every time they went up
         and back.A I don't know but Tom says they were pretty well selfsupporting,
         but I've heard old-timers tell, and Mildred's Dad
         was one of 'em, about going to Palouse to get their flour ground
         because there was a flour mill at Palouse. Of course, I imagine
         there was a flour mill maybe in Colfax or maybe Lewiston and some
         of these other towns all this time, too.
         So they had to go that far?
         Go over one day get their wheat ground and then lay over a day
         and then bring it home the next day. Or just trade it for wheat,
         I don't know which they would do.
         That's pretty interesting, because I know that people in the
         end of the county went to Palouse, but I had no idea that
         the draw was so big, getting people all the way down to Genesee.
         Did you guys know your Grandfather Piatt? Was he still alive?
         Oh, yes, yes.
         What do you remember about him?
         I remember great grandfather Harris. But mostly what I can
         remember about him was the old corncake that he used to smoke in
         that pipe of his. remember him better than Grandpa Piatt, he was in that little house
         back of the churcl^when I lived
         with Grandma and went to school there. I used to go over there
         quite a bit, and he came over.
         Well, Grandpa Piatt apparently was quite a public minded citizen,
         because he was mixed up in quite a few things ^helpingjthe community.
         But this great grandfather we talked about,^he was an old minister,
         Methodist minister, and retired at the time Tom and I knew him.
         But he married my dad and mother in '98, and^was retired, of course,
         when I knew him. But he used to come down every Sunday, or almost
         
         every Sunday and have dinner with us down at the house and sit
         on the back porch and watch the ballgame and smoke his corn
         cob pipe and give the folks the fits for playing ball on Sunday!
         But he didn't miss a day anyway to come down.
         
         
         SS: He had been in Genesee as minister in the early days?
         He was a minister at Leland when he married Dad and Mother. He
         came from England. But, I don't know that he ever was a minister
         in Genesee.
         P: Well, he didn't come even until after Grandpa and Grandma were set
         tled there.
         H2H: No, that's right. He wasn't one of the real early ones. He came
         later anyway.
         
         
         SS: What do you remember about the farm when you were a kid growing up
         there? Did your father have a big operation? 
         
         
         SS: Well, pretty sizeable one, yes. Well, he had one big ranch and
         a little bit of cattle.
         
         
         SS: They farmed that ranch there in town, 170 acres or so, then they
         rented a little more around there and then they had 700 acres out
         on that Follett place plus the canyon, which was another 700 acres
         or so. That all was farmed with horses. And besides Tom's folks
         there, Tom and Kenny's folks both, had at least 200 head of pure
         bred herefords, that were kept there on the place in town. I say
         they were kept there, later when they got the Follett place they
         were run in the canyons, too, some of 'em.
         
         
         SS: Do you know about when they started bringing in the purebred stock?
         1ft: I would think it was in the spring of 1915, wasn't it? Either '14
         or '15. It was just before the start of the war, I imagine. And
         suspect that he brought the first Hereford cattle to Idaho. amy others,
         
         
         SS: What do you know about how he brought them in? Where he got them
         and how he got them here?
         He got them in Iowa and Nebraska. Just went back there and picked
         out what he wanted - I guess I should put it another way, picked
         out he could afford and shipped them out here.
         
         
         SS: And later some of them came from Kansas City when they took
         a bunch of stock back to that show back there and came back with
         a bigger carload than they took back in the first place.
         "Jfp: He went back there at a time when he was getting so many calls
         for bulls that he couldn't begin to supply it and went back there
         and bought a carload of young bulls and shipped out here. And
         brought Archie Cane along with him.
         
         
         SS: Archie Cane?
         
         
         SS: He was the herdsman for sometime.
         
         
         SS: By that time they were putting out a showherd and they needed a
         herdsman.
         
         
         SS: Do you know what made your father decide to go from his earlier
         operation to purebred?
         No, I don't, really. Maybe just wandered into it. Probably seemed
         like a good investment at the time,and I guess probably it was..
         
         
         SS: They always told me, both John and Bill, two brothers, that they
         owed about $125,000 to an outfit that was investing in livestock.
         It was a livestock organization that loaned money and they had of
         fered to pay it up time and again, but this outfit was never in
         terested in being paid up, it was just a good investment for them
         to leave it there and take the interest on it. Well, then when
         things began to get tough and they really got^to the place where
         the boys were getting pinched a bit, why then this outfit stepped
         in and said, "We have to have our money." And when they did that
         was practically the end of it. I can remember purebred Herefords
         being sold for- heifers being sold- for $32 a head, right at the
         end of the Depression, or right at the start of the Depression.
         Of course, they certainly couldn't come out with anything like that.
         ss. At the beginning of the purebed operation, how many did he start
         with? Do you know? About what size it was?
         
         
         SS: Do you remember how many stanchions there was on each side of the
         old barn there?
         g#: No, I don't, but I would suppose twenty on each side, probably.
         
         
         SS: Was there that many?
         I know that in the winter of '17, after I got out of the hospital
         with the typhoid, I went up and helped feed them and they
         put the cows all in, and I can remember there was twelve in that
         old barn, where they built the new horse barn, and we put the rest
         of them in the stanchions on the two sides of the old barn. We
         had everything covered. That was the extent of the cow Vk*N^
         
         
         SS: Forty-five, fifty head at the most^4hen-probably.
         KP: So I would say that he brought a carload, and those were cattle
         that you tied up in a car, so probably he started with around twen
         ty-five head of cows and heifers.
         
         
         SS: But one winter there Dad and I hauled straw, and that*s practically
         the only thing we did that winter was break trail out of there to
         haul straw for horses, for bedding, and I am sure that at that
         time they had about 200 head of purebreds. So that had kept
         building up anyway where they had quite a few head.
         
         
         SS: Do you remember how many years later that would have been?
         
         
         SS: Well, that wouldn't have been
         
         
         SS: The early '20's, huh?
         
         
         SS: I wasn't going to say it was even that far along, maybe it was
         '19. But in 1921 or '22, Dad was farming the Follett place. He
         was out there, so it was before that time, so it might have been
         just about in 1920.
         
         
         SS: Did he find much demand for the stock?
         
         
         SS: For a while there.
         It's a thing that goes up and down. When cattle are high there is
         a big demand for good bulls because people are stocking up their
         cattle, When they go down people begin to sell off and your market
         begins to drop on them, too. So it's an up and down roller coaster
         sort of a thing. KI don't know how you'd get away from that.^ 6""3C^.
         
         
         SS: Do you think that his bringing in that purebred Herefords had much
         of an effect on stock growing in that area? Do you think people
         started geting a lot more interested in a good breed of cattle?
         
         
         SS: Well, there is- a stockman, if he's any good, is always looking to
         better himself. He knows that when he betters his cattle he bet
         ters himself; so, yes, I think that it had a good deal of influence.
         
         
         SS: That would be like the demand for bulls.
         
         
         SS: Yes.
         
         
         SS: Of course, you have to remember too, that these two fellows had
         11,000 head of range stock on Salmon River. It took some bulls to
         keep that outfit going. They owned that much, you see, besides
         a couple of bands of sheep.
         KP: Actually the demand for purebred bulls was not in the Genesee
         community, it was in the outlying range areas, where range cat-
         tie were. So far as I know, my father the only purebred.
         in the area. They didn t sell to other farmers around that
         area, their sales were farther away,
         out on the breaks, people that had pasture like Clearwater
         Ranch and those people had a lot of canyon
         pasture out there.
         KP: I think you could say that the whole development of Gensee related
         to other areas. And when our grandparents came there, as Dave
         has said, the land ' already * taken up, they had to buy land
         they couldn't homestead. And when my father got old enough to
         start doing stuff on his own, there was not an opportunity to go
         into farming in the Genesee area without buying land or renting'
         So grandfather sent him off to Salmon River. And for many
         A
         years there was kind of a mutual benefit relationship between
         the stock in Genesee and the^stock on the range areas-
         Genesee being the supply point- Genesee had from 1888
         on, and Lewiston didn't get it until 1898, And during that ten
         years Genesee was the jumping-off place for freighting. Not only
         for the Clearwater Valley but. on as south and east as Grangeville.
         And the salesmen that came to Genesee hired buggies and teams and
         went on off into the back country to take orders and so on. So
         that Genesee was a strategic town for many years. And because this
         was before the time of automobiles there was quite a bit of re
         finement in the use of horses.fe Dave mentioned that his dad ran
         a livery stable but he didn't do freight hauling. Well, in townj
         the local hauling was done by people in 
         was a lot of specialization in the use of horses. In those days every grocery store
         made deliveries around town and
         they would have their own cart or their own rig or else they rented
         it from a dray outfit to do their delivering for them. And this
         was big business to haul everything around to the people that
         they bought. Maybe just a little bit of groceries, but then
         whatever it was, you had to haul it. You had to deliver it in
         those days.
         : Even in time a couple of families made a living on that, right
         in Genesee.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes!
         : The Gilts, had two dray lines.
         
         
         SS: Well, everybody didn't have a pickup truck. Everybody didn't have
         a one ton or anything of the kind, so if they wanted coal or any
         thing else somebody had to haul it to them, (recorder off)
         plain fact that they couldn't get enough decent bulls.
         There were some pretty poor bulls in there. They were registered
         bulls and all that, but there just wasn't enough good ones around
         and they wanted better ones and they couldn't get 'em.
         ftp; To go back a little farther than your questioning went, Sam,
         our Grandfather and father went to a purebred Hereford bull sale
         at Pendleton, I think it was.
         
         
         SS: La Grande.
         KP: 4La Grande? And that was in '96, I think.
         
         
         SS: I believe that's right.
         KP: And bought, I think, three bulls and put them on the range at Sal
         mon River.
         And to begin with, they were the laughingstock of the range com
         munity there because they were much smaller, looked smaller, than
         the big, longlegged cattle. But the end of the second year
         when they began to have the saleable steers from those bulls, they
         found out that they weighed a good deal more than the other cattle
         So this was one of the many factors that kind of
         worked together to get my dad and his brother into the^cattle busi
         ness twenty years later. They were known as having introduced
         these bulls, had the reputation of having the best range cattle
         in the area where they operated. It was a chore to get enough good
         bulls cattle of their own to supply part of their own demand
         some other people's demands. And it made a logical combination
         of enterprises. the operation at Salmon River they had this
         family farm at Genesee, that they had to take over responsibility
         for operating because Grandfather had died in 1912. And I guess
         they rented the place out for a few years. Didn't Kraut rent
         the farming place for a while?
         
         
         SS: I don't think Kraut ever did, but Stucker had it for a year or two.
         And Post had it for a couple of years. I don't know if there was
         anybody else. Do you know of anybody else?
         £: They got back onto it in 1915, that would be about the end of it
         unless someone rented while Grand was still alive.
         
         
         SS: Do you know much aboutN Salmon River operation was set up?
         What kind of an area they had and the seasonal work situation?
         "^8$: Well, Tom would remember that better than I.
         
         
         SS: Well, it was a typical range cattle outfit and as far as this area
         is concerned was rough country; very rough. Cheat grass, bunch
         grass, not very much brush.^ They summered on the mountain.
         summered here in the meadows up here.^ Raise enough hay on
         the river to winter the cattle. And of course, it
         grass beef, They didn*t feed 'em. Easily sold to buyers from-
         oh, some of the packers in Spokane or Seattle or somewhere like
         that. SWiten fry Mooldj So |-h ,.
         KP: Cattle were ordinarily sold right on the range, 
         
         
         SS: Quite often. But those buyers like John B$ar for instance, he
         represented £ Spokane outfit. He was buying with their check
         book.
         
         
         SS: Where on the Salmon River was the operation? ?
         
         
         SS: Do you know where Winchester is?K It was about twenty miles straight
         south; due south.
         KP: It was on both sides of the river, from there to the mouth of the
         river. 
         
         
         SS: That area was heavily used by a number of ranchers in those days?
         
         
         SS: Yeah, there was lots of homesteaders in there. They were very late
         surveying, around 1909 or '10 that it was surveyed out and after
         wards, after it became surveyed the homesteaders just flocked in
         there and took it all.
         
         
         SS: Was your father's place purchased or was it homesteaded?
         
         
         SS: It was his homestead.
         10: There was some irrigated land later on this Deer Creek place,
         wasn't there?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes, there was; they used to call it twenty acres, but I questionitwenty,
         but that's what they called it. It was very produc
         tive, it had never been really cropped, you see, it was virgin
         land. Put water on alfalfa in that kind of soil and it will do
         pretty well. I don't know, he bought Wes's relinquishment on
         that, but it had never been surveyed at the time so actually he
         was the original entry on it. Couldn't say what 
         or Wesls squatter right and Wes bought his from another fellow.A No one knew
         what they were taking up or where it was. It was not according
         to the survey^ or anything like that, you just had a place there
         and you was there and in possession nobody bothered you. At that
         particular time there was lots of land, but a few years later it
         was gone. But of course, these homesteaders such steep country
         that they had no way on 160 to make a living, just spent the win
         ter and what part of the spring they couldn't find a job on the
         place and planted a garden and built a house and managed to prove
         up^then^sold it. If they couldn't sell it to one of the stockmen
         they mortgaged it to the bank and let the bank take it over. That
         was it.
         
         
         SS: What about the old Deer Creek mine there? Was it early days or
         wasn't it?
         
         
         SS: Well, the Deer Creek mine was fairly early days. The Horseman Mine
         on top of the hill-
         
         
         SS: That's the one I was talking of.
         
         
         SS: I thought maybe it was. But that came along just before the First
         World War, that they started that. But the other one was around
         1900, on down below where they had the big tunnel and where they
         put in the mill down there. I don't know, it was a typical pro
         motion. They did have considerable value in both those places,
         but it's just not concentrated enough that you can go in there
         and make it pay off. And, I don't know, with gold the price it is
         now, maybe those mines could be profitably operated, if somebody
         wanted to take a chance on how long those prices would stay up.
         
         
         SS: Did you help very much when you were a kid, on the place?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes. My dad bought me a saddle horse when I was five years
         old, and I've been punching cows ever since until here four years
         ago I had a stroke and I had to sell the ranch.
         You started riding at five then?
         I don't know how old he was when he used to ride at these rodeos.
         Thought he was making pretty good money at five dollars a head
         for riding ponies out of the chute.
         I'd like to know what it was like when you were a kid working on
         the place; what kind of work you did.
         Oh, I did about everything. Pitched a little hay, fed a few cows
         with it. About everything you do on a saddle horse.
         Did you start to do some pretty man sized work when you were just
         a kid, then?
         Well, I don't know; I used to. with my dad up the mountain, have
         to move the cattle out and he'd go off and leave me to run the
         place when I was nine, ten years old. So, I guess that was doing
         what a man does.
         You have to put the Salmon River and Genesee operations together.
         How did they fit together?
         After- the pattle operation^ setup, complement to the ex
         tent that the Genesee ranch produced the herd bulls for the range
         operation. never used thdTGenesee operation to provide feed
         for the range, that was entirely a different type of wintering.
         You're not entirely truthful there.
         Did they send some grain—?
         No. But in the beginning the beef cattle were brought to - beef
         cattle were brought from Salmon River and fed at Genesee.
         Just before they were sold?
         Yes. They were sold as fed cattle rather than grass cattle. This
         is in the beginning. Now when my grandfather was running the operation
         and my dad was just a kid helping him.
         KP: Was that some use of the hay that was made that Pop used to bale
         then?^ Baling outfit?
         I suspect he didn t bale very much.hay, I think he was in that for
         A
         a few side dollars. According to the book that I had on his opera
         tions there- I don't know whether you got that or I still got it
         down there, but there's no £latthay listed as being baled. It's
         people mostly on the breaks on the reservation.
         TRH-: I didn t remember about the cattle ever being fed there.
         
         
         SS: Yes.
         KP: This must have been very early in the operation, in the '90's.
         
         
         SS: I know part of it was when we had the butchershop. .You didn't even
         A
         know about that I suppose. Can't think of the other Dutchman's
         name, he ran off with all the- Oh, yeah, Piatt and Bomberg. And
         Piatt and Bomberg had a butchershop once- I can still remember
         -getting the books out on that butchershop operation and
         you'd be surprised how many people around Genesee owed Piatt and
         Bomberg a butcher bill that they never did pay.
         
         
         SS: That butcher shop operation was pretty much cutting out the middle
         man?
         
         
         SS: It was, but it went broke anyway. (Chuckles)
         
         
         SS: Talking about Bomberg then, what was the guy's name that drown
         down at the Clearwater, that was with Eli that time? It was a
         name something like that. I don t know that was it. He
         drown there at the railroad bridge.
         
         
         SS: I know, they used to ford that river there. I remember sitting
         on Watson's front porch and he was telling about that. But I
         don't know the name.
         SS; W^hat was it happened when this guy drowned?
         across the river and, apparently
         got in trouble and he didn't get off of him, he was still sitting
         on him and down he went. -The horse just fell down or went into a
         deep hole or something; stepped into a hole.^ It was kind of a
         dangerous ford anyway.
         £ft. As I got the story, this was a heck of a big man anyway, horse
         didn't even come up for a while.
         When you were talking about the operation and you were saying about
         how the. two tied together, raising the bulls in Genesee.
         It was short lived because of the post World War I depression,
         that there wasn't much of a story to tell, but it seemed to me a
         natural putting together of resources. Had the family farm in
         Genesee that needed to be used and was the logical place to raise
         purebred cattle because they needed a different kind of care;
         supervised breeding, to the
         range set up. And then, of course, they still had the range setup
         and they supplied the bulls andoccasionally they even weeded out
         the cows. So it made a natural combination of resources. Also,
         there was the factor that my father and uncle each^fully compe
         tent of running either end of it, they didn't need both of them
         on one so they divided forces for that. So it was a natural^enterprlse.
         from 
         
         
         SS: Was that pretty wild country when you were growing up there, the
         Salmon River? I've heard some more West kind of tales from
         North Idaho coming out of that country.
         
         
         SS: Most of that sort of thing is made up, but it wasn't all made
         up.  a rough country in there; real steep, you don t go any-
         where much without a saddle horse, it's too hard walking, and
         there's no other way. You can fly over it with an airplane but
         you can't land one there.
         
         
         SS: Are there any incidents, the stories that they told?
         
         
         SS: Oh, there were rough times there. There were sheepmen killed
         eveM
         and horse thieves hung and one thing and another. I knew a man
         he had a scar that ran right across there,
         Monv ' :he said a rancher caught him stealing a horse
         one time and that's where a .30-30 creased him! He didn't get
         away with the horse.
         KP: We used to hear allegations of cattle rustling and horse thieving
         and so on I don't know how much of it was ever true. It's
         one thing to miss a cow or a steer and another thing to find it
         in somebody else's possession. There was some of that went on.
         
         
         SS: Well, I've heard the stories, too about that country; somebody
         said one time about a cowboy coming up there from Texas or down
         in that country and after about a month or so 0J6 that Salmon
         River country he was all through with the idea that land so steep
         that a cow couldn't even stay on the sidehill. That wasn't his
         idea of a place to ride or herd cows. Find someplace else to
         herd. I guess this happened, too, quite regular,^Tom, that in
         a bad winter they'd slip off the hillsides.
         
         
         SS: Oh, you bet, a cow or a horse'11 slide.in that country. And you
         go in there now in some of those places I used to trot and run a
         saddle horse down, I wouldn't run nothin' down there now. You
         couldn't pay me enough to run a saddle horse down some of those
         hills.
         
         
         SS: Did you get snowed in there for months at a time in the winter?
         
         
         SS: Sometimes.
         
         
         SS: See, they had to come over the hill by the forest and come out
         over the top of the Craig Mountain in order to get out of there.
         
         
         SS: At that time you could figure on about five feet of snow on
         Craig Mountain _ Unless there was a good deal of travel through
         that kept the trail packed, you could get into a lot of trouble.
         You could even then because if it happened to warm up and^ thaw
         slide off the trail and get bogged down in the snow on the other
         side. And there were years when they had lots more snow than
         that. I don't know if you'd remember, Kenneth, but remember where
         the shop was at the Yates place in the mountains there?. Maybe
         you remember there were some black pine trees there. Well, there
         used to be a lot more of those I guess, but there was three or
         four stumps out in there and you take a horse about
         size and ride out there and just reach over and lay your hand on
         top of the stumps. Yateses got caught there one winter and that's
         where they sawed the trees down on top of the snow for wood, right
         there, it was just about seven feet of snow.
         The answer to your question, Sam, is that people who lived down
         in the bottom of the Salmon River Canyon ordinarily packed in
         their winter's supplies in the fall and they expected to be 
         up for from three to five months. 
         
         
         SS: Do you remember pretty much what you lived on in the way of food?
         During the winter there.
         
         
         SS: Oh, I suppose I do. We usually had plenty of home grown spuds
         and quite a lot of canned vegetables; bought some in cans. I
         guess mostly what anybody else would live on.
         $ft: Had your own bacon, and beef. Had hogs, too.
         
         
         SS: No, we didn't raise hogs there. It wasn't very successful. That
         packing grain fourteen miles on a pack horse to raise hogs! It
         didn't work either way. In 1919 there was a lot of grain over on
         Dumac there and Billjhe bought a whole bunch of this wheat over
         there and then bought feeder pigs and took 'em in and along in the
         wintertime they got ready for market so he started to drive them
         out to Grangeville and drove them up to Whitebird and got over the
         hill down towards Toto Lake there and got 'em into a barn overnight
         and when they went out the next morning, it was zero weather, the
         damn pigs was all piled in one corner and only the ones on top was
         alive! So it wasn't a paying proposition.
         KP: My recollection of what we ate includes lots of beans and rice and
         macaroni, almost all kinds of dried fruits. We had relatives in
         California and we'd send there and get raisins and dried prunes
         in wholesale lots. The bacon we bought in whole sides, of course.
         And I suppose there was some salt pork and that sort of thing, too,
         wasn't there Tom? Lots of cured and dried stuff that we packed
         and kept without a storage problem.
         
         
         SS: There was no refrigeration in those days. People that lived where
         they could cut ice of course had iceboxes, but out on a lone ranch
         there was not much chance of that. So you had to buy things that
         could be stored.
         
         
         SS: What about the neighbors around you when you were on the ranch
         there? Did you see other people much in the winter?
         
         
         SS: Oh, occasionally there was dances and one thing and another
         through the winter. Kind of got 'em together. I suppose by today's
         standard, you. didn t see very much of each other, really.
         1$: How far did Harry live from us?
         
         
         SS: Five miles.
         By saddle horse.
         Was he a close neighbor?
         Well, no, we had one neighbor a mile away. As as long as Ross was
         .there, but he proved up and moved right out. We had one a mile
         away in each direction then.
         Well, I guess, Tonu during the - say from about 1910 to '15
         when the homesteads were being mostly being taken up and the
         country was mostly being filled up with young people, we had 
         housewarmings and weddings and that sort of thing. Didn't take
         too much of an excuse to get people to go somewhere.
         
         
         SS: No, they kind of looked for an excuse to go somewhere, I think.
         
         
         SS: But there was no store- but, was there a school in there?
         KP: It was at our house.
         
         
         SS: Only private.
         KP: Just our family. Father hired a teacher that lived at our house,
         and taught there. There was one housewarming I remember, I didn't
         go to it, I was too small, but my dad and mother went to a home
         stead cabin housewarming two miles up the river from us. Mother
         made a cake to take along and also took along a kerosene
         lamp to light up the occasion. When they got there they found the
         lamp- the kerosene had soaked out of the lamp into the cake!
         
         
         SS: Was the teacher there for just a part of the year?
         KP: The months that we were holed up on Salmon River. About five
         months,^that she taught there, something like that.
         
         
         SS: Had her closer to six. It was pretty standard, I guess. I know
         that as a seventh grader I came out to Genesee just a couple of
         weeks before the end of the term, and enrolled into the seventh
         if
         grade and passed the examination there with no problem. So I
         think that what was taught was pretty standard stuff. 
         
         
         SS: Did you have a number of teachers through the years, or would the
         same person come back?
         KP: We had one teacher two different terms.
         
         
         SS: Were they very hard on you as far as making you stick to the
         grindstone? With you not being in a classroom with a lot of kids
         I'd wonder—?
         If: As I recall, we observed school hours pretty closely. School was
         always and adventure to me, so it was never a hardship. I wasn't
         even aware that school was supposed to be hard.
         
         
         SS: Well, there probably wasn't much you could have done at that time
         of year anyway outside, so you probably would have been in anyway.
         
         
         SS: How many of you were there of you kids going to school?
         KP: I guess five is the most. I know sister was just barely old
         A
         enough to start to school, the last year at Salmon. Tom, you had
         a couple of years in Genesee before thatAstarted, didn't you?
         
         
         SS: Three years, I think. I wouldn't swear to it anymore, I think it
         was three years ^4V\oo^V\.
         $H: You stayed with Grandma Piatt and went to school.
         
         
         SS: Would you tell about the bad winter again? What that was like
         when it was so hard on the cattle after the war? When was that?
         
         
         SS: 1919 and '20.
         
         
         SS: What was it that happened?
         
         
         SS: Well, it was just a winter with a lot of snow and a lot of cold
         and short feed. That particular area just didn't have any feed in
         there. It was an extremely dry, cold summer and the grass never
         grew very well, and so when it come time to put cattle in the feed
         lots, why, they just didn't have enough feed. Eventually seven
         hundred head ended up down at Toppenish, the feed lots down there.
         Well, in numbers that would indicate that they were something like
         60% short of feed. And it was cold enough that they drove those
         700 cattle across Salmon River on the ice; which is getting pretty
         cold if you've seen the Salmon River, because it's a pretty fast,
         turbulent stream, when they went to take them out of there.
         B#: As I remember the story, at the time they said that they started
         feeding- John says in thisAthey started feeding thie 700 head of
         cattle $7 a ton hay and before they got through it was $50 a ton.
         But the thing I remembered was that the price of beef was about
         $36 when they went there, . was only $9 in the spring and they
         fed them all winter, brought 'em through the winter. So they had
         to bring part of 'em back home, there wasn't anything they could
         do with it. They did sell quite a few of 'em.
         
         
         SS: Would you tell me again about how hard that was on the cattle;
         that cold weather?
         
         
         SS: Well, the cow that consistently stays that cold, unless she's
         awfully well fed, she just won't hold her own or do any good. And
         of course, it stayed cold way late in the spring so they lost a
         lot of calves. And the cows were in such poor condition that
         they didn't pring back and the next year's calf crop wasn't any
         good. And a thing like that carries on for several years.
         the teats
         
         
         SS: Did you ever see any that were so cold that they froze?
         KP: Yes. Cows that were sucking calves, the calves would suck and
         get the cow's teat wet and then it was so cold that it would
         freeze and drop off, destroyed the uddersof the cow.
         
         
         SS: I think the remarkable thing about this whole thing though was
         way that Bill and John, after they had gone through this and had
         everything put up for sale, and John took 350 head of gummer ewes,
         the ewes that wouldn't sell anyway, the old ones, Bill took six
         teen or seventeen head of bred Hereford heifers and they went their
         own way and within two or three years, John was a sheepman and had
         a band of sheep and Bill was back in the cattle business. This,
         to me, is the remarkable thing that cattlemen or stockmen can just
         sit back and wait for nature to take its:course and the increase
         will come if they can wait long enough.
         KP: If you can find some way to eat, while that's going 
         
         
         SS: Oh, okay, that probably was part of it.
         
         
         SS: How would you recall just what that postwas depression meant in
         this area for farmers that had a hard time?
         
         
         SS: Well, I wouldn't say that farmers generally had a hard time. The
         price of wheat stayed reasonably good, it wasn't like it was, but
         it wasn't too many years until it was $1.25 or $1.50, around there.
         It was because of the shortage of hay in certain areas, well, in
         fact, on large areas that hurt the stockman. The ones that sold
         his beef during the summer when he could have got a good price for
         it instead of holding it for a higher price, he didn't do too bad.
         And a lot of farmers will cry about that because they could have
         sold their wheat for $1.45- or $2.45 aiid was going to have $2.50
         and eventually they took $1.25 for it.
         
         
         SS: Why did the bottom fall out of the cattle market?
         
         
         SS: I wouldn't for sure know. .The war was over and maybe there was a
         little more meat around than they needed or something. The govern
         ment quit buying tremendous amounts of this, you see, and when
         they brought a couple of million men home from France and quit
         haying to ship that stuff oyer there to feed 'em, why, they just
         didn't buy any more.
         
         
         SS: This came quite a little while before the start of the real depression.
         This was ten years before. If this came in 1920, say,
         A
         or shortly after that- the farmers were still enjoying pretty
         fair prices through 1929, at least. Then they began to get the
         pinch. As Tom said, some of 'em took $1.25- I've had 'em tell
         me they took 35C and some of 'em as low as 17c a bushel.
         
         
         SS: What time are we talking now?
         
         
         SS: In the early '30's then.
         Yeah, so far as the Latah county farmer is concerned the^ 30's
         were far, far worse than the other one.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yeah. No question about that.
         
         
         SS: But to the ranchers, would you say the earlier one was as severe?
         
         
         SS: Don't you suppose this came; as Tom said, from a poor grass crop,
         a poor crop of hay and having all this stock that had to be fed,
         this just naturally threw these fellows into a depression, maybe
         it wasn't wide, although it must have been wide, too, because if
         they said that they could have got 36c for their beef when they took
         it down there and could only get 90 when they got ready to move
         it out of there, beef must have been dropping pretty fast over
         the winter.
         Well, after that war, the fact that a lot of industries shut down,
         too; there was a good deal of unemployment and there wasn't the
         money around to buy high priced stuff that had been a short while
         before.
         Itf: There was a different cause of difficulty in Latah County among
         the folks " were strictly farmers, and that is that during the
         last years of World War I, the price of wheat got up to $2.50 a
         bushelvmaybe higher, and this touched off a lot of land buying
         speculation. Land in the Genesee area that had been worth maybe
         $75 an acre before the war was selling for $200, $250 an acre.
         And people who bought that land and went out on a limb without
         in laid enough money.to pay for it were caught in the depression after
         the war. low crop prices.wouldn't pay for it at land valued that
         And some of those folks had to give up; lost their farms
         and this was a kind of beginning of combining farms into either
         patches for folks that had big enough areas and were well enough
         financed to stay with it and bought up some of these farms
         be abandoned bankruptcy.
         
         
         SS: There were speculators, too; for instance in the early days here
         this man Williamson that had the store here in Moscow, was a
         speculator. His son is my neighbor now. And Frank told me that
         he always worked on the idea that once he had enough of a hold on
         a ranch that he could borrow some money on it, he'd go out and put
         it down on something else. Well, when he got all through Frank
         ended up by having just one 160 acre ranch over at Pullman that he
         could save out of all that his dad had. And the Toomey place down
         at Genesee was one of 'em that he had at one time, you know. But
         he just kept buying everytime he got a foothold on a piece of land
         and could borrow some more money, then he'd go out and buy some
         thing else. And if times would have kept going up, why, he'd a
         been alright. But they didn't. What I wonder about now, aren't
         we in the same kind of a thing, right now? We were talking,
         Kenny, about the price going from $75 to $250 or something, now
         they tell me that some of our farm land is selling as high as
         $850 an acre. No one can make that kind of money from that piece
         of land, if they depend on the piece of land to make the money.
         KP: That's right, and it isn't farmers that are offering that kind
         of money, it's people who have other income; people who have in
         dustrial income or some other enterprise; against which they can
         take a loss on a farm and take a tax credit for it. I was told by
         fludcflph M^ty,tne last time x talked to him that one of his neighwas
         bors.offered $1,200 an acre for 1,000 acres of land over toward
         Uniontown. And this was not an offer made by another farmer,
         it was an offer made by a California investor, who perhaps has an
         industrial development or some other business against which he
         can take credit in a tax writeoff
         What would his long range interest be in owning land that would
         cost him that much? What would he be able to do with it?
         
         
         SS: Under our present income tax setup he can take off any loss- if
         it- he can show a loss on this farm that isn't paying out, he can take
         this directly out of his profits from the other organization,
         whatever he has. Until they straighten up this kind of a thing,
         there'll always be some of that going on. But, I know, Kenny,
         one or two cases where it has been the farmer who bought the land
         but it was land that joined him and he could farm it without any
         additional equipment and he probably had the money to buy it.
         KP: In this circumstance it makes some sense.
         
         
         SS: You were talking about speculation; they say that a lot of places
         there was a certain amount of speculation in the pioneer days,
         some more than others. Some places had boosters come in, guys
         that were just trying to take advantage of the fact that the
         land was just opening up, didn't plan to stay there. Do you
         knowhow much of that there was around here and Genesee, opposed
         to people just coming in to buy and settle for what they could?
         
         
         SS: From what I can remember, I would say that most of the people who
         came in there, came in with the idea of staying, because the valley
         to the north was Scandinavian; the valley to the west was Germans.
         They just kind of came and landed in communities and they built
         their homes and built a church, planned to stay right there, I
         don't think there was very little speculation. The place where
         there might have been a little speculation early, would have been
         like this town of Blaine, which isn't even here anymore, just over
         Paradise Jfill, used to be on the old Genesee to Moscow road. There
         was a sawmill, a grocery store and a church and a school, and
         cut quite a little timber right in there, but now it's all farm
         land; it's all been cleared and it's all open to farm land. Might
         have been some speculation in places like that.
         
         
         SS: That speculation was mostly on the town probably, that there might
         be a town there that would be something.
         8: I think that's true and that was a phase which passed very early.
         It was part of1 tide of land settlement and early development.
         Before the railroads came there was always an uncertainty of where
         the railroad would be when it did come, so there was speculation
         on that. You can read the history of the railroads in Latah Counfind
         ty and adjoining Whitman County and. a half a dozen towns thought
         they were going to be the capital of the state one of these days
         the railroad was going to come there first. But it didn't
         it went somewhere else, so a lot of these little towns just stabi
         lized at a much lower level and some disappeared almost entirely.
         They didn't get a permanent setup to back up their needs.
         
         
         SS: In the first ten or twenty years of a lot of pioneer communities,
         from what I've read, there was a great deal of turnover. Trying
         to do some statistical research they find that 70-80% of the peo
         ple would not stay from one census to the next. Do you think that
         around Genesee there was a lot of stability?
         KB: Yes, I do. I think Dave has the right idea; people that came to
         settle most of that country came intending to stay. They came from
         harder circumstances when they came, too, even though this was a
         pioneer country. The Scandinavian people and^ German people who
         came in here came from much more difficult climate and limited
         land resources and limited opportunities and they had no way to go
         but up, when they got to a good farming country where they had
         their own land and all persevere. And that's
         pretty much how it went.
         It's a commplace.land development in most areas that it
         takes about three generations of investment before the land ac
         tually pays back enough to pay off the last investment. This
         has been true of virtually all of the irrigation project*' Idaho,
         doe example. McnM irrigation project has opened up and peopie
         move in and homestead land and they spend all^their resources
         in developing as much of the land as they can, and they find they
         can't make a living so they sell out to somebody else, ordinarily
         taking considerable loss on their investment up to that point.
         some more land
         The next fellow puts in his investment and develops,^ and he can't
         make a go of it and finally the third investor comes along and
         enough of
         by that time.the previous investment has been written off
         jprice that he pays and enough improvement has been made in the
         resource that he can make a living, and. stabilize .
         
         
         SS: And the third one's probably got a bigger ranch. He probably got
         two ranches or more by that time. I think this is true, I think
         this is true about in the irrigated country, in the Big Bend and
         all that country. 
         So, I don't know whether this goes so much that way, but
         I think of the Genesee country now— you fellows remember young
         Crauley, Ernest Crauley down there. His dad raised a family -
         I don't know how big a family on 80 acres. When he started farming
         he had to have two or three times that much, now his son is far
         ming and I don't know what size his ranch is, but I suppose 800
         acres or 700 acres, like all the rest of them down there to make
         a living. But still, his dad raised a family on 80 acres.
         KP: This is part of the explanation, or at least relates to the explanaadditional
         tion of why farmers can pay seemingly impossible prices now for^
         farm land; you usually find that the farmer pays such a high
         price already has a substantial, going outfit and if he's a
         third generation farmer like the Crauley grandson, who is now far
         ming in the Genesee area, he has pretty much inherited what he has.
         So if he has 1,000 acres for which he paid nothing, say, he can buy
         another 160 acres to average in with that at a very high price
         and his overall cost of land is still a reasonable figure. This
         samNman, if he had to go to the bank and borrow the money and buy
         that land and pay off a loan covering the whole value of the land
         assets that cost much less.
         
         
         SS: I always think of that way of old Charley Funkhouser who was a
         banker at Palouse for many years; he owned a couple hundred acres
         out there and he always claimed that Palouse land was only worth
         $67 an acre, but it come time to sell his he got $200 or $225 for
         it. But probably as far as the bank was concerned, $67 would have
         been the figure they'd started using; that'd been the amount they'd
         loan on it.
         
         
         SS: Speaking about that post World War I tough winter, and I was just
         was that felt strictly by the cattlemen or
         wondering about was it across the board
         for what it did in the country around here?
         
         
         SS: I'd say it was on all livestock men, anyway, sheep and cattle, any
         way. I don't suppose it affected the hogs very much because in
         the wintertime hogs are locked up anyway.
         
         
         SS: It must have affected the labor market though I ran a camp, NRA,
         which was the National Resource Act, I believe- Recovery fct- and
         they paid those boys 60£ an hour, I think, $1 an hour for cooks
         and so forth, but they had plenty of takers and that was something
         on the order of the CCC, except that they were just working for
         wages, and so I would imagine that there was plenty of labor force
         that was looking for work.
         fc£: What year was that?
         
         
         SS: That was '34,
         
         
         SS: I was talking about the 19- we're skipping around- 1918-'19.
         
         
         SS: Okay. You're still talking about 1919 and 1920.
         
         
         SS: You said the horse's tails-
         
         
         SS: Cow's tails froze down at nights when they lay down. And when
         they get up they just pull the hair out of their tails. There
         was cows all over the country without any bush on their tails,
         next spring. VitaM i^d ^where they d tuck their tail between their
         tail between their legs and the heat on the body would melt 'em
         down in but during the night it'd get so cold they'd freeze up
         again. And I remember Bill Piatt coming out here and telling it
         was so damn cold that they had cows laying down on the bed grounds
         that were froze down, they couldn't get up, right on the bed
         ground in the feed lot. And these were well fed cattle he was
         talking about; reasonably well fed. And they had to go around
         in the morning and break 'em lose so they could stand up.
         
         
         SS: I don't think wages were very good for sometime after this '20
         thing, because I can remember working for the Genesee Union Ware
         house for a couple of years and I'm sure I worked for about 600
         an hour or something of the kind, working in the warehouse. And
         before that and after that, wages went up some in price, although
         maybe not so awully high.
         KP: By the time I was working for wages out in harvest in the,/20's
         two bits an hour was harvest wage, $4 a day for a twelve hour day.^
         
         
         SS: Figuring along that same line I worked for Bunker Hill and Sullivan
         for six months in the mines, and that was either in '20 or '21 and
         I got $4.25 a day for that.
         
         
         SS: Eight hours?
         
         
         SS: Eight hours. So that wages weren't anything outstanding.
         
         
         SS: You didn't have very much.time you paid for your bed and your board.
         
         
         SS: Paid for your room and board adn so forth; I've forgotten now what
         it cost, but it couldn't have been more than $30 a month or so.
         
         
         SS: Did you find on your operation you could keep your help pretty
         well?
         
         
         SS: Oh, I don't know, we had quite a few incompetent people out there
         at the ranch at different times that I remember of. Kids that
         came out of Spokane and one thing and another. Take 'em out to
         a1000*"
         pitch hay and you'd just.as well pitch it yourself, you got along
         better. They never had a pitchfork in their hands before you
         know, didn t know what to do with it.
         
         
         SS: By and large now, I don t think that Bill had any trouble on Sal
         mon River. He had experienced men there all the time. But they
         were homesteaders from around there that had been there a while and
         knew something about the country.
         W: tor a ew dollars.
         
         
         SS: Yeah. And he didn't have any trouble there.
         KP: I would think that by and large, all through that period.until
         after the 1930's depression, the labor market was largely a buyer's
         market, even on ranches. There were some men who were pretty
         hcu) mock
         picky and choosey about where they worked and they got paid,
         but you could nearly always find men who were looking for work.
         There was a great deal of itinerant labor needed the Palouse
         country then, because the harvesting piled up, the grain was bound
         combineAand the harvesting required a lot of extra help to
         manage the horses and pitch the bundles and thresh the grain and
         so on. And there was quite a lot needed in haying time. There
         was a lot of seasonal work. With the tractors, and selfpropelled
         combines they do up this work in thirty days that used to take a
         much longer time with horsepower and handpower, and
         lot fewer people to do it.
         
         
         SS: Well, I tell the story Kenny, that^along '18, '19 somewhere along
         in there they had a contract south of Genesee building road.
         That was one of their first jobs, probably, and all in the world
         that outfit owned was a tent for a cookhouse, and a tent to cover
         the horses and some horses and a plow or a couple of plows and
         Fresnoes. That's the way they built that Genesee highway,
         to start with. And it's still in the same place it was built then
         although they've come in since then and cut one or two of the hills
         
         down a little more. But they went on from that and went off
         down i that Boise country and during the second war or something
         they became another Morrison-Knudsen and went all over the world
         building airfields and so forth.
         
         
         SS: This the Turteling outfit.
         
         
         SS: Turteling Brothers. They started here at Moscow. In fact, there's
         one of them living at Boise now. Well, there may be more than one
         of 'em, but there's one of the grandsons living at Boise now, they
         tell me. that has a big ranch out there and he's collecting old
         machines and old sawmills or anything of this kind that
         the next generation would be interested in and is making it into
         a kind of amusement park, I think, to take children out to to
         let them see how things went on in the 'good days', if that's what
         you call 'em.
         
         
         SS: Did you have to cross the Salmon At other times with cattle?
         Was river crossing part of the operation?
         
         
         SS: At times when it had to be. That's too big a rivef* cattle won't
         cross that unless they're forced to it, of course. But in our
         mis
         time there were no bridges, and £ beef cut being taken from Joseph
         (fountain on the other side of the river had to be swum across.
         There was no other way. They did have a ferry at RJtce Creek and
         .Whitebird, but there was no corrals or anything leading onto it,
         so there was no way to get these cattle on there.
         
         
         SS: Did you lead cattle across yourself?
         
         
         SS: I've helped swim cattle at Salmon many times.
         
         
         SS: What's it like?
         
         
         SS: Oh, you just take a small bunch that you can be sure to handle,
         maybe seven or eight or ten head and decidw - you're going to
         put 'em in and two or three fellows- a couple behind and one on
         
         each side to start 'em on the run down to the river and they'll
         go in. If you can keep that lead bunch headed across the others
         will go fairly easy. 
         The early day people and maybe still some of 'em do, they
         swam cattle across the Snake, too.
         K!fJ: Tom, did you ever see the technique used of putting a young calf
         in the back of a rowboat and coaxing the mother in?
         
         
         SS: No, but I've coaxed a whole herd up ^ highway that way, not in a
         rowboat!
         Wrtll a calf in a pickup.
         right! Put a calf in a pickup and let ma find out exactly
         where he is and you've got a leader right up the highway. Take
         the whole bunch and just go! (Chuckles)
         lift: That's the technique as old as time, I've seen in the old tomb inscriptions
         in Egypt, in the^ inscriptions there, a picture of a
         a calf bawling °o4r of
         boat crossing a body of water with the back end and the
         mother following along bawling. I suppose they were crossing the
         Nile.
         
         
         SS: I'd like to ask you a little bit about what you remember about
         the World War I years in the Genesee area; how the local people
         reacted to the war and what effect that had on them. What the
         people did.
         KP: Well, I saw it of course with very young eyes, because I was only
         ten years old in 1917 when we moved to the Genesee country from
         the Salmon River. But I remember it created a great dedication
         on the part of everybody. In school we knit mittens and we sewed
         this and that and so on for the soldiers and we saved prune pits
         because they took the nuts out of those and extracted something
         that was used to make gas masks. We saved all kinds of stuff;
         tinfoil, I remember was something we were supposed to save. And
         there was great enthusiasm whenever there was a bond sale or any
         kind of a money raising deal. I remember we had an old rooster
         that must have been about a ten pounder, he was a great, big
         Plymouth Rock and old as time, and my Dad took him to an auction
         sale and he was sold several times at this sale, nobody wanted
         to keep him, so they'd buy him and put him backpn sale and my dad
         finally came home with him! That one rooster raised $15 or $20,
         by being sold over and over again. 
         
         
         SS: Incidentlaly they used the shell, the nut shells and the shells
         of the prune pits or anything like that was transformed into char
         coal for the gas masks. That's what they used.
         
         
         SS: Well, one thing I knew about it was that this- there was an Idaho
         company down on the Mexican border before this thing started, they
         were training down there, they were called into active duty and
         then taken down to guard the railroads and.type of thing before
         they finally went into this western outfit that went overseas.
         And there were quite a few boys from Genesee area that were in ac
         tive duty over there. Kenny says he was about ten years old,
         I was seventeen- would have been seventeen at the end of 1917, so
         I was just about to the age where I could have gotten in when the
         thing ended.
         
         
         SS: Do you remember there being much concern locally about the IWWs?
         
         
         SS: Oh,okay, I'll tell you a story. The IWWs had been in full swing
         anyway, for some little time, and I was working for an outfit,
         Jones, Frank Jones was one of 'em, I can't tell you the other guy's
         name now, but anyway, there was two partners in on this threshing
         machine. We pulled into a field and were threshing on it, and we
         were threshing loose oats, and the wind was coming just the wrong
         way and it was coming right back in our face, and I went in once
         and unloaded, came out choking to death. And so when I went out
         in the field then to load up again with the wagon, I came back in
         and I told these fellows, I said, "I'm not going back in there any
         more. That isn't any place for a guy to be at all, unless you want
         to turn this machine around, I'm just going to unhook. And some
         of your other fellows are going to quit you, too, because they're
         all grumbling about it." Well, that was the wrong thing to say,
         because right away they said, "We'll just take you to town then
         for IWW  And this was Frank Jones and the other fellow that was
         there he just kind of laughed about it and he wrote out my check
         and he offered me a ride to town, anyway. But Frank was all for
         taking me in to Moscow; I was one of the strike leaders! I would
         have been alright if I'd just told him I was going to quit, that
         I was through, but when I told him the rest of 'em didn't like
         it that was- that they were all going to quit-taking her a little
         too far, I guess.
         
         
         SS: Well, I've heard rumors about suspected sabotage that the IWWs
         did in the farming country. But from what I've heard from old
         loggers, it was pretty much along the lines that they didn't be
         lieve that they did much damage during that period of time in
         the farming country.
         
         
         SS: The idea was that they were supposed to have boxes of matches
         or something of this kind in the separators and the separators
         blew up and smut explosions. But how many of 'em were just smut
         explosions and how many of 'em were- had something to do with
         PLATT/HICKMAN/PLATT 53
         somebody settin' 'em off, I don't have any idea.
         
         
         SS: I think there were two or three sizeable grain fires in the Big
         Bend that were set. Who set 'em, that's something else, and they
         who 
         never did prove did. I don't think that it amounted to
         much.
         
         
         SS: Was smut a big problem: were smut fires real dangerous? A real
         possibility in the Genesee country?
         
         
         SS: Oh, yes.
         
         
         SS: Always dangerous.
         $J: They didn't have the smut resistant wheat varities the|.
         Smut was much more common. I was involved in a smut explosion
         in the threshing crews I worked with one year. I was the last
         wagon unloading at the end of the day when you scoop up the accumu
         lated stuff off the bottom of the rack, that you shattered out in
         your bundle rack the day.A Anyway, the machine exploded while
         I was unloading, but the operator was all braced for it, it was a
         smutty field and he was operating a steam powered outfit and he had
         a steam line from this boiler right into the separator, and when
         that machine blew, the engineer revved up the engine, turned the
         steam ir^ the separator and the separator tender stood up on the
         top of that separator in a flash, if he wasn't there already and
         he cranked the straw blower away from the straw stack and, blew the
         A
         fire right out of that machine. It was out in less than five minu
         tes. It blew a big hunk of flaming straw out onto the edge
         of the straw stack but there were a half a dozen guys standing
         around there and they got in with their pitchforks and shoved that
         away from the straw stack and it burned a piece of stubble maybe
         half as big as this house and in^ two minutes maybe, it was over with,
         They replaced some burned out in the machine that
         night and the next morning it started off on time. But I think
         this is probably no different from most smut explosions that
         time, they didn't have to be set. The operators were taking every
         possible precaution to avoid it, and be ready for it if it did occur.
         handled.
         
         
         SS: Did the smut problem start in the teens or was it something that
         was there from the beginning? Do you know?
         fcft: Well, I don't know, but I presume we always had it from the time
         we got wheat into the country. Especially here.
         Especially Red Russian.
         KP: The smut spore gets onto the healthy wheat kernels, and is carried
         wherever the wheat goes. If you imported seed from an area where
         smut was common you'd have smut with it. Then when you plant the
         seed, the smut germinates along with the wheat and grows right in
         the wheat kernel and comes up. the stem of the wheat as a parasite
         and invades the new head, takes over the kernels there and just
         multiplies until it completely replaces the normal vegetation
         there in the wheat kernel.
         
         
         SS: I wonder how much of a problem that was, Kenny, though in the
         early days when they used more headers. Didn't have the bundles
         and so forth. They headed the wheat and put it right into the
         machine. Do you suppose that this reduced the smut possibility a
         little?
         KP: Don't know how it could have any effect.
         
         
         SS: Well, I was thinking it might be a little more moist by still being
         standing wheat.
         KP: When the wheat was headed that early it was stacked, and ripened
         in the stack, rather than going direct in the machine.
         
         
         SS: I worked on one of the last header outfits Sherm Wall had out
         fo\M of Header boK -Qr i
         there, just for a short time, and that was going directly into a
         machine.
         Well, you haddry what.
         
         
         SS: Uh-huh.
         KP: But one of the reasons the header went out and another system
         came back in was that they could not wait until the wheat was ripe
         because by the time they got around to the last wheat it was shat-
         tered badly, on account of the wind.
         
         
         SS: I've heard all over the eastern part of the county, Park, Deary,
         Troy that in the early days people used to come to Genesee for
         the harvest from there, as just a regular part of the work when
         they were homesteading out in the Troy area, and so I get the idea
         that the harvest was really quite a big time for the county centered
         around Genesee in the early days.
         
         
         SS: Well, I think this last outfit I worked on down there had something
         like sixteen wagons, so that would have been sixteen wagons there
         plus four pitchers in the field, plus a separator tender and the
         guy hauling water and the cooks and the engine man and all this type
         of thing; there probably were thirty people; twenty-five to thirty
         people up this operation and this could go on for thirtythirty-
         five days.
         
         
         SS: Were these owned by an individual or were they owned by a—?
         
         
         SS: By individuals, mostly. This one that I was telling about- one
         of them that I worked on was this Kloster and Jones and then I re
         member another one, Old he ran there for years. That's
         all he did was just run this threshing outfit in the summertime.
         
         
         SS: He made enough threshing to
         
         
         SS: (Chuckles), for the rest of the year!. Yeah, I guess.
         It was a big business time you got all these men together and
         then by the time the farmer fed all these horses out of the stock
         that was out there- out of the grain that was there- so this took
         an enormous amount of grain , to keep the outfit going, too.
         You asked something about wheat— Up until the first war, there at
         Genesee, wheat wasn't such - really such a big business probably,
         because none of those flats up there were even in wheat, they were
         all either in hay or pasture; one or the other. The hills were
         raising grain alright, and it was after the start of this First
         World War that they finally decided they could raise wheat on the;
         flats. So now it's strictly a wheat country.
         
         
         SS: You were talking about the weather changing. That's a common thing
         that climate's changed around this county. Have you got any ideas
         about anything that people would say- used to say about why it
         changed; how it changed? I know it changed, but what's the specu
         lation on that?
         JB$: Did it change because the timberline moved back? Does that make a
         difference?
         I don't know.
         
         
         SS: Of course the timberline has been moved back. 
         
         
         SS: It's moved back a long ways.
         
         
         SS: Used to be timber clear down around Blaine and in there.
         KP: This winter change seems to be a worldwide phenomonen. I ve
         articles recently about this and what effect it may have^ So-«*•
         I certainly recollect much harder winters when we were kids than
         we encounter.
         
         
         SS: Course, one thing about these, Kenny, too, is they didn*t have any
         equipment for moving snow, so wherever it fell that's just where
         it stayed. They just tromped it down and left it right there,
         where now they'll come«long with the motorized equipment and they'll
         knock it all off the highway and put it over on the edge of the road.
         
         
         SS: When people started growing what on the flats, was it because they
         thought the winters were getting milder or were they just experi
         menting? Do you know how that development came about?
         KP: I would venture a couple of guesses: it sort of coincided with the
         A
         high price of wheat during World War I. It was worth taking a flyer
         meadows
         to plow up some pasture and.try to grow some wheat. Another guess
         would be that probably more winter-hardy or frost resistant varieties
         had been developed by the experiment stations up to that time.
         So, I think it was probably a natural change. And then, of course,
         once the tractors started coming in they didn't need all that mea
         dow and hay ground and they had to find something else to put Gn
         and wheat was the natural thing. We always had lots of livestock
         to feed and so we raised feed crops on our flat ground. We had
         clover and grass mixtures on some of it and we raised summer crops,
         corn or sunflowers or something like that on some of the other.
         But I think that's probably an explanation of the changes. There
         has been, I'm convinced, some change of climate but some of these
         other changes would have occurred whether the climate changed or not.
         
         
         SS: The change has reduced the water level around Genesee, considerably.
         I don't know if you know about it, but Rudolph has got a shallow
         well out there back of the barn, a pitcher pump in it and a small
         trough and he always, when he was using horses and milking cows
         there, he d just by hand pump water for i livestock, and he had
         all the water he wanted. Now he can pump it dry in a few minutes.
         Gone down that much. Of course, that's just a shallow thing, but
         still the water is just plain lower, even on the flats,
         that that
         KP: But I would guess.again, resulted in a combination of factors.
         When we used to summer fallow half the land, and was only cropped
         every other year, and now we crop every year, if it isn't wheat
         it's peas or barley or lentils or something else every year. And
         every year there's a crop and crops require tremendous amounts of
         water. And when half the ground was summer fallowed there was a
         chance for some of that water to go on down and add to the ground
         water. Very little of it gets there any more.
         
         
         SS: There is one area we haven't talked about at all that I would like
         to ask you to give some general impressions on, and that is the
         different cultural groups that were around at the time, and any
         recollections you have of some of the early differences in ways
         between the Germans and Norwegians and other groups that were
         there.
         
         
         SS: I don't remember much about the early days because I didn't have
         much contact probably with those people. The Germans and the
         Catholics, probably, were pretty much west of town. The Scandina
         vians were north of town and pretty much in one valley. But when
         I was working with the CCC boys along in the late '30's, I found
         that these Scandinavians, anyway, you never could go to their house
         without having cookies and coffee and so forth. Well, they had it
         for themselves there and anybody that came in had to stop and eat
         with them, that's all there was to it. You at least had coffee and
         cookies. But I think they were people who were kind of clannish
         but still they were all progressive and they all worked in
         the community, I don't think they were clannish to the place where
         they wouldn't associate with anyone else.
         The need for interchange of labor in harvest, I think pretty
         The need to
         well bridged whatever cultrual gap there might be. . work to-
         gether i a pioneer situation. I was never aware that there were
         any cultural barriers
         Then you had these little towns, like Lenville and Blaine, they
         were quite the litte community there at one time, when people didn't
         have to go to town to buy a couple of pounds of sugar or something
         of this kind, whatever they needed. Most of the things they could
         raise on the ranch, and so they could go to these smaller places
         and buy them. And each one of these little towns usually turned
         out with a ball team of some kind. Something to keep the community
         spirit going.
         
         
         SS: There were some flaky times around during the First World War about
         the Germans around town. It never was very bad.
         
         
         SS: Oh, yeah, I guess there was.
         
         
         SS: I guess  was the only one that I knew of ever having 
         They fixed his place of business up pretty good. Didn't do him
         any damage as far as I remember.
         JBfl: They plaster it with signs or something?
         
         
         SS: Didn't they move an outhouse close to his door and put up some
         signs there and one thing and another? I think that's about what
         they did.
         KP: There was plenty of that done free for nothing on Hallowe'en!
         
         
         SS: Especially in the vestibule of the schoolhouse, or something
         that Kind.
         
         
         SS: Was there much moonshing and that sort of thing around Genesee,
         like th. ere was in some places?
         
         
         
         SS: There was an old boy named Hardy that had the reputation anyway.
         I notice that Old John talks about him there in that book, also
         had the reputation around Palouse, so I imagine there was some
         moonshining going on, alright, I don't know that there was any
         great amount of it.
         
         
         SS: Doubt if he was mixed up in any moonshining, just plain bootleg
         ging.
         
         
         SS: Yeah, he was.
         Don't know whether he made it or whether he was just peddling it.
         There was quite a number of people that made a little and there
         was a lot of 'em made their beer. Not very many people that sold
         it. Just home use thing.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13568</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Pierce_Selina</previous>
      <next>Platz</next>
      <disp_name>Platt</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
