<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/27/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Helmer Ringsage, 1976-02-27, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:25:04</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Ringsage, Helmer</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Farmer; logger</occupation>
      <birthyear>1888</birthyear>
      <residence>Park, Central Ridge</residence>
      <origin>Parents were Norwegian homesteaders (1890); he is Edward Swenson's nephew</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crops"&gt;crops&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#livestock"&gt;livestock&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooperatives"&gt;cooperatives&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#plowing"&gt;plowing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#neighbors"&gt;neighbors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lawyers"&gt;lawyers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#doctors"&gt;doctors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#suicide"&gt;suicide&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Park"&gt;Park&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Central Ridge"&gt;Central Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Canada"&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13652</file_name>
      <mp3>13653.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13653.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Crop Speculation led to losses; Difficulties in raising hogs</title>
            <synopsis>Roosevelt's help. Speculation on beans and wheat led to losses. Difficulties starting
               to raise hogs; moving the building for hogs with a stump puller to get it close to
               a pond.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1080</time>
            <title>Modifying the pond for stock; preparing the hog house to move</title>
            <synopsis>Lining the pond with clay so it held water for the stock. Laying peeled logs under
               the hog house for skids. Work was easy for him when young.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Moving the family to Central Ridge; Early clearing and farming efforts</title>
            <synopsis>The family move to Central Ridge. Climbing the ridge with the wagon and no trail.
               Father's early clearing and farming efforts. After threshing he brought home shoes
               for the boys. Broadcasting flax seed by hand.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Improved hand broadcasting; Father threshed around Genesee</title>
            <synopsis>Improved hand broadcasting. Father threshed around Genesee.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1980</time>
            <title>Grandfather and father's work in Minnesota; Driven out of Swift Falls and went to
               Park
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Grandfather and father's wood cutting with oxen in Minnesota. Grandfather loved Park
               and split wood even when he was old. They were driven from the Swift Falls area by
               grasshoppers and hail, and went to Park.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Father's fire insurance company; Education in Spokane; There was no future in Norway</title>
            <synopsis>Father started Farmers' Mutual Fire Insurance Company, a cooperative, on Camas Prairie.
               Father changed his name. Getting education in Spokane. No future in Norway.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2760</time>
            <title>Homesteading on Central Ridge; Hauling Harvested Flax; Plowing the fields since he
               was eleven
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Opportunity to homestead on Central Ridge. Father made money raising horses. Father's
               arduous trips to Kendrick with the harvested flax. At eleven Helmer was ploughing
               the farm with a walking plow; he practiced on four horses so his father got a gang
               plow. Straw bottoms.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3420</time>
            <title>Last year farming Central Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>His last year farming on Central Ridge: good money on pigs, problems with summer fallowed
               land, desire to get out.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Quitting the ridge because of a bad neighbor; Bloowurst stole cattle</title>
            <synopsis>A bad neighbor was a major reason why he quit the ridge. They fought after his boys
               persisted in dogging Helmer's cattle. Bloodwurst then dragged Helmer's lead cow down
               to his pasture. He'd also stolen cattle from a big stockman, Helmer discovered from
               a lawyer. He decided to "neighbor" with Helmer. A fight and a near-fight with two
               other men as a result of tangling with Bloodwurst. Teaching neighbors to saw cordwood.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4860</time>
            <title>Confronting Bloodwurst about cattle theft; Sons harassed Helmer's boy</title>
            <synopsis>Helmer called him on stealing three cattle and two were returned. His sons harassed
               Helmer's boy.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5100</time>
            <title>Helmer's son ran away from home in the winter of 1931; Found son in Pomeroy and wanted
               him to stay to get an education
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Helmer's son got balky and ran away from home (1931). The agonizing winter drive to
               Parma in his Whippet with a bad case of stomach flu, only to find that the boy wasn't
               there. Locating his son in Pomeroy - urging him to stay with the farmer, who was providing
               him with a school education he couldn't get in Park. 
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6180</time>
            <title>Helmer's experience in running away from home to try to homestead; Working in Avon,
               Deary, and Craigmont
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Helmer himself ran away at eighteen to raise money for homesteading in Canada. His
               horseback journey to Gifford to find it still too early for farm work, then north
               to Park in a snow storm. His jobs working near Avon for a French-Canadian (who later
               killed his wife) and at Deary, His father discovered his whereabouts when Helmer tried
               to collect money owed by a farmer. His father persuaded him to work on the railroad
               from Craigmont to Nezperce, but the job was no good.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Didn't homestead in Canada when he couldn't raise the money; Father built the house
               and barn in 1908; Father's education in Missouri
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father persuaded him not to go to Canada when he didn't get enough money. In 1908
               father had house and barn built. Father went to chiropractor school in Missouri.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7620</time>
            <title>French-Canadian killed his wife and himself; Father's chiropractic work</title>
            <synopsis>The French-Canadian he'd worked for killed his wife and himself, becoming extremely
               jealous of her going with woman friends. Father's work as a chiropractor - helping
               Helmer's injury.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7860</time>
            <title>Pleasures of dances in homes; Sneaking out to dances</title>
            <synopsis>Pleasure of waltzing in homes. Learning from their aunt. Masquerade dance. Basket
               socials. Dances till daylight; you'd hear the violin as you were trying to sleep.
               Sneaking out of the house to dance despite father's wishes.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>8400</time>
            <title>Brothers worked for Malcom, a good neighbor</title>
            <synopsis>His brothers worked regularly for a good neighbor, Malcolm, whose offspring now hold
               a lot of land.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Running away from home. Struggle with a bad neighbor. Family homesteading on the
         ridge. Country dances. 2-27-76 2.4 hr 64p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         HELMER RINGSAGE: — Years and the crop would a spoiled over there. And I
         woulda been sunk worse over there than I did get over here. Here I
         only owed a thousand to Deary Bank and I had forty-four head of cattle
         to offset'. They got their money's worth, or would have if they could
         have sold 'em. 1932, manwent down to two bits, over there to Park.
         And the only man that saved me was old President Roosevelt. Delano
         Roosevelt. He made the stipulation that any family man that had—
         regardless, if he was farmin' and had — he was exempt fifty-five acres
         of crop for his family. No mortgage could take it. So that's what I
         done. I had a little oats, two, three hundred dollar's worfk probably
         is all I had. I sold; pocketed the money every time I come in. Old
         Harsh was a nice banker, I didn't want to go borrow that much money to
         start with. I only wanted five hundred. Here was the deal; I didn't
         tell you— I'd boughtstate land on terms, eighty acres right there in
         Park, close to this Noland place. Well, it'd be west of where Gellaburg
         is, up in the mountain there. Just about as soon as you enter
         into Park, over the top of the grade. Well, anyway, I got that four
         teen hundred dollars and my brother, Simon» the one that died with can
         cer, he lent me the cash to make the downpayment. And when I got to
         farmin' on the Ridge, you see, the first few years I was making pretqood
         ty good; some of it, that is, one year, I mean I made— I raised some
         beans on forty-four acres of ground that my dad had. And I got thir
         teen hundred pounds to the acre and I come pretty near missing it like
         some of 'em. One of the neighbors there he tried to WK me, "Oh,"
         he says, "don't sell yet." Says, "They're retailing in Spokane-Kirye. 
         Well, I coulda got nine cents. I speculated a little bit. Could have
         got nine cents. But, old Guernsey, had to haul clear on the other side
         then, — Old Guernsey he says, "You want to sell this morning, Ringsage?"
         "Well, I don't know, what's the price?" He says, "Nine cents." And
         he was laughing kinda, you know. Him and Magill was in partnership.
         And, I thought, "Goddam,"that smile, maybe he had got something up his
         sleeve, I could get a little more, I said, "How about a dime?" "No,"
         he said, "nine cents is pretty good." Well, it was. I was a damn fool
         not to take it, see. Well, I held that doggone crop til pretty soon
         the thresher man command he wanted his money. He wanted it RIGHT NOW.
         Old Ned . I said, "Okay, I'll call up Magill." I wasn't gonna
         fight him, he come and threshed when I asked him to; he wanted his money, by God,
         he had a right to get it. He said he had to pay his crew.
         Which was nothin' more than right.
         
         SS:  How long after the crop was in, was this?
         
         HR:  I had it hauled down to the warehouse.
         
         SS:  Was it very long after he'd threshed it?
         
         HR:  Well, not too long. I don't know. Maybe it was a month or two, I
         can't remember. But anyway, I called up Magill. I says, "How much
         are beans?" And he was kinda of a squeaky voiced guy, he says, "Beans
         are comin' down," he says, "they're still seven and a half cents/( and
         you better sell." And, I said, "I'll sell my share." But my dad had
         told me not to sell his share, til I let him know. Now, he was a dang
         fool for not letting Magill know. He could have told Magill, "Here when
         that price is suitable; sell." What he shoulda done. He didn't do it.
         By the time I wrote to Dad and he finally piddled around like some of
         the rest of the farmers, he left it to Magill then, and he got five
         cents. The rest of the farmers' beans laid in the warehouse. They
         couldn't sell 'em. I was dang lucky I got that seven and a half cents.
         
         SS:  Your father sold for five cents?
         
         HR:  He sold for five. This third share. And I sold mine in the fall, you
         know for the seven and a half.
         
         SS:  The other farmers didn't sell at all?
         
         HR:  No, a lot of 'em didn't sell. They kept a speculating. This one guy,
         Dan Gone(?) that's brother to the one that threshed for us, by God,
         he was the one that told me about prices so good in Spokane. How they
         were retailing. They were retailing for that,you couldn-f go by that,
         us little damn farmers; these grain buyers, you better listen to them.
         I got my lesson there. Then I went as far as one year then, by gosh,
         if I didn't even borrow a dollar and a half on my wheat. Wheat was a dol
         lar and a half. I shoulda sold. No. I had the damn thing til the next
         year. Know what I got? The warehouse took it for storage; eightyfour
         cents. (Laughter) That's what put me under.
         
         SS:  Cost eighty-four cents for storage?
         
         HR:  No. Yeah, it amounted to that. It amounted to that. Well, that is,
         counting what I borrowed. I borrowed a dollar and a half. I had to
         pay up. Don't you see? That dollar and a half I borrowed!
         
         SS:  A dollar and a half a bushel?
         
         HR:  Yeah. I borrowed the seed, let's see, that'd be eighty-five— what?
         That'd be fifty, sixty-five cents extra that I overdrew. That I owed
         the bank.
         
         SS:  Which year was that?
         
         HR:  Oh, God, that was about 19— wait now, I can pretty near figure that—
         What year would that be? 1919!s when I had the good beans. And, let's
         see now. 1919— now wait— I had the beans. The way I keep track is—
         My oldest daughter, she was born in 1918, and she was a year old. Dad
         was working with the bean horse and my other boys and she was a year
         old— that'd be 1919 I had the good crop of beans, that I sold. And
         I got twenty-one hundred dollars for my share at seven and a half cents.
         Now, he could have got a thousand dollars for his. No, he didn't be
         cause he only got five cents, you see, so he lacked oh a couple or
         three hundred dollars of getting what he should have got. Well, any
         way, I got this done.
         
         This idea of speculating, if you look back at it, would you do better
         to sell right away,as soon as you get your crop in?
         I did— after that I did. Then, what I was going to tell you then—
         I think it was 19— Let's see, no. 1919 I had the big bean crop I sold.
         And then, anyway, in 1919; the bean crop, I sold. 1920 or '21, I can't
         remember for sure, that I got two and a quarter for the wheat. But I
         didn't have much yield. I only had sixteen bushel of that Marcus spring
         wheat, see.Ostlt was clean. Crawford, the warehouse on this side, was
         the man that give me the big offer. He said, "How much of this wheat
         you got?" I said, "I've a thousand and nineteen sacks, counting the
         Old Man's share. He gets a third of the wheat, see. "Well," he says,
         —wheat had been going two twelve, fourteen, sixteen, along there—
         
         SS:  I think you told me this.
         
         HR:  Yeah.
         
         SS:  You got good money.
         
         HR:  Yeah. So then, — "Now," he said, "it's been jiggling up and down,"
         he says, "How will two twenty strike you? "Fine," I says, 'Make it more
         if you want to." NO- let's see— now I got that mixed up— Yes, by
         gosh, it was two twenty. And the next day I come down and he says, "I
         understand the other warehouse is giving a little more." Oh, yeah,
         that's when he says, "How would two and a quarter strike you?" And so,
         that year I got good money on the wheat. Fifty-one hundred dollars!
         
         HR: But, Dad had to have hundred of that, you see. But that still
         didn't put me out of debt. Then I got fed up with wheat. I happened
         to have one sow in a half an acre lot, that used to be the old orchard,
         and I'd planted it to oats for pasture. We didn't have no alfalfa
         then. And I had a little barley. I ground the barley; rolled it, fed
         it to this sow and just crowded 'em, I wanted to see what I could do.
         And, by golly, in five months I had two hundred pound pigs. And I
         got to figuring on that. I said, "Jesus, that beats wheat all to
         pieces." Beat the price for raising wheat on that little lot of ground.
         "Man," I said,"I can just go into hogs, if I can get a building." Well,
         the first year I didn't. I used Dad's— he had a big machine shed and
         I made a mistake; two mistakes. One was, where the sows was penned
         off together, partitioned off, and I had one sow that would eat this
         other sow's pigs as fast as she hatched 'em, she cleaned up I think
         one sow's pigs, or damn near, before I caught on. Well, then another
         mistake I made that year was— The first year I was there we had cat
         tle, I sold them, though quit, couldn't get no place. So, I said—.
         The salt I put in this big cattle trough, see, rock salt, and melted,
         and the pigs'd come and drink that. And they died off like flies.
         Went down to the water pond and swelled up and busted. I didn't know
         what was going on. Nice, fat, pigs.
         
         SS:  Just from that salt?
         
         HR:  Yeah. One of the neighbors come along there and he says, "Helmer, I'll
         tell you what's the matter." I says, "What?" "We had a sow we fed some
         ice cream salt, brine," he said, " an hour or two after she drank that
         she bloated and died." He said, "That's your trouble, you got this
         salt trough here." He said, "If you get block salt it won't happen."
         Boy, that's when I got busy. Only had seventeen pigs left out of eighty-five little
         pigs, that first year. I mean, that's the second year
         after I one sow. Then I got busy. Boy, I said, That's no
         good." I wrote to my dad if he'd let me move a house he had on the
         back field, that Skelton place, where I had thebean crop. I said
         could I move that over? He wanted to know how I could do it. I said
         "I can do it."
         
         SS:  How did you do that? You started to tell me before.
         
         HR:  I done it. I got a stump puller down at this poor little neighbor,
         this poor little friend of mine that died last spring, Chuck Graham.
         His dad had a big Hercules stump puller, about this high,A His dad
         run a little sawmill up in the canyon there above Peck, besides he had
         a gristmill in Peck, where I get my flour ground. And he was a nice
         old man. Anyway, he says, "Go ahead and use it." I took it up there
         and borrowed another neighbor, two hundred foot cable; that's
         four hundred feet of cable; spliced 'em together.
         
         SS:  You had two hundred on the stump puller?
         
         HR:  No, two hundred foot cable. I had to dig three quarters of a mile
         through a field- I'll show you that field over here—
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         HR:  Three quarters of a milehad to dig every four hundred feet, log ten
         foot long, three foot in hardpan to anchor, don't you see? You didn't
         have to fill the hole up. You had to have that deep in order to hold
         it. And we never did let one slip, always had plenty of anchorage.
         
         SS:  How did those old stump pullers work?
         
         HR:  Well, you had a team with a sweep, and they pull that around, wind the
         cable right around the stump put And you hooked one end of the cable
         over there to your building; she started coming. Oh, was I feeling
         good. Didn't move fast. It took us about ten short days. We was ten
         because we only put in about five or six hours a day, 'cause we
         both had a lot of chores, late in the fall, in November; cold weather.
         Which I was glad of. I'd plowed this field, I was pulling right through
         this field that I'm gonna show you, three quarters of a mile, and I
         was just wishing I could get throughAbefore bad weather, cause that
         would have been a mess. Well, we did, we got it right down on some
         orchard grass, right by the pond, pretty close to where I wanted to
         set the house. And, I told my neighbor then, I said, "I can handle
         it now," I says. I knew there'd be a lot of work to it yet, butA all
         I had to do all winter, chores and that, that was my job. The reason
         I wanted it close to the pond, so I could have handy to water for the
         sows. Dad had a good pond, but he didn't have it good enough to suit
         me. One winter, when we had the cattle, my little brother, Joe, was
         with me and we had to drive our cattle three miles to get to water.
         That little pond that Dad had froze over, solid. But Rogerses had a
         great big pond and we drove our cattle down there. Once a day is all
         you could afford to do, it was cold weather and they'd drink good once
         a day and then fed 'em straw, see. And so, I said to Joe, "Next spring
         we're gonna fix that pond." I says, "I think I got an idea." You
         see, you had to dig down the ditch and fill it with clay to make it
         hold. And I ai|, "The water back into the field, but, " I says, "I
         don't care, I want water. I don't want this kind of a job no more."
         Which I did, I raised the bank up, see. I forget now, three or four
         feet.
         
         SS:  Just with clay?
         
         HR:  Well, no, first clay in next to the bank. About three or four foot
         wide bank, that'll hold the water, and then finish filling the curb
         that you had to have to fill your bank.
         
         SS:  What time of the year did you get this done?
         
         HR:  Oh, this was— we done that late in the fall when the pond was practically dry.
         
         SS:  Did that do it?
         
         HR:  You betcha. Instead of three feet of water in dry weather, I had sev
         en or eight feet of water. Nice clear water. Dad was smart enough
         to have a pipe to pipe it into the tank outside. Then we had another
         pipe from that down to the hog lot with floats in, don't you see. I
         didn't have to bother with the water for the sows after they got their
         little pigs and they got weaned and they got outside, they had the wa
         ter out there. All I had to do was feed 'em their grain.
         
         SS:  Did this clay come from the place there?
         
         HR:  Yeah, we just dug down, dug off the black dirt and down to clay and
         dug it out. By golly, it was work, but we did it.
         
         SS:  What did you use? Just use shovels?
         
         HR:  We had a team and what they call a slip. That's a two horse thing.
         They do have what they call a Fresno, four horse scraper. We had a
         two horse; little handier. You could handle it with two horses. You
         can do a lot of work with one of them, a couple of guys can. And get
         in narrower places, you see. And that's all you had to have was a
         little— and they were only about three feelh, something like that.
         And it's all one team can do to pull one of them when you fill it full.
         We filled that up— I mean I got that all fixed up. Then one year
         I was out of money— The year after I got this house put in, I had
         these fourteen sows; fourteen partitions in this house, see.
         
         SS:  I think you told me how the hogs made good then.
         
         HR:  Yeah, yeah, well, maybe you don't want that.
         
         SS:  Well, there's one thing I do want is— on moving that hog house how
         did you get the— how did you get it on skids? Was that a big job?
         
         HR:  Oh, no, we had to jack it up enough so we could work under that. And
         Dad had timber on the place, and I got a couple of big, bull pine trees
         peeled; green ones, they were slick. You see, you peel the bark off,
         and they would slip along easier. They'd wore off anyway, and I said
         "Peel 'em before we get 'em under there." God, I was young then!! I
         could work like a tiger. I was only— that was, you see, in 1923 and
         '24 let's see, '23, I was what? Thirty-five years old. And work
         didn;t amount to anything to me. I just worked my tailbone off on that
         ranch, but, I tell you, I made a go of it.
         
         SS:  Listen, why don't we go back and kind of start at the beginning and
         work out way up to here, and see it all as a picture? The whole thing.
         
         HR: Yeah, that's what I wanted to tell you. Yeah, I wanted to tell you
         when we first settled on the Ridge.
         
         SS:  Are you talking about Central Ridge?
         
         HR:  Yeah. Well, yeah, that's where we lived. That's where Dad homesteaded.
         Central Ridge. And, see, I was only eight years old when Dad moved
         over there.
         
         SS:  He moved from Park, did he?
         
         HR:  Yeah. With a wagon and cayuse team. Cayuse team. Got over onBear
         Ridge first day, and the next day, I think, got, as near as I can re
         member, either Cavendish or Peck. And when we got to Peck, we stayed
         there— we left all the family but me, I went with Dad. I was the
         oldest, but I was only eight years old. He took me along, anyway.
         And, God, there was no road up that mountain. You had to go right up
         that old ridge, the cayuses couldn't pull the whole wagon, so he just
         played smart. Dad was a good figurehead, he worked hard. Now if
         he hadn't had a little head on him, now, he wouldn't a done all that.
         Now, what he done, he put a pole in this hind wheels, you know that
         makes just like one cart. Hooked his horses on that, all he piled on
         that was just the cookstove and some dishes. A box of dishes and cookstove.
         We got to going up this mountain and it was so doggone steep
         some places, they couldn't pull it, see? Well, Dad unloaded the dishes
         and I guess he finally made 'em pull the stove a little ways, and then
         he went back and carried the dishes up. I was too little to help him,
         eight years old, you know. But he done all the work and I seen him do
         it.
         
         SS:  Was there even a track to follow up the hillside?
         
         HR:  No. We got up the hill, well, there was kinda what they call a saddle
         after you got about two-thirds of the way up the mountain, kind of a
         level spot, see. We rested there pretty good.
         
         SS:  No trail or nothin' up there?
         
         HR:  No nothin'! Just a mountainside. Just a hill- grade. I mean, we call
         it— I don't know what you would call it. Kind of a ridge. They did
         build a grade, later on, see. The farmers got together and cooperated
         and worked together, shovel and pick and maybe they had scrapers, I
         suppose they did, because it was quite a grade they made. About a three
         four mile see. Made switchbacks, on that grade. That was the old
         grade.
         
         SS:  So you rested two-thirds of the way up and then he ?
         
         HR:  Then when we got home— I was gonna tell you that— when we got home—
         He had a little cabin on the homestead. He'd been over here and homesteaded,
         filed on it, see. You see he had a little homestead in Park
         above where Granddad's place is, where Steiner lives now, but, he
         could relinquish - them days, you could relinquish— what they called
         relinquish. And he played smart— Oh, everybody in Park thought he
         was a fool, you know. Didn't figure he could make it. But he was
         smart enough that he took this place, it laid in the it was east
         and west there West, yeah, yeah. He got a eighty laying here,
         east and west and then anothere one over here, east and west. That
         forty joined — the east forty joined the west forty, see. So it
         laid in a Z. Well, this neighbors place that he bought, as I tell
         you that I raised the beans on was the thirty or forty acres that laid
         in between - in the corner of this Z. Filled his place out, see.
         Beside made a lot of pasture land down in the canyon. That place had
         a hundred and fifty, sixty acres on it.
         
         SS:  Well, why do you figure the east-west? Does that give 'em more ?
         
         HR:  Well, it was the best land, the way the land laid, in between this
         draw and the canyon.
         
         SS:  So, it was all on the ridge?
         
         HR:  That's the Ridge, it's called Central Ridge.
         
         SS:  Well, if he'd a took it the other way, you woulda gotten canyon.
         
         HR:  Oh, he wouldn't a gotten near the land that he got. No, you betcha.
         He played smart taking it like he did. And, anyway, he had this lit
         tle cabin built from these timber that was on there, you see, just
         pine logs. I think it was about eleven by twelve, something like that.
         And it didn't even have a door, just a hole, to jump in and out of.
         Just a dirt floor and he had some sourdough that he had made all ready
         to go, see. He had left that— I guess sourdough you can leave it
         tuite a while and it's still good, see. And he had a frying pan. And
         the only thing else we had to with was just some fat pork. flcDidn' t fry
         it very good. But, you know, when you get real hungry, it tastes pret
         ty good. And he was gonna be smart; "Now look," he says, "I'm gonna
         show you how I can flop 'em." He throwed it up liKe. that and it fell
         down in the dirt. We just brushed it off, it was good. Tasted good.
         But, I can remember that just like it happened yesterday. There I
         was, just a little eight year old kid, see. Well, another little job
         he had me doing,,. After he got established, he scratched up twelve
         acres of ground. He borrowed a neighbors horse, so he had three on
         a little fourteen inch plow, scratched this twelve acres up with. And
         he butchered a cow along in the winter, I guess, he didn't have hay,
         he had to butcher her, and kept part of the meat, just part of it, and
         he traded the rest for some seed to sow this ground the next spring.
         
         And the next year, he sold hay off of this piece of ground that he'd
         plowed up to help them along. And do you know how much he made in
         the harvest field, when he went out? He had to leave all of us there
         and no water at home; wasn't no water on the place. And left a horse
         there for us with a couple of syrup kegs on each side of him, and we
         had to go down the canyon where there was a spring and pack water up.
         And us little barefooted boys, that was our summer's job! And so,
         when he come home, of course, he 'd bought some shoes for us; I think
         it was a dollar or a dollar and a halfthose days. And, oh, us kids
         we was wild to get out and try them new shoes on. God, he'd come out
         there moonlight night and say, "You boys get in the house and take them
         shoes off, if you want to tear around, you save them for winter."
         Just that hard up. Well, I'll tell you, we had to obey him, little
         devils. Alright. And then the next year we got a little more ground
         plowed up so we had enough to sow flax. You know what flax is? And
         he was just lucky enough to get a good price for that flax. But,
         what I started to say, when he sowed that, he broadcast with his hand,
         that way, I was a little boy maybe ten years old then, had to go
         walk in his tracks so he could see how far he had to go away from it,
         see, you know what I mean? So he'd get it lapped just right. And
         he'd sow this early,,morning, about four o'clock before the breeze'd
         come up, cause that flax is light and the breeze'11 blow it. There
         I was, just trotting along barefooted and cold, .
         
         SS:  You would follow him?
         
         HR:  No, I'd go ahead of him.
         
         SS:  Oh, yes.
         
         HR:  He got a good job seeding that way. Later years, then, here's another
         improvement they made over that, or he got the idea. Somebody, I guess
         had done it, and he seen it. On these two hind wheels, that I was tel
         ling you about, that he'd fixed, you know.
         
         SS:  Locked.
         
         HR:  He put a tub - washtub- put grain in that and then he had me driving
         the team— No- had one of us boys driving the team, the other one on
         a pony out here riding the wheel tracks with a rope to the horses so
         they couldn't only be just so far, and, Dad, of course, he'd stand
         there and sow with both hands, broadcast bo-fch ways, and he could sow
         forty feet wide. He could sow forty acres a day that way.
         
         SS:  He'd stand in the back of the wagon?
         
         HR:  Stand in the back of the wagon; grab his wheat out of this, and go
         this way. Forty acre a day. Well, then, we had to harrow thatget
         it covered so it'd grow. Later years, then he finally got him a
         broadcast seeder. They got little shovels and there's only about
         eight or ten foot, and that didn't sow nearly as fast, but you could
         sow— oh, you had to go like the devil to sow twenty acres a day with
         that. Three horses I think's all that they put on that one.
         
         SS:  I asked you how much he made on harvest that first year and you didn't
         tell me. What happened in that first year of harvesting when he went
         out.
         
         HR:  Oh, I forgot that. Thirty-five dollars. That's what he got.
         
         SS:  How long did he go?
         
         HR:  Oh, God, not very long- well, that thirty-five dollars, hell the
         wages— well, of course, he was stacking, but I don't know if he
         stacked that year,, though. See, later years, when the farmers started
         to getting bigger fields and they found out Dad was a good stacker,
         gee, they hired him right and left. I had to go over and help him
         to pitch. When I was fifteen years old I took a man's place. Boy,
         I was out there pitching them big bundles on the stacks. And I'll
         show you the stacks right there—
         
         SS:  Did he work around Genesee or some place?
         Do you know where he went to work that year?
         
         HR:  Oh, Genesee country. They were more advanced, them farmers, see.
         
         SS:  How was it that your folks wound up leaving Norway and coming to Park?
         
         HR:  You mean my folks coming from Norway?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         HR:  Oh, yeah, see Dad was only five years old when the grandparents come
         over the ocean, see. And they settled in— Want me to tell where they
         settled?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         HR:  Well, they settled in Minnesota. And they stayed there a while. And
         Dad didn't get married until he was twenty-five, see. And so, he got
         to working out after he got to be quite a little man— young man, you
         know, and saving his money. Them days people would save their money
         better'n they do nowdays. Well, they had to. And Granddad had hauled
         oak poles. I think he said nine miles, Dad told me. With oxen. He
         didn't have much transportation. With oxen, see. And they stayed
         there, and they had bad luck. But, Dad was smart, he was working out
         for wages; he wasn't farming. Didn't get big wages, but he kept sav
         ing what he could, see.
         
         SS:  They had bad luck with the oxen?
         
         HR:  No. No. They had bad luck with the crops. That's what I wanted to tell
         you, later. Maybe I shouldn't tell you about this hard luck he had
         getting his wood. He said they'd start at nine o'clock in the morning
         and him and his buddy, he was a husky man, Old Granddad- he lived to
         be ninety-seven. The sickest he ever "saw, he stayed with us one yearone
         winter- over there in Park when we was on the Conn place- and
         coming up walking, "Helmer1,1 he says,— couldn't talk very plain- "You
         will haul the logs down here, I will cut 'em up. Split 'em up, carry
         the wood in." Them days, we burned wood, see. Cookstove and all.
         "Well." I said, "Granddad," I said, "I did have a tree climber." You've
         those "tree climbers woodsaws, ain't you? I traded a gangplow that I'd
         bought fromARidt fellow over at Park, traded even up. So I had
         this gas woodsaw, and there was a great, big tree up on the mountain
         side there. "Granddad, if I cut this big log I can't snake it down,"
         I said, "but I'll saw the blocks up and bring them down to you, and
         you split 'em up." "Oh, yes, dat be alright," he said. But he did
         saw the little logs. He was smart enough to roll it up on skids, see,
         and he'd stand straight. And I could file a saw because I'd learnt
         that when I was cutting cordwood the first year we's married in Orofino,
         1914. That's how I made my living that winter, cutting cordwood. A
         dollar and a quarter a cord.
         
         SS:  Your grandfather, he was pretty old then?
         
         HR:  Well, he was about as old as Steiner is now, about eighty-five or six
         year old. But, hell, he was a husky. God, he was out there working
         like that, see
         
         SS:  Right when he was that old?
         
         HR:  Yeah. And I felled this tree and knocked down five others, as luck
         would have it, the little ones got in the way, see. But it made it
         nice. They laid on the hill like that and the upper part of the tree
         the stump part laid up the hill and I could move my saw down the hill
         see. And I hauled the blocks down. Oh, he was tickled. Oh, hell,
         they was four or five feet in diameter, great, big, blocks. But it
         made good cook wood. It was yellow pine.
         
         SS:  Okay, but you were talking about him and his logging when he was a
         young man, himself.
         
         HR:  No. Yeah, I am getting too far ahead. Now, we jumped from Minnesota
         to Park. Okay, we'll finish Minnesota, now. The way it was, he got
         his wood that way, him and his brother, Throwen , he called him,
         they would go out there and he said they could saw— No, they didn't
         saw them days, they just chopped— that oak was hard to saw and them
         saws they had them days,wasn't a good saw, it was just a - like a hand
         saw, no drag to it. So they made headway by chopping- he was a very
         good axeman, oh, God, they chopped four cords— 'course that'd be
         four foot lengths. Said they could make four cords in a day; go there
         and come back. Took 'em six hours, see, to do all that and make that
         nine mile trip. That was agoing some, they had to go like the devil
         to doaAL and make all that trip, nine miles. I don't know how they
         done it, but he claims he done it. And, so, they were farming there
         for four or five years. Two years, I think it was, they had hail
         storms; either two years, either hail storms or three years hail storms
         and visa versa, grasshoppers. Five years of hard luck. And Dadhe
         had enough money saved up that I guess he could move all of 'em;
         grandparents and all over to Park. And this Granddad of mine, of
         course, he was a husky and he'd go out in the harvest field, too. And
         he was a good stacker. That's how he come to make a go of it. Every
         summer he'd come out here to Genesee country and stack grain for the
         people. And in the winter he would,and split shakes, that's what Ed
         was telling about, how he carried them shake blocks, you remember?
         They didn't have horses, they made snowshoes to walk on top of the
         snow. Split them shakes, see.
         
         SS:  He did that in Park?
         
         HR:  Yeah, that was in Park. Now you would think that a man wouldn't go
         across an old canyon- there wasn't no grade there- but he just loved
         that country. What he was after; the timber. He got all that cold
         stuff in the East, no timber close, you see. He wanted to get where
         there was plenty of timber close, and besides the water. He was
         smart enough to find a good spring on that place and it's still there.
         Water and wood. He had her made.
         
         SS:  Do you know where it was in Minnesota, more or less, where they were?
         
         HR:  It was close to Minneapolis. Let's see, what do they call that? Yeah,
         I believe was their closest place. Let me look at my
         birth certificate. - Looky there, I got it on carpentry, by God,
         I took up welding first and I only lasted on it— I mean it got the
         best of me—Here it is, here it shows, Swift Falls, Minnesota. That's
         what I tried to think of.
         
         SS:  Did your grandfather ever talk to you about why it was that he left
         Norway and come to Minnesota?
         
         HR:  God damn, they'd starve to death back there. Yep, they had what they
         called-- that's how,Dad come to get the name. Dad's name was Swenson
         too. But Dad.a little bit better than the rest of 'em, a
         little more brainy, I guess they'd call it, He went, and he was all fh-
         time reading. He hadn't got much education, but, by God, he read.
         And he took up— down on the Ridge he got the idea that the farmers
         should organize and start a Farmers' Mutual Fire Insurance Company
         of their own, which Dad started,, in Nez Perce County. See what I mean?
         That's what he started, and he'd go canvassing around and he left us
         boys to do the farming. He give us all just what to do. Well, he
         kept us together, five of us boys, after Mother died. She died in
         1901. Seventy-five years ago.
         
         SS:  So this was a cooperative with all the farmers?
         
         HR:  Dad organized it that way. And he said like this, he only charged
         a dollar and a half a policy, but, they would be assessed according
         to whatever loss there was. Like if there was a hundred farmers—
         we'll illustrate— a hundred farmers belonged: alright, if one poor
         fellow lost say five thousand dollars by fire, these other farmers'd
         club together and pay that loss. And that a lot cheaper way of getting
         along than it was to goto these big companies. That company
         now, of course, is inbig hands now. Somebody got wise and made a
         little more money on it and kept fooling the poor farmers and she's
         big cooperative now, you know.
         
         SS:  Well what did it have to do with him changing his name?
         
         HR:  Well, that's what I wanted to tell you. Dad's— after he got brother
         Edward and brother Gilbert, both moved over there, and Granddad, that's
         three Swensons, and is four. And his mail'd get mixed
         up pretty bad, don't you see. This mailcarrier'd put his mail - Dad's
         mail,— and so Dad wanted — this was the old name, I mean, the name
         of the old place, only it had an "r" on it, Ringsager (gives the Nor
         wegian pronounciation) that's acreage. And so, of course, he had to
         pay for it. He went to Lewiston, County Seat, and it cost him forty
         dollars. But, us boys could change our name before we had real estate.
         And the first year we went to school in Spokane, like I told you, get
         ting that college— there I didn't finish that— I was twenty-two,
         Steiner was twenty. We finished the seventh and eighth grades in eight
         months. The longest term we ever had. We had a private teacher. And
         I never knew grammar in my bones till she illustrated it and I could
         understand it.
         
         SS:  Was there somebody ? (noisy)
         
         HR:  Oh, I wouldn't know that. Oh, they probably read papers or news gets
         around. Hard to tell how they found that out. But, anyway, that's
         about how old he was. They had lived in Minnesota about— what did I
         say?
         
         SS:  Twenty-three years.
         
         HR:  Twenty-three years. So they struggled there for quite a. while, you see.
         But the last five years was the worst, that's when they had that tough
         time, and convinced 'em to get out of there, I guess.
         
         SS:  You said that people were starving in Norway. People were really starving?
         
         HR:  Well, I don't know. They just wanted to get out. They had no future.
         You know what Norway is, little old strip of land along the— That's
         where Granddad got the habit of eating He could eat the fattest
         fish and pork. He could eat boiled fat pork He'd got that habit, see.
         But, Uncle Ed, his youngest son said that he musta had a good bile, or
         whatever you call it, that digests that
         
         SS:  Okay, when your father got to Park, did they take a homestead there?
         
         HR:  They took a little homestead above of where Grandpa's is; right above
         him, in the lower edge of that mountain.
         
         SS:  Do you remember about that?
         
         HR:  No, I don't remember that time.
         
         SS:  It was before .
         
         HR:  Much. Everything was after we moved to the Ridge, see.
         
         SS:  Why was it that f decided to go to the Ridge and leave Park?
         
         HR:  Well, Jesus Christ, a big prairie land instead of that old brush land?
         Who wouldn't? Wouldn't you do it? Would you do it?
         
         SS:  Sure. There wasn't no timber on top of that Central Ridge?
         
         HR:  Oh, yes, we had timber in that little draw there, yes, for firewood
         that's all we wnated. The rest of the land was all a hundred and sixty
         acres of farm land.
         
         SS:  You mean it was prairie land before he found it?
         
         HR:  Prairie land is what it was. It was the Nez Perce Indian Reservation.
         Got opened up; there was a while that wasn't opened up for nothin,',
         see; for settlement. And the government allowed 'em to get a homestead
         free; no charge. All they had to do was improve it. Get on there and
         plow it up and make something out of it. By golly, my little old
         daddy did, besides making us little devils help him. And that was al
         right. He made men out of us. Well, than, you see, they got there
         and, oh, Dad— I didn't tell you about that— I don't know whether you
         want to put all that down in or not— but, see, on the Ridge then when
         we got to going, he started raising horses, that's where he made his
         money. Them days everything was farmed horses. And, boy, he had
         awful good luck with horses. He'd have four, maybe six colts sometimes.
         And he'd sell 'em to farmers that didn't raise them. And they brought
         all the way from two hundred and fifty to three hundred dollars a horse,
         them days. If it hadn't a been for that horse raising he never would
         a got any place. The grain wasn't much, he just fed that doggone stuff
         to the horses and made money on the horses. That's where he used his
         head, going into horses, til machinery, of course, then when I got to
         farming that was clear out. Everybody started putting in machinery.
         I farmed with horses.
         
         SS:  How come these other folks in Park thought he was crazy to go to—
         
         HR:  Well, dammit, they just couldn't see the future over there, like Dad
         did, see. Naw, my uncle— two uncles on my mother's side- Steiner
         was one of 'em he joined this Granddad place, one forty of his, joined
         on the north— his north forty, he took his land north and south,
         this uncle, he had a nice place. It was really the best place in Park,
         almost. Laid a lot of it level, but it was a little bit on the wet
         side; swampy. But it was nice and level. And, you see, whoever come
         in there first got their choice, you might say on them homesteads, just
         like they did over on the Ridge.
         
         SS:  I heard,Ed Swenson told me, that there was one guy that they called
         a land grabber. One guy there that took a lot of good land in the bot
         tom.
         
         HR:  Well, I don't know who that would have been at the time. Let's see-
         
         SS:  Oh, it doesn't matter.
         
         HR:  Well, I'll tell you, they sold out, but they couldn't homestead more
         than one quarter, you know. That's all they could do.
         
         SS:  Well, I guess from what you're telling me that Park just didn't have
         the potential that other places had.
         
         HR:  Oh, yeah, that's just a small place compared to— well , it isAon the
         Central Ridge, when you get up to Nez Perce, there is all that Craigmont
         country. That spreads out wider, then there's another ridge to
         the east of where we lived, called Russell Ridge, another one to the
         west called Melrose Ridge, and then another little ridge down beyond
         that, north of it, called Angel Ridge. And then, here I wanted to tell
         you how Dad started, getting that flax out. There was no railroad
         at Peck, Idaho for several years. But his flax— delivering it to Kendrick,
         he got two and a quarter or two and a half a bushel. But he
         couldn't haul much, he only had twocayuses to haul with. A wagon was
         pretty near a load, cause they had to go up that— they went down to
         Peck, up the Sunnyside, Clearwater side, on top of big Potlatch, down
         to Kendrick and that Kendrick grade to get to the Kendrick warehouse.
         It took him pretty near a week to make one trip! Now can't you imagine
         that Dad was struggling? So, by God, he had to have a lot of guts to
         do all that. Not only guts, but strength. I said,"A man doing all that,"
         I said, "He was alone." Then he had to do all the WA work, we kids
         wasn't big enough, at that time. My God, he was krejffkt boy. I tell
         you he was Srlita. Then, to do his harvesting, all he had was a six
         foot binder, with three horses on it, that pulled it, and heone old
         mare so goldang old that every time he'd hit her, you know, she'd speed
         up a little bit and then she'd stutter, brrrrrr—. (Chuckles) Oh,
         Dad'd come in and it'd be hot, But as luck would have it, you know,
         they'd learnt to keep cows. And do you know what he done? He'd come
         to get something to drink that was quenching, got over to the pan of 
         sour milk, clabbered milk, and drank.AThen when us boys got big enough
         to do the shocking we had to get out and shock up the bundles. After
         Mother died, let's see that was— I was thirteen, fourteen years old,
         you betcha— we shocked them, we was working like mad. See. I was
         plowing when I was eleven years old. a. I plowed that whole ranch for
         three or four years, til I was about sixteen, before he got a gangplow.
         I couldn't drive four horses, see before that. But I practiced driv
         ing these four horses because he had me go down and water his horseshe'
         d go out and harness 'em, see, and feed 'em early in the morning
         before breakfast and then come in and get his breakfast while I'd go
         out there and hitch 'em up for him. Well, I thought, "Here's a good
         chance to drive four horses." They wasn't hooked onto anything, I'd
         get 'em watered, hitch 'em up and I'd practice pulling the lines of
         this horse and that horse. Pretty soon I got confidence in myself, I
         told Dad, I says, "You can get a gangplow now," I says, "I can drive
         four horses." He says, "Do you think you can?" I says, "You betcha,
         I can handle 'em on the gangplow." And sure enough, he did. I set
         the plow around this big field, half a mile long, you know. Oh, it
         was a nice field. And got into straw bottom.
         
         SS:  A what?
         
         HR:  Straw bottom. And I let the old plow plug up. I learned something
         then. Boy, I didn't go close to a straw bottom any more. (Chuckles)
         And another thing, I could ride that thing, see. That was easy work.
         The only work I had was to harness the horses.
         
         SS:  This straw bottom?
         
         HR:  You see, the cattle would eat it down and it'd be piled up— tromped
         down two or three feet of it, and that's what I thought I'd go through.
         I mean, go over it. I figured I'd go over it. It didn't go over it,
         it grabbed it and plugged it up is what it done. So then I stayed
         shy of it, I went around it.
         
         SS:  You were doing all this work with a walking plow, that's because you
         
         HR:  Well, that was when I was eleven til I was sixteen— fifteen, or six
         teen.
         
         SS:  Now, why did you do this? Was that because your dad was out selling
         
         HR:  Well, he was probably out canvassing, yeah. He was out canvassing, or
         maybe fencing the place. He had to fence the place all by himself.
         Make his timber, posts. That's what I told Steiner, he thinks he's
         doing something. I said, "Listen, Steiner, Jesus Christ, you got a
         little old dinky eighty acres, and you've got it all fenced in for years
         Poor Daddy had to fence all that and I was the instigator to coax him
         to put hog wire on, and he never raised a hog in his life." Hadn't a
         been he had that hog wire on that I probably wouldn't a raised hogs,
         but because he had it I got the idea and went in there and raised 'em
         and made money. The first year, I told you, I didn t make any. The
         second year, '23, that's the time I want to tell you about. 1923, yeah,
         that's the first year, I had good luck. Fourteen sows brought me a
         hundred and nine pigs.
         
         SS:  Now, you told me that.
         
         HR:  Well, I saved them— I saved a hundred and five, but I had to bor
         row five hundred dollars to feed 'em over til my grain was threshed.
         Did I tell you that?
         
         SS:  Yeah. Yeah.
         
         HR:  You got that? Well, that was it. And then, the next year I didn't
         have such good luck, you know. But, as I said, that last year, that's
         when I borrowed that— you see on summer fallow I had half corn,half
         peas, and I would hog the peas first, cause they'd come on first, and
         then soon as they were done, by that time the corn would be plenty ripe
         and the pigs'd go right into it. By then the place was hog tight, I'd
         just turn the hogs loose. ( hey had to come over to the pond to get
         their water, but that's all they had to do, go over and back and fill
         up and.maybe the middle of the day was hot, they'd come and drink up
         and then along in the evening go out and fill up again. Hell, it work
         ed slick. And so, that year, as I said though, I didn't have quite
         as many. I only had, instead of a hundred and five, I saved, I think
         it was about eighty-five pigs. And I let the brood sows run in with
         the fattening hogs and they got too fat, so they didn't have good luck
         with their pigs. But I did save that many and the price come up. The
         first year that I borrowed the five hundred dollars, only got six and
         a half cents a pound.
         
         SS:  But this next year the price came up?
         
         HR:  The next year the price come up. The first half I sold, I got eight
         and a half cents and the other half, you see, you couldn't sell 'em
         all at the same time, because some of 'em didn't mature quite as good.
         And the other half I got ten and a half. Well, that brought me fortyfour—
         I mean, put me out of debt. I was in debt forty-two hundred
         dollars, besides I had a little money left to live on. And I told Dad
         what the banker and all said, and he said, "You just getting a good
         start. You're doing fine." I'd paid the bank up and I was able to
         pay Dad up and I said, "I want to get out. I've been there seven
         years struggling like mad." And I was just about petered out. I didn't
         weigh over a hundred thirty, or forty pounds. I'll tell you why, the
         missus was sick that spring and I had that last summer fallow that I
         was telling you about—wouldn't a got anything off a that ground, didn't
         get it planted— plowed early— it dried up in May. Well, his name
         is Wesley Thomas, John, I called him.at Deary, he was living on his
         Dad's place— or his uncle's place, Wesley Thomas was his uncle's name.
         And he had this steel roller patent, and I got the idea then that
         this ground was so bad, that it plowed up, great big chunks, and I had
         a double disc, seven horses on it— that's what I had to farm with, so
         I could plow the ground, it was dry, see. And that would chop the
         clods up, but it didn't pack it the way I wanted it, 'cause I wanted
         to put peas in, and you gotta have the ground in good shape for peas
         and corn. And it was so dry. Along about the twelfth of May, and I
         got over to Tom, said, "How about hiring your roller?" "Go ahead and
         take it. I'm throughth it." See, he'd got his crop all in. So I
         went and used it and I just rolled it, packed it, then I'd disc it,
         and harrow it and pack it again, and I just had that doggone ground
         just packed and worked up and it looked pretty good. Did the best I
         could, 'fnen I planted my peas and my corn. Took til the Fourth of
         July for any of that to come up. And I thought, "Well, gee whiz, if I
         get something I'll be lucky." No rain! But there was moisture in
         the bottom. That land was rich, and in the winter it would absorb,
         in the winter
         this subsoil below would hold it, if there was enough moistureto go
         down. You see, I had plowed— no, by God, that summer before, I hadn't
         plowed— I generally did plow my ground in the fall, but hadn't got
         around to it. I was too busy, for some reason. Froze up or something.
         And there, that spring, I had two mares gonna foal and my wife was sick
         abed. Wheee. She brought birth to a dead baby boy, ten pounds, and
         pretty near died with him.
         
         SS:  And a neighbor family and their kids were giving you trouble.
         
         HR:  You want that?
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         HR:  Well, that's the reason I moved. One of the reasons, not altogether.
         No, no. But, I told Dad9 Bloojmirst was their name— they lived- see,
         he bought Uncle Ed's place. That was the dirty trick that Ed done to
         sell out to that old— that's what made it bad. He had two mean boys,
         and they was torturing my boy t. Not only that, but, when Dad and I had
         these cattle, and Dad had more pasture land along the road than he did,
         he only had a little strip there from our corner fence up to the hill
         wasn't over hardly a quarter of a mile of pasture land, and Dad had
         that Z all along the north side there; lot of pasture land. Well, I
         asked Mr. Bloopurst, I said,, down on the grade. His boys'd been dog
         ging my cattle and I didn't like that idea.
         
         SS:  Dogging the cattle?
         
         HR:  Sic the dogs on 'em, run 'em away, over the hill. Jesus
         Christ, I wasn't gonna put up with that. And I was a young man, boy,
         I wouldn't take nothin' from none of 'em. I was gonna have my rights.
         So, I met old Julian down, - I mean he was in the stock business down
         below. He had a little ranch down in the canyon, Shaw place, they cal
         led it, and he was there digging out the road for hisself to get up
         off the grade, after the new grade was made.A So, "Julian," I says,
         "how about us making an agreement about not dogging our cattle?" I
         said. "Alright, Julian, I like to be neighborly," I says, "let's get
         along," I says, "keep them boys from dogging my cattle," I said, "I
         don't like that. Some of my cows is heavy with calf. And you wouldn't
         like it," I says, " if I was out there dogging your cattle. Would you?"
         Well, that didn't do a bit of good. Them kids kept it up dogging, dog
         ging. And, Jesus, one Sunday it happened. This man that was in the
         warehouse business, Guernsey, had married a cousin, his, wife's cousin, lol.
         see what I mean; they was related that way.A They tried to buy Dad s
         place one time. So, I sure fixed him once. I was telling Dad about
         how— I says,"I'm gonna go over the hill and get my cattle back, but
         first," I says, "I'm going to stop and see him." And he happened to
         be out there by the house washing his face, wiping his face with a
         towel. I seen another man there, and I couldn't hold myself, I wasn't
         scared ."Julian," I says, "come down here, I want to see you a minute."
         "Alright," he says. I says, "Julian, what do you mean," I said, "by
         golly, I asked you nicely the other day," I said, "to be neighbors and
         try and get your boys to quit dogging my cattle." "By God, we'll
         settle that right now," he said. He jumped over the fence. "Good,"
         I said. I jumped off my horse. 
         
         He called me liar about then, Bango!
         I whanged him! I grabbed him,. I could see the other feller coming down
         and I grabbed him around the neck,, and I said, "Goddam you," I said,
         I'm gonna fix you right, if that's the kind of a neighbor you are, we'll
         really have it." Guernsey come down, of course, he was a friend of
         mine, and his wife come down and she says, "I don't think it's nice
         for two neighbors to be fighting." "No," I said, "I tried to avoid it,
         but what you gonna do," I says, "when a neighbor— I don'.t call that,
         a neighbor. I says, "Your boys have been fighting my cattle all the
         time," I says, "that's not fair." "I didn't do that, my boy didn't
         do that, and they been picking on the boy besides, at school. They
         take his hat and rub it in horse manure and everything else. Two of
         'em," I says. " Older and stronger. It just ain't gonna work." And
         he's the very man that I got to help me move, see. He got good after
         that. After he found out that I was a man of my word he got neighborly.
         I made a neighbor out of him.
         
         SS:  So, was that the end of the fight?
         
         HR:  Oh, yeah. Well, wait, not right then. "Let me up, let me up" I let
         him up. Then he thought he was gonna be smart, he thought he was gonna
         grab me by the legs, see; well, when he stooped down to get my legs, I
         grabbed him again around the neck, like that, and I held him. I was
         just choking the shit out of him. I said, "The next time I catch you
         out," I says, "you ain't agoing to last long." Old Guernsey, of course
         standing there, he says— ? -"after the first
         of July," or something like that. I says, "That remains to be seen,"
         I says. noisy — unless something drastic happened,
         see.
         
         SS:  What were you saying about renting pasture land?
         
         HR:  No. This was road pasture, see. But you know, that little struggle I
         had with him then, I guess is what started him to - he took a cow of
         mine down to his his bench. And I got the hunches, you know, the kids
         was fooling around there all the time, and I happened to open up this
         pond, because the water was getting so low it didn't run in the trough,
         and that was over there by that place that Dad bought where this house
         I moved was- I got a hunch, it's funny how you get hunches, that Sun
         day morning. I got to thinking about that pond being open, I says,
         "Say, you know, I got a bad hunch. I wonder if I hadn't better go over
         and see about them heifers." If they're down in that pond— I had my
         horses and my cattle running loose in the field, see. And I got the
         hunch that if them heifers got in there and the horses got in there,
         they could hurt it, maybe kill it. And, I said to the woman; she was
         husky then, "You walk the south side, and I'll take Barney and ride
         around on the north side and see if I can spot the cattle. Get 'em all
         gathered together, and see if everything's alright." And I got around
         by the barn, and this cow that had a bell, we had a great, big bell,
         you could hear it for a mile off, see, and that very cow that he had
         drug down there the day before, left. I seen the missus, I said,
         "Well," I says, "I found," let's see what was it we called her? Daisy,
         I think, because she had a white strip backline, besides she was shak
         ing the bell and I knew darned well she was there, the sound of that
         bell. 
         
         That give her away, see. "Oh, I says, I found it." She says,
         I found a place where it looked like some cow'd been drug through the
         fence here, on the south side." I said, "You did?" Went down there
         and looked, I followed them tracks right around that trail over to
         where we joined fence. Hog wire and all, he'd torn that down and led
         her into— he'd plowed his field there and showed the tracks,
         "Oh, good," I said, "now I know what I'll do. I'll just take old Barney
         and ride down there and get the cow." So, I got around by the house.
         And he was road boss. He'd been dragging the road, fresh tracks. You
         could track fresh tracks, see, because the road was drug that evening
         before, Saturday. Sunday morning these fresh tracks showed and he
         had another cow to go with him; two cows. And I had the boy behind aod
         the saddle on my horse, 'cause I wanted him to kinda-d''" ' 
         to have him chase the cow along. Got down to where I turned off to
         go down— see, our place run clear down, this corner, this new place
         that Dad bought, just like this, and he had his Ki-Wi right across the
         fence from us. But this was our land here. And there he laid, behind
         a great, big boulder on my land.
         
         SS:  The cow?
         
         HR:  No. No. The man. He raised his head up when he seen me turn off the
         grade to go down the trail to meet him. He got leery then, you see.
         I got down there, and see— he knew I was a better man already, be
         cause I'd a had hold of him. I said, "Julian, what the hell do you
         mean, take my cattle down here like this?" See, he'd butchered cattle
         right along for neighbors around there, but nobody could catch him. I
         was the slicker smart enough to get next to him. So then,-
         
         SS:  You called him on it?
         
         HR:  Oh, yeah. I called him, I was getting close, I was getting pretty mad.
         I Goddam near crawled his frame, but the two boys that was behind there
         they was either hunting birds, or making a camouflage shot, see, they
         was shooting a gun over the stacks. Of course, there were birds— there
         were trees up on the bench there, I thought they mighta been hunting
         them and shooting at them. But, anyway, it was a lucky thing, because,
         if I'da beat up on their dad there, and them kids come around with a
         gun, no telling what they wouldn't do. So, I just held off and I told
         him. I cussed him out. "Julian, Goddam you," I says, "keep your fingers out of the
         pie, or else you're gonna get burnt, and burnt bad."
         So, when I started back with the cow, you know. "Wait a minute." He
         got friendly right away, he knew better.. I made that man know, by God,
         I wash4-: a perfect fool. So, he says, "Wait a minute, I'll help you
         drive 'em up." I says, "No, the boy'11 take it alright." So, we did,
         I and the boy made it. But I got so mad that I went clear to Nez Perce
         to talk to a lawyer. And he had had law trouble with this big cattle
         man up the canyon, Old Sullivan But old had played smart, he took
         a picture. He had a cow just like I had, a muley cow that had a star
         in the forehead, and not only that but, Sullivan had played smart, he
         was a big farmer, and he was going to catch whoever was a doing it. He
         did, too. But, this dang Bloorst had a friend that was running a
         moonshine still, that was going to be the witness for Julian, and he
         had told him thathe was going to squall to 'em on the moonshine still.
         So that's what the lawyer told me, he says, "Hell," he says, "Old Sul
         livan was mad enough," he said, "when we's atalking here in the office,
         that he just picked up a chair, and if it hadn't abeen for me, he'd a
         whammed him over the head."
         
         SS:  So did he beat the rap?
         
         HR: Well, I told him, this lawyer, "By God," I said,— "Well," he said,
         "where you made your mistake, you got too mad. you should a got your
         neighbors." "Neighbors," I said, "they're scared to death of that man.
         They don't want nothin' to do with that kind of a deal," I said, "and
         I couldn't expect 'em to. That's the reason I come to see you." "Well,"
         he says, "you can't do nothing. Sullivan tried it," he said, "that
         witness of his, got him bluffed out, because he was running that still,
         and he didn't come," he said, "Bfrootfwurst got away with it. But he
         probably learned a lesson." "By God, he'll learn a lesson from me, if
         I have to beat the hell right out of him," I said. "By God," he said,
         "I admire you." I said, "Boy, I tell you, I hate to do it, but if a
         man gets as Goddamn stubborn as that, I'm willing to fights my rights."
         And, by God, from then on, that man, he was put agin it, he only had
         that hundred acres of farm land. He didn't have no machinery to cut
         that grain, and he found out that I was a man of my word. He come over
         there one day, he said, "By golly, Helmer, I'd like to get somebody to
         cut my grain. Could I shock for you," he said, "then you cut my grain?"
         I had bought a secondhanded eight foot binder, see, and I had four
         good horses on it. "Yeah," I said, "Julian, I want to neighbor, God
         damn it, if you want to neighbor. I'll forget the past." If he'd just
         behave himself. 1 saiJP, "Yeah, you bet," I said, "that's fine." Well
         we agreed that it was a dollar and a quarter an acre for cutting, and
         two and a half a day for shocking, and that way he got his grain cut
         and I got my grain shocked, til it was paid up, see, whatever it took.
         And the neighbors, I didn't tell you that— Along in the fall,—when
         I had this crop of beans, see, just before that, he was sewing sacks,
         this Bloodwurst was— And a young fella there by the name of, Hunter, 
         Louie. was sewing sacks. They kidded him, see, for letting an old
         man like— young little pup like me get the best of him. And then
         they just razzed him, you know. "By God," he says, "he's a powerful
         little devil, I'll tell you that." Well, this made this young Louie
         Hunter get smart, see. He's big, he's a bigger man than I was, he
         weighed a hundred and eighty-five pounds. He was just husky enough
         that he could pick me up like that—'cause I only weighed a hundred
         and thirty-five pounds then, I was lightbut I was all muscle. "Haw,
         haw, haw," stood there laughing, like I was nothin', then he dropped
         me down to his feet. Just the minute he dropped me to his feet, I just
         throwed my arms around his legs and I set him on his ass, CABANG!
         Jesus, he lit harder'n I did. 
         
         Then he got up, see. And boy, he got
         me. He'd get me here and then he'd on me. He was pretty Stout.
         By God, I was just stout enough, I backed him around, clear over to
         the south feeder, you know. And some of them guys that was feeding
         there, Old Tom Smith, he was a friend of mine, farmer, we'd exchange
         work together, he was a very nice man. And, I says, "Louie, get out
         here in the field where we got a lot of room." "Alright',' he says.
         We got out there, and Goddamn, I scuffled around that old son of a bitch,
         and he started, huh, huh, huh; he was panting, you know, about all in
         and I was still good. I had good lungs, Goddamn, I coulda wrestled all
         day. He says, "By God," he says, "let's quit." I says, "Whatever you
         say," I says, "Godammit, if you want to keep on, we'll keep on a while."
         If I'd a kept on five more minutes, I'd a had him. He was just big
         enough that he could keep me away, see, powerful enough. He come back
         to the sack pile and start sewing, you know. And old Bloodwurst said,
         "By God, I told him you was a powerful man? (Chuckles) Well, then,
         wait now, - when I was a hauling grain down at Peck— now that was a
         brother-in-law to this Louie Huf, Frank .liftvC . He was a big huskyhe
         was big enough that he could just wipe the earth with me, you know.
         He'd been kind of a bully, and rich, too. And he come up to me, I
         was standing there watering the horses, there at Peck. "Hey, Helmer,"
         he says, "I got a notion," he says, "to push you in the water trough.
         I put Old Man Bloodwurst, Julian's dad in there." And I said, "By God,
         Frank," I said, "don't spoil a good notion. Never let something like
         that pass. Help your self..I guarantee you'll go in with me." He
         shut up. We were friends. He found out I could saw— I mean file a
         saw, 'cause I'd learnt that when I was cutting cordwood, see in 1914
         the second year we was married. 
         
         And so I could make a saw bring the
         shavings out, see. And they couldn They couldn't fix their saw to,
         cut. And we neighbored back and forth. And his daddy, there's a fine
         old man, Doug Hunter, and I'd went to school with his wife, you know
         all of Doug Hunter's children, and we'd went to school and all neighborly. "Yeah,"
         I said, "I'll fix your saws." "Well," he said, "I was
         just thinking, why don't you skid up some of them little bull pines
         you got," he said, "and make quite a skidway," he says, "and,we'll do
         the same, and then we'll all get together and help each other saw."
         "Good, Frank," I says, "that's fine." So that's what we did. And I
         said, "Frank,now listen, look at your daddy-in-law,"— And this Louie
         was just a small boy then, hadn't growed up yet. They were standing
         there just like this with little short strokes. "Well, Frank," I said,
         "let 'er go full length. And I'll bet you we'll beat 'em. It's easier."
         And we did. I said, "I'll bet you," I said, "I can saw with any one
         guy," I said, "that does that short stroke and beat 'em." And, I said,
         "You could, too." They found that out, and boy, that just changed ev
         erybody's gait, don't you see. Well, we got along, I filed the saws,
         sawed our wood. I helped saw theirs and they helped saw mine. We just
         had a big picnic time of it.
         
         SS:  Do you think that time that guy was gonna throw you in the watering
         trough, do you think that was because you had been fighting with his
         cousin?
         
         HR:  No, because he was teasing me because I'd got the best of Bloodwurst,
         see. And he got good, and they was gonna try to get— see if they
         could irritate me to start something, don't you see? They thought they
         would. By God, I just backed 'em. When he got that smart, see, I said,
         "By God, don't spoil a good notion."
         
         SS:  Let me ask you one more thing about Bloodwurst there, that time that
         he took your cattle down there, that he led your cow down there and
         got 'em in there.
         
         HR:  Oh, he done that in the night, probably or early morning.
         
         SS:  What was his thinking? What do you think he had in mind?
         
         HR:  Well, God only knows. 'Cause I tell you, — here I got to tell you
         another place that he done for me that summer. There was three of
         my cattle disappeared, somewhere. And I just knew where they went.
         See, what they'd done, between him and Sam Porter, Sam Porter lived
         on, over on Russell Ridge, just above Peck, I mean, but it was Russ/f
         Ridge, you might say. It was off of Russell Ridge, and they
         would transfer— Julian would catch cattle over here and during the
         night bring 'em over there and he'd get 'em take 'em on, and they'd
         go maybe to Kamiah or some place else. Hide 'em somewhere. And an
         ordinary guy'd have a hell of a time them days to find 'em. Well, I
         just got that damn smart one morning, I told the miss scatch up with
         this son of a bitch, somehow. And I had a double barrel— not a double
         barrel, but a repeater shotgun, Dad's old shotgun.. "I'll pretend I'm
         going bird hunting, and','1 said,"I'11 go along the breaks of the can
         yon , over to this Shaw place." Where PIcoctMfst was, and I only
         had to go about a half or three quarters of a mile to get down to it
         from the top of the hill. And, I went down there, and what do you
         suppose I found? A critter just freshly butchered. Nobody around.
         Just freshly butchered. Well, there was a fellow name of Tom Norris
         run the butcher shop at PeckA. And he wasn't any better calibre than
         the rest of 'em. Don't you see how they could work that? They could
         butcher that critter and divide the price or whatever agreement they'd
         made. And I got wise to that. So one day—
         
         SS:  Was this on Bloodwurst's place?
         
         HR:  This was on Bloodwurst's place where this critter was butchered.
         
         SS:  You mean it wasn't even over on the other guy's place, it was on his
         place?
         
         HR:  Oh, no, it was on his own place. I had this hunch to go sneaking up,
         don't you see, spying, in other words.
         
         SS:  Was this after your three cattle was missing?
         
         HR:  Well, I can't remember that for sure.
         
         SS:  You started to say— So one day—
         
         HR:  Well, them cattle— if you want that, that's what I'll tell you.-
         I scared him one time. I went down to th bench with a .30-30 that
         time, rifle. And I went down to vr-becb See, his land- he was
         pasturing outside land on this forty that was vacant on east side of
         our land, and our had a spring here. That was good land— I'll tell
         you later— that Dad wanted to sell, and I sold it to him for fifteen
         hundred dollars, cash. Made him dig up the cash. I worked the son of
         a bitch— Well, anyway, first when I come down there with a gun that
         morning; he had a saddle horse and he was just about to - see we had
         a gate on the east side in. case our cattle got out, we could open up
         and chase 'em back in. He was just getting off his horse to open that
         gate, and I was just a little too fast, and I come around and he spied
         me- got on his horse and went up the hill again, back home. That's
         the day that I might have done something drastic, if I'd a caught him
         a driving a cow of mine, but I went a little too fast, I shoulda stayed
         a little longer and I woulda got him in the act. But then he got
         pretty slick. After that's when I lost my three cattle.
         
         SS:  He was right on the edge of going right into your land.
         
         HR:  Oh, he could go in there because the gate - they wasn't locked. He
         could go in and out. We couldn't help that, especially when they
         wanted to go through, it was a little closer, saved him going around
         down on the steep hillside, good bench to ride on, see. So, anyway,
         that's the time I told him again. And it happened to be a heifer calf
         like Sullivan had - a muley and had alstar in the forehead. And I think
         it was a yearling steer or heifer, and the mother to this calf. I said,
         "Julian, some son of a bee, has got three of my cattle. And,"I said,
         "I pretty near know who it is." I said, "If they don't come back pret
         ty soon, I says, "before fall," I says, "something's gonna be a pop
         ping right." I looked him right square in the eye, let him know I yiftS
         plumb mad. "Oh," he says,"I'11 tell you. I think I seen them in the
         pasture up here by Jim Steele's." Sure, he'd seen 'em, he's the one'd
         put 'em there! I said, "You tell that son of a bee, that he'd better
         bring 'em back or hell's agoin' a be a popping for him!" And, I said,
         "I don't mean maybe." 
         
         Well, he knew that When fall come, the cow and the come back, but the—
         that calf, I hadmarked it, see. Pretty slick for him to put there.
         Next spring when my youngest brother went down to look at his cattle,
         there was my heifer; yearling. She was about a yearling then, with
         his brand on it. "There's old what-her-name's calf, but he had his brand
         on it." What could I do? I didn't start no more trouble, I just let
         him have it. But he never took no more.' I didn't say nothin' either.
         I just give him one good ripping that time, see. And if it had a hap
         pened that he'd a taken any more— I would. I guess maybe we sold the
         cattle about that time. I told Dad, I said, I didn't like to be fight
         ing the neighbor there. He's a damn nuisance, but he'd been stealing
         cattle from Dad right along, but Dad couldn't catch him. Dad was too
         old a man. So, anyway, that's the way it went. That was why I wanted-
         One of the main reasons — You know what happened after I left and Dad
         got on there. "Course they claimed that it was the boy that set
         the barn afire, but I don't know, it could have been, and it could
         have been the neighbor boys, who done it.
         
         SS:  These kids really gave your boy a hard time?
         
         HR:  Oh, they was dirty as hell. That's the worst of it. You see, he
         wouldn't make them boys mind. They were devils. And I heard though—
         they ain't none of them left over there now, neither one of 'em. The
         oldest one, I guess, was out in the woods working and he got killed, d1
         and, of course, Old Bloodwust was old enough that he finally died,
         and I guess his wife, too. That place— the house is gone. Some big
         farmer's got the whole works there now.
         
         SS:  Was your boy younger?
         
         HR:  Oh, yes, he wasn't able to take care of himself. I didn't want him
         to be fightin' anyway. I said, "You're too young." Now, here's the
         boy, here, him and his family. He's quarried and got a daughter. That's
         their daughter there, she is ten years old there. We was down to vis
         it 'em. I'll show you one when he was a young man. He's baldheaded.
         I told him, I said, " now, Myron"— he was a boy that wanted schoolAjC)«
         And I was just so damn poor when we lived up in Park— I was just so
         doggone poor that I couldn't afford nothing. I had three daughters,
         see. "Myron," I said, "you go out and work, you got a start, you're
         big, husky, and get out and work best you can and get educated, if
         you can, and I'll try and take care of the family. You don't have to
         help me at all, I'll do the best I can to take care of the family."
         Well, he did, he minded me. He went out and got him a job. He work
         ed for the CC camp, you remember them days? And than he finally got
         a job down , at Pomeroy—no, that was the year he ran away, got
         made at me, see. Well, he had it a comin'. That's the fall that we's
         renting that Hoyt place and had to haul water, see, for the stock.
         
         There was no water on the place, and it was a bigger job to drive
         the cattle to water than it was to take a tank and haul it. And so, I
         had four horses on this tank and had to open a gate to get into the
         pond. I said, "Myron, get off and open that gate, so I can drive in."
         And he got kinda bossy, "Dad," he says, "you get off." I said,"Myron,"
         I says, "I told you to get off and open that gate." "No, you get off."
         I said, "Goddam, if you don't get off and open that gate, I'll give
         you a good tanning." Sose of the boss, my cousin, Ervin Swenson— . u bos5y
         there was a little devil and Harv De Groff 
         I don't know why. What steered Myron off, his little pal— not Harv
         De Groff, but Warren De Groff, had got shot and killed and died and
         he just seemed to lose all confidence in himself, and was just a dif
         ferent boy, entirely. And I got made, I couldn't take that from him.
         My dad made me mind, made a man outta me, by God, I'm gonna make a
         man outta my boy. I lfcved him; sure. So, he got off and opened the
         gate. That was about January when he ran off. He didn't run off
         right away, but it was January. Cold weather and we was all doing the
         best we could, milking thirteen cows. Them there Guernseys that I
         didn't get any use of only the milk while we lived there.
         
         SS:  So he just ran away that night?
         
         HR:  Yeah. He went away. And he was gone, never hear from him, never wrote,
         nothin'. Well, the girls and wife, they cried their eyes out. I
         was just lucky I had a little old Whippet car. You know, they was ec
         onomical on gas. Well, this neighbor, sister to the boy that he'd been
         so friendly with, her name was Rist— Jean Rist, was her name. She had—
         or told us that Myron was down in Southern Idaho with her sister at
         Parma, Idaho. Well, I got the bright idea that I should look him up.
         It was getting annoying to have the children and the woman worrying
         their heads off about him, which I didn't like either. I didn't like
         the idea. We just didn't know what coulda happened because he didn't
         have no money.A He had the guts to go. So, just like I did. By God,
         I thought, OK, I got in this Whippet car and I happened to come out
         here to Deary. Old Ed Swenson had his dad,A old Bricky there, you
         know. Old Bricky wanted to go with me. "God," I says, "Bricky, I
         ain't got no heat in the car," I says, "it's winter, it's gonna be
         cold." Well, he was used to cold, he'd been up in Canada, he didn't
         mind. Said he'd take his overcoat and he wanted to go and I couldn't
         turn the poor bugger down. I said, "If you're gritty enough to take,
         I sure am, too. I surely ought to be, I'm younger." And we took off,
         one morning, and I got down to L Junction. It's funny how I— It's
         just like somebody said, "No, don't go there." See, the year before,
         I forgot to tell you that— the hear before he'd been staying down
         at Parma— Now wait a minute—Starbuck, Washington. That's below
         Pomeroy a little ways. Now, that's where I shoulda went. But I
         wouldn't a found out anyway. Here's what I did do. I went down
         there because of this influence that girl — this boyls sister had
         said he was down there at her sister's. Well, there we drove down
         here to Riggins, that night, that's as far as we got.
         
         SS:  That's a pretty rough trip.
         
         HR:  Yeah, it was then, you betcha. And snow! But I knew where I could
         stop over night— the next night. This first night we had to stop in
         Riggins, we didn't get any farther. And I was cold, we'd had a cold
         lunch for noon, and I said, "George, by gol, let's have a good supper
         I got a few pennies." "Alright," he said. And I ordered beef steak,
         and Jesus Christ, if I could have got a roast it wouldn't have been so
         bad, but this beefsteak was so rawhide tough; but I downed it. And I
         got sick that night. Boy, maybe I was already catching it. Cold
         sick. Next day, I got to running off at the A every few minutes I
         had to get out in the snow and do my number two, you know. George
         set in there, no heat in the car. He had to set there til I come
         back. And every little while I'd have to get out. "Well',' I said,
         "we can't get to Parma today," I said, "but, I know a pla I think we
         can make." And that was my wife's stepsister's husband lived on a
         place down there on the Meadows— beyond the Meadows a little ways.
         They had a farm out there in the country. We had to get off eighteen,
         twenty miles, off the main highway. I said, "We'll drive in there
         anyway," I said, "George, we ought to— it's to far to go to Parma
         today, anyway." And, I said, "Let's go in there and stay. I know
         them folks, and I know we'll be welcome." Which we did. We got treat
         ed fine. Only, I was sicker'n a dog. And I told his wife, I said,
         "Don't give me much," I said, "all I want is a raw egg." That's the
         best I could get for stomach flu. And I happened to have a chunk of
         pitch with me about four foot long and eight inches in diameter. And
         this Moore, his name was, said, "You know," he said, "I'd like to
         have that to start fires with." "Well,," I says, "you know something
         brought that just in case we had a breakdown of the car and we'd
         get out here and we might set and freeze to death," I says, "I just
         brought that along to have a fire, keep us from freezing to death."
         Oh, he just begged, he begged and begged. I shoulda given him part
         of it, but I didn't, and he never charged anything even for stopping
         you know. But I just couldn't see it. I wasn't a well man anyway.
         I told him, I says, "Moore, I'm pretty sick, I don't know how much
         I can take of this cold." 
         
         Well, the next day we got down there to
         Parma where this sister. And the first thing I asked was, "Was the
         boy here?" "No." She didn't know a thing about him. Well, as luck'd
         have it, I'd met this woman— Mrs Rist's daughter, see— so I said,
         "Golly," I said, "I'd like to stay all night." "Well, sure," she
         says, "you can stay all night." I says, "Have you got the room here?"
         "Well, that's fine," I says, "but have you got a drugstore in this
         town?" "Yup." I said, "Boy, good. I'm gonna go down and get me some"—
         them days.use cokes when they got diarrhea Chamberlain's Colic Remedy.
         I went down and got me two, three ounce bottle. "Now," I said, "lady,
         I'd like to have access to a little warm water," I said, "that's all
         I'm gonna do all night. I'd like to try to down this every so often."
         Get rid of this thing, this stomach flu is what it was. And I did.
         The next morning, by God, I felt pretty good. I didn't want to over
         load my stomach. I said, "Just give me a couple of soft boiled eggs."
         And, of course, it didn't cost me a cent, they wouldn't take no money.
         Well, then I got the idea not to backtrack. I said, "George, I'm
         gonna head for Walla Walla." Well, what happened, George had a friend
         over above Walla Walla, between Dayton and Pomeroy. Said, "We'll go
         there for dinner." "Okay, George," I said, "you know 'em?" "Yeah."
         "But first," I said, "I want to go to the police headquarters in Walla
         Walla and see if anything's on the scoreboard there about such a run
         away boy." No, they hadn't. Then I says, "I want to leave word, I'll
         give you my address and if you find him, let me know. I'll pay the
         damage, whatever charges there is." Well, they agreed. So, we went
         and got our dinner at this friend of George's that day. Felt pretty
         good, had a good visit. "Well," I said, "let's go to Lewiston, now,"
         I said, "we haven't found him yet." So we headed back to Lewiston.
         This way— we was going right back by Starbuck. "If he's in this
         territory we could find out." It's about five o'clock in the evening,
         gettin' dark, you know. Short days in January.
         
         Got into a service
         station, I said, "I've got to get some gas and let's get a lunch, I
         don't want to bother auntie and uncle this late in the night." Be
         probably nine, ten o'clock before we'd get down there. So, "Alright,"
         George said. And we got a pretty good lunch, and I got to talking to
         this service man. I said, "You fella's didn't happen to see a boya
         runaway boy, did you? By golly, I've lost my boy. He took off and
         I haven't heard from him or nothin'" I said. He said, "Give me a des
         cription." So I did. "Why," he says, "I believe that boy is working
         out here for Ed Patterson." I said, "By golly, I wisht I could find
         that place." Well, he was out four, five miles out in the country.
         "God, I wouldn't know how to find him." "Well,"he said,"you wait til
         I shut the service station down, I'll take you out there." "Fine."
         He took us out there. We got out there and nobody there! Then, it
         dawned on him that the boy and Patterson's nephew was going to school,
         'cause Patterson was a rich farmer. He had a building in Pomeroy
         that the nephew was staying in, and my boy. And I come to the door,
         and this nephew had already gone to bed, it was ten o'clock at night.
         And this boy of mine was just getting ready to go to bed, and I knock
         ed at the door and he said, "Huh!" 
         
         Shocked him. "Huh, where'd you come
         from, Dad?" I said, "I just dropped out of the sky!" Well, he'd got
         shocked, you know. "You're going to take me home, are you?" "No, you
         bet I ain't gonna take you home," I said, "what I want to know, is
         what kind of a deal you made with the farmer out there?" "Well," he
         says, "I agreed to work for him for to get to go to school." "Oh,
         that's fine, you're doing alright, stay with it." I said, "For God's
         sake, give that man his money's worth. I couldn't afford it," I said,
         "and if you find a farmer that'll keep you and give you a job and work
         to go to school," I says, "that's just the thing to do. But," I said,
         "For God's sake, write once in a while." I said, "The girls and your
         mother, they're just a cryin' their eyes out over you, going without
         money." I said, "I wasn't feeling a bit good either, that's the rea
         son I took this trip." "Alright, Dad," he said. "Well," I said, "we
         might come down next summer and visit you and the people. We want to
         get acquainted. But," I said, "stay with him, whatever you do., and
         be sure he's satisfied. Don't play no trick on him. If he's that
         kind of a man thatcould take you in to go to school, and give you
         work, you'd better stay put." So he did. And, God, they were nice
         people. I took the whole family down there the next summer, and they
         give us a big,dinner. We got friendly, you know. By God, he even
         wanted to let me have the boy'jome. "No," I said, "Mr. Patterson,
         he's agreed to stay here and work for you," I says, "he stays." I
         said, "If he wants to come when you're satisfied with what schooling
         you've given him," I says, " we've moved to Moscow now." That was
         after we'd moved to Moscow.
         
         SS:  How old was he when he ran away? What grade was he in?
         
         HR:  Oh, he was— wait a minute—I'll tell you. Now it was '32 we moved
         sway and before that was about '31— just a minute, now— He was about
         fifteen, sixteen. He was born in '16, see.
         
         SS:  You said that he had the guts to go just like I did. Did you ever run
         away? TpVa0
         
         HR:  Oh, yes. When I was eighteen years old, you betcha. You see, Dad was
         hard and I was young, spirited young then,and I figured I had worked
         hard there at home. I told Dad all time— you see, we'd heard about
         to go to Canada and get a homestead, get a whole half a section. Be
         cause you could take a patch of land as a stone and timber claim, I
         guess they called it. And when you was eighteen you was eligible for
         half a section alone, and I had two pals on the Ridge, Al Settle, a
         Swede boy, and thisGerman boy, only he had made money,
         he'd already been out working and saved his money and he was gonna
         go and he talked us two kids in the notion of making some money and
         coming up and joining him. The three of us could take pretty near—
         what do you call it?—section together, see. There'd only be a quar
         ter left, or half a section left. So, yeah, we all agreed that we
         had to make that money to get up there. It'd take money, by gosh, to
         get started. Well, I had a little pony, and I had plowed for Dad
         that spring, I plowed some timothy sod— it was an open winter, some
         thing like this, plowed that ground and he wanted to sow his oats
         early, see, it was about March then. And had an open winter, nice.
         But you couldn't plow this timothy sod, too wet for old ground. But
         I'd got this ground plowed for him that he wanted to seed oats on
         early, and he goes up the Ridge about ten miles to get this seed oats.
         That's when I made my getaway. I told the boys, I says, "Now, listen
         don't tell him where I went. I'm gonna try and sneak away." And
         St iner, too. And, I was, let's see, yeah, I was eighteen and St iner
         was sixteen. But he was big enough to do quite a bit of field work
         then, you see. And Simon, my brother, now, let's see, he would be
         seven years younger; he was only eleven, but he was big enough so he
         could cook in the kitchen. This little Julius, he was nine, two years
         younger than that. Nine- eleven- and, of course, little Joe— how
         old would he be then? I think he was over to Grandma's yet. Let's
         see, Julius was eleven- or nine- Joe would have been, well, I'll tell
         you when he was born. — Now, let's see, she died in 1913- Yeah,
         1906, sure. And I was eighteen.
         
         SS:  Did you make your getaway?
         
         HR:  Oh, wait. I took this pony, see, and I knew I didn't dare cross the
         Clearwater River, he'd know right a way which way I went. I switched
         and went up Melrose Ridge. I kinda had a hunch I might get a job
         down : i. Gifford, that was out towards the breaks of the canyon -
         Clearwater Canyon. I thought they'd surely be earlier there and they'd
         get and the farmers would hire me, you know. Huh, the first night,
         of course, overtook me right on top of the ridge, and I stopped at
         a farmhouse. And I said, "Now, I ain't got no money," I says, "but
         if you got some work to do, I'll work for my stopping." "Yeah, we
         got some wood." Them days they burnt — all burnt wood, you know,
         "Chop some wood tomorrow morning, if you want to." Too dark that
         night. "Okay," I said, "I'll do that." And I chopped til they were
         satisfied. Chopped a big pile, split up cookwood, that's what they
         wanted. So, I got that so. I went on down. That throwed me kinda
         late getting started. I went on down towards Gifford, and I found
         somebody kinda getting ready it looked like. Man and his wife they
         was out there in the barn working away. I guess they was getting
         grain ready to crop afterAwhile and I said, "You people hiring any
         hands around here in the spring work?" No, no,they-hadn't got start
         ed yet, and they didn't know of anybody x either. They didn't
         give me no satisfactory answer. And there was quite a bit of snow
         scattered along. Well, that's when I decided to switch back, turn
         back and get over to where my grandparents lived, see. Just lucky I
         did, too. I'll tell you fifie. So that night, night overtook me be
         fore I got back to even where I had been the night before. I stopped
         at these people and they had four grown boys, they had no room. "Well,"
         they said, "if you want to sleep on the barn floor." "Well," I said,
         "that's better'n staying outdoors." I said, "I'll work for my stuff."
         
         No, they didn't need no work. Well, they said, stay anyway. Them
         days, you know, they seen I was a young man, and I told 'em, I was
         trying to get a job. They kept me overnight, didn't charge me. I
         didn't have much sleeping quarters, but I rested. Next day I pulled
         out for Peck, across the ferryboat. As soon as I was on the ferryboat,-
         I guess Dad had been down there that day inquiring- the ferry man
         asked me, said, "Did you see your dad uptown?— or did you see your
         dad yesterday?" "Yeah," I said, "I seen him uptown." I lied, you
         see. Well, I didn't have no money to pay four bits to cross the ferry
         boat with a cayuse, but Dad had good credit. I said, "Charge this to
         the Old Man." I went up on the Ridge— I mean Potlatch Ridge, 'cause
         I had school friends, that I'd went to school with, the Roch boys,
         there was three boys and a girl, Dola,
         And they had a boy that wasn't all there; twenty years old. Boy
         couldn't talk. But, anyway, I got there and they treated me like one
         of the family, you know. I was welcome as could be. The next morn
         ing— there was still snow on Big Potlatch, you know, quite a bit
         of it. The next morning it started snowing, from the east. I
         thought, "Oh, oh." This little pony I had couldn't go faster than
         I could walk. And I didn't have nothing but leather shoes on my feet
         anyway. No overcoat, just a coat. They tried their very best to get
         me to stay. "No," I said, "I gotta get there today," I said, "if I
         don't, I won't make it with this short legged pony, I got." There
         was twenty-two miles that I had to still go in that storm, see, and
         cold. It was getting around twenty below zero. I walked pretty near
         all the way. I got over there and my feet froze to my shoes. 
         
         And
         Uncle Ed'd be there, of course, f knew he was there, grandparents.
         I knew I'd be welcome when I got there you know, Grandma's just as 
         a mother, you know, and so was Granddad. But they had a big dog named
         Woods, come and met me at the gate, but it was luck, it was them slide
         gates, pole gates, see, and I was just hoping it'd open itself. I
         didn't dare get off, I was scared to death of that damn big dog. He
         was a bulldog, you know. He growled at me and I wasn't about
         to get down, he mighta took a leg off, and I was so cold I couldn't
         hardly a moved anyway. I got to the house and I hollered and old ED
         come out and the dog was right between me and Ed, and he called to him,
         said, "You go on to the woodshed, Woods." He called him Woods. I
         said, "Ed, by golly, my feet are froze to my shoes." "Well," he says,
         "go on in, I'll put your cayuse in the barn. And we'll get some,"—
         them days they used snow water in a dishpan or something— washpan, I
         mean to thaw 'em out. Finally, they come out of it. Saved getting
         chilblains, you know, that thaws 'em out gradual. Well, they wanted
         to know what was up. I told 'em, says, "I's looking for a job."
         (Chuckles) And, it snowed, that was a big snow winter. the
         latter part of March and April,JLt snowed til it was— hadn't been
         much snow before that, but that time it snowed so the fence posts
         was covered. About five or six feet of anow. And it didn't go off
         til way out in May. Well, then I had another uncle living out at
         Deary, Isaac. This Carlson's dad. Carl was a little bitsy— 1906-
         he was six years old, see, he was born in 1900.
         
         SS:  You stayed with them in Park all the time?
         
         HR:  I stayed with Grandpa and Grandma for, I don't know, I guess it was
         two or three weeks, and I got restless. I said, "God, I'd like to
         get out and see if I couldn't get some work, somewheres." The weather'd
         kinda settled then, and it had snowed lots alright, but, I guess it
         had started thawing, too, before I ever took out. I think it was
         April, already, then, I think. Yeah, it must have been, because the
         snow had gone off quite a bit. Oh, there was still snow at Deary.
         But I got out there to my uncle's, you know, and they happened to 
         know about a French-Canadian, they thought that he might ac
         cidentally need, or I could work for them. I said, "By golly," I
         said, "let's go see him. I don't care what kind of work it is." Yeh,
         by golly, he had a job, little pines. Dollar and a half a
         day and board. And I took it on. Ten hours a day; fifteen cents an
         hour! I thought that I was lucky. But he was a big, husky and he
         had a double-bitted axe, God, he could just slice those little pines
         agoin' and a comin'. I couldn't do it, I wasn't used to an axe then.
         Because I lived on a farm, all I knew was a hatchet. But I told him,
         "I can't do it as fast as you can." "Well, do the best you can." And
         I tied in to it, and chopped as fast as I could. Young and tough then.
         Eighteen and ate like a little pig. He had a Sears-Roebuck woman, they
         called it. You know what I mean? He'd ordered, through mail, by
         golly. And I thought they got along pretty good when I was there,
         I didn't see any trouble. So, he decided he wanted to buy this pony
         from me for fifteen dollars, so I sold it. I wanted to get all the
         money I could get together, I could. I stayed there a while til my
         uncle, he found another job that was— that he thought would be a better
         place for me, name of Swanson. Lived right the edge of town, and
         he was a nice man, nicer man man than the French-Canadian. And he
         says—
         
         SS:  Where was this French-Canadian's place, by the way?
         
         HR:  Huh?
         
         SS:  Where was this French-Canadian's place?
         
         HR:  Out towards Avon.
         
         SS:  Yeah. Keep going.
         
         HR:  And so, he says— I quit him, you know, and I come over to Swanson's.
         
         SS:  Your uncle got you to quit?
         
         HR:  Yeah. He got me to quit, yeah.
         
         SS:  So he got you to quit and you went over to
         
         HR:  Yeah. I got over to Swanson. "Yeah," he said, "I'd like to hire you."
         He said, "Tell you what I got to do", he says, "I got some stumps to
         burn and morning and evening I'd like to have you help me milk my
         cows. And I'll give you so much a month." His wife tried to jew me
         down—she says, "I'll give you a twenty dollar gold piece,"just like
         that was more money than twenty-five. He offered me twenty-five.
         "No," I says— I knew that much, if I didn't have much schooling yet.
         "By golly," I says, "I want the twenty-five." "Yeah," Swanson he's
         a bighearted old man, "we're gonna give him twenty-five." I went out
         to work. He showed me how to do it and I kept burning stumps and
         helping him with this, milking the cows. And everything went fine
         and dandy. Til finally, I had a little money coming from that Swede
         guy on the Ridge, Oscar Nelson, that I'd helped in haying. And the
         son of a gun never paid me, he'd owed me, I guess, for two, three
         years. One of these guys, he'd let his debtf run quite a while, you
         know. I don't remember how much it was, but I'd pitched in the field
         for him for three wagons, and I figured I ought to have that money.
         Well, you know, them days, them old-timers they got it in their head
         they got to see the old man first or they might have to pay that bill
         twice. Now they say, they can't do that. They can't collect the
         young man's wages. But over there they did, and I don't know to this
         day if that man ever paid. But here's the way it went.went
         and asked Dad, see, permission to pay me the money. 
         
         Well, Dad found
         out where I was at. So he writes over there and he said, "You know,
         Helmer, I could send the sheriff after you." "Yes, Dad," I wrote
         back. "But," I says, "I could run away again." Oh, the next time I
         got a letter from him, it was different altogether. I told him, "Dad,"
         I says, "I want to, make some money to get out there and go to Canada.
         Get a homestead and that half section of land." God, he seen I had
         something in mind, I guess so he got pretty civil. So he'd searched
         around and he found out there was a railroad shortline going to be
         built up there from Craigmont to Nez Perce. And I guess he had a Nez
         Perce Herald, thatway he found out. They was advertising for farm
         ers to come and— them days, they run four horse scrapers when they
         done any grading. There was no machinery. So, they was paying six
         dollars a day for that, but you had to board yourself, and they just
         really jewed you down, you know, them bastards. Well, I and this
         here Swede boy that was going to Canada, he got permission from his
         Dad to take his four horses and a load of hay and I did from Dad.
         Yeah, when Dad told me that, I told Swanson, I said, "My, oh, my,"
         I said— he had already got me to help him to saw saw logs over down
         side of Deary, that's when the Deary townsite was being built. Old
         Swanson, he jumped my wages. He said, "I'll jump your wages ten dol
         lars a month to stay here .  tay ) all summer. You'll
         be money ahead." And I would have. But I didn't see it. That six
         dollars looked awful big. And I thought, "Gee, I want to stay on the
         good side of Dad, he's offered it to me. I better go and pay atten
         tion." So, I didn't take the Swanson deal at all. He hated it and I
         hated it, and in a way I hated to turn him down, but I just got the
         idea that I liked horse work better'n I did crosscut saw work, you
         know. That was my talented work in those days.
         
         SS:  By the way, did you actually work on that townsite? Did you cut logs
         for them on that townsite?
         
         HR:  Oh, yes. Til Dad found out and talked me in the notion of coming
         there, you see. I don't remember how long I was there, probably a
         week or two, something like that.
         
         SS:  Okay, so you went over there.
         
         HR:  Yeah, I went back over to home and got to working on this railroad
         between Craigmont and Nez Perce. And, after we'd worked a week, they
         laid us off and we had to do rockwork by hand and still feed our hor
         ses. couldn't see it, I and the neighbor boy and we quit. We was
         about of hay, anyway, and we had to come back and get a load of hay,
         and that was no good. We just quit him. I says,"Al, this harvest's
         coming on pretty quick now, I think I can get a job a harvesting."
         Well, that's when I got a job a harvesting, and so I made a little
         money there.
         
         SS:  So it didn't work out any better there?
         
         HR:  No, it didn't pan out at all. I had to quit and I went to harvesting.
         I tell you, I worked for Jeff Stample, the next one, in harvesting.
         I got two and a half a day there and board for twelve hours work.
         And he had a header, and I drove header. And so, I stayed there all
         summer. Well, Dad he was pretty good. That learnt him a good les
         son, see. Now, he got smart to help St iner. St ;iner stayed home,
         so he told him, and he told me— he wanted this cash that I had, be
         cause I didn't have enough to go to Canada on, and Dad was hard run,
         and he said, "Now, I'll sell you boys a cow a piece, and you get the
         offspring and you'll just be increasing that way. Well, we agreed,
         and stayed there and worked and kept getting cattle ahead, see.
         
         SS:  You mean you gaVjs up the idea—?
         
         HR:  Yeah, I give up because I couldn't make money enough to go up there
         to Canada and Dad ' . fixed it that way. I guess he .inda wanted
         to settle us down. I guess he kinda figured that he didn't want to
         let me go clear up there and try to struggle in that cold country, I
         suppose that's what he figured. So, we stayed with that, it was 1906-
         1906, see was it 1907, Dad took a notion, he was studying in Moscow
         and he could get to go to school, finish up his high school at the
         University, which he did. He passed his high school at Moscow University. Now here's
         Dad, 1908, it was— first I want to tell you,
         about, it was 1907, I guess, that Dad was building a house— I'll
         show you after while— this fellow that he bought oats from up on
         the Ridge— Fredrickson, was a good carpenter, and Dad them days,
         didn't have to pay— oh, two, three dollars a day was a big wage, and
         he was hard run, he only had a small farm, forty acres .there on the
         Ridge. So he was going to have to get some work, but he was a good
         carpenter. Dad knew it, and Dad got him to build this house and al
         so the barn. 1908, they had got the barn built-and that's what I
         wanted to tell you- here he is, he took off to go to this school.
         (Wait, and I'll find it pretty soon. Here he is) That's my Dad.
         
         SS:  What school is that?
         
         HR:  Well, that's That's chiropractor. He got the idea
         he wanted to take that up. And he did, he passed on it.
         
         SS:  Where did he go to school?
         
         HR:  Missouri. Clear back to Missouri. And he had rented the place to
         St iner, see. St..iner then, it was 1908- I was— wait a minute, 1908-
         I was twenty, wasn't I? Yup. Twelve years on eight, I was twenty.
         St iiner was eighteen. And I didn't want to rent it, see. I don't know
         why Dad wanted to rent it to him, but he did.
         
         SS:  And he went back to Missouri?
         
         HR:  Back to Missouri and he left us boys there, and I wanted to keep work
         ing out, whenever I had time, see. I helped Stiner on the farm.
         Well, he had a boy there name of Lee Galloway to help him plow. Them
         days,— let's see, 1918— or 1908, we had a gangplow,— Oh, I knowhe
         was running a gangplow and a walking plow. That's what he was
         doing. That's what he was doing, 'cause I knew we had a gangplow and
         used lots of horses.
         
         SS:  What was your father's interest in chiropractor. What was the idea of
         that?
         
         HR:  Because he thought that he could make— being as us boys were big
         enough to do the farming, dammit, he'd go out and do a little doctor
         ing. Which he did. He went over to Kendrick one year and practiced.
         And then, when he rented out to me after I was married, you know,
         1917. Then he went to Kirkland, Washington. Bought a house and lot
         there. And the grandparents stayed with us that summer until fall,
         'cause Uncle Ed— see, was he sold out? Yeah, Uncle Ed had
         already sold out. So that was the trick that Ed played on Dad. He
         first got Dad to promise to take care of the old parents for twelve
         hundred dollars, and yet Dad had helped him get that place over
         there. He'd bought this property over here to Park for twenty-two
         hundred dollars, Dad did, to get him a down payment on that place.
         And then, Ed was lucky, that last year that he farmed he got two
         thousand dollars worth of beans off the place, and he got eight thou
         sand from the place, and it only cost him five thousand to begin with.
         He got reckless with that money and he went down to Southern Idaho,
         where my aunt, his sister lived and started in with some cattle,
         but-4hevcouldn't make it. It was a dry country, so he didn't stay
         there long. He just let it go. And then he got the bright idea to
         
         SS:  Now, is that the one that killed his wife?
         
         HR:  That's the one. Yeah. He killed his wife. He finally shot her, with
         a rifle and then he took his own life with a knife; butcher knife.
         
         SS:  What did you hear? Did you hear about it after that?
         
         HR:  Nooo. Relatives told me. Uncle And They found out. News scat
         ters, you know. Yeah, that goes like wildfire, something like that,
         you know. He was jealous of her. She would go out with the neighbor
         lady in her buggy. And, ah, he was nuts! I knew there was something
         wrong with the old bastard when I was there. He was sort of a bully
         sort of a guy. French-Canadian, you know, they're pretty hotheaded.
         And so, I was glad to get out of there. Geez
         
         SS:  Was he mean when you worked with him?
         
         HR:  No. he didn't order me around, he didn't do that. And that was when
         they was first married, sweet, then, don't you see.
         But this was, I don't know, a year or two years after when he shot
         her, that they got on the outs with each other for some reason. He
         got jealous of her going with the neighbors— women, talking, I don't
         know, maybe some of 'em were pretty mouthy, or something. And he'd
         overheard something that made him mad, don't you see.
         
         SS:  Another thing I was going to ask you was— Now did your father, did
         he do much practicing of chiropractor.
         
         HR:  Yeah, he did. You see, he done a little in Idaho, in Kendrick, but
         when he got out to Kirland, Washington, he had to get some licenses
         out there. But he practiced out there, too. You betcha. He had a
         lot of time. Well, like I said, I farmed his place for seven years.
         
         SS:  Was he practicing all that time?
         
         HR:  Yeah. He was practicing what he could. And Granddad, he had him
         there then, before Grandma died, that was before 1922. Granddad
         was cutting wood for him. They had wood around there, you see. And
         I guess he had a fireplace or something that he was feeding. Or,
         the neighbors, he might have been cutting wood— I don't remember that
         
         SS: So he believed in that chiropractor pretty strong?
         
         HR:  Yeah, he's helped out- Now, I'll tell you, one time he did help me
         out. Let's see, but that was before I got married. I was helping
         him haul alfalfa hay in and this barn he had had hay chutes to shove
         the hay down, you know, down to feed walkway. And I was up in the
         mow, Dad was down there unloading with slings— we had two or three
         slings to a load of hay. And I was up there placing hay around, and
         tell him when totip it. Well, I stepped back, like that, you know
         in a hurry, and there was a little loose hay on this chute and lit
         right on my tailbone. Wheee! Put me d.Atotfy t311 all my weight right
         on my tailbone, board walk. Dad holled at me, "What's the matter,
         there," he says, "what's going on?" I says, "Oh, Dad, I fell down
         the hay chute and I can't get out." By God, he come in there and he
         treated me for about a half an hour on my back and down my tailbone.
         By God, he took me out of it. And I learnt from then on, there was
         quite a bit to it. He treated the nerve, see.
         
         SS:  What he did? He massage you, then?
         
         HR:  Massaged me good. So if it hadn't been for him— I never did get
         over it right away, but it started me, it took me,out of that shock,
         see. Him knowing something about nerve treatments, it took me out Cnr
         that shock, and I went right back to work. Only half an hour that he
         had to treat me that I went back up there placing hay. Finished
         hauling his hay in. Another thing,— well, maybe we better leave
         that til next time— You see when he went East to get this schooling
         then I painted the barn, 'cause he had the carpenters leave their
         scaffolds up.
         
         (Another subject)
         
         HR:  But the Torgeson girls, and  name was Emma she
         was just a good full-blooded Norwegian— she could talk Norwegian
         good, but I couldn't, but I could understand it, 'cause I always
         talked with  in Norwegian. So I could talk it plenty good, so
         we could understand one another. And she wanted me, damn bad, she'd
         a liked to got me. She tried her damndest. I just didn't cooperate
         she didn't suit me, see. I had a lot of chances, when I was young,
         you know. But anyway we's a dancin' away— 'cause this was good mus
         ic. We'd dance from one room into the other. That's how we danced.
         Small rooms, probably as big as this, and we just danced— waltz around
         in this room into the other. The whole crowd did the same thing.
         It was just a lot of fun. And Fritz Olson, and Billy Osburn, they
         was playing violin and I think, I forget now whether it was a accordian
         or a harp of some kind that Fritz was playing formusic. Ohhhh,
         You just couldn't set still, you had to waltz, it just pulled you around,
         you know. When them old-timers played them waltze, I tell you,
         that really moved your legs, if you had any waltzing in you. And
         we'd a learnt, St iiner and I had learnt, dancing on the Ridge when we
         was kids. You see, my aunt used to cook for Dad after Mother died.
         We's just kids but all the neighbor women over there would love to
         dance with us kids, just because they felt sorry for us that we were,
         I say orphans, no mother. So they never turned us down. We'd go
         ask 'em. Well, one lady 'specially, Mrs. Malcolm, her husband didn't
         even dance on the floor, for some reason, and she was a good dancer,
         I always got her to dance.
         
         SS:  Were these dances at homes on Central Ridge, too?
         
         HR:  What?
         
         SS:  On Central Ridge would they have dances in people's homes?
         
         HR:  Yeah, that's where it was.
         
         SS:  Just like around Deary, then?
         
         HR:  Just like around Deary. I said that's where we learnt. Yeah. We'd
         go from one neighborhood to the other, and once in a while we'd go
         clear up, what they call mOorZ- f that was a little country town,
         you know between Nez Perce and Craigmont, kinda a little bit north.
         And this this Dutch kidy you know, says, "Come on up,
         Helmer, sometime and we'll go up there, they're gonna have a masquarade.
         See they had masquarade dances, so you couldn t tell who they
         were.'1 Oh, God, we had a hell of a good time that night. And there
         was all kinds of young people. He had a sister, Laura; I'd dance
         with her and all the rest of 'em. They was all mixed, God, there
         was no high-hattin' goin' on, everybody got busy and enjoyed theirselves.
         See what I mean? Just like we did at Deary, too. When we
         lived in Park, we used to go over to Cedar Creek once in a while.
         And the Cedar Creek folks'd come to Park; dance in our schoolhouse
         there. That's what we did there, and over at— over on Cedar Creek
         there was Smiths— did you ever hear of the Smiths over on Cedar Creek?
         
         SS:  I think I've heard of them.
         
         HR:  There used to be Ben Smith, and George Smith- the two boys- and Eva
         Smith, she's the one that became the owner of the homeplace. They
         lived just across from the Longfellow place, if you remember where
         the Longfellow place is.
         
         SS:  Yeah, I've heard of that place.
         
         HR:  Well, we danced in Smith's house. They had a big house. And she
         was a good dancer, she was a big woman, but, by God, she was easy on
         her feet. Oh, God, I could dance waltzes with her just like no
         thin' !! Just fine and dandy. She finally moved down to either Clarkston
         or Lewiston; became a nurse, I guess, after she sold out.
         
         SS:  This masquarade dance? Everybody got dressed up.
         
         HR:  That wasn't a masquarade over there.
         
         SS:  No, I'm thinking about—
         
         HR:  But, the masquarade, oh, that was. Oh, you bet, that was lots of
         fun. We just tore around together, you know. And, of course, about
         lunchtime, then they'd pull the maskj off and you wouldn't know who
         the hell you had for a pardner, see! (Chuckles) Sometimes you'd be
         buying baskets, too, you know; basket socials.
         
         SS:  You'd bid on it?
         
         HR:  Yeah, you bid on it, you wouldn't know who your pardner was, 'til
         you got the mask off. Sometimes you'd get what you wanted, sometimes
         you wouldf.
         
         SS:  Then you ate your lunch with the person that made it.
         
         HR:  Oh, yeah. You bought a basket from somebody, you had to eat your
         lunch with that pardner, regardless. An old lady, that didn't matter, you'd eatdinner
         with her anyway. But there wasn t any old
         ladies out to the dances. Mostly all young youngs. Well, there was
         married ladies, but, that was alright.
         
         SS:  How long did these dances go? Did they go late into the night?
         
         HR:  Ohhh, yeah, sometimes, by God, we wouldn't get home til daylight.
         You take the Fourth of July, especially, we'd go to Peck, Idaho and
         then we didn't come home til daylight, you know. Dance til daylight.
         But you was a trying to sleep in the daytime and you'd hear that old
         violin agoing, and you couldn't go to sleep!
         
         SS:  You were trying to sleep after the dance?
         
         HR:  Yeah, after the dance af home in daylight. You just couldn't hard
         ly do it. And, old Dad, you know, oh, oh, when we were there on the
         Ridge, I and Steiner, just learning, next morning, you know, after
         we'd been dancing, we'd be in the bed, maybe a couple of hours, and
         just nice and sound asleep, and Dad'd come up and holler, "Come on,
         boys, get your chores done." Whuuuu!! The way we snuck out, see,
         Auntie told us, Dad didn't want us to go to the dances—we'll put a
         ladder up,,she was two years older than I was- put a ladder up by
         the upstairs window, we got out on that. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:  That was some of the first dancing you did?
         Hr: Yeah. That was when we was first learning. Oh, I guess we were lit
         the devils, but, thank God, I went through it all. And I'm glad of
         it. I get a thinking about what a hell of a good time I have
         had;in my younger days.
         
         SS:  Now, these lunches, by the way, now they had real good feeds?
         
         HR:  Oh, we had cakes and donuts and sometimes they'd have some cooked,
         maybe beans or something like, you know. What do you call 'em,
         baked beans. Oh, you bet, they really fed. The country people, you
         know, they could bring their own. And those old farm ladies they
         could cook good, I tell you, they knew what a farm boy eat. They'd
         get 'em all plenty, too.
         
         SS:  The whole family would go?
         
         HR:  No, no. Well, now Malcolm, his children were too small, so it'd just
         be him and his wife. And them boys over there, that man started out-
         There was a nice man— nice couple. He come to that Ridge, he didn't
         homestead, he had to buy the land. He bought eighty acres from Old
         Man Mc Kay, and then he bought Cade's Mc Kay's eighty. There was
         two boys and the old man. Three eighties. Then when he got able
         he bought the other man's eighty— that was Dennis Mc Kay. Well,
         Rod Pfeiffer had bought one of them eighties, see, well, later on
         then— Old Malcolm was a prosperous guy, he raised his own horses;
         had a stallion of his own. And he was pretty prosperous; he was a
         good farmer, and his wife a hard worker and they got up early. They
         had a long ways to haul to market, see. They were five miles up the
         Ridge and then five miles to Peck from there. He had ten mile haul
         in the old grade. But, anyway, old Malcolm, he had this money ready
         for the Pfeiffer place and he bought that. That made.two hundred
         and forty acres. And he had my brothers,Julius and Simon helping him
         plow. He had two six horse teams- gangplows- black Percherons- and
         he hired them boys, them days, dollar a day was big money- dollar a
         day and board. They plowed and took care of the horses the best they
         could. And they became good friends of Malcoms and he'd hire 'em
         every spring, see to help plow, because he could depend on Simon, es
         pecially. 
         
         The only trouble with Simon was he was a sleepyhead. He
         was hard to wake up in the morning. But Julius wasn't. Julius'd
         come right out. And so, that's the way it went and later years, af
         ter we moved away, they kept— well, his boys growed up, see, he had
         two boys and a daughter. And she married a farmer over on Angel
         Ridge, that had a farm. So she was gone, but the two boys stayed
         and the old folks they just kept building up. The boys helped, helped,
         helped. And they got into this modern machinery and they coulda
         start grabbing more land, you see. If you got one section of land,
         or half a section to farm with and you buy another half a section
         and that makes two sections, you could pay it lots quicker, and he
         was smart enough to figure that out. That's the way he kept going.
         Today, them boys are farmin'— the last I heard they was farming
         sixteen hundred acres. And, of course, they got a lot of grand
         children. They're all growed up and now it's the grandchildren tak
         ing over. You see, the oldest boy's— he's around, now let's see—
         the youngest boys around sixty-five. He's younger than I am, quite
         a bit, about twenty some years, but the older boy he's a little older he's
         about, I guess, about seventy.
         
         SS:  It looks to me like that clock—
         Hr: Yeah, it's one o'clock.
         
         SS:  Looks like it's stopped.
         
         HR:  Yeah, it's quarter after one. Yeah, I haven't wound it. I got to
         wind it.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13652</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Ringsage_Helmer1</previous>
      <next>Ringsage_Helmer3</next>
      <disp_name>Ringsage_Helmer2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
