<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">11/7/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Jean &amp; Stiner Ringsage, Interview #3 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:56:35</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Ringsage, Jean &amp; Stiner</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #3</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife; teacher; nurse's aide</occupation>
      <birthyear>1905</birthyear>
      <residence>Park, Alberta, British Columbia</residence>
      <origin>Moved to Idaho with husband in 1933</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#nurses"&gt;nurses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#smoking"&gt;smoking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#birth control"&gt;birth control&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#religion"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Park"&gt;Park&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Canada"&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Central Ridge"&gt;Central Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13648</file_name>
      <mp3>13649.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13649.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Stiner's father curing a man with the flu; using cupping to drain blood; influence
               of mother's death on father
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A man with flu cured by Stiner's father. Diagnosing illness with a special apparatus.
               Hot fomentations Cupping was used to drain blood from Stiner's tubercular mother.
               Influence of mother's death on father.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Beating a man; working and travelling in southern Idaho; Stiner didn't let people
               know he could wrestle
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Beating a man who got whatever hold he wanted on Stiner. Working and travelling with
               a drinking man in southern Idaho; Stiner didn't let men know he could wrestle. Handling
               two men who attacked him on a pleasant day's walk.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Hunting to feed yourself and others; getting deer in southern Idaho</title>
            <synopsis>Hunting to feed yourself and others. Getting a deer in southern Idaho. A wolf intercepted
               the wounded deer.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Getting a wounded deer; falling through the ice on Raven river</title>
            <synopsis>Getting the deer. Falling through ice on the Raven River and getting out. Walking
               through snow.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Aunts' training in Boston; Aunt Margaret working as a chambermaid; Smoking in secret</title>
            <synopsis>Her aunts were trained in Boston. Aunt Margaret shocked visiting sisters by being
               a chambermaid rather than a nurse; her preference for boyfriends over marriage, after
               mother's experience; she had to smoke in secret. Stiner's
               grandmother tried to hide smoking from children. Margaret's ways.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3420</time>
            <title>Gift giving when visiting; brother's opposition to Stiner taking Park place</title>
            <synopsis>Gift giving when visiting a custom. Brother's opposition to Stiner taking Park place;
               help from stepmother. Gifts from Aunt Margaret.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Caring for family members who needed help</title>
            <synopsis>Caring for half-orphans in the family. Mother helped cousin raise children after wife
               went insane. Rather than missionary work, family helped each other, without being
               showy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3900</time>
            <title>Intimacy of country dances; Love, realism in marriage, and birth control; Changes
               that made for acceptance of smaller families
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Intimacy of country dances compared to loneliness of young today. Love and realism
               in marriage. Birth control methods. Depression and spread of machinery forced acceptance
               of smaller families
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Work open to women; her ambition for being a wife; differences of work women did in
               Canada
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Work open to women was limited, but working women didn't feel socially inferior. Her
               ambition to be a "kept wife." Lack of creativity in most work. Sharing experiences
               with friends. Women didn't do outside work in Canada.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Men taught during depression as steppingstone; more work for women in Park.</title>
            <synopsis>Men taught during depression as steppingstone; More work for women in Park.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5640</time>
            <title>Changes in beliefs; Stiner working for love not money</title>
            <synopsis>Her dependency and resentment changed to acceptance and religious centering, Stiner
               worked for love, not money. Men's need for liberation from wives problems. Tendency
               to try to make mate or children over into image of perfection.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6180</time>
            <title>Her religious experiences and how they changed her</title>
            <synopsis>Her religious experience transformed her life Thankfulness dissolves agitated feelings.
               Reservoir of God's power.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6660</time>
            <title>Discussion of the religious order is she in and the types of meets they had</title>
            <synopsis>Her religious order has no name - its beliefs and practices, in small family groups.
               Her awakening to dogma. Bible study like feeding in a pasture. Types of meetings.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Sunday meetings were in homes and the role of preachers; overcoming extremely difficult
               situations
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sunday meetings in homes. Sharing thoughts from the Bible: "it spoke to me." Role
               of preachers to show life of Jesus, and the simplicity of his teachings. Turning thoughts
               to love; overcoming extremely difficult situations.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7980</time>
            <title>Her earlier religious group affiliations; commitment of preachers; friendships with
               other members
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Her earlier religious group affiliation congealed into doctrine; her full acceptance
               of current faith. Many in the faith had bad experiences in their churches. How the
               members refer to their "way". How she became involved through a meeting at Park (1939);
               a woman who first heard them when she was thirteen. Commitment of preachers. Recognizing
               other "friends"; friendship with another member. Problem of involvement in social
               change.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>9000</time>
            <title>Dullness of third generation's life stories; finding out about father through trip</title>
            <synopsis>Dullness of third generation's life stories compared to first. Finding out about father
               on a trip through Canada: his travel on the Frazier River.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10080</time>
            <title>Her family's colonization of Prince Edward Island; family connections to the Civil
               War
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Her family's colonization of Prince Edward Island in the eighteenth century. Learning
               Yankee ways. Uncle a southern doctor in Civil War.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>10620</time>
            <title>Building mud walls; Americans knowing machinery; Ukrainians surviving because of mud
               buildings
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Lathe for mud walls was four inches apart. American know-how in Canada came from their
               experience with machinery. Ukrainian ability to get by because of their mud buildings.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Hard times on the farm in Alberta; her refusal to sign banknote; Loss of grandparents'
               clock
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Hard times on the farm in Alberta; her refusal to sign banknote. Loss of grandparents'
               clock.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11340</time>
            <title>Family problems in Park</title>
            <synopsis>Family problems in Park caused circumspection on her part. If you were for Roosevelt
               you had friends.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11640</time>
            <title>Aunt's disappointment because Jean became a farm wife; Aunt Amy saw poverty in the
               future; Jean's move towards reconciliation
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Aunt's great disappointment because she became a farm wife instead of using her brain.
               Aunt Amy saw the poverty in her future. Her move towards reconciliation.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>11820</time>
            <title>Mistreatment of bullet wound caused cousin's death; admiration of Stiner by neighbor</title>
            <synopsis>Mistreatment of cousin's bullet wound caused his death. Admiration of Stiner by neighbor
               family. He would have been quite successful if they'd had the breaks. His pleasure
               in breaking mean horses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12240</time>
            <title>Fixing wagon wheels; burning the wheel onto wood</title>
            <synopsis>Fixing wagon wheels; burning the wheel onto wood</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12540</time>
            <title>Segregation of a African-American on a threshing crew by a Southerner</title>
            <synopsis>A Southerner who segregated the black on his threshing crew, making him eat outside
               in the cold. The English accepted this.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12600</time>
            <title>Southerner's wife more prejudiced than he was; treatment of Native Americans on Central
               Ridge
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The man's wife was more prejudiced than he was. If Stiner had been black, he would've
               lost his place. They treated Indians on Central Ridge like whites.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>12900</time>
            <title>Stiner wrestling on threshing outfits; never hurt anyone wrestling; helping an Alberta
               wrestler train
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Wrestling on threshing outfits - they liked to try Stiner out because of his reputation.
               "Calf roped" was calling "uncle." He never wrestled with Idaho's champion wrestler,
               by mutual agreement. He would never hurt anyone
               wrestling. Helping an Alberta wrestler train for a championship fight.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>13620</time>
            <title>Riding rails.</title>
            <synopsis>Riding rails.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>n/a</description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13293_lcoh_13293.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13648</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Ringsage_Jean2</previous>
      <next>Rowan1</next>
      <disp_name>Ringsage_Jean3</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
