<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">6/19/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Hilda Carlson Ruberg, 1976-06-19, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:06:06</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Ruberg, Hilda Carlson</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife; harvest cook; housekeeper</occupation>
      <birthyear>1893</birthyear>
      <residence>Big Meadow, Burnt Ridge, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Family came from North Dakota (1912)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#family life education"&gt;family life education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooking"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#literary"&gt;literary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#newspapers"&gt;newspapers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#music"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Norwegian Americans"&gt;Norwegian Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pregnancy"&gt;pregnancy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fishing"&gt;fishing&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Big Meadow"&gt;Big Meadow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Burnt Ridge"&gt;Burnt Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Spokane"&gt;Spokane&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Karen Purtee</interviewer>
      <file_name>13650</file_name>
      <mp3>13651.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13651.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Hilda's family coming to Troy</title>
            <synopsis>Hilda's family coming to Troy, Nov. 1912 to farm in Big
               Meadow. Mud in the streets of Troy, clap board house had
               to be remodeled. Hilda and two sisters go to Spokane to
               work as housekeepers. Father sells firewood in town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>Housekeeping in Spokane; met future husband at dance</title>
            <synopsis>Housekeeping in Spokane. Thursday afternoon off. Met future husband at a dance - he
               had relatives in Troy. Always had the most responsibility at home being the oldest
               daughter.
               Mother worked outside, Hilda worked inside. Father's
               reasons for coming. Mother liked Troy because it reminded
               her of Norway, her homeland.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>540</time>
            <title>Little Sister Fern burned to death in 1918; winters in Dakota</title>
            <synopsis>Little Sister Fern burned to death in 1918. The day before
               had been a family reunion with pictures taken. In Dakota,
               kids climbed up on the windmill, Hilda gets her
               finger tip cut off in the windmill hook-up. Getting in trouble
               in school for something she hadn't done. Winters in the
               Dakotas. Helena and sister on the frozen snow in Troy.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Mother's children all born at home; pregnancy and female puberty</title>
            <synopsis>Mother's children all born at home. Helena and sister
               sent away when sister is born. Didn't know mothers were
               pregnant, secrecy of childbirth - no discussion with adults
               about facts of life. Helena hid in the closet when first menstrual
               period came. Helena too embarrassed to watch birth of
               kittens. Children were better off without knowledge, they
               enjoyed being children.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Hilda describes her play; chores</title>
            <synopsis>Hilda describes her play, harvesting imitated. Chores
               included dishes and scrubbing the wood floors.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Play continued; Helena and sister imitate the family's dainty cows</title>
            <synopsis>Play continued. Helena and sister would imitate the family's
               daity cows and chew their "cud" in the shade - pitch gum.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1860</time>
            <title>Hilda's cooking for men on thrashing crew</title>
            <synopsis>Hilda's cooking for 28 men on a thrashing crew., thirty days
               in Genesee. The menu, the cook wagon described, Family
               and threshing pictures. Serving the meals, keeping the wagon
               clean, "public" plumbing. The threshing crew. The
               undependable clock. The shade cooler; they did the washing too.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2940</time>
            <title>Cooking for threshers on Burnt Ridge after marriage</title>
            <synopsis>Cooking for threshers on Burnt Ridge after marriage. Made
               $5 a day - big money - on Genesee thresher crew.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Work as housekeeper, lots of girls found employment in Spokane</title>
            <synopsis>Work as housekeeper, lots of Troy girls found employment
               in Spokane. Helena's sister didn't like being a "servant",
               Hilda felt like part of the family. Thursday evening dates.
               Entertainment at the Palouse Round Hall in later years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Literary programs on the Burnt Ridge</title>
            <synopsis>Literary programs on Burnt Ridge, oyster soup, the Literary
               Paper (continued).
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Literary paper; Helena taught at Burnt Ridge school, boarding with Hilda</title>
            <synopsis>The Literary paper. Helena was teacher at Burnt Ridge
               school, boarding with Hilda. The music and dances at the
               Literary. Churches.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Hilda's mother was a good hostess and served lots of food; Norwegian recipes; ladies
               employment opportunities
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Hilda's mother was a good hostess and served lots of good
               food. Fattigman, "poor man's cake" - a Norwegian recipe.
               Mother's cooking, some about mother and father. Posing for
               portraits. Ladies' employment opportunities: housekeeping,
               teaching, clerking in a store. Knee pants for boys, the
               stylish tight sheath dresses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Hilda's mother was extremely clean; mother's goiter and death</title>
            <synopsis>Hilda's mother was so clean she wore the paint off. Once
               when she spilled boiling oil on her foot, her only concern was
               for the stain on the floor. Mother's goiter and death.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5160</time>
            <title>Swedish and Norwegian names; setting up Hilda's first home</title>
            <synopsis>Swedish and Norwegian names - all "sons"; Carl Carlson
               becomes Carl Rose due to confusion. Setting up Hilda's
               first home (1914). Hilda operates the farm after her
               husband's death in 1931 for 5 years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Raising beans, farmers' economics after WWI; depression</title>
            <synopsis>Raising beans, farmers' economics after WWI, depression.
               Selling wheat at 220 a bushel during depression so she can
               by her girls some Christmas gifts. Sold butter, had people
               follow her into the store to buy hers. How she made butter.
               Helena's creamery tales. Hilda's chores to keep the farm
               running. Hauling water to Burnt Ridge.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6240</time>
            <title>Hilda has her babies at home; pregnant girl though the was growing because she ate
               watermelon seeds
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Hilda has her babies at home, first daughter arrives before
               the doctor does. The pregnant girl who thought she was
               growing because she had eaten watermelon seeds. Morals
               were of a higher standard then as compared to now. The bad girl was marked and an
               exception. Hilda's chores before her
               baby was born.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6660</time>
            <title>Hilda and her husband fishing; what Troy looked like in 1912</title>
            <synopsis>Hilda and her husband fishing. What Troy looked like in
               1912; horses up to their knees in mud. Raised strict by
               mother.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6960</time>
            <title>Milking and responsibility not entrusted to all the children; Mother's tumor turns
               out to be sister fern
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Milking a responsibility not entrusted to all the children.
               Ed's tricks in milking. Ed wears a dress to fool the cow.
               Mother's tumor turns out to be sister Fern.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>With Helena Carlson (sister-in-law) Work as cook, housekeeper and farmer.
         Women's responsibilities at home, Childbirth and children's ignorance. Neighborhood
         entertainment. 6-19-76 2 hr p KP
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13297_lcoh_13297.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13650</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Rowan2</previous>
      <next>Sampson_Clarice1</next>
      <disp_name>Ruberg</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
