<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">1/25/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Clarice Sampson, 1975-01-25, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:30:24</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Sampson, Clarice</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker; teacher; clerk at David's Store</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Utah (1892)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#poor"&gt;poor&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#murders"&gt;murders&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#brothels"&gt;brothels&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#libraries"&gt;libraries&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#weddings"&gt;weddings&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#movies"&gt;movies&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#home economics"&gt;home economics&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13587</file_name>
      <mp3>13588.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13588.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Father's views about family; mother's broken collarbone and surgery</title>
            <synopsis>Father liberalized his views about family and gave
               her more freedom. Charging at stores. Father's
               ledger. Mother's broken collarbone and serious
               surgery.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Brother's death in the Philippines; parents favoritism; resentment of her brother's
               freedom
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Brother's death in the Philippines. The children said mother favored boys, father
               girls. Her resentment of brother's freedom to go places; he was accident-prone.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Mother giving mittens to a poor family; sister getting very gold chaperoning</title>
            <synopsis>Mother managed to give a poor family mittens without
               them knowing. Sister got very cold chaperoning a
               sleighing party.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Poor families in Moscow; Use of first telephones and baths in town</title>
            <synopsis>Poor families. Use of first telephones and baths in town.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1980</time>
            <title>Stories about a man named Wild Davey; Dr. Watkins shooting</title>
            <synopsis>Wild Davey. Kids pretended he was after them and said he ate his dogs. Hotels fed
               him. Hearing news of Dr. Watkins shooting. Killing of Steffens.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Curiosity about red light district; father finding a diamond ring</title>
            <synopsis>Children's curiosity about red light district. Father found a diamond ring, probably
               dropped by someone who'd won it gambling.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2940</time>
            <title>Going to school in Moscow; mothers coming to visit unexpectedly</title>
            <synopsis>School in Moscow. Program on the last day of the year. Speaking pieces. Subjects.
               Mothers came into the classroom to visit, unexpectedly.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Reading as a child; assigned card number one in the library</title>
            <synopsis>Her reading as a youngster - Elsie Dinsmore books. Assigned card number one in the
               library.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4140</time>
            <title>Being a flower girl in a wedding; first cars and movie theaters in Moscow</title>
            <synopsis>Flower girl at wedding. First cars and movie theatre.
               Summer stock in Moscow.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4740</time>
            <title>Going to prep school and being interested in physical education; disliking home economics;
               wanting to be a doctor
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Prep school. Interest in physical education. Father's limited view of what women could
               study. Dislike of home economics study. A woman teacher training to be a doctor inspired
               her to become a doctor, but father was strongly opposed.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Red Cross work in the flu epidemic</title>
            <synopsis>Red Cross work in the flu epidemic.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Schooling in Moscow. Interests as a girl. Limitation of career opportunities.
         Mother's poor health. 1-25-75 1.5 hr 31p LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         LAURA SCHRAGER: Did she have much say in money matters?
         
         CLARICE MOODY SAMPSON: Well, you know, my father, you pretty near always had
         to ask him for money. He just. But you could charge and he'd
         pay the bills. But like we youngsters, course I was the last one and
         if anyone would have had an allowance I'd been the one because he liberalized
         his way of thinking about his family so much. And my brother who was five
         years older than I, we did so many things that our older brothers and
         sisters couldn't do. We weren't told you have to be home at ten thirty
         from a party. I was never told that in my life. But we didn't go and stay
         unearthly hours or anything, but my older brother and sisters even if
         they went to a dance they had to come home at ten thirty. Of course, the
         dances started earlier, but that was just the rule of the house. But as
         far as money was concerned there wasn't a lot of it but we had to ask.
         And I think I showed you a check the otier day my father had written; I think
         it was to buy a hat one time. But he never said you can't have it. thad
         to ask for it, and sort of say wlat you were going to do with it. And
         with running the house, my mother was never restricted as to what she could
         buy or anything but of course, once every year when Creighton's had their
         "Red Tag Sale" she would go in and buy so many sheets. Well,she made the
         sheets, you see, she bought the muslin and made the sheets way back when
         I was a child, and so many white tablecloths and like, yardage. And then
         I think it wasn't charged on a monthly basis, it was probably paid twice
         a year, the account at Creighton's Store. And as far as the groceries were
         concerned, the man would cd% around to our door each morning to see what
         we wanted. We always had a charge account. And Mama would order what she
         needed and they would deliver it later|in the day. But, of course, didn't
         need to go in because there were no fresh vegetables or anything, you didn't
         need to go in to see what you wanted. It was just a matter of staples and
         things like that that you ordered because the vegetables you
         had, they were canned and in your own cellar rather than being in bins at
         the store. 
         
         But my dad, every night, he'd read the evening papeis after we'd had
         supper. And he'd read the papers, the daily papers, and then he'd go to his
         desk which was in Papa's and Mauris bedroom and sit at his desk as long as
         it took him to account for all the day's spending and put it in a book4.a
         a ledger. And that was done every day, and he knew exactly the amount of
         money that had been spent or that hft been given to each child or if he'd
         given Mama any cash. I know in that book that I'm going to let you see,
         that register: "Wife—$2." WellnoY don't have no idea what Mama wanted to
         spend two dollars for, but that was the way it was recorded in the book:
         "Wife—$2."
         
         And as far as our school books and school supplies, Bodg in's were
         the only ones vho had school books in those days. W'e got what we needed and
         charged it, and my dad would pay the bill. And we weren't extravagant, I mean
         buying junk and stuff we didn't need. We knew we should get what we needed
         and that was it. And my mother's health wasn't very good. When I was a little
         child, about eighteen months or two years old, she was taking my
         oldest sister out to visit friends in the country and some boys came along
         on horseback wearing chaps, and yelling and shouting and having fun. It
         frightened the horse and he ran away. And he went off of the read down
         an incline and I don't remember this of course, but it broke my mother's
         collarbone and s onebody brought her into town, and I guess got the horse
         and the buggy and so on. And I had wanted to go so bad with Mama but
         she left me at home with my other sisters. And it was very fortunate that
         she didn't have the baby sitting in her lap or something while she was driving.
         But the way they, and I think it must have been Dr. Watkins, I don't remember,
         but the nextdoor neighbor came over to help when the doctor came. And he
         like had her make out of muslin, an old sheet or something, two big doughnuts,
         stitch 'em together, and my mother's arms were put through the holes; they
         stuffed 'em with cctton, and my mother's arms were put through the holes and
         they laced em together, front and back,to hold that collarbone in place.
         
         Well, as a result, it mended across at the end—it didn't heal directly
         the two parts of the bones together, one was on top of the other. And she
         always, always had aches and pains in that collarbone, you know, damp
         Wiather or anything. But it must have been neuritis, it - pfbably pressed
         on a nerve or something. And so years later—I remember this—Dr,Gritman
         did an operation on Mama's collarbone and sawed the bones apart and wired
         them together and she was that way . the rest of her life, with her
         collarbone wired together. But from the time, oh I would judge I was eight
         or ten, she had to have some very, severe surgery. I think it was for a
         kinked bowel, a kinked colon. But it was very serious surgery and they
         despaired of her life, but my mother always went to prayer meeting, every
         Wednesday or Thursday night, whenever it was at our church they had
         the mid-week prayer meeting. And so that particular night they turned it
         into a piayer service for Mama. And she finally recovered. But it was such
         a big incision they made in her abdomen that she was never strong again,
         you know. And sa I remember my father got her, it was bigger than my little
         girl rocker, just a next sized rocker. And she would sit in that because
         it was hard for her to sit in an ordinary rocking chair. And she wore what
         we oiled dressing sacks. They were like our house robes now, only they were
         short,.she wore a skirt underneath. But her abdomen was . quite big after
         that because of the surgery. I suppose the muscles never recovered from
         such a big incision. And so she always wore a dressing sack. We usually
         had our clothes made at home, but a dressmaker made her a fancy one. And
         I can remember, it was lightweight wool, grey, and it was tied with a ribbon
         around the waist and it had a fancy collar. So that was sort of her dress
         up clothes while she was recuperating from her surgery. But so my mother
         never could do heavy housework or anything after that. And everybody had
         their chores to do in our home.
         
         LS: What did you do?
         
         CS:  Well, I don't remember so much, only I always had to wipe dishes 'cause we
         wiped em then, you know. And I can remember having to wipe dishes after
         supper. And ray oldest brother was in the Philipines then because he graduated
         from college in 1901, and he took his degree in absentia because he was sent
         to the Philipines. And I have a picture of Albert telling Mama good-bye
         out on the front porch, and she had this dressing sack on At I've told
         you about. And Albert there in his overcoat with his suitcase, and he'd
         for some reason had gotten a wide-brimmed hat like, well Teddy Roosevelt
         wearing them, you know, I don't know why, it probably was a Stetson, a good
         hat or something. But he was sent to the Philipines by the United States
         government, he was a civil engineer. And he had charge of lighthouse and
         bridge construction in the Philipines. And it was considered a very fine
         job, and I think President Taft was president then. And they had a great
         deal of social life in Manil a and my brother kept polo ponies you know.
         Their houses were built up and the animals were below, but they were built
         up for—well, it was thier to live up off of the ground because, I
         don't know whether it was swampy ground or what it was. But Harry and I
         visited Manila in 1963 on a trip to the Orient, and it was three to four weeks
         voyage to get there, y'see. And when my brother, older than I, Morris, who
         was five years older than I an, he was in prep school at the university.
         Well,he was at the age, he just didiPt think he was getting anyplace.
         And my father was pretty lenient with Morris like he was me. And Albert
         wrote that if Morris wanted to come over there, he knew he could get a job.
         
         And so Morris, I think he was eighteen or ninetten, he hadn't finished
         prep school, and he went over there. My father let him go over there. And he
         lived with Albert in his home over there. And of course they kept Filipino
         to do thair work and Morris really.thought that was the heighth of
         perfection, to have a Filipino boy come and hand him a book or his cigarettes
         or something, whatever he wanted, you know, to be waited on. He just ate it
         up. And Albert had told him, you had to have your white clothes all made,
         you know, made to measure. They wore whites entirely because of the heat,
         white ducks and so on. I think they were all duck material. And so he told
         Morris he could go to his tailor and have him what Morris thought he needed.
         Well, Morris liked clothes awfully well. So. went all out, he had everything.
         He had just everything he could use. And then after he'd been there a little
         while he got a job with the Manila diMftil Hospital, which was a huge hospital
         as chief clerk, that was who kept the books and the accounts and so on.
         So he did all right for himself even though he was very young. And of
         course there was a great deal of social life which he enjoyed. But my
         oldeat brother Albert then, had to come home in 1908 because his
         health was getting bad—the climate and his work and all. And even before
         he could come home he went to some health clinic on the coast or some place,
         or San Francisco. 
         
         I don't know where became I just was young enough that
         I didn't pay much attention, to build himself up a little before he ever came
         home. But he arrived home in time for my sister Ethel's wedding which was
         in December of 1908. But in 1911, Morris, who was still over there and
         working as chief clerk in the Manila General Hospital became very ill and
         had to have surgery. And it was evidently a gall bladder operation. Well,
         my mother and my father didn't know about this surgery ahead of time but
         somebody wrote in the meantime that he was in the hospital and had had
         surgery. But in February of 1911 the cablegram came to my brother Albert who
         was living in TaiComa then, he'd taken a job with a big construction company,
         in fact he built that big, famous depot in Tafcoraa that has been made a
         national And the city of Tacoma is keeping it although it isn't
         in use as a station anymore. But it's a beautiful building with a big dome
         on top, it's beautiful. Whenever I've gone th%e, I always admire it with
         great pride because my brother built that, the company he was with. But this
         cablegram came to Albert that Morris had died of septicemia, which is blood
         poisoning of course. And they were to have a funeral service there in
         Manila and then his body was to be sent home. So about the middle of March
         his body arrived in San Francisco and my brother and my father went to bring
         it home, and he was buried the Moscow Cemtery at the age of 
         which was pretty sad. And ray mother never quite got over that, it just about
         broke her heart.
         
         LS: Was Morris sort of her favorite or something because he was young?
         
         CS:  Oh no, he was just her boy. Of course when we were kids we always said
         Mama favored the boys in the family and Dad fajbred the girls. (Chuckles).
         You know how kids are. But to Mama, her boys were just perfect, and they
         were good to her. But my brother Albert, my two sisters were in college,
         and he was so good. He sent them money every year, and they bought nice
         material and had a new ball gown every year, party dress. Because they were
         in college and maybe Dad couldn't always afford it, and having two in
         college at the same time was expensive in those days for their family income
         as it is now. But Albert always did that for the girls evety year, and I know
         they were so proud of the dresses.fney had that Albert had sent them the
         money to buy the material to make their party dresses.
         
         LS: Was that unusual for women to go to college in those days?
         
         CS:  Oh no, no. Many Moscow girls went on to college, and of course by that time
         the Ridenbaugh Hall had been built so they had a dormitory for women although
         they had no accomodations for men stutters* Sutptnere were quite a few girls
         who went.And well many Moscow girls went on to college,, tnat was the
         thing in our family—everybody was supposed to go to college. Although my
         oldest sister, Mabel, did not finish college, and this is a long story,
         shall I tell it?
         
         LS: If it's a good one.
         
         CS:  Do you wat to shut it off for a minute?
         
         LS: Sure. (Break)
         
         CS:  I suppose their boys went through a time when they didn't like girls. Of
         course, I know my bro'her, Morris, when I was, ha-was five years older, and
         when I was about ten and he was fifteen, he thought I was the scum of the
         earth, you know. And I used to resent it that the boys could go out to the
         satfpit and swim and good little girls never could do things like that.
         And the boys would go on hikes and girls couldn't. Of course I was enough
         younger that Mama wouldn't have let me go because I would have been a
         responsibility for him. But it alfc seemed like everytime he went on one
         of those hikes that the boys used to have something, always happened to
         him. Whether he was accident prone or what, I don't know. But my dad hai
         given him—this shows how lenient he was--a .22 for Christmas. And one time
         Morris had taken his,22, which any mother worry about, went out with
         several boys and some way, whether he was walking along or what, I don't
         know, but he got shot through the calf of his leg. That was one accident.
         And then another time, he was always collecting, wherever he went he was
         collecting something. And on this hike he was looking for some special kind
         of rocks. And some boy in the group threw a rock against a tree, a live
         small tree and it bounded right back and hit Morris in themouth and knocked
         out hi8 two front teeth, his upper teeth. So I can just imagine my mother
         hating to have a Saturday come when the boys wanted to take a hike for fear
         something would happen to Morris. But I don't thiik she ever deprived him of
         going. But those were two things I remembered that happened to him on these
         hikes.
         
         LS: Did you play outside much?
         
         CS:  Oh yes. In the winter we did lots of coasting. And I can remember I always
         stayed too long and my hands get so cold. My mother knitted my mittens,
         and she made me new ones every winter, whether they were worn out, whether I
         needed them or not. And if the old pair, there was a real poor family who
         lived around the corner from us and they so many children, but they were
         proud. But she'd take those mittens out,, way from the sidewalk in front
         of our house and drop them down. And when they'd come along for school they'd
         pick them up, and of course they didn't know to whom they belonged so
         they had a pair of mittens. they were always bare-handed. And she
         used to feel so sorry.
         
         But I'd come home from coasting and I'd squall because my hands were so
         cold. Well, instead of putting them in warm water as we think the thing is
         to do now, she put 'era in cold water and t!at made 'em hurt all the worse.
         I'd cry all the harder, but she was very patient. But we'd stay out too
         long, you know. We were having such a good time and all at once we'd just
         be so cold we had to go home and get warmed up.
         
         But the snow was different then, It stayed on so much longer. Sometimes
         we had snow for Thanksgiving but not always. But it would stay on for
         several months as I remember. And then as I got a little older we had
         sleigh ride parties and go to Pullman and have oyster stew or something
         over there, you know.*go out in the country to some friend's house have
         a supper. And that was a form of our winter social life, going on sleigh
         rides. And I remember once my sister, Myra, who was home, chaperoned one of
         our sleigh ride parties, boys and girls. Of course the man who drove the
         team had this big bed on the sleigh and he it with straw and we'd
         all take blankets and we were cozy and warm. But because my sister Myra
         was the chaperone they thought she should sit up on the seat. And I know I
         had a muff, and the style then in muffs, they were kind of flat and they
         weren't with a lot of llling in them,aso I insisted she take my muff. And why,
         she practically froze to death. She held the muff up in font of her face,
         you know, I don't know that she ever chaperoned a party again for my group
         of friends because she was] just entirel5°uncomfortable on that sleigh ride.
         Do you want to shut it off a minute?
         
         LS: Um hum. (Break)
         
         CS:  We didn't as far as bofrs and gkls being together, I can remember when we
         were around twelve and thirteen we had a club. Oh, there must have been
         twenty-four or twenty-five children, boys and girls mixed. And we would have
         parties every once in a while somebody in the group would have a party. And
         we called our club the Q. A. E. Club. Did I tell you this?
         
         LS: Urn hum.
         
         CS:  Well, we better cut this out, well, you've heard this, um hum. (Break).
         
         CS:   poor households. Sometimes just didn't have adequate, warm
         clothing. But I don't know tiat there was every any. We didn't have
         rummage sales, and maybe church organizations, women's aid societies and
         so on, ladies' aid societies in the churches did something to help out
         those people. But this family around the corner from us, the^father was a
         blackfnith, and in the winter, I suppose, he didn't have tocjmuch to do. And
         we always considered that they were poor people, they didn't have as much
         as some of us did. But of course then none of us had. Telephones weren't
         too common. Not many of us had phones; we couldn't call other up. Only,
         we had—did I tel you this? neighbor who was a young lady in the
         family was one of the telephone operators, you know. And they lived about
         blocks from our house. So I used to go down to--their tune was 
         to the Ralph home and call up Lillian , my friend, because her
         father was a doctor and they had a telephone. So I could call her up. I
         think she was about the only one of my friends who had a telephone. But I
         always thought that was pretty fine to be able to go to the neighbor's and
         telephone. And , another friend of mine—this is funny—and it was the
         Naylor family. They lived in town4hen, and Roy and Ralph and their
         sister Ruth lived out on the farm. They ware through high school and
         lived out on the farm. And Mr. Naylor had an insurance business in
         Moscow so they lived next door to Ralpht two blocks. And the youngest grl
         in the Naylor family, and I were great friends. And they had a bathroom
         put on their house before we did, the sewer hadn't gone up as far as our
         house. And so Saturday morning Mrs. Naylor used to tell rae,"Bring your clean
         clothes over and take and bath at our house. I used to do that, and
         oh it was fun, you know, to have a bath in a real bathtub. But of course it
         wasn't long after that the We had city water, of course, but the sewer
         came up Lynn Avenue so my father built on a bathroom and we had our own
         bathtub with toilet facilities right in the house then.
         
         LS: Can you tell what you know of Wild Davey?
         
         CS:  Well, when I was a little girl, we lived down Lynn Avenue, 722 Lynn Avenue.
         And Wild Davey lived, I don't think it was in the city limits, but it was
         down at the end of Lynn Avenue toward the bridge that crosses the creek
         down there on the Highway 8. And a little house, and I thine it must have hd
         about two rooms in it. But when we'd go on picnics or anything and walk by
         there. Of course a favorite place for us to take Sunday walks was to go to
         the cerat.ery and took at the monuments. And of course I was very interested
         of my father. But we had to walk by Wild Davey's house and we always went
         by pretty fast because we weren't actually afraid of hira, but we just knew
         that was his home. And then he always had at least three dogs around and
         I don't remember even that the dogs barked at us, but we didn't tarry when
         we were passing Wild Davey's house. But he did go along Lynn Avenue going
         to town with his three dogs and I thought his hair was braided but I see
         it was just flowing long hair in the picture. I don't remember of him wearing
         a gun or anything as he hadt in tne picture. But he would pass our house,
         and of course if I was out in the yard playing or anything, I always looked
         at Wild Davey as he passed by. But did I tell you the experience at
         Naylor's farm?
         
         LS: Not on tape, I don't have it on tape.
         
         CS:  Well, when I was a little girl then at this time that Wild Davey lived down
         here, I was invited to the Naylor ranch every year for a week two or three
         different times during the summer. And he used to drop in at Naylor's every
         so often and they'd invite him to eat at noon, he'd be hiking around the
         country. And they were always good to him, they gave him dinner. And Neppa-
         Naylor and I, you know, Ruth the oldest sister was living with her brothers
         and they were running the farm and she was always scared we might be kinda
         smarty or somefeiag with him. And she always cautioned us. But then a favotite
         game of ours was to run through the rows of corn and pretend that Wild Davey
         was after us. And I don't know that he ever diased anybody in his life. I
         don't think that he was that kind of a person, but it was fun to imagine
         that.
         
         LS: Was it just his looks with his dogs that were so. 
         
         CS:  I think so, and then he was very much to himself. I don't know that he ever
         And how he happened to stop at Naylor for his noon meal, I don't know
         that. And the Naylor farm was four miles out of town or something and probably
         it was just a good morning's walk out there, but we were always told that
         whoever ran the hotels were very good to give him leftover food. And Mr. Creighton,
         who owned Creighton's Store, would give him clothing we were told. But as far
         as his ever doing anything, working at any job, I neveir knew of it if he did.
         But he was a character in Moscow and we all accepted him as such, you 
         Nobody seemed to step over bounds and try to communicate with him or
         anything unless he wished it.
         LS Did he just leave town?
         
         CS:  Well, I don't actually know what ever happened, and I can't remember how old
         I was or when we didn't know there was Wild Davey anymore. But finally
         somebody bought the house and moved it out on Orchard Avenue where it still
         is. Rooms have been added to it. And then in the upper part of that land that
         his house occupied people built a home, and if was afterwards, I can't
         remember who built it, I could If I thought a while. But afterwards, Mrs. Lainey,
         that was Dr. and Mrs. Lainey's home. He was on the faculty at the university,
         and that was on the land that Wild Davey had lived on.
         
         LS: Did you ever hear that he had written a book?
         
         CS:  Well, I don't think I've ever heard that Wild Davey wrote a book, but I know
         a man came here, not too many years ago, it sems to me, getting information
         on Wild Davey. And I didn't know that Wild Davey had been with Kit Carson
         and so on. I just knew him as a child as Wild Davey in Moscow, and that was it.
         Course the children used to say that why he had so many dogs if he didn't
         have any food he'd kill and cook one of his dogs but I think that* just
         childhood speculation, you know, I don't believe that was ever true
         because I'm  I know the hotels were good to him to give him food
         
         LS: Are there any other people that were like him, that were sort of unusual?
         C : Well, we did have a man here later, and they called him "Seven Jackets." And
         it was because he actually wore seven jackets. I don't know whether he wore
         all the clothes he had. But he wasn't around very long. And I don't know
         where he lived or anything about what he did or anything. But he was called
         "Seven Jackets", and he actually wore seven jackets. And whether he did it
         just because that was all the clothes he had or not, I don't know, but
         he wasn't around Moscw for very long. And of course, they were eccentrics,
         those two men, but we had , other people to wonder as a
         child and I never asked for an explanation how they came to Moscow.and
         one was Sir John Moore. Did I tell you this before?
         
         LS: No.
         
         CS:  But I don't know why he was called, but my parents always called him
         Sir John Moore. And whether he had come from England or what. . .i know where
         he lived in Moscow, but I don't know anything about him. But I know that he
         was always known as Sir John Moore.
         
         LS: Was he an English fellow?
         
         CS:  Well, I just rather imagine he was. And of course you know about the Bovills?
         
         LS: Did you meet them as a chtd?
         
         CS:  The Bovills? Oh yes. I went with my family up there on a camping trip at
         Hog Meadows, I think. They expected to fish, and I was a small child on that
         cfhping trip because my mother drove her horse and and I was the
         baby, left so early in the morning that I wasn't even dressed; I was
         carried out in ray nightgown and wrapped in a blanket and put in the buggy.
         And I suppose when they stopped for a lunch or something later on, I
         was dressed. But I don't remember too much about camping trip. Only that
         that was when Dr. Watkins was shot. And as we came back home on Sunday after
         the week's camping trip, out at the half-way stopping place where the A/egro
         family, the black fanily lived, a man drove up with a team of horses in a
         buggy or a hack or something and told the news about Dr. Watkins being shot
         that morning and what had gone on in Mcsw. But by the time we got to the
         afternoon, which was real late afternoon, there was no evidence of
         it at the Steffen home. But afterward we were told there were bullet holes
         in the house. They wald have been on the other side anyway, than the roadside
         on the road because the posse came down though the field and were in that.
         The creek was different in those days, they dredged it and made a new
         chanel for it. But it did cross the Steffen's place, Paradise Creek, so
         it was summer you see, and the posse wai down , perhaps the creek was dry
         or almost dry and that was their barricade, the bank of the creek. But
         of course as you know, the story was-feid of how young Steffen mother came
         out and seid,"Don't shoot any more, he's dead."And so the posse didn't. . .i
         don't know how they happened to see her or whether she carried a white something
         so they didn't shoot or what. And several in town claimed it was thenbullet
         that killed him. I know there were two men in town that I know of ,
         thought they were the ones who shot him. But maybe he killed himself, you
         don't know. But that was an event in Moscow, of course, that will always be
         remembered I presume by oldtimers. And of course It- in Carol Brink-s
         book so it
         
         LS: Another thing I wanted to ask was were there any divorced women in town
         and was that
         
         CS:  Well.
         
         LS: Because Carol refers to a few and she makes them sound like they were very
         ostraized by the people in town.
         
         CS:  Right off I can't think of any that I actually knew who were divorced. Of
         course divorce was very much out of line in those days, you know. And I
         just can't think of any. Of course we had what they aall the red light
         district. And of course that was always a great source of curiosity
         amongst the youngers in Moscow because we knew the houses that ttey occupied
         in the part of town where they were. And of course,
         about delivering things down there to them, but it was just all
         hearsay as far as we children were concerned. We were terribly curious aboout
         the red light district and so on.
         
         LS: You didn't know. 
         
         CS:  Oh no, we didn't realize what they were talking about. In those real early
         days, maybe before ray fattier and mother and the family came to Moscow,
         before I was born, there was a great deal of gambling in Moscow and for
         high stakes, too. But I don't know where the gambling took place or anything
         because if it was still going on after they came to town, my father was
         not a gambling man and Jo we never heard of who participated in these big,
         high stake card games. But I think I'll tell you this.
         One day ray father was going to town, and he, walking along, he was
         going to work. He saw a ring and he picked it up, and it was a diamond
         ring Nobody ever put an ad—well, we did have a pper but there was never
         any advertising for that ring or anything. And evidently ray father didn't
         run an ad that one had been found because he just kept it for a while in
         safe keeping. But we presumed that somebody had bet that diamond ring on
         cards; that/es always what our presumption was in our family and perhaps
         were intoxicated and lost it.But by and by, my father had my mother start
         wearing that ring, she just had a wedding ring. And she wore it, and that's
         been handed down In our family. I don't have it but it still belongs in the
         family. It's an unusual mounting. My sister Myra wore it after my mother
         died, it was given to her. And then when she died she wanted it to go to a
         niece in the family, and it's there today.
         
         LS: Can you tell me some more about some of the things that went on in the grade
         school that you remember and high school?
         
         Things like, you know, what the school day was like. Things like that.
         
         CS:  Well, I went to three different schoolhouses; we had three during then.
         And none of them are in existence now. But my first two grades were in
         what we call the old high school on Third Street, which is where the
         educational unit is there now, across from the Methodist church. And
         then my third grade was up in the old Russell School, which was a wooden
         structure, which was the first schoolhouse that was built in Moscow.
         But it was just a two room school, one above and one below, aroora below,when
         but they'd added a wing across the front with four rooms—two above and
         two below. And I was in the lower room toward the north when I was in the
         third grade. And Miss Clara, an old family here in Moscow was
         ray schoolteacher. And there were outside toilets. You had to go out of
         the building to go to the toilet and I think they were just a privy sort of
         a toilet at first. But then I went back to that building when I was in the
         fifth grade, in an upstairs room in theprginal part of the building and by
         then the toilets were outside but they were the kind that when you sat on
         the seat caused the water to coiae down from the tank or something. You
         didn't flush them yourself, they automatically flushed when you sat on the
         toilet seat. And then after that, my fourth grade, however, was up in
         Irving School which was a wooden structure up on the corner of Adams and
         A Street, right on the corner. And I think there were only four rooms in
         that building as I remember, they were huge rooms because the teachers
         carried a very great student load in those days.
         
         LS: How big were the classes?
         
         CS:  Well, I think there wee at least forty children when I was up there in
         my room in the fourth grade. And Miss Lena Whitmore was ray teacher. And
         ray sister Myra, that was her first year of teaching, and there was a little
         building down in that same block where the Russell School and the
         Irving School were that they called the  And she taught a fourth
         grade that year. There were lots of fourth graders it seemed in Moscow
         tlft year. And she didn't have that many students though because the
         building was small. But all my friends went to my sister but she didn't
         want her little sister in her room so I went to Miss Lena Whitmore. But
         Miss Whitmore was a lovely, lovely teacher and I enjoyed my year in her room.
         And I remember so well at the close of the year, I probably have it yet
         some place, she gave us a little folder with her picture on the front, and
         then maybe it was the program for the last day of school or something inside
         because we always had a program and spoke pieces and sang songs, and our
         ithers always came to the progr^j. There was never any fathers because they
         were working. But out mothers always came to the last day of school for
         where we.
         the afternoon program I used to speak pieces there, and then as I told you
         before, I gave readings as I got older so that was my particular talent.
         
         LS: What kind of things would you do at reading What was the difference between
         a reading and a piece?
         
         CS:  Well, a piece is usually poetry—that's what we considered then. But when I
         graduated from the eighth grade we had graduation exercises just like high
         school. Only of course we just had a new white dress to wear for graduation.
         And I read the class reading, I gave it that year, was James Whitcomb Riley's,
         "The Bear Story". And you probably don't know that; it was several pages long.
         But it was, he sort of wrote free verse, you know. And tJat was the reading
         I gave. It was on the program as a reading. And then when I graduated from
         high school I gave tiie class reading, and that was a chapter from Mrs. Wiggs
         of the Cabbage Patch. And I don't suppose you've even heard of that book.
         
         LS: I've heard of it; I never read it. How were you picked to give the reading?
         
         CS:  Well,just because you had spoken piecesall your life, I guess.
         
         LS: Did most people go on to higfi school from eighth grade?
         CS" Well, our eighth grade class was very big; I think there were two eighth
         grades, proBbly all these fourth graders had come on to be eighth graders
         together. And that was in the Irving School, and we had the two upper
         rooms then, the eighth grade.And Mr. who was principal of the
         school taught one. And well, I think they were, how was it? I don't think
         there were any little children downstairs, no seventh grades were downstairs.
         And it was departmentalized, we had different teachers come in for different
         subjects, you see. They'd come to stage in our education. And before you
         go I'll show you a picture of that eighth grade class. I've got it downstairs
         already to go to the museum. But the eighth grade classes were big because
         there were several families who had gone to country schools. Well, all the
         families hadNmoved to town because Arthur tt^e was in ray eighth grade and
         his family still lived out on the farm. So whether the country schools quit
         having anything above a sixth grade then I don't know,the country schools
         surrounding Moscow. Because there was a girl Clarice Abrahamson, they called
         her Clara, but her name was Clarice, like mine, came in from out here at Blaine.
         And I think she was driven back and forth by the family. And Arthur would
         have had to have been brought in to school. And I think there were others
         in that eighth grade who—Ward Gano was in that class, but his family had moved
         in from the farm by, the time he was in the ejghth grade.
         
         LS: Was there any difference between the kids that tame in from the country?
         
         CS:  Not that I remember, urn hum. Not that I remember. They fitted right into the
         were
         school program here. But thereKbig classes and how the teachers could handle
         so many. . .But having it departmentalized it made it easier with those
         big classes because probabjr one teacher in all four seventh and eighth
         grades, y'see. So that they actually didn't have to cover as much as if tlry
         taught all the Because I know one thing we had was agriculture. We
         had a little red book and just about farming and land in general, you
         know, that was what it was. It wasn't a very big book. But that was one subject
         that was taught in eighth grade—agriculture. And I don't know of anything
         else that was different. Of course they weren't dividedJfcto social studies
         and scientific studies and so on as they are now. But we had physiology,
         and spelling and even writing, we had writing lessons and reading, and a
         separate course in grammar from the readingcause the reading was actually
         reading literature out of a book, ysee. And you were asked to read orally.
         And I think that's why the children don't read so well today, many of them,
         because they tiaven't had oral reading in school, but we did. And it was always
         a great pride if your mother came, and ray mother would visit the school
         several times, visit my room several times during the year, unannounced of
         course. She'd knock on the door and the teacher would open the door and here
         was my mother come to visit the school. But many of the children's mothers
         did that. But if it would happen to be reading class and you were called
         upon to walk up front and read you were quite delighted, you know. And
         that was one of my better subjects so it pleased me greatly to be asked to
         read when ray mother was present. I read a great deal as a child, though to
         myself, books.
         
         CS:  Quite often some member of my family would get me a new book for my birthday
         or Christmas, but when I was a little girl, and this was before ray oldest
         brother left home because he used to tease me so. I read the Elsie Dinsmore
         books. Have you ever of them?
         
         LS: Uh uh.
         
         CS:  Well, Elsie, her fathov was at^ay and she seemed to live with her grandparents.
         This was a whole series of books. You took Elsie through many years. But
         her father woild come home to visit occasionally, and he expected such perfection
         in her, you know. And he would punish her if she didn't come up to his
         expectations, you know. And so my brother would tease me and Well, come
         Elsie, father's going to spank you for not doing so and so." And of
         course Elsie would weep. And so I shed many tears along with Elsie. And that
         was a whole series of books—Elsie Dinsmore books. And then a little later
         the Five Little Pepper books came out. And I have Five Little Peppers and How
         They Grew and Five Little Peppers Abroad. And then of course when I was a
         little older I read Louisa Alcott's I progressed through my reading.
         
         But when the library came to Moscow they had a room up over where Brown's
         funiture is now, where they keep their appliances, maybe you've had this
         story told to you about one summer. Well, every so often a big chest of books,
         as I remember it, it was abig wooden chest, would come in from Boise with
         a new series of books, and you could borrow a book. And one of the books I got,
         I think the books were in Moscow for a month from this one chest load. And
         of course, you'd try to read several, you know. But the last book I got was
         quite a big book and I didn't get to finish it and I had to return it and I
         don't know to this day what that book was, but I thought it was fascinating.
         
         But when I've described it to people, they have told me they bet it was Brinker
         and the Silver Skates because it was quite a thick book. And it may have been
         I didn't get far enough into, that I just don't know whether I was reading
         Hans Brinker. Of course I read it afterwards. But I just can't associate what
         it was.
         
         LS: What kind of books did you like to read?
         
         CS:  Oh, just children's stories. Of course I can remember from a child I was
         interested in the newspapers. I didn't sit down and read the newspaper
         through but there were certain things I loved to read as a little child
         in the newspaper when I could read. And then of course the magazines that
         came into the home like the"TL.adies' Home Journal" which was like this then,
         you know. And the "Delinear" , which was a style magazine and so on. Those
         things even as a small child I enjoyed. And then when Carnegie gave the
         money for the city library, why of course I started getting books there
         right away. And because no home library had enough books "keep you supplied
         with reading if you were a reader in those days. And so I started, and you
         they got a new card every so often, Jchecked your books out on a card. And I
         don't remember what my first number was. Mrs. McBride, her husband had been—
         now there's a case about a divorce—a dentist here. And she became librarian,and
         I don't know whether she did before he died or not. But she was the librarian
         for years and years and finally whoever held number one card,
         my card ran out and Mrs. McBride told me, she said,"You've read so many books
         in this library I'm going to give you the number one card now. And so I held
         that number one card until they quit using that card file system. And I
         thought that was pretty nice. Do you want to shut it ocf just a minute?
         
         LS: How did people feel about him and about her. 
         
         CS: In the divorce. Well, I never knew Dr. McBride personally, he wasn't our
         dentist. But she was a very intellectual sort of person. 
         
         LS: His first wife.
         
         CS:  His first wife. And I think she probably had a great deal to do with like
         the Historical Club and study clubs in those days because she was that
         type that liked that sort of thing. And I don't know why they were divorced
         but he did marry this younger woman who became the city librarifi. I can't
         her name. But as far as I can remember right off that's the only
         actual divorce case I know of
         a little
         
         LS: What you said reminds me of what you had to say about Mrs. Lebrooke Can
         you describe 
         
         CS:  Well, no I really can't. She was a great friend of this Mrs. Heddington who
         boarded in our home when she was in Moscow after she gave up her own home,
         she was a widow and had lost her little girl. And she lived in our home
         for several years, was a boarder. And at that time she was very active in
         tfts Historical Club, and I know Mrs. Ledbrooke was too. And then later
         Mrs. Ledbrooke moved to Spoane and Mrs. Heddington used to go up to spend the
         weekend with her and so on because they had such similar likes and enjoyed
         the same things so much. But I don't know anything about the Ledbrooke
         homelife more than the episode that Carol tells about. I didn't even know
         they were Methodists or anything but Carol of course tells about the episode.
         
         LS: Did make much of an impression in Moscow?
         
         CS:  Well, I tell you, Mrs* kedoYoeke lived down in Moscow for quite a few years.
         But I don't remember that there was ever much discussion in our home or
         amongst my friends about that. But of course we didn't go to the Methodist
         Church and we didn't know this family of Booth like the Methodist people, you
         see. And the Ledbrookes were also, evidently he was a Methodist anyway.
         
         LS: Did most of your friends as a child go to the Presbyterian church also?
         
         CS:   it just happened so. One or two didn't when I was real small, one or
         two didn't. But my real close frieBs, because we were in the same Sunday
         School class. I remember when we were about ten, I judge, or maybe eight or
         nine, the oldest Butterfield girl was married and so she asked four of
         us to be flower girls. And she taught our class in our Sunday School, but
         Butterfields were originally, I think, Episcopalian. But I know Ralston
         Butterfield was a great Episcopalian afterwards. But Mrs. Butterfield, the
         mother, in her later years she lived at Hotel Moscow, I believef she always
         came to our church. But anyway this Miss Butterfield, and I can't say her
         name right off—her first name— asked us to be flower girls at her wedding
         and that was held jtfe the Episcopal church. And that wasn't this church
         that's here now, it was a wooden church. It burned up later. But there was
         a center  and it wasn't very big, just as I remember about the size of
         the Episcopal church as It is now. And I remember when we had the rehearsal
         the night before. Mrs. Butterfield, the mother of the bride, we were taking
         it so seriously to walk up the aisle two by two just as we were supposed to
         do and with our little baskets of rose petals. But we were so serious about
         it, I remember so well she said to us,"Smile children, smile" because she
         didn't want us to be like that at the wedding. She was trying to put us at
         ease I think, and she didn't want us to be little sour pusses at the wedding.
         
         LS: Were most weddings big?
         
         CS:  Well, that church wasn't too big so I'm sure it was filled for that wedding.
         And as far as the—I thiflc they had the reception up in the bjg Butterfield
         home which is up on Polk Street. Because Miss Butterfield used to have us
         to her home for parties, her Sunday School class. And of course none of us
         had come from big homes like that and we just thought it was wonderful when
         she had us for a party.
         
         LS: Do you remember the first cars coming in?
         
         CS:  Yes, I do. I think Dr. Carathers had the first car. And I can just remember 
         seeing it, but I never had a ride in it or anything. And then Dr. Gritman got
         a car. But then some friends of ours had moved in—this was the Brown
         family from the country—and they lived in house built home just within
         the next block and around the corner from us. And their d'.tugheter and I were
         good friends. And somebody they knew had bought a car and it was a front
         seat and then one little seat—it wasn't a rumble seat, it was just a little
         seat sitting behind. You didn't lift up anything, the little seat was just
         there. And so he was going to take my friend, Alma Brown,for a ride, this man,
         ho was a friend of her father's and so she asked rae to go along and I sat
         in the little seat behind. And o I thought it was marvelous to ride in t3^
         car. That's my first experience with cars. And then Ward Gano, when we were
         in high school his father got a car, and I used to go places with Ward
         sometimes in the car he'd fill the car with high school kids to go
         someplace.
         
         LS: Do you remember the first movies or motion pictures?
         
         CS:  Yes, uh huh, I do. And there were two movie houses here. And I think Mr.
         Kenworthy had one on one side of Third Street and somebodyMse had one across
         the street. And we went to the show so often on Saturday night, and they cost
         ten cents a piece^or children. And if you had a quarter we could go to both
         shows and have a. bag of popcorn tao, which we did. And I don't remember of
         us going any other time of the week—only Saturday night. And then later
         on they started having matinees for children on Saturday afternoons. Bat I
         think that was when the theatres had moved out on Main Street, and that was when
         they started ! the matinees for children. And ofcourse I thought I was much too
         big to go to a matinee then. But along when there was a theatre on Main
         Street, we had a stock company in the summer. And they just lived here, you
         know, and I don't have no idea how they made enough money to keep them all
         on. But my sister,^ and I were at home. This was after 1908 because I don't
         know whether I was in high school or where I was. But we went to every change
         of , which was every week. We just thought the stock company
         was wonderful.
         
         LS: What kind of things did tiey do?
         
         CS:  Oh, they pretty near always had sort of a wild west show with a love story
         going in because there was pretty near always shooting and I had to hold my
         ears of course because I didn't like the shooting. But oh the man who played
         the leading man we thought was just—the young girls of the town thought he
         was perfectly wonderful. I don't think the company consisted of more than four
         or five people. Sometimes they had to do a dual role, you know, to take
         partv And the scenery was, I imagine if we'd see it now we'd just think it
         was—they had backdrops, you know, with a city street on. And of course the
         front curtain, before they'g raise it was all these little ads of businesses
         in Mcrcow painted all over it, you .They had printed programs the cast 
         I can't remember the names of any of those, but they were--oh, theywere quite
         some shows we thought.
         
         LS: When you went to . prep school from high school, what was it that made you
         decide to go up there? What kind of kids would go up there?
         
         CS:  Well, Just thought it was kind of—this same group of girls that we'd been
         all through the grades together, ray friends, three of us, and we were three that
         were always together. We just thought it was kind of smart, you know. We were
         just doing something different, we were at that age. But of course, I just
         went the one year; the other two girls stayed on. They didn't live as far as
         did, though. To get to an eight o'clock class wasn't as hard for them probably.
         
         LS: Did many people come from the high school to the prep school?
         
         CS:  Not too many, no, no. Not too many. Most of them stayed.
         
         LS: Did you have to have good grades or anything?
         
         CS:  No, no. They were just glad to have the students in prep stool. Because the
         floor wasn't used for dasses .It did draw in from
         over the state, young people where there weren't high schools, you know.
         know in my class,  from southern Idaho, he was a state
         legislator from down in southern Idaho somplace for 
         I knew he lost out on an election. But then Fred  came here from someplace
         and I never would have gotten through physics if he hadn't a helped me set
         up my apparatus every time. And then I remember a boy, I don't know where
         he was frora--a country boy—who came. And they all stayed on for college,y'see.
         It was just a chance for them to get their high school a3 then go on to college.
         
         LS: Was it any harder than regular high school?
         
         CS:  Ho, no Only it was departmentalized, you had different teachers of course. But
         we had that in high school too. Only I think instep of the teachers changing
         room in high school, the pupils shifted to anaher room because the halls weren't
         very big and there was always much confusion. Of course we dih't mind that
         a bit when we weri that age.
         
         LS: So prep school wasn't really that different.
         
         CS:  No, no, no. It was just like high school. Only were a little freer. You
         didn't have to sit in a study hall, y'see, if you weren't  classes. We
         jist always hung around in the hall and looked out the ter by the fnat of the
         building. And from the  floor we always saw everybody. And ff course college
         wasn't so big now, and there were girls we admired very much and we'd watch
         for them, whom we thought were very pretty and
         think it was just a desire to be adult and grown up. We figured it was more
         like gotig to college, y'see.
         
         LS: But then you went back to the high school for your.
         
         CS:  Yes, and then the prep school went out within a year or two. They closed it
         out when they felt the state then had high schools—that everybody had a chance
         for high school.
         
         LS: Can you tell the story about your wanting to go to college and your father's.
         
         CS:  Oh, well.. it was the year I was in prep school, the physical education
         teacher said,"Why don't you figure on (this was a coming thing, you know,
         physical education in the public school) why don't you go on with that?" And
         well, at the university everybody was required to take physical education.
         wasn't much more than calisthenics; I don't think we even played volleyball
         or basketball or anything. It was just mostly, calisthenics and folk dancing.
         And so the Lewiston Normal offered a course un physical education.
         
         LS: I want you to tell the story about enrolling at the U of I.
         
         CS:  Oh, yes.
         
         LS: Your father, you know, thinking that there were only certain majors.
         
         CS:  Well, yes. My father was of the old school. And he thought you should efcher
         be a teacher And he came to being a secretary was all right too, I
         or stay at home. And he was always a great admirer of fancywork we called it,
         h9dwork and so on. He thought it was wonderful when young girls just could be
         satisfieto do that sort of thing. Well, I wasn't of that disposition and so
         I did start to college, regi stered and went to college. And I took home
         economics which my father thought was a very fine thing. And the home econoraics,
         was before they were even in the Administration building. That was one thing
         they did in the Administration building when they got rid of prep school,
         they put the home economics later on up ttfre. Of course it was the law school
         for a while too, in the third floor. But I registered in home economics and
         the first assignment in home economics over in Ridenbaugh Hall, where they'd
         set up this temporary home economics department, was to can fruit for Ridenbaugh
         Hall. And if was of course fall, and the pears were on. And we were to can
         pears. Well, we had to wash the jars, and so everybody took their jars--old
         Mason fruit jars—to the sink to wash them. And I ran hot water on mine and
         broke it. And of course that wasn't the thing I was supposed to do and so
         the teacher—I don't know that she said to much—but she explained that
         that wasn't the way to wash fruit jars, just running hot water over them
         and so on. So I didn't last very long that year because I just knew that
         I wasn't the right temperament for that sort of thing, so I didn't finish the
         year. 
         
         And so then the next year my father let me go down to Lewiston Normal
         to take my physical education. And it happened that a head of the department
         in Lewiston was a Miss  from New York who was teaching to earn money
         to go on through medical school. And I liked her very much and I liked what
         she taught us, and I just thoroughly enjoyed her, and that just made me want
         to be a doctor because we had to take so many courses that were so foolish
         for young people to take. We took the same anatomy that ttfy took at medical
         school and kinesthiology. She'd had a year or two of medical school, y'see,
         so as I remember, she didn't teach any of the floor work as we call it in
         physical education. She just taught the book subjects that went along with
         the course. And we just adored her. And she had a skeleton that hung ' a
         on the line.
         screw up in a box case, you know, And we knew physiology and we had anatomy
         and bacteriology. The bacteriology was over in the home economics building
         becaise all girls in home economics at Lewiston Normal had to take the course
         in bacteriology too. But after I was through and I wanted to go on medical
         school—ray father, no, no daughter of his would go to medical school. That
         wasn't a profession that woen should be in. That was a man's profession. And
         then so I just was at home.until. And I told you my experience of teaching in
         the Kendrick schools, didn't I?
         
         LS: Yeah. Did that bother you when your father said that or did you just accept it?
         
         CS:  Well, I just had to accept it, that was all. And my brother was the same way
         with my niece, she wanted to be a nurse. And she would have been a wonderful
         nurse, they lived back in Chicago. But she went to Beloit but he wouldn't
         think of her to8study nursing. That just wasn't done in their way of thinking.
         Do you want anything else, we've got to get our breakfast pretty soon.
         We can finish the tape.
         
         LS: Okay. What was it as a young woman after you came back from Lewistn, what
         things did you do?
         
         CS:  Well, I'll tell you, there really wasn't too much in the way of social life.
         There was quite a little group of us who were not In school and we'd get up
         a dance occasionally. But then you see during the flu years, we had soldiers
         at the university, in ROTC. Well, it was just a general, it wasn't ROTC, it
         was just they were sent in to be trained. And the flu epidemic came on and
         I wdked in Red Cross then because I was needed and other young women in town
         who weren't in school worked in the Red Cross. There were so many ill people
         among the soldiers that they had them in many places, in just temporary
         hospitals, y'see, they took buildings in town. So there had to be bedding
         provided and pillows and sheets and everything. It just seemed to ihe every
         week I had some certain amount of solicitation among the residents of Moscow
         something. But people were so good because te necessity was so
         great. And thai some Of the youngjomen they had a place where they prepared meals
         for all of these outbuildings that were hospitals. And so, well the food
         had to be taken, you know. And I was driving at that time, my father had gotten
         a car; he didn't learn to drive it, but I drove it. And so I often was called
         upon to drive. But that was a very difficult winter here in Mosco because of
         so much flu. And like Harry was in the store then, in David's and he'd measure
         a man, he ordered all the uniforms, and maybe the young fellow would be dead
         before the uniform euer came. There were so many deaths. It was very
         sad. But that's the way I occupied my time. Until I was married.
         
         LS: did you help a lot at home?
         
         CS: Well, yes. Yes, I helped with the housework. I didn't learn to cook, but
         I did other things, because my sister Myra was home and my mother died
         in 1918 and of course she hadn't been doing the housework anyway. We
         both did...
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13587</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Sampson_Clarice1</previous>
      <next>Sampson_Clarice4</next>
      <disp_name>Sampson_Clarice2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
