<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">11/13/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Clarice Sampson, 1974-11-13, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:05:50</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Sampson, Clarice</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker; teacher; clerk at David's Store</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894</birthyear>
      <residence>Moscow</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Utah (1892)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#businesses"&gt;businesses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#University of Idaho"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#monuments"&gt;monuments&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#WCTU"&gt;WCTU&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#confectionaries"&gt;confectionaries&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#parties"&gt;parties&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clubs"&gt;clubs&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#parties"&gt;parties&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#circuses"&gt;circuses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Chautauqua"&gt;Chautauqua&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#revivals"&gt;revivals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#books"&gt;books&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dentists"&gt;dentists&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Laura Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13585</file_name>
      <mp3>13586.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13586.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Father leaving home at 13; Father moving to Ogden, Utah; and then finally relocating
               to Moscow in 1892
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father left home at age 13. Learned monument business from a brother. Met her mother
               in St. Louis. Later Father moved to Ogden, Utah and he set up a small hardware store
               and sent for his wife and five children. Relocated in 1892 in Moscow, attracted by
               university, and set up a monument business.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Father traveling to sell monuments; father lettered the Spanish American warm monument
               for the University of Idaho
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>In 1893 Father travelled all over trying to sell monuments and worked on them in the
               kitchen. With their last money he bought flour and a two-bit cigar. Lettered the Spanish
               American War monument for the U of I.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Watching the Administration building burn; old steps being hauled away and then later
               placed near the garden
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Went to see the Administration Building burn and Mother
               cried. U. hired small boys to clean the bricks after the fire. Huge old steps were
               hauled away and buried in city lots. Later a class found enough of the old steps and
               put them near the garden.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>What father preferred to work in and where he got his rock; making different size
               monuments
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father preferred to work in marble, but also sold granite. Got his rock from Vermont.
               Eventually had agents that sold for him from kits of designs. Made things out of marble
               for the home. Monuments were big if the family finances allowed. Father often asked
               to initial his stones.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Recalling smallpox epidemic; brother had diphtheria</title>
            <synopsis>Recalls smallpox epidemic and being vaccinated by Dr.
               Watkins. Brother had diphtheria. Quarantined homes then.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Recalling early stores in Moscow and the things they sold; being able to eat in the
               kitchen
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Recalls early stores. Moody's shopped at Creighton's
               for dry goods. Bought groceries from David’s—a man picked up and delivered orders.
               Recalls buying her first ready-made coat. Ate on white tablecloths three times a day
               and a treat to eat in the kitchen.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1860</time>
            <title>Different businesses that were in Moscow; women lifting their skirts in passing saloons;
               ten inch high crosswalks
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Grocery stores, meat markets. Thirteen churches and 13 saloons. Women lifted their
               skirts when they passed because the sidewalk was dirty from tobacco spit. Ten
               inch high crosswalks.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Mother working for the WCTU; sister pledging to not drink; kids learning fundamentals
               in school
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother worked for WCTU and took petitions around. Sister
               pledged she wouldn't drink and still feels funny about
               drinking liquor. Kids used to learn the fundamentals
               better in school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Confectionery stores in Moscow; driving to Genesee and having to walk in the mud</title>
            <synopsis>Confectionery stores. One had a small table for children.
               Got oyster cocktails in winter as a treat. Sleigh rides.
               They drove over to Genesee for a basketball game in a
               sleigh and walked the last four miles home in the mud.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2880</time>
            <title>Girls' basketball; parties at school; often having study hall in superintendent's
               office
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Girls basketball. Parties in the halls at school. As a senior there was no room for
               study hall and they often went to superintendent's office.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Discussion of variety social activities for children and tricks they played as children</title>
            <synopsis>Fourth of July—stores had floats, several dances. A children's social club, QAE (quit
               at eleven) Club.
               Halloween party masquerade. Common tricks were tipping over privy or stealing gates.
               Would go out with tic-tacs to scare people or ring doorbells. Carol Ryrie Brink's mother
               shipped in molded ice cream from Spokane for a birthday party. For a leap year Sunday
               School party they faked going home and then went back and danced.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3660</time>
            <title>Discussion of the circus; would wake up early to watch circus train
               come in about 4 a.m.
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Circus. Would wake up early to watch circus train
               come in about 4 a.m.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3780</time>
            <title>Description of the circus and parade; Recalling medicine show; the Protestant churches
               building a tabernacle for revival
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Boys got free ticket to circus if they carried water for the elephants. Description
               of circus and parade on Main Street. Dog and pony shows also came. Statues of acrobats
               a highlight of the circus. Recalls one medicine show. Hypnotist would come to town.
               Chautauqua shows lasted a week. Had lectures and musical shows. Protestant Churches
               built a wooden tabernacle for a revival.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4380</time>
            <title>Recalling Armistice Day; helping get blankets and pillows of flu epidemic</title>
            <synopsis>Recalls false Armistice and then the real Day. University
               was barracks for infantry and many died from the flu.
               She went door-to-door for blankets and pillows. Many
               women knitted for the war effort and she carried wool
               to them; cookie recipe from Mrs. McConnell
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Recalling getting water in hydrant and indoor plumbing; mother caring for coal oil
               lamps; getting wood
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Recalls progress from getting water in a hydrant to
               inside plumbing. Mother spent 1 hour every morning caring
               for coal oil lamps. Got 9 or 10 cords of wood a year.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>There was good support for the war; different groups did different tasks to help war
               effort
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Good support for the war. Scandinavian women really
               turned out the socks. Red Cross made hospital gowns. Ladies Aids rolled bandages.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Discussion of the Ladies Aid society; going to Sunday school with parents</title>
            <synopsis>The Ladies Aid was a social affair and tended to the
               local wants of the church. They were a large part of the
               social life of the town. Mother and other parents used
               to go to Sunday school with the children. Christian
               Endeavor for the children in the earlier years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>Recalls Dr. Watkins being shot</title>
            <synopsis>Recalls coming back into town the day Dr. Watkins was
               shot. It happened much as it was in Carol Ryrie Brinks' book.
               Stephens had planned to shoot deputy sheriff but didn't
               because he held his baby.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Having a molar pulled out; mother having her teeth pulled</title>
            <synopsis>Recalls having a molar pulled out by the dentist. A
               later dentist, Dr. Watkins, extracted the nerve from the tooth and then filled it.
               Mother had her teeth pulled,
               then then they put in dentures after a few months.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6480</time>
            <title>Visiting Grandmother on Fix Ridge; drying apples; sprinkling the road to keep down
               the dust
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Visiting Grandmother Smith on Fix Ridge. She knew many old-time remedies. Feather
               beds, prunes. They dried apples on wood house roof. Sprinkled the road to keep down
               dust. People sat on verandahs then.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Having a large gardens; raising piglets and packing the meat in salt</title>
            <synopsis>Large garden. Father worked there in evening. Raised
               piglets in summer and packed the meat down in salt.
               Didn't eat out in Moscow. Church suppers, GAR bean bake.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Social life of women in Moscow; meeting Dr. McLane</title>
            <synopsis>Women on University side of town stayed home one after
               noon a week to receive callers and the other side stayed
               home another day. Enjoyed serving punch at University
               dances. Were picked up in cabs, which was special.
               A tall man escorts her and two other little girls under
               his umbrella in the rain. He was Dr. McLane, the President of U of I.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Parties, circuses, sleighrides. Consumerism in Moscow. Women's volunteer work
         in World War I. Father's monument business. Prohibition sentiment. Town visiting.
         11-13-74 2 hr 43p LS
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         CLARICE SAMPSON: My father was George H. Moody, was born in St. John, New Bruns
         wick. He was the thirteenth child and all the rest of the family had been
         born in Scotland. And his own mother died when he was eighteen months
         old, and his father remarried, because, I presume to take care of a
         big family. My father, although he was so young, he didn't accept it,
         and the stepmother allowed the older children to take advantage of
         the younger ones. So, when he was thirteen he ran away from home and
         was on his own from then on. He made his way to Boston and worked in
         a book bindery there as a young man. His brother, one of his brothers
         was a worker in marble in Vermont, and he finally moved to Missouri
         and there he opened a monument business. It was the day of big monu
         ments, and tombstones, they called them. 
         
         My father apprenticed him
         self to his brother and learned the trade, and when he was a young
         man he established his own monument works in Fort Scott, Kansas. But
         before he established his own business he was in St. Louis, and I imagine
         he was working in some such a concern. He boarded with a Mrs. Man-
         ning, who had been recently widowed. Her young daughter, Mary Ida,
         helped her mother and served the boarders at the table and she and
         my father fell in love and they were married in St. Louis, Missouri.
         He took her to Fort Scott, Kansas, where several of my brothers and
         sisters were born. There was.great desire in many young people or
         that time to go West, so he thought he would sell his business and
         go out to California, leaving his family there til he was settled.
         He met a man on the train who told him all about Ogden, Utah, and what
         a boom town it was, so he decided to get off of the train there at
         Ogden and see what it was like. Well, he opened up a small hardware
         store, and finally, in a few months sent for my mother with five child-
         ren, the youngest a three months old baby, and they all had their
         little piece of luggage to carry and somebody had to carry the bag
         for the baby, and somebody had to carry the bird in the bird cage.
         And they made their home in Ogden, Utah for several years. And, I
         think my father was not very happy being out of his own field, so
         my mother and the family went over to Salubria, Idaho where my moth
         er mother had come. She had remarried and had come there, and they
         were mining there. My father, evidently sold out his hardware bus
         iness and followed them. Early in 1892 he had heard about the town
         up in northern Idaho, Moscow, where a university had been recently
         established and he thought that would be a good place to move his fam
         ily so that they would have the advantage of a good education for each
         of them. So he came on alone to Moscow in, as I said, early in 1892
         and opened a business; got in a stock of monuments in a little build
         ing that was then on Third Street, and my mother followed. My father
         found a house they could rent, and they settled themselves in Moscow,
         Idaho. They lived in a couple of houses, I think, and my mother told
         about taking care of an old blind lady, and I think the pay for her
         care was probably a pretty good part of their income at that time.
         Then my father had the chance to buy a house on Lynn Avenue, they
         called it then. I even remember the numbers, 722 Lynn Avenue. And
         he bought that place; it was a five room house with, I imagine it was
         about a half an acreogoining it that was the garden spot. It had fruit
         trees planted in it and a garden space. There in that house I was born
         in January of 1894. 
         
         But, the year before, 1893, had been the bad year
         in Latah County. It had rained and rained and the farmers were unable
         to harvest their grain, so the only monuments my father could sell,was
         he would get on horseback and take a kit of designs and go about the
         country and if he could sell a monument, he would come back home and
         engrave the monument in the kitchen, because he'd had to give up his
         building downtown, and he kept his store of his stock of marble in
         the barn. But he used to tell us about— they were just about down
         to the last bit of money they had and my mother needed a sack of flour
         so he went to town and purchased the flour and he had twenty-five
         cents, two bits, they called it left. So, he bought himself a twobit
         cigar and smoked it. But by and by things bettered themselves in Latah
         County and once more he opened his shop down on Main Street this time.
         I remember when I was a little girl he ordered the Ole Hagburg monu
         ment, which stands on the campus. There were two boys from the Univ
         ersity of Idaho who were killed in the Philippines in the Spanish—American
         War. I don't know how that monument was purchased, Ait was
         by public subscription, I presume it was, and the help of the University.
         When it came, of course, we all wanted to go down and see it.
         Well, it was so long, and such a long, heavy box, that it just about
         filled up his showroom. And, I thought that was just about the big
         gest monument that had ever been made. It stands on the University
         of Idaho campus now.
         
         LAURA SCHRAGER: He had the marble shipped in?
         
         CS: : Yeah— no,the form was made, he didn't chisel out the form, but he
         did all the lettering on it, and it stands there on the campus yet,
         facing the northeast, or the mountains. And, to me, it was the most
         wonderful thing.
         
         Then, when I was still a little girl, quite young, the Administra
         tion Building of the University of Idaho burned. Everybody in town
         could see the blaze in the sky and everybody went to the fire, and I
         was a little girl and my mother held my hand and so I cried because
         she cried because the Administration Building was burning. The thing
         I hated to have burn up was -in the entry hall of the Administration
         Building, there were two glass cases, and in those cases were little
         artifacts that the boys who had been in the battalion over there had
         brought home with them. And I remember a little grass covered hut
         that I thought was so adorable, and I regreted, of course, the loss
         of those things. But the records, fortunately, were saved. The Dean
         of the University saved the records. I had a sister that year, my
         sister, Ethel, who was a senior in college. The women's gymnasium
         was built at that time and Ridenbaugh Hall, they were existing build
         ings, so the classes were held in those two buildings, but the sen
         iors had to go across town to the Methodist Church and the City Lib
         rary for classes. And, that was a great experience because, even though
         it was hardship for the students, they all rallied around and in a
         few years we had a new Administration building. But to make use of
         the bricks that were left from after the fire, the University hired
         small boys to clean the bricks. To clean the mortar from the bricks,
         and my husband, Harry Sampson was one of the small boys hired to help
         clean bricks, and a
         
         LS: o my brother, Maurice Moody, five years older than
         worked on that, too, cleaning bricks at the University. Course
         that was quite a windfall for small boys. But the beautiful old steps
         the granite steps, they were in the front of the Administration, and
         then there was a wing on either side, then there were huge steps going
         up to each wing, so there were actually three main entrances to the
         Administration Building. Well, they thought they were of no value, so
         they were hauled away and they were buried where leveling was done on
         city lots. I can't remember the year, but the University garden was
         up behind where the old Administration Building had been, and some
         class reunion decided they'd restore the old steps. And so, they
         found enough of the old steps to build a flight of steps as they were
         originally up to the garden. And, of course, they're there now, the
         old steps.
         
         Can I ask you about your father's business trip? Where did he get his
         rock from?
         
         Oh, well, of course, around here there was no marble, and that was his*
         material he liked working in best, was marble. But, of course, marble
         isn t too good^outside, the elements are too hard on.. outside. So
         he had to go into selling granite monuments, too. And he got Rock of
         Ages marble and granite from Vermont, and that was shipped sometimes
         by boat and sometimes by train to San Francisco, and then put on trains
         and shipped to Moscow, Idaho. So the cost of transporting material
         to his business was very expensive. I often wonder how he did most
         of the lettering himself, until the business became so big that he had
         to employ men to come in to assist him. 4Then he had agents who went
         about, oh, all over Nez Perce prairie and all around Moscow, and as
         far as Yakima in Washington selling for him. And they would take the
         orders and they would carry the kits of designs, just about like
         those pictures, and people would choose what they wanted, or they could
         come in to Moscow and see the stock on the floor. But when my father
         showed stock it was always with such love, and when he was showing a
         special monument, without thinking, his white handkerchief would come
         out of his pocket and he would wipe it off a bit, and that showed the
         beauty that he could see in that particular piece of stone. As a young
         man he made, oh, things for our home— that oval picture frame, here
         hanging on the wall, with my mother's and father's picture in it, he
         made that out of marble. And how he ever could chisel that out and get
         it so perfect, I don't understand. And on the table there is a little
         marble book with my mother's initia
         
         LS:  engraved on and it was to represent a little white bible. He gave it to her as
         an engagement pre
         sent. So I treasure my things that I have that he has made, very much.
         As that old book over there on the table, he made.. But later,
         then, he got— he would ship in some marble for interior use, like in
         bank buildings and so on, from Italy. And then, he got beautiful green granite from
         Alaska, and then from Georgia, some
         very beautiful stone came. But monuments in those days were inclined
         to be big, if possible, if the family finances warranted that, and
         they would sit on base the same as the monument itself was made
         of, and that in turn would sit on a rough granite base. And those
         rough granite bases came from over here in Washington. I can't just
         remember where. But that was the style in those days of the monu
         ment business, and they would have individual stones that were large.
         And, then, always at the foot, would be a footstone; smaller with the
         initial of the person who was buried there on the footstone. Often
         friends would ask my father to put his name someplace down on one side
         showing that he had engraved that particular stone. I see many monu
         ments in the cemetery with either GHM or Moody down in one little cor
         ner at the back of the monument, showing that he had engraved that monu
         ment.
         
         LS:  Did he go through periods that were harder times?
         
         CS:  Well, after that year his business just gradually grew and grew, and
         he kept having more agents out and selling more monuments. And you'd
         be surprised to know that the Indians were some of the very best buyers
         of monuments. That just appealed to them. When they'd come into his
         shop, he had rather a quiet voice, and Indians liked that, they don't
         like to be spoken— often, we think we need to speak in louder tones
         to someone who is different than we are, you know, for fear they won't
         understand. But, they liked him. I know he had a namesake, an Indian
         baby named for him down on the prairie: George Moody. Afterwards I
         knew that baby, when he grew to be a man.
         
         LS:  Were there any epidemics?
         
         CS:  I remember when I was a little girl, there were time we had a smallpox epidemic
         and we all had to be vaccinated, of
         course. I was taken to Dr. Watkins' office and had my arm scraped
         with this— they used a quill, in those days, and would scrape the
         skin on your arm and put the vaccine on it. I remember, I cried and
         another little girl laughed at me, and I never liked that little girl
         because she laughed. . I thought it hurt.
         
         LS:  Was this Dr. Watkins?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh. That was Carol Brink's grandfather. And then, my brother
         who was five years older than I had diphtheria at one time. I was
         quite small at the time, and it seemed from what my mother told me, I
         played right around in the same room where he was and I didn't take it.
         So, I don t think there was an epidemic or anything. I think. just
         happened to be one case. And, then, of course, they quarantined the
         homes in those days when people had scarlet fever or diphtheria or
         smallpox. And there would be a sign put up by the front door—Quar
         antined— and the name of the disease. And us children, of course, if
         we'd ever see that on somebody's front door, we'd cover our mouths
         with our handkerchiefs and just run by as fast as we could, so we
         wouldn't get that germ.
         
         LS:  Could you describe some of the stores in Moscow?
         
         CS:  Well, Moscow was always quite a good trading center, even in the early
         days. Of course, the first store, I think, was the McConnell-McGuire
         Store, and that was where the— Mr. Brown's furniture store is now,
         the Building, now we call it. And, later Mr. F. A. David was
         associated with that firm, and then that store went broke and it was
         started again, and I don't know the year, but it was started again by
         Motter and Wheeler. This advertisement doesn't give— but I can
         remember this store— yes, Motter-Wheeler Company, The Hustlers, and
         they had a fall opening, and it doesn't say what year it was. But
         some of the prices are very interesting: ladies' wrappers, the seven
         ty five cent ones, went at fifty cents. And the mens' hat- a seventy
         five cent hat went at sixty cents. And there were - all during that
         opening they had specials of fruit jars and Golden Crown tomato catsup,
         regular fifty cent special at twenty cents or three for fifty cents.
         
         LS:  This happened before your time?
         
         CS:  I remember this store, because, you see the McConnel-McGuire store
         had gone broke, and I don't remember when that was there, but I re
         member this store, this particular store. But I don't remember of
         the Moody family trading there very much. We were customers of
         Creighton's store, in regard to dry goods and clothing, and then we
         bought out groceries from David's store. Mr. David had started up
         his store. They sent a man around each morning to your kitchen door
         to take orders for groceries that you might need, and then they del
         ivered them with a horse and cart later in the day, which was a great
         convenience in those days, because in the winter the snow was quite
         deep, and in the spring and fall the mud was deep and it was a great
         convenience to have things brought to your door. Creighton's store
         had a delivery boy, and my brother, Maurice, was their delivery boy
         at one time. That was after the bicycles came in- we had bicycles.
         There were several dressmakers in town and if they'd call and want a
         pattern, a certain pattern, or thread or something, their delivery
         boy would get on the bicycle and go and take it to the dressmaker.
         That was a great convenience, of course. I remember one time, being
         the youngest in the family, a great many of my clothes were made over
         but I never seemed to mind, because, they were of much nicer material
         than would hrfWtbeen purchased probably for a little girl. But, I re
         member one time I needed a new winter coat and we went to Creighton's,
         my mother and I, and looked for a coat for me. I think it was prob
         ably the first ready made coat I'd had, because it was red and it had
         a red velvet collar, and I thought it was sooo beautiful. But, my
         mother really it was more than she could afford to pay, but
         Mr. Creighton happened to come back to where the coat was
         being shown, I think he knocked off a dollar or so, and my mother pur
         chased the coat for me, 'cause Mr. Creighton could see how badly I
         wanted that pretty red coat.
         
         LS:  You wouldn't shop around in those days?
         
         CS:  Well, no, I tell you, we didn't shop around too much, they knew you
         and like at Creighton's store, I don't know, I think our bill was paid
         twice a year, that was the way they did business. They didn't bill
         you monthly, as I remember. During the sales my mother would go in
         and stock up on the number of sheets and tablecloths and so on, she
         needed. Mr. Creighton went to Ireland every year and bought linen,
         so even in the early days you could buy very beautiful linens, here
         in Moscow. Like many homes, I suppose, our home we ate on a white
         tablecloth three times a day, and my father wouldn't have it other
         wise, and we all had white napkins. We never ate in the kitchen dur
         ing my time. Sometimes for Sunday night supper, I just thought it
         was so much fun, when I was a child, if we would have our supper in
         the kitchen and open the oven door, and we were all sitting close to
         gether, and it was such fun.
         
         LS:  In the book -
         
         CS:  All 
         
         LS:  She mentions about how there were grades of groceries, grocery stores-
         
         CS:  Well, there were, really. That's true. There was a store down on
         Main Street, near my father's place of business, and
         he would get in fruit and watermelons and thingsr-- they didn t come
         in trucks, they came in hay wagons from Julietta and Lewiston and
         so on, and when he'd get in a load, why, everybody in Moscow would
         go down and get their fruit to can— it would be stacked in boxes
         out on the sidewalk and his prices were always supposed to be
         a little cheaper, but his family lived above the grocery store and
         I think he did most of the work himself, so his overhead probably was
         lower, and he could sell cheaper. I don't like to say anything more
         about. But, then, there were other stores in town: Mr. Swan had
         a very nice store, grocery store, and I think it was considered very
         first class. Probably his line of canned goods, and so on, was a lit
         tle more, but of very fine quality. And, then, as the years would go
         by, someone would start a grocery store and it would go a few years
         and they'd decide to close out or somebody would buy them out. So,
         over the years, there^quite a few grocery stores, as I remember.
         
         LS:  Would many of them sell meat?
         
         CS:  Well, no, we had meat markets. I think we had at least— I remember
         three meat markets when I was a little girl. And, that was one thing
         my father always purchased. He always bought the meat. And it would
         be delivered to our home. He'd stop in as he went to work and choose
         the meat that my mother had wanted. And, quite often, I know, we had
         round steak, and all the family liked that. He'd send home a great
         big round steak, and I think, perhaps, it was only twenty-five or
         thirty five cents. When it was prepared they would pound it with a
         knife, you know, and then dip it in flour and fry it. It may not have
         been so good for us, but it tasted awfully good. And then the drip
         pings made delicious gravy, you know, over potatoes or biscuits, and
         so on.
         
         At one time in Moscow, we were supposed to have had as many saloons
         as we did churches, that was one thing we talked about. And I think
         there were thirteen saloons and thirteen churches. And to go from
         our home, we always walked down Third Street, and either side of the
         street we went on, we had to pass a saloon, and, of course, the men
         were standing around outside and they would chew tobacco and spit on
         the sidewalk. I remember the ladies with their sweeping skirts, in
         those days, well, you held up your skirt when you passed those places,
         because— so it wouldn't touch the dirty sidewalk. And, of course,
         then we had no paving, and then every block was a crosswalk to get on
         the other side of the street. Well, those crosswalks were quite high,
         I'd judge eight or ten inches, because the mud would get so deep, you
         see, in the winter, fall and spring when it would rain. So they had
         to be high in order that you wouldn't sink clear in and lose your boots!!
         
         LS:  Those were all wooden planks.
         
         CS:  Wooden planks. And the sidewalks were of wood. But, I don't remem
         ber when the paving came, but, of course, the main streets were paved
         first and cement sidewalks were put down. 'Course in the residential
         neighborhoods we had board walks, sidewalks, we called 'em, long after
         the downtown streets had paving and cement sidewalks.
         
         LS:  Do you remember what the feeling was at the time about the saloons?
         About drinking?
         
         CS:  Well, I think it was just an accepted thing for a man to drink. My
         father was never a drinker, but I think, many, what we considered -Ive better
         class citizens, drank. But, my mother belonged to the WCTU,
         and she was a very ardent worker, and I can well remember when they
         would take petitions around to try to get.saloons out. At one time,
         the Prohibition Party always was on the county ticket, that I can
         remember. My father, we were, Republicans, always, but my
         mother, one time, they persuaded her to run on the Prohibition Party
         as state treasurer, but,of course, she didn't win. She took a great
         deal of teasing from my father over her experience in politi
         
         LS:  Did she actually run a campaign?
         
         Oh, no. Her name was just on the ticket. But, then, of course, when
         prohibition became the law, why, the saloons went out.
         
         What were some of the things you know that the WCTU did in the early
         days?
         
         Well, I think that was just- the most of it was just carry petitions
         around. They had their meetings. I never belonged to this, but I
         know my sister, one of my sisters, would never, and she and I are the
         only ones left- she doesn't even like to take a drink of wine, be
         cause she signed the pledge when she was a little girl— they had an
         organization for the children. But during my time, that never
         seemed to be- they didnit have that organization. But she said"l
         signed that pledge, and Idon't feel right yet to even take aglass
         of wine. Iwasn tin it, so Idon'tAknow what it was. But, Iimagine
         they had children's meetings and talked to them about the evi
         alcohol. Course, in our ' there was always a chapter
         on drinking alcohol, and the harm it did to your body. I don't know
         that they have aphysiology- Idon't think they teach physiology that
         way today, out of a book for children. It's part of their science.
         But we had a book, physiology book, and there was always a chapter on
         the harms of alcohol to the human body. And, I think we had very good, conscientious
         teachers. Some of them would be quite
         young when they started to teach, but they were very anxious for Mos
         cow children to learn. In some ways, I believe our learning in grade
         was superior in some ways than what children get now. Although,
         children know more than we did, because of their advantages
         of seeing and hearing and reading other boks, and so on. They have
         more knowledge, but I don't think they actually learned the funda
         menta
         
         LS:  as well as we did, of education.
         
         LS:  Is there anything in particular that they've changed?
         
         CS:  Well, I don't know too much about the education now, but, I do know
         that my grandchildren, with the new math, it takes them a great deal
         longer to figure out something than either their grandfather or their
         grandmother if it's a matter of dollar and cents, or how many, or
         something. Their way of going about it takes so much longer. 'Course,
         we're mature and we can see in a flash what it is, you know.
         
         LS:  I want to ask you a couple of questions about stores, too.
         
         CS:  Yes.
         
         LS:  Now, wasn't there ice cream parlors?
         
         CS:  Yes, indeed there was. In fact, at one time, I think that there were
         more than two, but it was a great pleasure to go to the ice cream par
         lor— and one of them had a table especially for children— like a
         wrought iron, or an iron table, you know, like porch furniture today,
         with little chairs, and, of course, it was lovely to go in there and
         sit at that little table. And, we bought sundaes more than anything,
         you know. We'd have ice cream with pineapple or strawberry or some
         thing over it, and that was quite the thing.
         
         LS:  Did they make their own ice cream?
         
         CS:  Yes, I think they did and it was very good ice cream, too.
         
         LS:  Did they have a lot of flavors?
         
         CS:  Well, not too many flavors. It was mostly just vanilla and chocolate,
         I think, maybe strawberry some of the times. Then you could have it
         made into a sundae. But I remember the one time befote my husband
         and I were married, we went into one of the confectionery stores,
         and ice cream parlors, that's the way they usually called them, be
         cause they made their candy too, much like Mrs. Hunter makes today
         their candies, you know. And we used to, in the winter, we d go in
         there and get oyster cocktail , oh, we just thought that was wonder
         ful. It was cold, you know, and why we'd like it in the winter I
         don't know, but we did.
         
         LS:  What was it?
         
         CS:  Well, it was oysters, raw oysters, with a spicy sauce over it. I
         supposCketchup was the foundation of the sauce. But, we thought that
         was fun.
         
         In our high school days we had lots of sleigh rides, because our
         snow seemed to stay so much longer than it does now. And, that was
         quite a popular form of entertainment in the winter to go on a sleigh
         ride party. hire either the livery stable or some farmer, and
         he'd put a hayrack on runners, and put straw in, and we'd all take
         our blankets, Sometimes we would go to Pullman and have oyster
         stew at some eating place over there. 'Course, that would take the
         whole evening to go over there and back, and that was quite an enter
         tainment, we thought that was a lot of fun. Or we'd go to somebody
         who lived in the country, and sometimes each of us took along some
         refreshments like a cake or something, and quite often they'd have
         hot cocoa for us. But, I remember one time, when I was in high
         school, Moscow was playing Genesee High School, and Mr.  took
         a group of us over, we started out right after school. We drove
         over the mountain road because, he went over that wav, it was shorter
         I think in order to get us there in time for the game. And we all
         were supposed to take along a sandwich to eat, because we would 'just
         have to go to the game as we took our sand-
         wich in a bag and ate it on the way over. 
         
         And, the game was played
         and, I don't know whether it was in a warehouse, but they didn't have
         a gym or anything, you know, and while we were at the game a Chinook
         wind came up, o you know what they are? A warm wind,tfnd the snow
         all disappeared, and so we started home, and Mr. then came—
         the highway isn't as it is now, but there ' a more level road— and
         he came that way. from four or five miles out from Moscow we all
         had to get out and walk, because those horses couldn't pull — those
         runners wouldn't go with that many— twenty or twenty-five young people
         in the wagon. Of course, it took most of the night, walking so far 
         because I know my mother wasn't concerned about me because I was going
         home to stay all night with one of my friends, io when I came ia walk
         ing in about seven o'clock in the morning, she wondered why I came
         home so early, and I told her we were just getting home from Genesee.
         But we had a bad misfortune out where the railroad tracks cross down 
         South Main, you know, fhe runner on the sled got caught in the track
         and Mr.  was driving the sled and we were all trailing behind,
         of course, but we were pretty weary by that time, and the sled being
         caught in the track, it threw him out and he hit his head and it knock
         ed him out. Well, we were all very frightened I don't think he was
         knocked out for long, but it was fortunate that he was so near his
         livery barn. And I don't even remember who won the game, (chuckles)
         after the experience of that.
         
         LS:  What kind of game was it?
         
         CS:  Basketball. They were playing basketball then. And we were in that
         old, old high school, you know, that I told you about on Third Street.
         And there was no place there, of course, so they rented a warehouse
         down on Main Street, where one of the grain companies is now,
         it was just a big wooden building, you know, and that's where they
         played basketball. I used to play girls basketball in that place.
         
         LS:  basketball very popular then?
         
         CS:  Well, it was then, and then it went out and now, of course, it's back
         again. They had us play six girls to a team then. The rules were a
         little different than boys, but we wanted to play boys rules, but we
         weren't permitted to.
         
         LS:  Would you play around with different school?
         
         CS:  i never was on the team, I wasn't good enough, but they did play the
         other teams around. Mrs.  was the center because she was so tall,
         she was Mabel Drury. They did play different towns around. I don't
         think there were too many outside games played, and there weren't too
         many girls involved in the basketball program.
         
         LS:  Something you said?
         
         Our parties— sometimes, I know when I was a senior in high school
         we used to have parties there in the old school house, but there was
         no recreation room or anything, we just had to play Skip-to-my-Lou,
         and so on in the halls. They were that sort of parties. But the
         school would let us use the building. Of course, we had to always
         ask some teacher to chap«rone us. But, the year I was a senior in
         high school, there wasn't room for us to have a study hall, so we
         just had to kind of stick around in the halls and keep our books on
         the window sills someplace, you know. It was great fun (chuckles)
         but we didn't get any studying done in school time, we had to do our
         studying at home, because we had no place to go, although we did hang
         out down in the school superintendent's office, and how he ever stood
         twenty— there were twenty in my class— all of us in there, I'll never
         know, but he was a very good natured man. The new building, which is
         the office building on Third Street now, was being built then, and he
         was so, Mr. Randall, was so wrapped up in that new building. I don't
         think that he actually knew that we were he was over to the
         new building so much— that he actually knew that we were just making
         use of his office like we did. So, we sort of had open campus then,
         (chuckles) the senior class.
         
         LS:  What were some of the social events? Do you remember?
         
         CS:  Well, Fourth of July, they made a great deal of Fourth of July here
         with a big parade, and the stores would have floats, you know, and
         the band would play, and then, usually, they would have several dance
         halls where the bands would play during the afternoon and evening. I
         remember one Fourth of July, they had draped all the store fronts with
         bunting, red, white and blue bunting, and it rained just terrifically.
         Well, the bunting would drip down on all the white dresses, you know?
         But the dance halls were very popular that year, because people, even
         if they weren't dancing ' crowd in, so the floor space was very
         sparce, because there were so many people standing around the edges
         to get out of the rain. We had our special friends that we had par
         ties in our homes. I remember, I belonged to a club— and I don't
         know, there must have been twenty or twenty-five of us boys and girls
         and we called it the QAE Club, and that meant quit at eleven!! We
         had to go home at eleven, that was the rule., And, we were always say
         ing, we wished our mothers would let us change it to the QAT Club,
         twelve or two, then we could stay 'til twelve, you see. We
         were grade schoolers, what would be junior high, and those parties
         were in our homes. I remember I had a Halloween party one time, and
         it made a house full, but, of course, everybody came^masquarade and
         we had great fun pretending we didn't know who people were, and so on,
         and ducking for apples, I guess you called it, and bittg ^a dough nut
         tied to a string, and all the Halloween stunts we used to do.
         
         LS:  Were there many tricks played on Halloween?
         
         CS:  Well, of course, there were privies in those days. And the bigger
         boys would tip over the privies, or steal the gates — the front gate
         off of the fence. There was always quite a bit of that, so it was
         pretty wise to put your gate away for the evening, but the privy—
         there wasn't much you could do about that!! (chuckles) But, our
         next door neighbor was always so concerned— my dad never seemed
         to be too concerned, but he sort of patrolled his property the whole
         night, I think. And, of course, the kids, knowing that, would always
         do something to him. I don't remember of being mixed up in anything
         very much. We didn't trick or treat, we just didn't know about that
         in Moscow then. But, we'd make tick-tacks. We'd notch a spool, and
         my brother usually made mine, and put it on a little stick or pencil
         then wrap a string around it and go up to someone's window and pull
         the string, and, of course, the spool would turn and make quite a
         racket. Or, we'd ring somebody's doorbell and run, that was the ex
         tent of our mischief, I think. But, we just didn't know about knock
         ing on a door and saying, "Trick or treat." I don't know why we went.
         If somebody didn't have a party, we'd go out with out jack-o-lanterns
         around our own neighborhoods, of course, but we didn't expect them to
         give us anything at all.
         
         I think one of the nicest childhood parties I remember was the one
         that Carol Rttrie's mother gave her, and she shipped in the ice cream
         that came on the noon train from Spokane, as I told you, it had all
         been molded like little animals rabbits or chickens or so on, and
         we thought that was the most elegant party, because we had never seen
         ice cream molded like that before.
         
         LS:  Was that QAE Club, was that at all formal?
         
         CS:  Oh, no, no.
         
         LS:  Anyone could come?
         
         CS:  Oh, no, we had a membership. Yes, it was a membership club. And
         I think there were about twenty to twenty-five of us, and we never
         went home with a boy, or anything, we'd just all go in groups, you
         know. And, the fellow that lived the farth est, I suppose, he had
         to tackle the last part of the way by himself.
         
         LS:  Did you dance?
         
         CS:  Well, we did. We didn't go to dances like children do now, even in
         high school. But, if we had older brothers and sisters we'd just
         gradually learn how to dance at home, you know. I have a terrible
         story to tell, but I don't know whether you would want to tape it or
         not.
         
         It was— I don't believe we were — well, we must have been in
         high school— but we had a Leap Year Sunday School party. The girls
         class in the Presbyterian Sunday School and a boys' class, they were
         about the same size, so each girl asked a boy to go to this Leap Year
         party. Well, there was a woman teacher for the boys' class and we
         had a man teacher, the girls class, and so we went to — this girl
         was a niece living with her aunt that year, going to school— it was
         the Day home, we went there to the party. That was the big home of
         the city. So, we had sort of made a plan that after the party was
         over and the refreshments were done, we'd all start home, and then
         we d go back and dance. always bothered me, and I don't believe
         our nice Sunday School teacher ever knew what we had done, because,
         this girl, her aunt was away, and she'd asked the next door — a young
         lady and her fiancee to come in and chaparone— but our dancing was
         very hoppity, I imagine, (chuckles) But that always bothered me, be
         cause this Sunday School teacher, he was such a peach, and we'd have
         Sunday School parties, and he played the piano, and that was such a
         great thing to do in those days, to stand around the piano and sing.
         Well, he'd play all these popular songs, sheet music, you know, and
         we'd sing, and he was so good to play for us to sing, and then we
         treated him that way. always kind of bothered me. (chuckles)
         He was always one of my good friends, but I had a guilty feeling.
         
         Were there any circuses?
         
         Oh, yes, that was a big day when the circus came to town. And, of
         course, they traveled by train. And we'd have our alarm clock waken
         us, and several friends, we'd get together and go down to watch
         the train come in, and it usually came in around four o'clock in the
         morning, and it'd be cold, you know, but it was
         They would take off the elephants first, becausi
         big poles and the tents, the canvasses, to wherever the circus was to
         be. And we had several big open spaces, qijite close downtown in those
         days where the circus could be. And, so, after we'd watch the circus
         wagons, all painted, you know, beautifully painted. And, of course,
         very interesting,
         e they had to pull the animals inside, we could hear
         tigers, and so on. They weren't open, because we weren't supposed to
         see them until- Would hurry and go out to the circus grounds, because if they carried
         water to the elephants by pails and that's the way they had to do it,
         from hydrants, you know, nearby hydrants, why, they'd get a ticket to
         the circus. And, Harry did that, and I know my brother used to do
         that. And he 'd get a ticket for admission to the circus.. 
         
         But even,
         though we didn't have too much money, my father thought we should al
         ways go to the circus. He thought that was a very important thing for
         us to do. So there was always money for us to go to the circus. And
         we'd always go early, because, they had the animals: in one big tent
         the lions and the
         with the cages around the sides, and you could walk around and
         look at them before you went into the main tent to take your seat.
         And, of course, I don't remember of ever sitting in a reserved seat,
         which had a little back and was right at the center ring. These were
         usually three ring circuses. But, you'd try to get as near that as
         you could find a seat, you know, so you could see better. And
         then they opened the circus with a grand entry, you know, the parade.
         The bespangled girls riding on the elephants' heads, and the riders
         on the horses, and the cages coming around. But, in the morning, a
         thing which they never do any more, they'd have a parade on Main
         street, and that was one reason that. came to town so early, and
         of course, many children, that would be all they'd get to see
         ithe parade, because, the country people would drive in for the parade.
         I think it was usually scheduled for ten o'clock and it never came
         along til about eleven. And that was the one day of the year that
         didn't my father wouldn't.come home for the noon meal. So, my mother would,
         oh, I thought this was lovely, she'd buy buns and balogna when we'd
         go to town and we'd have cookies or something and we'd go to my fath
         er's place of business and eat. But every other working day of the
         year, he came home for his noon meal. But circus day, because of
         the parade, he didn't expect anyone to stay home to get him a meal.
         And, oh, that was very thrilling to have the parade go down Main
         Street.
         
         LS:  (very noisy) Was there only one circus?
         
         CS:  Yes,one. Oh, well,^sometimes we used to have-Ringling Circus
         first wasn't with Barnum and Bailey, you know. And we didn't get both
         big ones, every year, but then they— they were talking about it on
         "What's My Line?" the other night— I've forgotten the name of the
         smaller circus that used to come, and then we used to have dog and
         pony shows come. Well, they just had dog and pony performOnS.And
         they were delightful shows. They'd have a band, but oh, the ponies
         would perform, you know, and they had white ponies and little dark
         ponies and Shetland ponies. Horses. And, then, the little dogs, you
         know, would go through all their a , jumping through hoops. Course,
         we loved dog and pony shows. I think its too bad children don't get
         to see them now, because they really are a rather tranquil show for
         a child to see. They were delightful. One thing that the circuses
         used to have and it was quite the highlight for me— they would have
         the statues. Have you ever heard of that? Well, in one end of the
         tent they'd have this big thing all covered with white canvas or mus
         lin, or something, and then at this time of the show the big lights
         would focus on that, and they'd raise this and here would be about
         five performers in tights all perfectly white, their faces and all,
         and they'd pose as the Three Graces, or something, you know, and the
         band would play appropriate music, and then the cover would come down
         and they'd pose for another, and to me, that was just most exquisite.
         
         LS:  if.
         
         CS:  Well, I don't think they ever do that any more.
         
         LS:  Did they have acrobats?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes. And, of course, they always had nets below 'em. But then
         the crowd'd always go, ohhhhhh! you know, for fear they wouldn't
         catch the— some  through the air, you know. I
         Never remember of seeing anyone hurt, at all, because they always
         used nets. r6ourse, I think some of the performers today, especially
         European circuses, don't use careful care— they're so sure of
         themselves, or they're so much better trained, perhaps.
         
         LS:  Did you ever see medicine shows?
         
         CS:  Yes, I remember one, that came to town, and it's right where Short's
         Chapel is. I don't know what the medicine was. But they had this,
         sort of like a minstrel show, you know, two or three actors would
         put it on, and then the salesman would go through the crowd 
         the medicine. I don't remember that the Moddy family ever bought any,
         I can't remember that we did. And, I think that it was just mostly
         children ' went to the medicine show.
         
         LS:  They just put on a little skit?
         
         CS:  Yes, just a tiny little stage built 
         And, then a hypnotist would come to town. And they'd always put
         somebody to sleep in their store window,
         I think at one time they got a big block of granite from my father
         to go on this hyptnotized person's stomach.^ And then, perhaps, at
         a certain time they'd have a show, the hypnotist would in the Opera
         House or the GAR Hall, or wherever it was, and wake them from the stage
         you see. He'd have an accomplise there with him, but he'd awaken them
         from the stage and then he'd do all of his disappearing tracks, you
         know— soom. Then, we used to have chautauquas here at one time.
         
         CS:  Well, we did in Moscow, too. And, I I was of high school age
         then, and it lasted a week, and it was morning and afternoon. And,
         oh, people would just flock to the chautauqua , you know. They'd put
         uf in our city park a tent, "There the chautauqua would be, and you
         bought your ticket for the whole week. I don't think they sold tickets
         for each event,
         
         LS:  Did you go?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes, oh, yes, we went. We thought we were very well educated.
         They'd have lectures, you know, and then maybe a musical group. It
         was all brought in talent.
         
         LS:  What would the lectures be on?
         
         CS:  Oh, I don?t even remember that.
         
         LS:  Were they religious?
         
         CS:  Well, no, I don't believe they were religious. Margaret J^iaoke
         gave a program the other night on revival here, and I'd forgotten all
         about it, but it seems all the Protestant churches had gone in on
         this. And right back of the old post office, where the old Christian
         Church used to be, it's a parking lot now, they built a wooden taber
         nacle, they called it, just of boards, you know. And, she said in
         her story the other night that she went every night after school, they
         had a childrens'— well, I think I was enough older that— I'm enough
         older than Margaret, because I never went there to any children^ meet
         ing. I don't even remember of going at all. But Margaret said she
         and Marguerite jlin went every night after school, and Lillian Ottness
         to this childrens' meeting. But I think that I was probably
         enough older that I would look down on that sort of thing, you know,
         I was too big.
         
         LS:  Do you remember the revival?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh. Well, I don4t think Presbyterians ever went in so much for
         that sort of thing, as some denominations. I don't believe
         we did. So, that's kind of a blank, but, I thought, maybe, when she
         gave this paper, she was talking about where she'd lived before she
         came to Moscow. But she said, "No, that was right here in Mos
         cow."
         
         LS:  Do you remember when Armistice Day was?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes, I was a young woman then. And the fa
         LS: e Armistice came first,
         And, we all went down town, and then learned that it wasn't true.
         
         LS:  How did you hear about it?
         
         CS:  Well, I don't know. We didn't have radios. I don't know how we
         knew.
         
         LS:  Just word of mouth.
         
         CS:  Probably, uh-huh, because everybody went down town. But it wasn t
         many days before- probably there were rumors^hat it was to be signed.
         And then, on the real Armistice Day, we all went down town, and I
         think my sister—my mother died in 1918, and my sister, my older sis
         ter and I were at home with my dad— and she'd been sick and I think
         probably she had what we call 'flu now— well they did have 'flu on
         the campus up here. And it was very cold on November 11th, and she
         was ill most of the winter from going to that. She had a relapse from
         But that's another interesting thing. The University
         was a barracks, you see, for training soldiers for several years here.
         And when that flu epidemic came, thgy just they asked me to do the
         calling for the Red Cross in our neighborhood, and I went from door to
         door and got blankets and pillows, and the people were all asked to
         mark them so they could get them back. Because they had boys in the
         gymnasium, even in one of the livery stables here and the Elks Temple—
         sick boys. And Harry was in David's store then and they had to buy
         their own uniforms I guess just the officers had to buy their own
         uniforms. He would go up to take the measurements, he was 
         man, and he was supposed to wear a mask. Well, it was so much trouble
         that he'd take the mask off, and he never got it, but several he took
         measurements for.died before their uniforms even came. It was a ter-
         rible thing. And one of the big homes here in Moscow, the M. E. Lewis
         home, they used as a kitchen, and women went in to prepare the soup
         and so on. They transported it— 'course, we had cars by then— around
         to these places where the sick boys were. But  many died. It was a
         terrible thing.
         
         LS:  Was it mainly just the army?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh, army R.O.T.C., the infantry was what was here.
         
         LS:  And they were the main ones that got the flu?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh, isn't that terrible? 'Course, we had R.O.T.C. here in World
         War II, but then we had all brances of the services and accommodations
         were much better and those things didn't happen then. But in that
         First World War, the women knitted, you know, and because I was young,
         and foot free, I would carry yarn around to the women who
         knitted. They knitted socks and gloves and mufflers.
         
         CS:  No,the Red Cross brought the yarn in and it was given out. And, I know
         I'd take it to— so many of the Scandivanian women knitted, you know,
         and I lived in that part of town, so I would carry them the directions.
         But those women were such good knitters.
         Conversation concerning cookies was left out, and when the tape resumed the sub
         ject matter had changed.
         
         CS:  I went to an outside water hydrant to carry water into the house
         to be heated in a coal range with a water front in it, to heat the water,
         and then put in the reservoir to keep it hot, to indoor— the water
         brought inside, and then a hotwater tank heated by the kitchen range,
         and with sewer, and from an outside toilet to an inside toilet, and a
         bathroom with a bathtub, before that it was— we never bathed in tubs,
         as I remember, we had a big bathpan that was brought in. And that bathpan
         always hung out in the buttry. Now, you don't know what a buttry
         is. Well, my mother's father was brought up in New England, and they
         all had buttries, and it was just a place to keep the supplies, that
         were kept like flour and sugar and that sort of supplies. The big sup
         ply, and then you'd carry it into the smaller containers in the kit
         chen. And then, I went from kerosene lamps to electricity. And our
         first lights were just a drop cord, you know, with a bulb on the end
         of it, before we had any fixtures. But, the lamps, the coal oil lamps
         that was a hard time. My father was great on having every room
         lighted, in the house. And, so, that meant maybe several lights,
         like in our, we called it the frontroom then, it was the livingroom,
         several lamps there and then in the room, the diningroom probably
         where the studying was done at night around the diningroom table, you
         know. And she had at least ten or twelve lamps every morning to fill
         and wash the chimneys, and trim the wicks. And it took one hour of
         her morning, every morning, to prepare the lamps for the evening's light
         ing session. The chimneys had to be cleaned, too, you know, no lint
         or anything on 'em, they had to be sparkling. And then we burned—
         in the frontroom, the livingroom, we had a great huge heater, and the
         wood had to be brought in every night after school. And under one
         kitchen table, it wasn't the work table, but another kitchen table,
         was filled with wood every night for the heater. But, then, finally
         we started burning coal so it just meant just getting in scuttles of
         coal. But, that job fell to me after my brother was— had gone from
         home. I was the youngest so I fell heir to the job of bringing in the
         wood and mowing the lawn in the summer.
         
         LS:  Was the wood split already?
         
         CS:  Well, regular cord wood, that's the way my father bought it, he bought
         nine or ten cords every fall, was stacked in our alley. I think it
         was about four foot lengths, and then the wood sawyer came in with a
         mechanical saw and sawed it, and then it was carried into the woodshed.
         We had a great big woodshed and it was stacked clear to the ceiling.
         That supplied us until wood had to be purchased the next summer. But,
         of course, kindling would have to be split for the kitchen stove to
         ignite the but, before we burned coal though, the wood had to be
         split for the kitchen stove'cause there was a woodbox we had to fill
         behind the stove.
         
         LS:  When you were talking about going around for the—
         
         CS:  Red Cross?
         
         LS:  Yes. Did most people here really support the war?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes. And as I say, those Scandivanian people, they didn't— I
         couldn't converse with 'em, but they knew what we needed, and, boy,
         did they turn out the socks and things.And a lot of women couldn't—
         they had in their toe and hee
         LS: , it was a special toe and a
         heel they — the heel was kind of like this— indicates with hands—
         shaped, not just— and a lot of people couldn't do those, and so, I
         know my mother used to — I'd bring them to my mother after the long
         leg was— and I think they made 'em pretty long— and she'd put in the
         in the toe and heel..
         
         LS:  Would she take out what had been done?
         
         CS:  No, no, she'd just go right on and finish the foot, you see, the heel
         and the foot. The knitting was just the same, but she did that for
         many.
         
         LS:  Were there other things ?
         
         CS:  About the Red Cross?
         
         LS:  Yeah.
         
         CS:  Well, Mrs. Laney was head of the Red Cross here, then, and she just
         turned her home over. They made hospital gowns out of muslin. I never
         got in on that part 'cause I was just a young woman and I didn't know
         about that, but I was a good errand girl. Bu then ftjr different churches
         they'd roll bandages. Instead of a Ladies Aid meeting tip something,
         the time was spent rolling bandages. Moscow responded very well. In
         later years I was secretary of the Red Cross here, and Moscow always
         responded well to the Red Cross.
         
         Well, I believe maybe one reason— well, I don't know either—
         Dean Eldridge was in the YMCA— and that First World War, that was
         such a big thing, you know, the Young Mens Christian Association, and
         he was sent to France. But there were so many local people in it here
         that Moscow felt a great interest. I think the things that were
         accomplished, Moscow wasn't near as big then, were really quite remarkable
         for a town of this size. And this being the County Seat it
         went out to all the county from here. In every town there'd be a wo
         man wo'd set it up and tend to it. The response was splendid.
         
         LS:  Was there- the Ladies Aid? What was the Ladies Aid then?
         
         CS:  What was the Ladies Aid? Well, in our church there was— the Ladies
         Aid that really was just the organization in the church that kinda
         tended to the local wants of the church, you know. Gave icecream
         socials and so on, to raise money to augment the minister's salary or
         if they needed something in the Sunday School,why the money was used
         for that. And then, we had a minister's wife who felt that that wasn't
         sufficient, Mrs. Gormley, and so, she started a Women's Missionary
         Society. Well, the women began to think — a lot liked to go to the
         Ladies's Aid, that was more or less social, you see, and when they put
         on these special events, they all liked to work at them. But nobody
         wanted to belong to the Missionary Society, and so she got the bright
         idea of combining them, so it's been that way in our church to this
         day. It's all one organization. 'Course, it's that way nationally
         now, in my church, the Presbyterian Church. But, Mrs. Gormley had a
         very far vision by putting those into one organization, 'cause she
         made the Missionary Society as strong as the Ladie$ Aid, then, you
         see, because they all belonged to both.
         
         LS:  Well, did most of the women in the church belong?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh, because that was a big part of the social life of the town.
         Later on clubs started, various women's clubs, but in the early days
         that was the social light of the town. 
         
         LS:  Would each church have something like that?
         
         CS:  Yes.
         
         LS:  It wasn't just the Presbyterian Church?
         
         CS:  No, no. They all had their women's organizations. And I think a good
         many ministers might have been hungry if those women hadn't of helpeed
         raise money on the side to help out the church budget.
         
         LS:  Were there other things about the church that you remember?
         
         CS:  Yes. 'Course, my mother was a great church woman and my father always
         went to church, too. He made a Presbyterian of her, she'd been brought
         up something else. But, we all— my mother had six children, I was
         the baby, and I know she used to say she started taking me to church
         when I was six months old to Sunday School. She believed in the parents
         going to Sunday School. I don't remember my father ever going, but
         she managed to get six children ready and to get to Sunday School herself.
         So, we were brought up to think that was the thing to do. And
         then, my father would come on to church service at eleven, you see.
         The Sunday School was  and then he would come on and join
         my mother for church.
         
         LS:  She went— did she always do that?
         
         CS:  Always. Always.
         
         LS:  Would many of the other parents go?
         
         CS:  Quite a few. I think, like the Davids, they.all went to Sunday School,
         any many of the families in the church. Most of them. That was just
         a part of church life, too. And they're coming back to that now, which
         is very nice.
         
         LS:  Were there other activities for the young people?
         
         CS:  In the church? Well, yes, my oldest brother and my oldest sisters,
         they had a Christian Endeavor, which is a young people's organization
         that met in the evening. And then they had— that was their social
         life, to a great extent. 'Course, on Sunday night it was a religious
         service of sorts, you know. And, then, they'd have parties during
         the week. That was the social life of the town. You belonged to the
         Christian Endeavor— it was called other things in other churches, but
         in my church—
         
         LS:  Did you belong to that, too?
         
         CS:  I never did, uh-huh. That had stopped by the time I on. Well,
         you see, by that time we were having other interests. Being the tailend
         of the family, you know, it was developing into, like you know—
         I always went to Sunday School, but we didn't have any of this sort
         of thing or young people's meetings in my time. But later on, my sister,
         not the one who's living in Lewiston, but the next one who always made
         her home with us, Myra, went into religious education and she was the
         director in our church here. And, she started that again; the minister
         saw the need i the campus for that, and so it was started again. And
         she started a Westminster Guild for young college girls. But, really
         this is outside the scope of this— what you want. But that was con
         sidered an extra curricular activity on the campus, and it was accepted
         as that. And girls who participated in that got credit for their ex
         tra curricular activities, like in sororities and things.
         
         LS:  Did people from the University always come down to the churches?
         
         CS:  Yes, uh-huh, uh-huh.^ I think now— there isn't— although they're com
         ing real well at our church, but they do have— like the Catholics
         have their center on the campus, and they have the Christian Center
         on the campus, and I think the young people pretty much go to those.
         And then they have, during the week, these bullfests, or whatever they
         call 'em. That's out of the realm of what you want.
         
         CS:  quite small, because, we had gone on a camping trip up near Bovill
         and I remember, I was this small that in the morning I rode in the
         horse and buggy with my mother and father, and they carried me out in
         my nightgown, because it was early when we started, you see, so I must
         have been not too big. But we had our camping trip out there, and as
         we came home in two weeks, it was a Sunday, and there was a place half
         way out there, and a negro family lived there, it was kind of a half
         way house and the people used to stop on the way— the White Pines, we
         called it, around Bovill you know. People had timber claims up there.
         In fact, Carol writes about that in her book. And, so they told us,
         or I think somebody drove up while we were there with a team of horses,
         and told us what had happened in Moscow. So, of course, we were all
         very much excited about it. Well, by the time we got in there, the
         house where it happened was right down here where this service station
         catty-cornered— 'course, that was the only road into town and the
         highway wasn't here, so we had to go right by it, of course,
         all traces of the tragedy were gone by then. But, 'course, there were
         bullett holes in the house. I don't know that I actually saw 'em,
         but that was what they said. But, that happened very much as it was
         in the book. And this man who went berserk, had been told by Dr. Wat
         kins that he thought he should be committed to Orofino to the asylum,
         because he beat up and was so cruel to his mother. And this man's
         father, I think, had been a Mason along with Dr. Watkins. 
         
         And, so,
         Dr. Watkins was sort of taking him— I don't know how old he was—
         under his — you know, trying to do what was the right thing. So, he
         just went berserk that particular day, and Dr. Watkins went to his of
         fice every Sunday morning, and he shot him. Came ulfan his horse and
         shot him— Dr. Watkins. But the horse just kept going, and went down
         and stopped in front of the— his office as it was used to doing, you
         see. That was so matter of fact, the horse could — as it was it's
         habit to do. And, pretty soon somebody saw Dr. Watkins slumped, and
         then this fellow went on down the street on his horse, and Mr. Creigh
         ton, who owned the store where Creighton's is now, he always carried
         a cane, not for need, but for looks, and a hat, and so on. And he shot
         at Mr. Creighton, I don't know what his grudge was against Mr. Creigh
         ton, but he just hit him in the arm, and then he went on down and came
         up Eighth Street to where a deputy sheriff lived and he stopped there
         and asked for a drink of water. And he had intended to shoot the deputy
         sheriff, but he had his baby in his arms and I know those girls real
         well, they don't live here any more— and so he didn't shoot him. And
         then, he had, oh, there were several men on his list— as he came in
         towards the Presbyterian Church he came in Eighth Street, what Eighth
         street is now, and stopped at the Harold home, which I know, 'cause
         I was born in that neighborhood, and Mrs. Harold said that Mr. Harold
         was not at home, so he went on then, and got Dr. Watkins. And, so, by
         the time this had all happened, the posse had gotten together and they'd
         opened the hardware stores and got guns for all the men, and they came
         up by foot, If course, 'cause he'd come out to his home and barricaded
         himself in the upstairs. And so, they just poured the shot into that
         house and finally his old mother came out and said, "Don't shoot any
         more, he's dead." And one man in Moscow claimed that he'd fired the
         bullet that had killed him, you know, but nobody ever knew. And that's
         in, which one of Carol's books? Have you read any? 
         
         LS:  Yeah.
         
         CS:  Yeah, that's what I thought.
         
         LS:  Is that mainly what you remember it from?
         
         CS:  No, I remembered it. Well, 'course, it's mainly from Carol's book and
         then our talk in the home when I was a child, you see. But, I remember
         of going on that camping trip, although I don't remember any of the
         
         But I remember of coming back and going by that house.
         
         Were there actually any other things like that that happened in town?
         
         Well, of course, — was it in Buffalo Coal- where the minister's daugh
         ter went to Orofino— that was in the same story. That actually hap
         pened, too, you know. The minister's daughter went down to Orofino,
         with this doctor, and a murder-suicide, you know. No, I don't rememb
         er of anything real tragic like that ever happening.
         
         Oh, there were farm accidents and things that were bad, sometimes
         you know, but nothing that was just actual planned out like this was.
         Were there many trials that were ?
         
         Oh, yes, yes. Of course, in the old courthouse— what was that trial?
         But that was after this time you're wanting. But there were trials
         here. Then the Federal Court was here, you see, and the Indians were
         always brought here for their misdemeanors, because they had to appear
         in Federal Court, you see. And that was one of the talking points against
         has always been,
         our old post office, The Indians didn't like to climb those stairs
         up to the court. That always tickled me. (chuckles)
         
         Did you go to a dentist?
         
         Oh, yes. I think Harry had dentist on his list. But dentistry— the
         dentists we went to— I think he must have been a pretty crude dentist—
         but he was a big man and he had such huge hands. It was old-style den
         tistry, of course, but I remember once— I had to have one of my molars
         pulled, and I just fought that man terribly. And ffitnally, I just wig
         gled out of his chair and he pulled the tooth— I was on the floor when
         he pulled . But he gave me the tooth and I know I had it in alittle
         box for years. Well, we didnt know anything about the Tooth Fairy then
         either. (chuckles) But dentistry was so crude and it hurt so.
         
         How would they do?
         
         Well, I don't think they ever— 'course, I was so young then, I was
         just— I think they just pulled the teeth, but, later on, this would
         still be in the time you want, I guess, the dentist we came to, he was—
         by then they were putting cocaine- I don't think it was novacaine— but
         something in, you know, if they did work. But his procedure on dent
         istry was, if you got a cavity in a tooth, was to extract the nerve of
         the tooth and then fill it. And, I know he used that, he'd run this
         little wire in and twist it around the nerve some way and jerk it out.
         You felt one terrible excruciating pain, you know, and, of course, the
         tooth was dead then, because I know I had a dead tooth.in the front be
         fore I got dentures that finally gave me trouble. But that was his
         method to extract the nerve from the tooth and then fill it. He ran a
         little wire, he'd drill and then put this in and pull the nerve out.
         doesn't that sound crude? Well, it was crude. But he was considered
         a very good dentist. I remember him so well because he hummed all the
         time he worked on you. His daughter was one of my best friends. He
         extracted my mother's teeth, and my father was going to be up there to
         be with her during the ordeal, and he was late, something happened, and
         he didn't get there in time. Just as he came in the waiting room doorthe
         dentist's waiting room door— he heard Dr. Watkins, his name was
         Watkins, too, but it was no relation— he said, "I'll never pull another
         tooth for Mrs. Moody." And it scared my father to death, he thought
         she'd died or something, and he just meant he'd finished the job. But
         she was very uncomfortable I remember after that. And.they waited sev
         eral months before they put the new teeth in, you know, 'cause I know
         when I had to have my upper teeth extracted, they put the teeth in im
         mediately because they'd taken a mold already and made them.
         
         LS:  Can you tell me about your grandmother who lived out on—
         
         CS:  Well, yes, that was the grandmother, that was my mother's mother who
         lived in Salubria, where I said my mother came to. And she married
         Mr. Smith, we always called him, we never called him grandpa or any
         thing but Mr. Smith. And they bought a place down on Fix Ridge, and
         Grandma was just sort of the do-gooder on that ridge. Anybody was sick
         they'd call Grandma, 'cause she had all these old time remedies, you
         know. And anybody died}Grandma had to go and help lay them out, as
         she called it. But, they did have phones, but they had a signal that
         if anything happened central rang this one ring and everybody took
         their phones down, so they would know whatever had happened, you know.
         And that always seemed like that was quite neat to me, when I was a
         child. Mama went down several times during the good part of the year,
         the weather, and Iwas alittle girl and Iwent with her. But, we had
         to ford a little stream out here someplace beyond Lgnnville, and we'd
         start out early in the morning 'cause it took us pretty near all day to
         get there, because the horse never went at avery good gait for my
         mother, kinda walked all the way. An my mother always hoped that I'd
         be having anap when we came to the stream, because, as Iremember you
         could- it was just like that- but it scared me, anyway, that bumping
         across the rocks. And, I've never found the place where that was, but
         of course, it's so different now. Then I'd get out at the top of the
         hill above Grandma's house, they lived kind of down in alittle valley
         and go down through the orchard and beat Mama there, of course, 'cause
         she'd have to go around and go through the lane to get to the house.
         But, Grandma had feather beds and we didn't have feather beds, we just
         had mattresses, and Ohhh, Ithought that was just heaven to sleep in a
         feather bed.
         
         LS:  You'd stay over night?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes, we'd stay several days when we'd go like that, 'cause it was
         an all-day trip almost for my mother to get there, and we stayed several
         days. Iknow we often went when the peaches were ripe down there. And,
         Grandma— they had quite a prune orchard. They had quite a business
         of drying prunes, that was quite the thing here in the early days. Peo
         ple would grow prunes and dry 'em. And, I think they must have sold
         them to the stores. But they had a house dryer, where they had some
         kind of fire, I don't know what it was, and the prunes would be put in
         on chicken wire racks and they'd dry them. I don't know why they
         didn't taste smokey, but they didn't, they were delicious. 'Cause we
         always had a sack hanging in the buttry, when I was a child, and we'd
         play sort of 'cops and robbers', you know, and the buttry was always
         the jail, but there was kind of an advantage to being in jail, because
         you could eat dried prunes and dried apples, (chuckles)
         
         LS:  Did your mother dry the apples, too? 
         
         CS:  Yes. I remember she did. They'd put sheets up on the wood house roof
         and we'd spread just think of peeling all those apples— and then
         my brother, probably, was sent up to spread them out and then they put
         a net- what is this window netting, what did they call that?
         
         LS:  Mosquito?
         
         CS:  Mosquito net over them, to keep the bugs off. But they never thought
         about the dust, because our street wasn't paved and the dust would get
         about that in the summer. And a vehicle happened to go by the
         dust would roll in. But we always sprinkled down our road— the street
         in front of our house; ^several of the neighbors did, but on beyond us
         they never sprinkled, so we always managed to get quite a bit of dust.
         That was one job I had to do, was sweeping off the veranda every day,
         and it was quite a job, all that dust. But people then used to sit out
         on their porch in the evenings, you know, it was hot, but you sat out
         there and the neighbors would come over and visit. My father always
         sat out and read his paper in the evening until it got too dark to
         read. But, you used your porches a great deal in those days. And, so,
         that was one of my jobs, was to sweep off the veranda every morning.
         
         LS:  Did you have other jobs?
         
         CS:  Well, filling the woodbox, and then sprinkling the lawn.
         
         LS:  How would you do that?
         
         CS:  Well, we had a sprinkler, but, to get the edges I would hold the hose
         and sprinkle. And I know if I was anxious to go someplace, if I'd make
         it look awfully wet on the sidewalks and everything, my father'd think
         I'd done a pretty good job of sprinkling, so I could get going, but,
         actually it was just all surface. But, I was really supposed to start
         the hose late in the afternoon and give the lawn a good watering.
         
         LS:  Did you have much of a garden?
         
         Oh, yes. We had these two lots, you see, south of our house, and there
         were trees, and then in the center was all open with a garden spot. We
         always had our own potatoes and peas and beans and things, and corn,
         and my father used to hire the next door neighbor to come over and spade
         it up for him and then he'd plant it. Every evening he'd go out and hoe
         and work In the garden. And it was always a delight to go down in
         fruit cellar in the fall after everything was harvested. There were
         sacks and sacks of potatoes and all the shelves full of can
         ned fruit, because the stores— you just could only buy oranges and ban
         anas in the winter, you know, that was all you could ever buy. We didn't
         even have head lettuce or anything like that in the winter, then. But
         we had our own beets and carrots and they were stored and parsnips and
         all the things that you could grow that would keep, you know. But, I
         don't remember, we never grew our own tomatoes in those days. We always
         had to buy them. But several gardeners around town would— out in the
         country grew tomatoes. But, I don't know why we never thought we could
         have tomatoes in our garden. We thought they wouldn't ripen, you know
         the frost came. But, I think the varieties are better now and
         are earlier and so on, and so we can ripen tomatoes easily in Moscow.
         
         LS:  Did you can any meat or anything like that?
         
         CS:  No. We never did. We never did that, I know lots of people did. What
         we did do: in the spring of the year, my grandmother would always give
         us two little pigs. Our lot was big so we had a pigpen, you know, and
         we had our own chickens. But then, in the early winter, later than this
         when it started to get real cold, my father'd have a man come and butcher,
         but they never smoked the meat. It was packed down in barrels with salt, and so that
         made it- always had to be parboiled, you
         know, it'd be salty. But it was good. But I don't know what about the
         hams and things, they made sausage, but I don't remember whether they
         to be used fresh, or how they used them, cause they
         weren't smoked. Unless this man took them and smoked them. He must have
         because we'd have bacon. So this man who did the butchering must haYe
         smoked the meat at his home.
         
         LS:  Was it unusual for a family in the city to have a big garden? You know,
         chickens—
         
         CS:  Well, not in our part of town, it wasn't unusual. But down near Main
         Street people didn't usually have that sort of thing. My friends, I
         don't think that lived near in— one's father was a doctor and the
         other^was a blacksmith, and they never did have at their homes, because
         the blacksmith because the girl who had the blacksmith as a father lived
         where Safeway is now, their home was there, and his shop was right
         where the theatre is, the movie theatre. And then Dr. had a
         later he had a hospital over where the apartments are on First Street,
         across from the United Church down there. But, their home was up on
         First Street and they had no garden. They had a barn, they had a horse,
         but they had no garden. So, I don't believe as a rule, people who lived
         closer in— we lived then what was considered quite far out, and then
         having that big a lot, why, we always had a garden. And it was probably
         a necessity with having six children. And, then, Mr. Ramstad,
         who lived near us, it's Allen Ramstfad, who's in Creightons, his grand
         father, they lived right across the alley back of us, and he had a
         great big orchard, and we bought cherries, I know. He'd bring over
         great milk pails of cherries and my mother would can those, 'cause
         we had cherry pie, and apple pie, and so on. Lots of cherry pie and
         mincemeat pie and so on, in the winter. But, I know, Mrs. wn0
         was Aunt Elsie in Carol's book, Aunt Elsie who brought Carol up, used
         to say my oldest sister never could go anyplace on Saturday, because
         she had to make cherry pies. And she said she made seven. Well, I
         can't even imagine one family making seven cherry pies at a time, but
         Miss Elsie said that was the way it was at the Moody house, so I don't
         know. I don't remember that.
         
         LS:  Did you ever eat out?
         
         CS:  Well, no, no, we didn't. Actually the hotels were the only places who
         had diningrooms. I don't remember of being taken to the hotel to eat,
         ever, when I was a child. If you went to another town and stayed in
         the hotel, then you did. If you went to Spokane, or anything, you know.
         But, being in Moscow, I don't remember of ever eating out at the hotel,
         as a little child. 'Course, you went to church suppers, and as I told
         you before, the friends always took me to the bean bake and the GAR
         supper, and so on. So, those were the way you ate out.
         
         LS:  bean bake?
         
         CS:  Well, the GAR is the Grand Army of the Republic, the Civil War veterans
         used to have that, and these friends, the father belonged, so they al
         ways took me along with them.
         
         LS:  You said, when you were talking about that, that those were the old
         timers?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh, they were. We thought that they were, because the men all had
         great white beards, and so on, and we thought that they were— well,
         they were really the people who settled around here first, those people.
         
         LS:  Do you remember any of the older people that impressed you?
         
         CS:  Oh, -
         
         LS:  You know, the early settlers?
         
         CS:  Well, Mr. Neil^was one, and, of course, his daughter was my friend,
         but I thought he was pretty fine. And then, they had a friend, and I
         think he was an old bachelor, Mr. Mc Bane, who had this great, white
         beard, and I always was a little in awe of him, you know, with this
         great, white beard. 'Course now, Harvey Smith's father, Mr. H. R. Smith,
         was always superintendent of our Sunday School, and I think he had a
         smaller beard, and I think we all stood in a little awe of him. But,
         much after I was a little child, he was superintendent so many years—
         some little child went home and told their mother that they'd seen God
         that day at Sunday School. And they called Mr. H. R. Smith God, that's
         Harvey's father, whom you're going to talk to tomorrow. He was a law
         yer.
         
         But in those days, the University wasn't so big and the town wasn't
         so big, and there was much sociability and good feeling between— we
         always went to things on the campus, even when I was a small child.
         'Course, the things were recitals and declamatory contests and that
         sort of thing, debates, you know. But, the townspeople always went to
         those things. That was the thing that we all did. And, I think that
         was a good feeling. And the women of the town; the women who lived on
         that side, on University side, would have their afternoon at home one
         day a week and the women who lived on this side would stay at home for
         callers, you see, and they'd have their little teatables and serve tea.
         
         LS:  Who would come by?
         
         CS:  Well, the women from— who had friends on this side would come and
         call. They did a great deal of calling in those days. And the first
         time you went to call on anyone, you always left your card, you see.
         They always had a little tray or plate near the door you'd always
         leave your card. 'Course, even after I was married people called on me
         and left their cards.
         
         LS:  Women would have cards?
         
         CS:  Uh-huh, with their names on. Mrs. So-and-so. But that was rather a
         nice custom. We don't take time to call like that much anymore. And
         it was a nice custom. Of course, our groups of friends are so much
         larger that you just don't do that sort of thing. But it's too bad.
         Especially for newcomers who come to town. They have to sort of make
         their own means of getting acquainted, you know, it seems, by going to
         church or perhaps.asked to join some club or something. But, I think
         that was a very good idea. 'Course, when I was a little girl, we thought
         it was pretty nice when we were asked to serve punch at the University
         dances. They'd fix up a real— like the Junior Prom, or something
         beautiful table and ask several little town girls to come up to serve
         the punch. And we thought that was something, to be asked to
         come to the University to serve punch at a dance.
         
         LS:  What would the dance be like? Would they get real dressed up?
         
         CS:  Oh, yes!! They really dressed up, the girLls, had evening gowns. And
         I don't think they wore— the men wore Tuxedos or full dress or anything,
         but they had suits— the men wore suits. But they— we had cabs- horse
         cabs in those days, and so the young man, if he could afford it, he'd
         take his girl, especially if she lived across town, to the dance in a
         cab. But they always picked the little girls up, that was part of the
         expense of the class that was giving the dance. to get the little
         girls there that served, and we thought that. Only I was
         always the last one home, 'cause we lived the fartherest away, and
         my mother didn't approve or appreciate that very much. But it- I
         think those of us who had older brothers and sisters in college, we
         really had two educations, because we knew everything that was going
         on when we were children, you know, they'd come home and talk about,
         and then when we got older ourselves and did the same sort of thing,
         why, we sort of lived it before, don't you know.
         
         One time, maybe I told you this before— We were over to a
         party, it was about this time of the year, to a little friend's house
         and it got dark early, and it was just pouring rain, and my two little
         friends and I were coming home,'cause we lived on this side, and this
         big, tall man came along and asked us to walk under his umbrella, he
         always carried a great, big umbrella, he was from Canada, rather Eng
         lish, and we didn't know who the man was, but, oh, he asked us so many
         questions, what our names were, and if we had brothers and sisters in
         college, and so on. Afterwards, we found out it was the new president
         of the University, Doctor Mc  and there we d told the whole
         life history of our brothers and sisters who were in college, and they
         were pretty put out with us. Because the school wasn't so big then,
         and, of course, he knew who they were when he heard their names. I
         expect he wondered why three little girls were out around five o'clock
         on such a day. He ate his dinners down at the hotel, and he
         was going for his dinner.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13585</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Ruberg</previous>
      <next>Sampson_Clarice2</next>
      <disp_name>Sampson_Clarice1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
