<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/7/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Hanna Anderson Sandell, 1976-02-07, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:49:15</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Sandell, Hanna Anderson</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Nurse at Gritman Hospital; homemaker</occupation>
      <birthyear>1891</birthyear>
      <residence>Johnson, Troy</residence>
      <origin>Parents came from Sweden (c. 1870)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#wagons"&gt;wagons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#housekeeping"&gt;housekeeping&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#nurses"&gt;nurses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#marriage"&gt;marriage&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moving"&gt;moving&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hospitals"&gt;hospitals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#butchering"&gt;butchering&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#orchards"&gt;orchards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gardens"&gt;gardens&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#electricity"&gt;electricity&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lore"&gt;lore&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#medicine"&gt;medicine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#saloons"&gt;saloons&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mansions"&gt;mansions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Oregon"&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Karen Purtee</interviewer>
      <file_name>13586</file_name>
      <mp3>13587.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13587.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Mother born in Sweden; migrated to to Cordelia/Lenville area; mother's death; early
               Troy; Lutheran Church services
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother's birth in Sweden; Ruberg family migration to Cheney, Wash, then by wagon to
               Cordelia/Lenville area. Mother's death. Early Troy, Bohman's home, Lutheran Church
               services in Swedish and English.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Parents marriage; home farm; trading in Moscow; walking to school in Washington</title>
            <synopsis>Parents married by Rev. Peter Carlson, Northwest missionary who lived in Moscow. Home
               farm on Washington-Idaho border. Trading in Moscow, school in Washington. Walking
               l 1/4 miles to school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>660</time>
            <title>Inviting neighbors to dinner; catching head lice; worked through college as a housekeeper;
               music lessons
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Plenty to eat, kids sent with notes to invite neighbors to dinner. Visiting a family
               and catching head lice. She worked her way through college as housekeeper. The kind
               lady that gave her a salary and a music lesson each week.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Nurse training in Portland; giving x-ray treatments; man with cancerous lips</title>
            <synopsis>Nurse training in Portland (1920-1923). Patients in the halls;
               giving x-ray treatments, a man with cancerous lips returns after his cure.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Married and moved to Troy; people the apartments were rented to</title>
            <synopsis>Married and moved to Troy 1924. The reasons for moving from hilltop home to Main Street
               apartment (1960). Some of the people the apartments were rented to.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1260</time>
            <title>Gritman Hospital; 60th class reunion; firing the helper that lied</title>
            <synopsis>Gritman Hospital work. Back to Portland for 60th class reunion. Being in charge at
               Gritman; firing the helper that lied.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Confirmation classes; going to church; confirmed in Swedish</title>
            <synopsis>Going to Moscow for Confirmation classes every Saturday and into Church for Sunday.
               Confirmation all in white dresses, described. 31 in class. Confirmed in Swedish except
               for
               Miss Jacobson, the top student.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1740</time>
            <title>Boys and girls in the family; leap year</title>
            <synopsis>Two boys and six girls in the family. Leap year - no leap year from 1900-1910.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Mud in Troy; public outhouse; stores in Moscow; history of Creighton's</title>
            <synopsis>Mud in Troy Main Street, public outhouse on Main Street; stores in Moscow, history
               of Creighton's. Mud so bad that horseback was easiest way to travel.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2040</time>
            <title>Butchering; salted meats, pork, and beef; preparing for cooking; meat in the woodshed</title>
            <synopsis>Today's folks couldn't make it if they had to go back to the early ways. Butchering,
               salted meats, pork and beef, preparing for cooking, chickens eaten fresh. Meat in
               the woodshed; hams stored in the grain after smoking.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2280</time>
            <title>Making jam; father's orchard; milking two cows twice a day; walking to school</title>
            <synopsis>First peaches - made into jam. Father's orchard. Vegetables, carrots, cabbage, potatoes.
               Milk,cream and butter. She,
               sister and brother each milked two cows twice a day, then walk to school. The nice
               warm fire when they got to school.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2640</time>
            <title>Benjamin Franklin; Churchill speech</title>
            <synopsis>Benjamin Franklin story, Churchill speech.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2940</time>
            <title>Early lighting; making cheese; deer meat; killing and dressing pigs</title>
            <synopsis>Early lighting, mother's cheese making, dried meat. No deer meat. Killing and dressing
               pigs.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Mother's work; berries; government gave uncle a gun; lookout house in Moscow; snow
               and sleds; riding on unbroken horses
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother's work, berries. Government gave a gun to an uncle so he could shoot Indians.
               Lookout house in Moscow to spot Indians. Dad sleeps out on the way home because it
               was so dark. Snow and sleds; riding on the unbroken horses until caught by Dad.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Dressing for the cold</title>
            <synopsis>Deep snow; dressing for cold weather.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Stories about Marshall Hays and Blialock; working in Troy hospital</title>
            <synopsis>Stories about Marshall Hays and Blialock in Cornwall. Working with Dr. Myers as operating
               nurse in Troy hospital on corner of 6th and Main.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4080</time>
            <title>Delivering babies; mother attending for her children</title>
            <synopsis>Delivering babies, Mrs. Krier's hard delivery. Mother had Dr. Delne, Gritman and Asbury
               attending for her children. Mrs. Sandell delivers three babies in one morning.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4320</time>
            <title>Delivering a baby in the parking lot; population control; twin beds</title>
            <synopsis>Delivering a baby in the parking lot; population control needed; in the old days -
               twin beds.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4680</time>
            <title>Dad brought home candy; flies on the food</title>
            <synopsis>Dad brought home more hound candy; flies on the food and meat.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4800</time>
            <title>Streets in Moscow; chores after school; school terms</title>
            <synopsis>Moscow mud or dust for streets. Chores after school; school terms in spring and fall;
               school not too good, short classes; hearing other classes recite was good.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>Working as x-ray supervisor; working at Gritman; premature babies; changes in medicine</title>
            <synopsis>Hard work as x-ray supervisor; working at Gritman with old and new hospital wings;
               working with premature babies, one was her last case. Changes in medicine.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5280</time>
            <title>Penicillin allergy; first cars in Moscow; horses scared of cars; accident with her
               horse and a car
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Penicillin; allergy of head nurse to penicillin. First cars in Moscow owned by Dr.
               Gritman and Mr. Green. Horses scared of cars. Accidents with her horse and buggy and
               someone's
               car.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Driving a car; Model T Fords; cousin couldn't stop the car; storing cars during the
               winter
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>First car she drove. The old Model T Fords; cousin started to drive car before he
               learned to stop it, drove in circles until the car was out of gas. Side curtains instead
               of windows. Storing cars for three months in the winter.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5640</time>
            <title>Snow in the winter; everyone walked in Moscow; cars today</title>
            <synopsis>Snow in the winter, company in the summer only. Everyone walked in early Moscow. Using
               cars today.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5820</time>
            <title>Dogs coming school in Troy; Moscow before Prohibition; John Olsen's tavern</title>
            <synopsis>Dogs came to school in Troy. In Moscow before Prohibition, drinking was bad. She was
               glad when drinking went out. About John Olson's tavern in Moscow and his family.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Stores in Troy; Lutheran church history; Borah's death</title>
            <synopsis>Saloons and stores in Troy. Lutheran Church history in Moscow. Mother worked as domestic
               in home near McConnell Mansion. Borah's death.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Nursing experiences. Growing up on farm; food preparation. Nursing training. Early
         Moscow and Troy. First cars. 2-7-76 1.8 hr KP
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13301_lcoh_13301.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF index; no transcript available&lt;/a&gt; 
         
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13586</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Sampson_Harry3</previous>
      <next>Sanderson_Byers1</next>
      <disp_name>Sandell</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
