<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/7/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Ada Schoeffler, 1976-02-07, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:17:31</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Schoeffler, Ada</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Farm wife; harvest cook; housekeeper</occupation>
      <birthyear>1901</birthyear>
      <residence>Potlatch Ridge, Cameron</residence>
      <origin>Families came from Missouri and Iowa (1880's)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#midwives"&gt;midwives&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#housekeeping"&gt;housekeeping&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cooking"&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#illness"&gt;illness&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dentists"&gt;dentists&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#children"&gt;children&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pregnancy"&gt;pregnancy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#post offices"&gt;post offices&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#holidays"&gt;holidays&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mess halls"&gt;mess halls&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#tractors"&gt;tractors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch Ridge"&gt;Potlatch Ridge&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Juliaetta"&gt;Juliaetta&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Karen Purtee</interviewer>
      <file_name>13559</file_name>
      <mp3>13560.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13560.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Mother's education and family coming to settle on Potlatch Ridge; 1880 area opened
               for homesteading
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother's education and family coming to settle on Potlatch
               Ridge. 1880 the area was opened for homesteading. Father's
               family and travels to Fix Ridge on the Little Potlatch (13 miles
               from Moscow). Mother went to teach school on Fix Ridge
               and married her student. Mother, uncle, and grandparents
               took adjoining homesteads.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>240</time>
            <title>No doctors for babies; grandmother became midwife; mother sells homestead for big
               price
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>No doctors for babies. Grandmother became a midwife by
               reading a book, and ministered to all of Cedar Creek area.
               Her mother sells the homestead for the big price of $40 an
               acre.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Mox Mox licks butter knife; ornary adopted cousin</title>
            <synopsis>Mox Mox licks the butter knife before returning it to the bowl.
               The ornary adopted cousin.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>600</time>
            <title>Working as a housekeeper in Lewiston; working as a threshing cook on other farms</title>
            <synopsis>Working from 14 on as a housekeeper in Lewiston. Sister
               worked in Lewiston too. $5 a week doing all the laundry;
               attitude of her boss. Working as threshing cook on other
               farms. Mother's sickness. The only time mother went to the
               doctor was just before she died. Father's grit at the dentist.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Schools in Moscow, Southwick, Kendrick, Cedar Creek, and Crescent School</title>
            <synopsis>Schools, Moscow grades 1-4, Leland, Southwick, Kendrick,
               Cedar Creek grades 5-7, and Crescent School and Leland
               8th grade and examination. Moscow had single grades and
               more thorough teaching techniques than the one-room schools.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1080</time>
            <title>Having the twins, doctor was late so the husband was in charge
               and very nervous
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Having the twins, doctor was late so the husband was in charge
               and very nervous.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Father's joking about husband Fred being German; Germans stuck to their language and
               stayed together; very industrious
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Father's joking about husband Fred being German before they
               were married. The Germans stuck to their language and stayed
               together. They were very industrious and built good farms.
               Fred used "hurry" in every sentence. All Germans worked
               as hard as they could. Dr. Stoneburner at Leland. (Mrs.
               Nye is a history buff.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1680</time>
            <title>Father's girlfriends after mother's death; father's last days</title>
            <synopsis>Father's girlfriends after mother's death. Father's last days,
               her own gallstones. Running under the sidewalk in Moscow when
               little to escape Father's anger.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Father's brag; eight children, three boys died</title>
            <synopsis>Father's brag. She got in trouble talking back to father. Eight
               children; three boys died, only one boy raised to maturity.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
            <title>Older sister and husband died of tuberculosis; Mrs. Schoeffler's mother, sister, and
               self raised the two daughters
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Oldest sister and husband died of tuberculosis leaving two
               daughters for Mrs. Schoeffler's mother, sister and self to
               raise. She raised the two with her sister from her mother's
               death when she was 13. Slop jars and chamber pots in the house
               when plumbing is outdoors. Caring for her grandchildren.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Sister married at 39, she married at 17; Her children and
               births
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sister married at 39, she married at 17. Her children and
               births.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2580</time>
            <title>She did chores up to the day before her twins were born</title>
            <synopsis>She did chores up to the day before the twins were born
               including washing clothes, packing water; a fall while she
               was pregnant. Her husband was a Dutchman that worked his
               wife.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2700</time>
            <title>Mother never had phone in her home; no mail service at first; one neighbor a week
               would go to Genesee for mail
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Mother never had a phone in her home. No mail service at
               first. One neighbor from the Ridge each week would go to
               Genesee for the mail and pick it up for everybody. The road
               over Fix Ridge. (A joke about relatives coming west in
               covered wagons but she couldn't find the road from Moscow to
               Juliaetta today.)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2940</time>
            <title>Scotty Wilson, character who settled in Juliaetta homesteading</title>
            <synopsis>Scotty Wilson, character who settled in Juliaetta homesteading
               rocky pasture land. His wife had a hard life with 11 kids.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3060</time>
            <title>Playing school with nieces while caring for them</title>
            <synopsis>Playing school with nieces while caring for them. Her
               sister-in-law's good traits of school and cooking for extra
               company.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>Hosting her sister's company; old celebrations on the 4th of July</title>
            <synopsis>Hosting her sister's company; old celebrations on the 4th of
               July at all small towns. Lots of work.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Cooking for threshing crew</title>
            <synopsis>Cooking for a threshing crew when they came to their farm.
               Most often she knew ahead of time. Had to go to town for fresh
               groceries. Cooked for 47 for eight days. Stove wasn't big
               enough for that many; baked 20 loaves of bread a day. Her day
               from 3am-10pm. Glad when they were gone. Could only sit
               14 at a time. The meals; the hungry 13 man crew; the crops.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Bean crops; first farmers to raise beans; renting land since moving to town</title>
            <synopsis>Bean crops, wet years; first farmer to raise beans. No let
               up in farmer's work. Renting the land since moving to town.
               The city boys who wanted to rent her land.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Horse to tractors; Fred was the last to get a tractor; raising their own horses</title>
            <synopsis>Horse to tractors; Fred was one of the last to get a tractor
               after WWI 1. 30 work horses in Fred's stable; raising their
               own horses; not breaking them for work until 3 years old.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3960</time>
            <title>Her arthritis in her legs, her neighbor's good legs</title>
            <synopsis>Her arthritis in her legs, her neighbor's good legs.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4140</time>
            <title>Her accident when a bale of hay landed on her head; Her
               daughter's accident in a plane crash
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Her accident when a bale of hay landed on her head. Her
               daughter's accident in a plane crash.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Hard work on farm and in harvest. Childbirth. Parents. German ways. Caring for
         children. Housekeeping. 2-7-76 1.3 hr KP
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         ADA CYLEAR SCHOEFFLER:  had some education, but sbe got college down there.
         
         KAREN PURTEE: Well, then they all came over from Oregon?
         
         ADA CYLEAR SCHOEFFLER: Well, they started out in Missouri. She was born in Wisconsin
         but she was the only one, Ithink, the rest settled in Missouri
         and she-they settled in she went to college
         there. And then they heard about land being open here and they
         came here to settle. And I don't know how they got up on this
         ridge. It was up on this ridge over here.
         
         KP:   What you call Potlatch?
         
         AS:   Yes, this is Potlatch.
         
         KP:   About what year would this be?
         
         AS:   That was in 1880 when they came, to here, anyway.
         
         KP:   And there was still land open to homestead?
         
         AS:  Yes. This was all open, they were just starting in to settle up
         there then. It hadn't been farmed, the Indians had hunted and
         so on here; but there hadn't ever been any farming done. And
         about that time, I guess after it opened up and they could take
         out 160 acres, that's what you could homestead, but you had to
         live on it and show that you were making improvements, trying,
         you know, to do something about it. Why then, my father had came
         here from-they started out from Iowa. He was born in Missouri
         but they Iowa and my grandfather heard about the gold
         strike in California; well, he thought that was for him. They
         got there and he didn't find the gold, so he had 120 acres of
         farm land in Iowa and he went to California and foiled around,
         and he didn't make anything, then they come on up here and set
         tled on 160 acres he homesteaded up on-over Fix Ridge, it's on
         what they called the Little Potlatch thirteen miles, this side
         of Moscow. And so then, why, my grandmother, which Inever did
         see, she died before Iwas born, she had heard about some school
         teachers that was over here-heard about the Welkers, which was
         my mother's maiden name-so she took ahorse to ride and one to
         lead, so she decided to go back with her to teach school, they
         were going to open up aschool. So, that's how she met my fa
         ther, and he went to school to her only she was older than he
         was-and finally he got the-
         
         He got the schoolmarm, huh?
         
         Yeah, he got the schoolmarm and the ranch with it, she had.
         
         Oh, yes, you were telling me. Your grandparents homesteaded up
         there then?
         
         And an uncle of mine and my mother, they were the ones that were
         old enough-I think you had to be twenty-one before you could
         homestead. They were of course, beyond twenty-one.
         
         They all three took homesteads.
         
         They all three adjoined, they were right close together.
         
         Was this unusual for awoman to take ahomestead?
         
         No, Idon't think necessarily; they were entitled to it, so I
         don't know. But I don't think-there was one family there that
         we know the name of Hepler, that the man and both
         homesteaded. Iknow the others kind
         think it was right, but that's all I know about it. Course, I
         know the people; I remember the people, but that was before my
         time.
         
         KP:   Yeah.  Well, the whole thing is very interesting because of the im
         provements and things. Did your mother do her own work?
         
         AS:   Well, see, she done all of her own work, but she only taught for
         a little while and then after she married, why, the year after
         she was married she had her first daughter, well, then-her first
         child, she never taught after. And there wasn't such a thing as
         a doctor anywhere around there, there wasn't a doctor. And my
         mother had eight children; she never had a doctor for any of
         sent and got .... 'em. And my grandmother had A some sort of a book on child
         birth and she was what they called a midwife, and it was just
         what she read and my dad talked like that wasn't anything. Mo
         ther having those children, because her mother was a midwife.
         Well, I'd like to saw him have one or two of 'em.(Chuckles)
         
         KP:   You say your grandmother served as a midwife?
         
         AS:   And she'd ride a horse-people'they knew of her then and people
         would hear about her-and she had two older girls at home who
         could do the work at home and so they'd see 'em coming riding,
         they knew it was getting about that time and they'd go get her
         and she'd stay there and take care of the baby and do the work
         and cook for them. Of course, it's such a long way to go ahorse
         back. Up on Cedar Creek for miles around she'd stay and take
         care of women when they had their babies.
         
         KP:   Now, what was her name?
         
         AS:   Welker.
         
         KP:   She was-
         
         AS:   Yeah. That's the one my grandfather homesteaded. And of course,
         my father's name was Cylear. He lived up on Little Potlatch.
         There was aJess Oyiear that used to live near Moscow, he got
         the homeplace, but he was by the second wife. My grandfather
         had ten children by the first wife, and then she died and then
         he married awoman much, much younger than him and he was in his
         sixties and he raised-had four more children. He was busy! He
         was asoldier in the Civil War. Ihave apicture of him over
         here, him in his uniform. Then my father, he was never satis
         fied any one place and he always wanted to sell the ranch, sell
         the ranch though it was really hers and she put off and put off
         until she set aprice of $40 dollars, and that's where she made
         the mistake, as quick as she got forty dollars, she was awoman
         of her word and he sold it for that. And now, last year, I
         don't know, I've heard that they weren't so anxious to buy land
         right now as they were ayear ago, but if they'd awanted to
         sell that same land they'd agot $1100 an acre for it.
         Forty dollars! That doesn't sound like much.
         
         Course forty dollars them times wenf quite aways. But they
         have acredit, you know where stores would take credit for ayear.
         And my folks, they thought if they had about a$100 store bill
         and they thought they had an enormous store bill. Iabout spent
         that much yesterday going down trying to buy some birthday pre
         sents for the little girls and for my daughter.
         Of course, my mother, she died back in I91A-1914 she died
         at the age of fifty-seven, but my father died in 1951 and he was
         ninety-one years old when he died. But he didn't take things
         serious. He done more work with his mouth than he did with his other wise.
         That ain't going to sound very good to some of my-
         (Laughter) But it's the truth, I'm the only one that's speaking
         the truth.
         
         KP:   Yeah, you were telling me that before, about some of your times
         that you spoke up to your father. I wanted to ask you while we
         were speaking about the homestead and the Indians and things:
         do you remember Mox-Mox coming to dinner.
         
         AS:   Yeah, up on Little Potlatch Ridge. We were there one time at
         my aunt and uncles, they lived up there-had a homestead. My
         one uncle on my dad's side he homesteaded up on Fix Ridge or
         up on Little Potlatch,,and he come there and ate dinner with 'em.
         They were friendly, and he'd go there, but my sister she wouldn't
         take any of the butter after he had taken some because when he
         got ready to put some butter on something he'd took the knife
         and lick the sides of it and put it back in the butter and then
         Maude didn't want any more butter!(Chuckles)
         
         KP:   He served himself-
         
         AS:   Yeah, he wanted a clean knife.
         
         KP:   He cleaned all the butter off. Did you have dinner there when
         he was eating there?
         
         AS:   I suppose I did, but my sister's a year and a half older than
         I am,and I don't even remember it, but she remembered it, but
         I never did remember that part. I remember their house how it
         was and all of that. And they had taken a boy to—raise, they
         hadn't adopted him and we had to help him get in their wood. He
         was an ornery kid. And later, they couldn't keep him and they
         let him go back,and then he had to go to-back to the reform
         school. I think he is dead though now. They kept him there,
         but there was a big, high sidewalk where they had it built down
         where they had to go down steps to get down to where the wood
         was,, and he'd push us off of that big, high sidewalk. Well, I
         was only-well, I started school that fall, I was about six years
         oldjbut my sister was a year and a half older. We had to help
         but then we had to get shed off the sidewalk to get the wood.
         
         KP:   Did you have a lot of chores like that at home? Hauling wood or
         something like that?
         more
         
         AS:   No, I worked outside after I was married than I did- at home,
         well, I was married when I was seventeen, but I had worked out,
         I made a living after I was fourteen; I worked at housework.
         I went to Lewiston and worked.
         And that's all I knew, just to do housework, work for somebody.
         
         KP:   Did you live in the place where you worked?
         
         AS:   Yes, I had to live in. Of course, up here, they treat their hired
         help-I know we always did, anyway, keep 'em on the ranch and
         treat 'em the same as they did their family. But when you work
         in town some of those people serve their meals, and boy, you
         don't eat with 'em. You serve to them and then you eat in the
         kitchen. And they have a nice, big front room and so on, but you
         go on up to your own room after that. But later on my sister
         worked just across the street from where I worked and so we'd
         go to the show or something about twice a week* that's about all
         we could afford when we was aworkin'. Five dollars a week why,
         you did all of the housework, cooking and washing and ironing
         for five dollars, of course, five dollars went a lot further
         than it does now.
         
         KP:   But five dollars to do all the cooking and the housework.
         
         AS:   Do everything, and they didn't have electric washers than, when
         I was working. You had one- but I washed everything on the board
         but the flat pieces like the sheets and the tablecloths and the
         pillow slips, they sent to the laundry. And the other things I
         did.
         
         KP:   Did they treat you pretty good?
         
         AS:   He was a lot nicer than her, she was a person who was born poor
         herself and then she married a man who had a little bit. The
         lady where my sister worked she was more thoughtful. There is
         a lot of difference in women.
         
         KP:   Did you work just in the one place? in Lewiston.
         
         AS:   No, I worked other places and I worked up here in harvest, peo
         ple would have threshers and they used to thresh it all with a
         machine and well then, they had to have help. And I could hire
         out for that.
         
         KP:   What did you do for the threshers?
         
         AS:   Oh, cook and peel potatoes and so forth. Oh, I was only seven
         teen when I married, but mother was sick and we had to learn
         how to cook and do things-do housework early. She was sick for
         a number of years with Bright's Disease of the kidneys. She
         never doctored and she never complained and my dad had went out
         over by Moscow to harvest, he run a threshing machine there
         for thp threshing part of it, threshing tender of the machine
         that threshes the grain and when he come home why she'd changed
         so much he took her right away to the doctor, but it was too
         late, she only lived about a month after that.
         
         KP:   Was there a doctor here?
         
         AS:   There were doctors here but then she just never complained and
         so- She'd have spells when she'd be working in the garden and
         she'd get so dizzy and pass out in the garden and still she'd
         say, "That was just a bilious spell," was what she called it
         and she would never want to go to a doctor. So, I can't really
         hardly ever remember her ever having a doctor.
         
         KP:   She didn't have it for her babies.
         
         AS:   With none of her babies. I laughed so at my dad one time, he
         always was telling how much grit he had4and I knew he didn't
         have too much. So, one time he was atellin' me that-about a
         Dr. Moser that pulled teeth, how he pulled his tooth and he said
         how great he was nobody else but Old John Oylear, he always cal
         led himself Old John, could astood that. And so when I was about
         thirteen I had to have a tooth pulled and I went in there
         and Dr. Moser told me an altogether different story!(Laughter)
         Said he never heard so much cussin' in his life!
         
         KP:   You were also talking last time about going to school and how
         many schools you went to.
         
         AS:   I started in Moscow and I left there-I was in the fourth grade
         when we moved away, I was ten years old and I was in the fourth
         grade. Well, he didn't wait til the school was out, they moved
         back over to Leland, that's where we started out on the farm in
         the first place and they moved over there. And every time he
         moved he just made the wrong move* it cost him a little bit to
         move and so we got over there and finished up there. And that
         fall we started in Leland and then a little later why, we moved
         to Southwick and went there. Well, then the next year we moved
         to Kendrick. Moved us back down to Kendrick and we started there,
         and before school was out in the spring, well, we got back up on
         Cedar Creek. Well, my sister had taken her eighth grade exams
         I was in the seventh grade and she was through with that. But
         I went on up there to an accredited school. But that year, there
         was just a little bit of school left, so I didn't go any more.
         But I started in,and Ihad my report card and they let me go ahead
         as far as that goes, but I had to stay til my term was out. So,
         I started there, and Iwent that winter and in the spring before
         the school was out we was back in Leland, and that's where I
         finished up, I took my eighth grade examinations^and that is
         where I ended up. And of course, that's as far as I ever got in
         school.
         
         Was there a big difference between the city school, like Moscow
         and-
         
         Yes. Course, up at Moscow we not only had to write our spelling
         words down, we had to put the marks like it was in the diction
         ary or in your spelling book. And you'd get your written exam
         inations, you had to know how to mark those so you'd know how to
         pronounce them. And then, of course, after Igot back over this
         way in the fifth grade again, why, I never done-that} I just
         learned to spell 'em, that was all.
         
         Did the teacher -or the class was smaller?
         
         Well, they just have one grade and those up at Leland and the sane
         at Southwick, they had more than one grade and some of
         those schools, the country schools, they had all eight grades
         with all of the subjects to teach. Well, they couldn't do jus
         tice to all the kids and teach that many. But these little coun
         try schools they kind of dwindled down, people got so that- the
         old folks got through having all those children, they didn't have
         so many any more. When my son started to school there was a
         teacher there teaching all eight grades, had forty-two or fortythree
         children that she had to teach and had all those grades.
         Well, when the girls went they were eight years younger, well
         there were seventeen, they had dwindled down that much in the
         time when the twins started. He started to high school the year
         they started to grade school.
         
         Yes, I guess that would be right, eight years.
         
         Didn't happen with the next time I had children. I had one-
         I had one girl and in about five minutes another girl!
         Was that a surprise? Did you know you were going to have twins?
         No, I didn't know it, because I went down-in the fall when I felt
         sick, I went down to the doctor and he thought that's what it
         was but I never did go back. Later on I knew good and well it
         was but you didn't go and get checkups all time; at least I
         didn't. And on a Friday I didn't feel good, and I sent and got
         Fred's sister. She rode horseback up to be with me and he was
         way off there in the canyon somewhere cutting wood. Willard,
         he hadn't even started to school til that next fall- oh, yeah,
         he had, too, he had started to school, but he wouldn't a been in
         school that day, Saturday he was home. But I couldn't a sent hin
         back there anyway, because he wouldn't have known where to find his
         dad. So, he come home that night, well, he thought I had three
         weeks that I should go yet, and he said, he bawled me out for
         sending for his sister, but she said if you want me again, Ada,
         you phone don't pay any attention to Fred. So, I went on, I
         was home all day alone Saturday and Sunday I got up and I got his
         breakfast, and we had another barn where we had stock down there
         down the lane from our place there, there was a big barn down
         there, he had his stock. And I was getting pretty sick and when
         he come in the house he helped me fix the bed, and he started
         phoning to get some help. Now, boy, he was agettin' excited!
         And first thing he knew he had two babies on his hands and he
         didn't know what in the world to do with 'em! And Mrs. Stoneburger
         was the lady that came later they picked her up, and
         when the doctor came all he done was come in and look 'em over
         and everything was alright and he could go back to town. The
         mud was so thick and so deep and we had such terrible roads
         that they had to just come to this little town three miles from
         our place with a car and then they had to take the rig on from
         there and his brother brought the doctor on in, but we didn't
         need him and Fred's brother-in-law got Mrs. Stoneburger and she
         came up. Well, she had the babies all dressed an everything
         was over time he got there. He just as well stayed in town.
         So, your husband is the one that-
         
         What?
         
         Delivered your twins' then.
         
         Well, he didn't have much to do about it.
         
         KP:   Well, he caught 'em! (Laughter)
         
         AS:   He just asked me where this was at and that was at, that was all.
         But he was really excited.
         
         KP:   Well, how about you?
         
         AS:   Didn't bother me. I never been sick-I never worry about myself.
         It's the other members of the family. I think I'm tough, I'll
         come someday. My son-funny he likes to tease me, Fred did
         too. But anything that makes me mad they just keep saying that
         So, he got to teasing me after his dad died about u$r boyfriend
         I was at Lewiston; so here a while back why,Amy daughter was sick and I was down
         there sending the kids to school and taking care of them and he
         says,"There's about three of those old guys that you chase around
         with there in Juliaetta settin' out on your porch there, om the
         porch when I came down." "Well," I says, "you look again when
         you go back and tell 'em if they're still there to stick around,
         I'll be back!" (Laughter) So, if he wanted to play the game
         I'd play it with him.
         
         KP:   Then you were saying your dad used to tease you too about mar
         rying a German?
         
         AS:   German, yeah. Oh, he'd get a little bit perturbed at me because
         I talked back to him. Maude wouldn't talk back to him, so him
         and her'd get along fine, but if I didn't like something I let
         him know it. They usually know what I think. Then he said some
         thing about- he liked Fred, that was my husband, he liked him
         alright and he thought the world of his Dad, he was a German
         all right. And my sister went with a fullblooded German the same
         as I did and she married one, later on, course I was married a
         quite a bit before she was and I said, "What's the difference?"
         
         KP:   Was there a lot of rivalry between the German people?
         
         AS:   0n there was later years, I don't at first that there was. When
         they came here, well, even when Fred and I were married and I
         there at Cameron
         started going to the church that he went to that Lutheran church,
         they stuck pretty much to the German then, but you don't see
         that any more, they have married in. At first those older ones
         didn't want to marry anyone but a German and they didn't want
         'em to talk anything but German around home. Some of those old
         folks that had been here for years never did learn to speak En
         glish. And that's a whole lot stubbornness, nothing else. But
         they are an awful stubborn breed of people as I'm concerned, I
         lived with one for forty*-four years !(Chuckles )
         
         KP:   Yes, you're an expert then.
         
         AS:  n Yeah, they are- you're not going to tell 'em anything. But they
         over in Germany they don't have the resources they have here and
         they have to do a lot of saving and they came here-these other
         people had come and homesteaded, well, they eventually got tired
         of it and they'd sell out to the Germans^ and the Germans they
         built it all up and built nice homes and stuff. They come back
         and look at it after they sold it and saw how it turned out and
         they didn't like it. But it was their own fault. They could a
         done the same thing but they just wasn't as industrious.
         
         KP:   The German people around here were especially industrious.
         
         AS:   Yeah, they are. And you notice up around Troy, too; most all
         those people are Swedes and Norwegians, they're pretty well fixed.
         They just don't have as much as they had here, they can't afford
         to waste it back there- But my husband, he used the word, hurry
         more than any other word in the dictionary, he never told you to
         do anything but what he didn't feed you that hurry That's just
         the way his folks lived  just run, they'd just go as hard as they
         could. And he expected everyone else to keep up with him.
         Keep up with him, if they could.
         
         Let's see, I had something else I wanted to ask you about. We
         picked up some stories about a doctor in Kendrick^and I don't
         remember his name. He was supposed to have been a real character.
         It wouldn't have been Dr. Kelly?
         
         Dr. Kelly?
         
         Dr. Rothwell any of those?
         
         Anyway, I wondered if you remember any doctor?
         
         I remember the ones back as far as a Dr. Stoneburner that was up
         at Leland. That was a little town there two miles from where
         our homestead was. And I don't know just what-if I knew just
         what he might have done.
         
         Well, there was a doctor who was supposed to have a special cure
         where people would come all over to him.
         
         Must have been a witch doctor!(Chuckles) No, I've never heard of
         him.
         
         
         I don't know his name, right now? I can't think of it.
         I don't know-I may have heard of him, but I don't know what in
         the heck what he would have that would cure-
         Well, I don't know .he was genuine anyway.
         I never heard of that. All I know is that ^nas heard
         thing and if you tell her, why, she'll tell you. She does, she
         every!
         studies history and she does a lot of reading and she's got his-
         Marcia
         tory books. When is there, she always is there to take out
         books and she likes to read. But she tells stuff that Ihappen
         to know different. Of course, there isn't anything to that but
         I said','I've never been on that
         has told me
         she , that- ?
         
         my place many a time when we lived there." I've never been on
         that place yet to this day. I've been by it since that time but
         I've never been on that place, never stepped foot on that place.
         The Hill place is the name of it. But I've never been on that
         If she tells you somethingplace.
         
         AThere's two of 'em here, one's an old maid and she's
         a widow and they say something and they get into the darnedest
         arguments and I just shut up because there's no use talking be
         cause youre not going to convince her---
         
         You don't want to take a side.
         
         And sometimes this tell you something,before she gets
         through —boy, don't say that to her! (Laughter) She makes her
         self out a liar, she contradicts herself.
         You were talking about your dad, after your mother died how he
         went out - and how Ere didn't approve.
         No, he didn't and he'd get so mad, he'd try to go with -women,
         there was a widow up there had a little child and she was pro
         bably in her upper twenties, somewhere along in there and he had
         kids as old as she was and he wanted to go with her and she chose
         younger fellows, and he just hated those younger guys.
         He wanted to court her?
         What?
         
         KP:   He wanted to court her.
         
         AS:   Oh, yes. He did remarry, later on, after Mother died. And the
         first he told us, when mother was alive how no-good she was, how
         wild she was and everything and after he married her, he tried to
         tell us how good she was, but Leslie talked up to him, but I
         didn't; he was married to her and I just let him do his talking
         but he didn't change my opinion any. But then anyway he didn't
         have to know it. But I took care of him until months before
         he died, and then I just couldn't have him any more-got so nervous
         I just-and we took him and put him in the home and he done such
         terrible things, that's why I had to take him away. And they
         was going to send him up to Orofino-well, he was ninety-one then
         you have to give him a sanity hearing first. It was right around
         the first of the year and it was a holiday and I knew good
         and well there wasn't much you could do til after New Years.
         And so on the third of January, Fred and I, my husband I went
         up and saw Alma Betts up at Southwick and I told her just whatthe
         dirty stuff he had done and so on and I just got to the point
         I couldn't take it any more. And so she said she'd try and so
         we paid her then-he never had anything when he died. He had a
         little bit from the welfare and he took that and then we had to
         make up money to keep him there, as far as that goes? it was
         well worth it because I couldn't do it any more. But my brother
         and a sister up at Kellogg, why, we chipped in, but I got one in
         Lewiston and she could have chipped-just she and her left any more
         but she is one of those that she likes to be on the end where you
         take but not to put anything out. So, she's in a nursing home
         it'll be two years, now, down in Lewiston. And, of course, this spring I was sick
         and I just kept a getting worse; and I could just feel it pass
         off, and I fooled along until I pretty near let it go too long.
         I had gallstones, and I never had those awful pains, you know,
         like you get, but I'd get real pale and I'd pretty near pass out.
         And I would get dizzy, and I'd get my car started and go to start
         somewhere and I'd get dizzy, and I'd just put my car back in the
         shed. So finally, the kids got hardboiled with me and said I
         had to go. Well, I was getting where I couldn't take it much
         longer anywayJ* so I got down there and of course they had to x-ray
         and stayed at my daughters. Come to find out I had gallstones.
         I had to have surgery, but they had to get me readyJ if it'd a
         been two more days that thing would a bursted in me. I didn't
         have just a lot of 'em like some of 'em do, but I had one great,
         big one and then some sand in there; but this one was enormous.
         I have to diet all time now, that is watch-I don't have enough
         sugar in my blood, I guess it is, the sugar count is low, but I
         can' have anything with sugar in it because it builds up an in
         sulin, and the insulin is worse and so I use Sucaril and keep
         healthy and happy.
         
         KP:   Isn't it marvelous what they do these days? Where they didn't
         in the old days.
         
         AS:   Like when my mother died, why, I don't know, now, I think there
         is a cure for Bright's Disease- there wasn't at that time. But
         my grandfather died of that, too, and I had a cousin that was twenty of Bright's Disease.
         It must be
         
         KP:   Hereditary thing.
         
         AS:   Uh-huh, I think so. Another thing, we was awful doggone big ea
         ters. We liked to eat. That probably had something to do with
         it.
         
         KP:   You were telling me another thing that I hadn't heard before and
         that was about running underneath the sidewalks in Moscow.
         
         AS:   Oh, that was in Moscow, yes.
         
         KP:   I was trying to picture that. How would they build a sidewalk
         that way?
         
         AS:   A wooden sidewalk. A wooden sidewalk and it was up quite a little
         ways. I would run and hide under there and Dad would get mad at
         me when he come home and he worked down to the store. There's a
         
         END SIDE 1
         
         David's store there yet. Used to be David Ely's.
         
         KP:   She was telling me that she thought they told so much
         
         AS:   That's the way I was with my dadi and then later on after he was
         gone he knew who homesteaded this place and that and then Ivy
         at Cameron Newman wrote a book on the Ridge here and she'd call me for some stuff,
         and I wished I'd a paid more attention to him or jotted it down
         and when I tried to inquire of him later his mind had got bad,
         and he couldn't tell me by that time. And I'd start to reading
         the paper he'd start to talk,,so I'd get up and move in the kitdavenport,
         chen and when he'd go to sleep on the . I d go back in the
         dining room in the other room where the heater was and read the
         paper.(Laughter)
         
         KP:   Missed out on a lot of it?
         
         AS:   Yeah, missed out on a lot of it. But, oh, he was a tellin'-
         he liked to brag. Boy, when he told one of his kids that they
         was going to get a whipping, they got it and they was just no need
         of them running, they just as well come and get it-take it- be
         cause they was going to get it. And I let him tell these old
         stories and when he got through I says, "Do you remember that
         sidewalk in front of our place?" "Yes, yes, sure I remember that."
         I said, "That saved me from many a whipping." Of course, if he'd
         a got up and got after me, he could a got me out from under there
         all right. But I knew he had to be back to work at one o'clock,
         and I could stay there as long as I knew he went back to work.
         And we had a hayloft there in the barn there behind the house.
         At that time you were allowed horse I'd go up
         there and hide in the hayloft, too.
         
         Did you get in trouble a lot?
         
         Oh, heck-
         
         Sounds like it.
         
         Yeah, I was, I was an angel! I just always said what I wanted, and it
         wasn't always what he wanted to hear.
         
         That was usually the reason you got in trouble, though.
         
         Yes, 'cause I was gonna- and another thing, he was partial, very
         partial to my sister older than me, too; she was a year and a half
         older and she was-just couldn't do anything wrong. Maude- he'd
         brag on Maude. So Maude and Iused to fight quite abit, coursej
         why if I'd touch Maude, I get into it, so if I wanted to touch
         her I'd better do it after he went back to work, or drag her un
         der the sidewalk with me!(Laughter)
         
         Was it usual though for fathers to whip their daughters?
         No, my mother did-I know I didn't get very many.
         
         You ran a lot, though.
         
         AS:   Oh, when I was a kid I could run like a deer; course now, I
         can't even get in a good walk! But I was sure glad that I was
         fleet footed at that time.
         
         KP:   How many kids were there?
         
         AS:   There were eight, but they had three that died before I was born.
         Three boys that I never did see. One that died-they just diagnosed
         their own illness, there was no doctor they wouldn't have a way
         to know. The oldest one-the second boy-the oldest boy, he was
         the second child, they felt he died of typhoid fever, which there
         used to be lots of typhoid fever, but now you hardly ever hear of
         that any more. It was unsanitary conditions and the water supply
         and all that. And then, of course, they had the outside houses
         and flies and all that sort of stuff. There used to be a lot of
         typhoid fever. I know I had a sister that had it, the one that's
         in the nursing home; she had it when she was seventeen, typhoid
         fever and they used to have it-I had an uncle that died of it,
         too. He was in his thirties, close to forty.
         
         KP:   My goodness, there must have been an awful lot of that going on.
         
         AS:   And then nad that one-this one boy died of typhoid fever,
         that's what they called it. And the next one, why he had an in
         flamed face. When he was born-- have you heard of erysipelaswhere
         it all breaks out and swells up, the skin?
         
         KP:   Oh, yes.
         
         AS:   He was born that way. Well, my mother had had that. I saw her
         with that. She didn't dare get around fresh paint. She had to
         get out when they painted, why, she had to get out.
         
         KP:   It's like an allergic reaction.
         
         AS:   Uh-huh. And my father's one brother got killed in a hunting ac
         cident and of course^she got real upset over that, and when the
         baby was born, she blamed it to that, but no one knows that was
         it. He was born that way, and I think he lived three weeks and
         he died. And the other baby was a year and a half old, just ol
         der than my sister—that is just a year and a half older than I
         am. And he had croup and my mother was sick-grandmother was there
         but he choked to death in his sleep. So there-right now there's
         three of us alive, three girls and my folks had four boys and
         four girls and they only raised one boy to be grown.
         for those days,,
         
         KP:   This was quite common though, wasn't it?
         
         AS:   What?
         
         KP:   This was quite common, that little children-
         
         AS:   But my brother lived to be, what was it? Seventy-nine, I be
         lieve he was seventy-nine. And he died in his sleep. He had
         a heart attack, I suppose. I don't know, he wasn't well anyway.
         His wife died, too, several years before that; she died of a
         kind of a heart-she had a bad heart. She was dead before they
         ever could get her to the hospital. My older sister died of TB.
         At that time when she had it, they didn't have any cure for TB.
         But she taught school, and she'd get out and walk and ride a
         horseback maybe four or five miles to school in the morning and
         ride home at night in all kinds of weather^and possibly it was
         that that caused that. She and her husband both died of thatof
         TB three or four months apart. She died in October, and he
         died the following March. They left two little girlsp and then
         of course my mother took care of them as long as she lived and
         thn any sister and I, that was just older than me, we had to take
         care of those little girls after that. And I worked out a while
         to get some extra money to buy some clothes for myself and then
         I'd go home and Maude'd go and work out; so that she could getone
         of us stayed home.
         
         And then you took care of the two little girls?
         
         Uh-huh. But they're both dead now, the two girls; one died of
         cancer?and the other one died in her sleep with a bad heart,
         both those girls. One of them was five years younger than Iam,
         and the other one was seven years younger.
         
         You were a mother by the time you were thirteen then?
         
         Yeah, I was taking care of 'em. But my older sister, shewhen
         Ma died she took care of us all the time and bathed us and
         changed our pants-she had two of and she didn't have 'em broke
         til they was a year and a half. I don't know, I didn't have
         much luck with kids fully broke til they was two years old.
         
         KP:   Well-
         
         AS:   Just depends on how much time you spend on 'em.
         
         KP:   Yeah.
         
         AS:   But you gotta be there with-
         
         Yeah, there's a great deal of Mama training that goes on. I
         had pretty good luck with mine,' I don't know why. "
         Yeah,and some of 'em say girls are easier to train than boys,
         but I don't if that's so or not.
         Both of mine are girls. I think my oldest one was born with an
         extra special bladder^ because she didn't wet a diaper from four"
         months on. She'd sleep all through the night dry. I could get
         get her up in the morning at four months old^and she'd be dry.
         The second one I wasn't that lucky. I was still wondering about
         that you know,living out on a farm and things where you have
         just outdoor plumbing; how did you?
         Well, we had a slop jar, slop jars and pots.
         Oh, that's right. Poor little kids'd fall in out there!
         The toilet?
         No, the pot.
         
         Well, you could get those little potty chairs, too. I took care
         of that oldest granddaughter of mine, her dad was in the service
         and her mother was working somewhere, and she didn't like to be
         tied down with kids, and she don't yet, she's forty now,and she
         wouldn't want to be tied down with kids/yet. So Grandma was tied
         down. And sometimes I wonder, I still babysit, and I wonder if
         I'm ever going to get the the place-(Laughter)
         Well, you missed your chance. You started young and it's sticking
         with you.
         
         It's sure stuck with me alright. When my one sister, she didn't
         have children-her husband, the one she married later-got hurt
         badly in World War I, and they didn't marry; they were engaged.
         They started going together she was sixteen and he was nineteen,
         he was three years older'n her. And when they got married she
         was thirty-nine years old, and he was three years older, that's
         when they got married. She calls it twenty years, but, by golly,
         it was twenty-three years they went together before they ever
         were married.—I^m-not^that patient! (Chuckles )
         You were married at seventeen, weren't you? Now, that's kind of
         early, isn't it?
         
         AS:   It is.
         
         KP:   For the normal then?
         
         Yes, just got tired of herding little kids and working out, I
         guess, so I got married.
         
         Then you had your own work.
         
         Yes and Iwas married thirteen months, and then Ihad a child of
         my own. Then, of course, went for almost eight years then I
         had the two. So then, I decided I'd done something wrong, and
         I'd better quit.
         
         Next time you'd have three.
         
         Fred used to laugh and say,if you wait the first, if you'd wait
         sixteen years, you'd have four. I told him Iwas through.
         I didn't realize that he had delivered the twins. You said
         you had your babies at home, but Ifigured there was amidwife.
         Ihad all of 'em at home, as far as that goes, but my sister-inlaw
         came, and Ihad adoctor, at least the doctor got there be
         fore the boy was born. But I never had much trouble, and I
         could a had him just as easily, too. I was built differently
         too; oh, it makes a lot of difference how you're built. Now,
         you take this oldest girl here, my great granddaughter; my grand
         daughter, oldest granddaughter has narrow pelvis or something
         and that child-it's on her arm and shoulder that she laid so up
         against the bone somewhere that she carried abirthmark-she
         couldn't have large children. One of 'em ixid-what was itfour
         pounds and eight ounces and the second one was-weighed four
         pounds and two ounces. They were just small babies. But I
         never had a child over six pounds; the boy was bigger and the
         twins, one of them weighed four and the other weighed five. I
         figure have 'em little and they can grow! They thought I had a third
         one in there, but it was blood clots. It proved to be blood
         clots, because it caused too much swelling and everything.
         What did you do, you know, like now they have to take so many
         vitamins, and you have to do this and have to do that while you're
         pregnant. Were there any special rules then?
         
         Oh, no, I just milked the cows the night before the kids were
         born and turned the cream separator and pumped water* I was a
         doing chores right up til the time they was born only that mor
         ning when I got sick before he got back. I didn't milk the cows
         that morning or for a few mornings afterwards.But I done chores
         right up to the day they was born, but I don't think the average
         does that, but if you marry a Dutchman you might have to!
         That's the way it goes. Now, that's funny, because there's the
         old wives stories about you don't hang clothes on the line-
         Oh, I hung clothes on the line we didn't have electrcity then.
         I packed a lot of water from the well when the cistern d go dry,
         to do the washing and get up early in the morning and I'd hang
         the clothes out there before the twins was born,and I fell down
         and I looked just like a - (Laughter)
         
         Just rolled around. I was younger than I am now, sprier. I was
         twenty-six when the twins was born. Eighteen when the boy was
         born.
         
         Well, you don't remember anything like that, like^your-neighbors
         telling you not to do something.
         
         I didn't pay any attention. According to the husband-
         And he didn't have any of those tales-
         Annie, his sister, came over, and of course she knew how Fred was
         and he'd make me do chores, she started in abawling him out, and
         now, by gosh, I had to stay in, not send her out doing the chores
         right away. And Fred got madder'n heck-(Laughter) But I think
         Fred's mother done that way. I don't know if she had doctors or
         not; I really don't know about that. But there were doctors here
         then. Dr. Stoneburner was here when I was born, but he was some
         where else at the time-and they didn't have phones-a few people 
         did later on, when I was. I can remember a few people had
         phones-but we never, my mother never lived in a house that had a
         phone in it. When my folks came up here on this ridge, up here
         they didn't have any mail and they-of course, everybody, the
         neighbors all helped one another. And they had to go to Genes
         on horseback to get the mail. Somebody*d go about once a week
         and they'd bring everybody's mail along that was over here that
         they knew. And that was understood, that they had to in order
         to get by that they had to help one another.
         
         Yeah, that's interesting. How long did it take to ride to Gene-
         Oh, it depends on how fast a horse you had! Quite a little while
         more than twelve miles
         because- youid have to-- from here. The closest way to Genesee is over this Fix Ridge
         up here by the schoolnear
         Juliaetta. house And I don't know, it's quite a little ways up there to
         Genesee, I wouldn't know how many miles it is. I don't go that
         often. My granddaughter, this oldest one, one time she and I
         went to Moscow and we started down to come back home-we got
         there just fine,and they'd changed the road up around at Gene
         see somewhere and the road I intended to take I missed, so any
         way we found another one and I says, "Well this will take us
         down there." And I knew the houses and all that, but they'd
         changed the road and put around behind where it was in front
         of those people and back there we were off of the main road.
         Well, then I got where I didn't know things and by gosh we were
         lost-we got lost there. So there was a guy that used to live
         at Juliaetta down and works up there for a farmer. So, he come along
         with a pickup and he said, "I'll get you out on that main road,
         get you back on the road then I know you can find your way home."
         Which we did. So when we started out then, this granddaughter
         started teasing me, said, "You told out.your folks fioming in
         a covered wagon, clear from back East. How did they make it?
         you can't find from Moscow back to Juliaetta." (Chuckles)
         
         Well, there was probably only one road then.
         by Danvers
         
         Well, the way we went, we went up over- up at the top of the
         grade, you go past the schoolhouse here and that way. We went
         that way-we come back that way, too, after we got on the right
         road up at Genessee. But that's where we got lost.
         Do you remember the train coming through?
         Oh, yes.
         Coming into town?
         Oh, when it first came in?
         Yesr.
         Oh, no, that was way back in 1890*? but I wasn't born until 1901.
         1897 or somewhere along in there. I really have forgot, I read
         it, but I forgot. But I know my folks, there wasn't any train
         when they came.
         Did it make a difference in their lives?
         I imagine it must have. And Scotty Wilson, he was an old-timer
         he came here from Scotland and he came-that's how he happened
         to get here, he came, I think he landed in Canada and when they
         started building the railroad down here he come here and got to
         work and was working and he met a woman here-she was from Scotland
         too, but they didn't know each other back there-and her name was
         Burns and they met and got married and had, oh, about ten or ele
         ven kids. They used to have big families.
         
         Is that the fellow you were telling homesteaded up on the- he
         took a homestead way up high where he couldn't raise any crops?
         Scotty Wilson?
         
         Yeah.
         
         I suppose so, we bought that place,and it was just more or less
         rocks, I don't know why he ever homesteaded there. And Fred,
         he wanted to sell out; and Fred, my husband, bought the place
         before he died. I sold it now, but I used to own it^and I sold
         it to my son,because I don't have cattle any more, I have—it's
         more pasture land and I don't have any use for that. But
         he couldn't make a living for that familyJ he had to work out
         and she was a big, heavy woman,and she had to get out and run
         those cows down, too when he was gone and take care of her kids.
         She never had a very good life, I know that. I guess they had
         hardships; they were bound to. I read a book the other day
         up here at the library when Marcia was in here-I only take one
         at a time, I don't want to get a whole lot and some of them have
         their arms full? I don,t read that much* I like the television
         some; I have programs that I like, but I got interested in that
         book and it was real good. Well, I read at night, after I watch
         a few programs then I go to bed and if I don't sleep, I read in
         bed. My sister didn't have anything else to read, so I read
         it twice from last Tuesday.
         
         And you've got another week yet to go.
         
         Yeah, and I haven't memorized it yet. Memorizing is getting where
         it isn't so easy done any more.
         
         You had to do that a lot in school, didn't you?
         
         Oh, yes you had to memorize a lot.
         
         Do you remember They don't do that any more, in school.
         I used to tell little stories and poems and things to my kids
         that I learned when I was just a kid and all those little nur
         sery rhymes-I used to know all of them. Because I read them
         for myself, and I got so I could read and then when I had some
         neices and they were little, I'd read 'em for them. Maude, my
         sister, she was usually busy playing with her dolls. On rainy
         days on Saturdays and Sundays, we didn't go very much and Mother
         wasn't very well, why, we'd play school, the two little ones. And the lit
         tle one-one of the nieces, why, she wasn't much interested,
         she didn't learn so much, but the oldest one, she liked it and
         we'd play school, and that kid could read and write and do every
         thing before she started to school. And she just went through
         school just that way, she just liked to- tudy and she was an
         A student all through school. And she took high school in three
         year, which I don't think they allow that any more. She was
         in high school three years.
         
         You started her right then.
         
         Her mother was always a good student, too. I don't know about
         Glen, my brother-in-law, I don't remember him, but my brother,
         married - my brother-in-law's sister-married a brother and sis
         ter. And my sister-in-law was rea/good in school. And when she
         got out of school and moved to Lewiston, she'd went, I think,
         as far as the ninth grade up at Leland, and she got down there
         and she went to night school. And she always read something that
         would educate her, not like a lot of silliness, something that
         she could get better educated. And she was well read. But she
         was a marvelous cook; I never saw anyone that could cook any bet
         ter than she could. If it ruffled her, you never knew it,if it
         bothered her. Then I have a sister, the one that's in the nur
         sing home now, she was just the other way, and Maude's the same
         way, she gets all excited if someone would come in, just one per
         son come in at mealtime, it would throw her clear off. And
         they'd get nervous.
         
         Well, how about you?
         
         I would be that way now, but not before. Our there on the
         ranch, it was a free boardinghouse! My sister that lives
         in Lewiston, it'd upset her if we went in, but they'd come
         there,and if they got any company she didn't like to cook and
         they were stingier'n heck, well, they was poor, too. They
         figured it wasn' nothing for me because I had that garden, but
         she didn't know how I worked to get that garden. And they could
         eat cheaper if it didn't take as much in gas to get 'em up there
         why, that's where they come. And you could just rest assured
         that the day before the Fourth of July, see, that's when we'd be
         cultivating beans or putting up hay, one of the two^and I'd have
         a crew. They'd come in, I guess, right around noon on Saturday
         the day before the Fourth. And she wouldn't be ready; she'd
         have a bunch of ironing; she didn't like to iron, and end up by
         gosh, the kids a be a tracking in through the door a slammin*
         and she'd drag out the sewing machine. I done the cooking and
         then I have to do the dishes then I'd have-if she hadn't got around
         to press her husband's suit, her boy's suit wasn't pres
         sed and I was a doin' that and I had my kids all lined out a
         month before the Fourth. I knew if I didn't get ready I wouldn't
         make it.
         
         Was this celebration on the Fourth?
         
         Yes, they used to have great, big celebrations on the Fourth
         in every town, but now they don't do it any more. If it wasn't
         at Cavendish, it would be at Leland or it'd be here at Kendrick.
         I've been here at Juliaetta here to a good many celebrations.
         But they don't have 'em any more.
         Everybody get all dressed up.
         
         Yeah. Now, why, everybody does his thing, goes camping or goes
         fishing or does something. And I've got so I'm glad of it.
         You must have had an awful lot of work to getting all the
         kids ready and everything.
         I don't know how I done it. I always managed to get through
         one way or the other.
         
         I was thinking about when you were being a cook for the threshing
         crew.
         
         Well, I didn't go out and hire out for that, that was just a—they'd go
         from place to place you'd do it in your own home. When you get through with
         the meals that they eat while they was threshing your crop,
         that was it. They just thresh our crop and you had to-years
         ago when my folks threshed, why, they had cookhouses then. I
         ember the cookhouses, but they never had 'em after I wasthey
         was just on the ranch when we lived there; there was a cook
         house there. And my oldest sister, the one that's in the nursing
         home now, she helped my aunt, my aunt used to go out and cook in
         the cookhouse, hire out for that.
         But now like when they came to thresh; how much warning did you
         have? Did you know they were coming, or did they just show up
         in time to eat?
         
         Well, there's been a time or two they come that way, but usually
         I knew ahead of time and I went to town-then we didn't have re
         frigeration, we didn't have electricity, I didn't even have an
         icebox, then we'd have to have our meat sent up here with a
         stage that come up, and I'd call my meat order in or someone
         went to town and buy fresh meat. But now, that's something dif
         ferent, they have freezers and they have electricity -
         That's what I was wondering-how many men did you feed?
         Well, at one time I was cooking for forty-seven, I think, it
         threshing 
         was a big crew. It was just a big machine and then the
         separator tender had died, and the guy that come, why he-the guy
         that come he never had tended separator before, and he had a lit
         tle bit of trouble, smashed things up and I had 'em eight days
         that time.
         
         Oh!!
         
         But the worst of it was, see we had the big ranges, but they
         weren't to cook for that many,' your stove wasn't big enough.
         But you could cook-I baked twenty loaves of bread aday. Ten
         in the morning and ten in the afternoon. And I started out one
         meal- I made pies and I had to have so much room in the oven
         that I couldn't do it. I could get the cakes out some way, be
         cause they didn't take so long. Ihad to have twelve pies and
         did't have time to get the meat in and the bread and all that
         stuff. I'd get up at three in the morning and I'd be still
         going at ten or ten-thirty at night. Iwas glad when they was
         gone. Iwas young then and strong but Icouldn't take it now,
         Ijust couldn't do it. Well, if you had abig enough stoveif
         the stoves were larger, but you didn't have room for that
         much stove in your kitchen. You take these stoves now, the ele
         ctric stoves don't have as large aovens as the old ranges had.
         No, they don't. You had to bake the bread. What did you serve
         them for breakfast, hotcakes?
         
         No, I only tried that about once or twice; that's too much,
         we'd fry potatoes, and we'd have meat and eggs and acooked cereal
         That was easier than making pancakes?
         
         Oh, yes, because pancakes-you can't hardly flop 'em over fast
         enough to keep 'em going. Iset fourteen at atime, so they
         could set and at the last Ihad twenty some-I had abig dining
         room there at that place.and Irun two tables. But at the last
         why, I just had that one big, long table that seated fourteen.
         They just had to take turns.
         
         They left the table and then we'd have to get those dishes off
         and out of the way, then set some more on there. But I only
         tried that once-hotcakes for breakfast, that was too darn much
         work for that many men.
         
         And then there was lunch. Did you just make sandwiches or-
         Sandwiches and cookies, sometimes cake. We had to take it-I
         had to take the men coffee, Ihad to take that to the field
         at nine o'clock in the morning and then in the afternoon at
         four o'clock for lunchtime. Then all the cups had to be washed
         when I come back.
         Two lunches?
         One in the morning and one in the afternoon.
         Then they had a big dinner or a little dinner at noon?
         Big dinner.
         And that's when you tried to get all the pies in the oven.
         But then-
         Did you do this all by yourself?
         
         Oh, no, Ihad two helpers. Ihad aniece, my oldest niece,
         and I had another girl. Of course, Willard was a baby then.
         And you had all your own housework.
         We didn't do aheck of a lot.but make our beds; they didn't
         need making too often, we didn't sleep in 'em long!(Laughter)
         You didn't do much rolling around.
         And did they eat abig supper at night or just a little one?
         Yes. I had a crew of thirteen one time in the beans, and those
         thirteen ate as darned much food-they just happened to be a
         bunch where they all were hearty eaters, and then they get to running-
         up there, they got where the guys would see who could eat
         the most pie. And, by God, they carried it too far, and we allall
         those women around in there, we all went together, we put
         a stop to that. Heck any of the family didn't get these pies;
         they'd eat right down to the last one. We'd put it on apie
         plate, and give each a piece of pie.
         
         Was this taken out of their pay?
         
         Oh, no, huh-uh, the farmer fed the crew. They was boarded.
         Then you had to find a place for 'em to sleep?
         They had to bring their beds. They'd take hay or straw or some
         thing and fix it. I've had hay hands where they didn't have
         their beds, and I had to fix beds for them, but not the threshers
         they bring their own beds. Just abedroll. Idon't think they'd
         invented these here sleeping bags at that time.
         Oh, no doubt, abed roll worked just about as good. That's
         so much work.
         
         I wouldn't want to try it now, but it was all in a day's work
         then. I wouldn't want to try it now.
         — and then the next year was a wet year, too. We saved some
         but we lost a lot, too. Then later on they had another wet
         year,bad year, but we didn't happen to have any beans in that
         year. And we had quit by that time, we had quit raising beans.
         But there's no letup to it, from the time you start out in the
         spring agittin' your ground ready to seed to plant beans, then
         you got to cultivate those beans and get rid of the weeds in
         there. And when the beans was off the hay was ready, when the
         hay was off, why, the harvest was ready. There wasn't any rest
         between, it was just one thing right after another.
         Now, what did your father raise? The same thing?
         No, when he farmed they had never started beans. I was about
         ten or eleven years old the first time I ever remember them
         every trying beans up on the Ridge there and Claude Craig raised
         some, just as an experiment, and he done pretty good with it and
         then everybody started in and they made bean cutters and so on
         and they raised beans. These white navy beans and red beans;
         they was dry beans.
         
         And before that it was just oats and-
         Oats and barley. And then they straight summerfallowed some.
         They'd rotate it,every third year they'd summerfallow a certain
         amount of it; they'd lay a third off or something like that.
         Would this have been weed control or?
         Yes, they had to build the land up.
         
         Because of the moisture?
         
         Yeah, I suppose anyway they would summerfallow, they would always
         have some. They're good farmers. My son started out and he
         said- I put an add in the paper and people darn near run me
         ragged here; it was after we wanted to rent it. And some guys
         showed up wanting to rent it, and I said, "Do you have tractors
         and all this stuff?" "Well, he's got a tractor." "Well," I
         said,"you got to have more than a tractor to farm." They was
         going out trying to runa-ranch and didn't have any more idea
         what they was up against than anything. They'd have to have their
         living for a year until they got that crop off; they'd have to
         have money enough to buy their seed, because I wasn't about to
         buy their seed-take a chance on someone didn't know anything
         about farming! I wouldn't rent to someone didn't understand
         farming. Well, after that, I figured I don't think I'll run
         another ad-ever run another ad, I'll ask a few farmers that I
         think half ways know that they want to farm*, if they aren't
         good farmers, I don't want to be bothered. Cause I got some up
         there, I like 'em and I get along with 'em, but everything has
         to be their way and I'm sure-now we're getting along, but if I
         rented to them, we I'm not agoing to indulge in anything like
         that. But you'd be surprised at these dumbheads that go out
         and think they could farm and never farmed in their life.
         When did the horses go out around here?
         
         Oh, they started quite a number of years back having tractors,
         but Fred, my husband, he was the last one, I think on that whole
         ridge that still farmed with horses and didn't have a tractor.
         And he didn't get a tractor until-well, it was in the spring-
         Willard was in the service, World War II, and he had worked in
         the mines when he left here,and he decided to go back and try
         that when he got home—see Judy was born in '44(1944)—about
         '46(1946) when he got out of the service and come home and he
         farmed then that next fall, he started farming in '47(1947)
         but that was when we had- That spring my husband had bought a
         tractor-and of course, the boy took the tractor and then later
         they got a crawler.
         
         He used horses all the way up into the forties?
         All the time. When we were first married, he had thirty work
         horses that he used.
         you mean)
         I see he had to go feed the stock before he had his break
         fast-he had a lot to feed.
         And he'd raise all his horses. He had those mares and he raised
         colts,and they'd break 'em when they was three year old and break
         those horses to work.
         That long before-
         Oh, yes, they was just little fellows at first.
         Did you ever take any of your animals up to the stock shows in
         Genesee?
         
         No—we didn't even have a truck for a long, long time. We didn't
         attend things like that; in fact he and I went to two fairs in
         all of the time. He had got crippled up, and he didn't like to
         and couldn't walk and now I don't care to go because I can't—
         even to shop now, I was shopping yesterday for the kids, to get
         'em things-that walking-got arthritis in my knees. Long as I sit
         down it don't hurt, but, boy, my legs all twisted out of shape
         and here, this is all built up with that calcium or whatever it
         island it makes me look like I'm bowlegged! This Dr.-Hewitt, I
         think is his name, achiropractor in Clarkston said, "Have you
         always been bowlegged?" "No," I said, "just since I had that
         arthritis." Willard insisted I had to go to him, but he didn't
         do me one bit of good of course he x-rayed and give me a treat
         ment and then to come back in two days; I done that and I paid
         him his $60 he-wranted, and I ain't agoing back anymore! Becausehe
         told me that day he didn't think he could help me, so I said,
         "If it ain't agoin' to help, I ain't goin' to go jus to-"
         What did they do for arthritis back in the old days? Your dad
         had arthritis, what would he a done?
         
         I don't know. He was just as spry, only he got old and got weak
         and he could walk-there's aman down here that's 82 years old
         lives down here, and by God, he don't limp! Isays, "How come
         you don't limp, and all these others-the rest of us have to walk
         with acane and all that?" He says, "Well," he says, "I'll have
         to remember to limp!" (Laughter)
         
         Well, can't blame it all on hard work, because you've had your
         share with all your cooking and stuff.
         
         Well, Idon't know what. Sometimes it's from being-now, with Fred
         when he had it that doctor said-that doctored him-said it was
         jumping down off'n the machinery and exposure to the cold and
         stuff that caused it; that's all Iknow is what he told him.
         And Iwouldn't adone anything about it if- Willard insistedbut
         Willard, my son,he's got arthritis, too, and he's all criPT
         pled up. He's fifty-six and he's crippled up.
         
         My sister's got it, and she's twenty-six, so you can't win these
         days.
         
         I got it all through here,but Iknow what caused that. Iwent
         so I , to-and we had afence that was leanin' down^ had to crawl up
         under like this to go over the top, and Iwas pretty darned heavy,
         and Iwasn't doing very good, if I'd astruggled I'd amade her
         qlHght, but Itried to go through the barn and through the gangway,
         and they had adoor where you could walk through and you had
         an elevator. I was supposed to go out there and help him-Willard
         that was after my husband died, to go out there and help him
         mowing some hay and go with him to feed out around the canyon.
         And about that time one of those bales decided didn't want to
         stick on-wasn't going to come down the elevator, and it fell off
         a there and hit me right smack dab right on top of the head!
         Just knocked me down and I couldn't get up, just felt like my
         back was broke; oh, it did hurt. So Willard happened to look out
         there and looked down there and heard that funny noise-my breath
         every time I'd came funny; breathe, just like it was killing me.
         So he looked down-come down on that elevator he come down there
         he was going to get me out. I said, "Don't move me, don't move
         me." I didn't want him to move me, it just felt like it'd kill
         me if he'd move me. And I laid there till I could get up on my
         own, sit there for a little while. So then I went to the house
         and decided then maybe I'd better go to the darn doctor anyway,
         so I called Muriel, my daughter-in-law, and asked her if she could
         come down, and she said, "Who is this?" She didn't even recog
         nize my voice because I was-and so I told her, and she came and
         left a note for Judy. 
         
         Now, I told her-I don't like to scare her
         to death. Well, she finished her senior year with me after my
         husband died; and like to scared her to death. So went down
         there to the doctor and he give me them treatments(electrical)
         from a fellow down there, a chiropractor by the name of, ohbump
         by the name of Warren somebody. I got aA in the middle of
         my back. But this here-one of those twins was in a plane crash
         got her T ack was broke in four different places., and it was all
         splintered-wasn't anything they could ever set it or anything.
         W and one lung had collapsed and she lay out And she was so bad ana one
         from three in the afternoon on aSunday til the next night
         time they got her down off'n this mountain where that plane
         crashed it was dark when they got her off the mountain to a
         Uttle town down there not too far from Ogden. And her
         husband had abroken neck out of the deal, but he walked out
         with abroken neck, it could, abeen where it killed him,
         had been in that certain place-he walked out to get help.
         they couldn't find it. They didn't go far enough up the moungo
         with ajeep; they took him that far and started him up adraw
         he 'em then went back and they found her. and started out, so
         Her feet were frozen, partially, and she lay there,and that one
         passenger plane. He helped get her out of the plane;then he
         rte doctor-Dr. Tanner was his name. As quick as we found outseven
         or eight o'clock and Judy got word, and then she came down
         and called me and we had friends here playing cards. And I
         said,"I want to go, but haven't got only six dollars in my purse."
         THe, Were the most wonderful neighbors-he says, "I've got $100
         you can have." And so Iwrote him out acheck for the $100,
         and he had $150 when he counted it out and he says, "You can
         I savs "No." So Igive him this check, so he
         have it all. t says,
         the most wonderful could get his money the next day. They were
         she's moved away now,
         neighbors that I ever saw^but he died. This is an awful friendly
         town, I'll say that much. Maeci' might stretch the truth once
         in a while!(Chuckles) But, anyway, they are are an awful friend
         ly family.
         You've lived out of town most all your life then?
         Most of my life. I spent five years in Moscow when I was a kid';
         I was ten
         I went there and I went to school; when we left. Well, maybe I
         I may have been five or just going on six, I can't remember what
         year it was we moved to Moscow. But I know that's where I star
         ted to school-I remember I was ten years old when we moved away
         from there. The rest of the time I-outside of one winter we
         spent in Kendrick and my dad worked at the warehouse and I went
         to school. Why, we just- That's really the only work I know,
         that and cleaning house or something like that. Looking at mine
         now, you'd think I never did clean house!
         It looks fine.
         Oh, my God, my windows; I got storm windows there, and they should
         come off but it takes two husky guys to get 'em offhand I ain't
         even one husky guy! But it does save a lot of heat, I think.
         I never had that in my head that that would help to make a house
         cooler in the summer, but, by gosh, it tells it on the TV and
         on the news that-on the TV more than the papers-that it keeps
         double your house cooler to have the windows. I never figured
         it that way.
         Well, there's the sun coming in the window, supposed to heat up
         your room.
         It don't get against the window, I just draw my drapes then.
         Anything with glass, it can get hot.
         What do you do with your children? Do you have babysitters for
         them?
         
         END OF TAPE
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13559</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Schmaltz2</previous>
      <next>Schupfer_Herman1</next>
      <disp_name>Schoeffler</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
