<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">7/7/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Eugene Settle, 1975-07-07, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:02:37</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Settle, Eugene</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Warehouse superintendent for Latah County Grain Growers ; farmer</occupation>
      <birthyear>1894</birthyear>
      <residence>Aspendale, Moscow</residence>
      <origin>His was one of the few black families to settle in the area; parents grew up in
         Mississippi, came in 1899
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html# families"&gt; families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#racial discrimination"&gt;racial discrimination&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#armed forces"&gt;armed forces&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#education"&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childhood"&gt;childhood&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fighting"&gt;fighting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hay"&gt;hay&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Aspendale"&gt;Aspendale&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Moscow"&gt;Moscow&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Troy"&gt;Troy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13555</file_name>
      <mp3>13556.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13556.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Going into the army during World War I</title>
            <synopsis>Going into the army during World War I. He almost
               saw combat in the Argonne woods, but the armistice
               was signed. The German retreat. Training.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Serving in a segregated unit; assignment to a travelling track team; kindness from
               a French woman
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He served in a segregated unit with no black officers. At the front he served with
               the 139th Infantry. He was assigned to a travelling track team. Kindness from an old
               French lady.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Had trouble getting along with his troop; divisions between western and southern African-Americans;
               his brother's career as a stockman and professor at Virginia State College
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Trouble getting along with his troop, which drank and was rowdy. He was never around
               black people in Idaho, Division between western and southern blacks. His brother's
               career as stockman and professor at Virginia State College; it was hard for him to
               get help on the ranch because he was a Yankee.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Disadvantage of his unit being from the West; Texans feeling superior</title>
            <synopsis>Disadvantage in his unit of being from the West, small and a sergeant. Feeling of
               superiority of Texans— they'd never heard of Idaho or Washington. Southerner thought
               Idaho was next to Nebraska. An African black in France told him that Africans were
               superior to Americans because Americans had been slaves.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2460</time>
            <title>Getting an education in the Army and France; having a piece of shrapnel in his hip;
               Moscow boys petitioned for him to stay with them
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>He got an education in the army in France. He later found a piece of shrapnel in his
               hip which he probably got exploding hand grenades. Shelling of camp. He desired a
               purple heart. Work of the black troops during the war. Moscow boys petitioned for
               him to stay with them.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Growing up on a farm; not really experiencing segregation; stared at on his first
               day of high school
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Growing up on a farm, he knew little of segregation in Moscow. A Moscow restaurant
               didn't like to serve Black people in the forties. His first day at high school everybody
               stared at him, and the superintendent gave a little speech about treating everybody
               equally.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Accepted by high school kids; wouldn't let anybody push him around</title>
            <synopsis>Acceptance by high school kids. Being put in segregated unit was the worst setback
               he ever had. He wouldn't let anybody push him around, but he didn't have a chip on
               his shoulder.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3900</time>
            <title>Brother's success in the South; was told in 1968 that the South was a good place to
               live; what northern segregation was a result from
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Brother's success shows that blacks can prosper in the South, despite prejudice. In
               1968 teachers told him that the South had become a good place to live. Prejudice in
               the South. Advances of a people depend on bloodshed. Northern segregation is a result
               of poverty and housing patterns.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4500</time>
            <title>Father told him not to run from fights; being accused of trying to steal his girl</title>
            <synopsis>Some people around Moscow didn't like him because he was black. His father told him
               not to run from fights, and he roughed up people who gave him a bad time. A drunk
               boy accused him of trying to steal his girl at Eggan's Hall.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5220</time>
            <title>Father's hay bailing operation</title>
            <synopsis>Father's hay baling operation: custom thrashing for farmers, and straw baling for
               the universities.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Discussion on methods of bailing hay; gas engines got father out of business</title>
            <synopsis>Method of baling hay. How father began baling for
               others. Seeing the country. Gas engines got father
               out of business. Alfalfa was fed to the cattle, wheat to horses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6300</time>
            <title>Area around Moscow and Try was mostly Scandinavian; Colton and Uniontown were mostly
               German; cleared farmland couldn't compare with prairie
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Area around Moscow and Troy was mostly Scandinavian; around Colton and Uniontown it
               was German and more well-to-do. Cleared farmland didn't compare with prairie until
               fertilizers were developed.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6480</time>
            <title>Wife's father from South Carolina and farmed in California; farming near Dodge, Washington
               and having one good harvest then several bad one; moving to Oaksdale
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Wife's father came from South Carolina and farmed at Madeira, California. He bought
               bunchgrass prairie from the railroad at Dodge, Washington. He plowed and seeded the
               entire 160 acres, and paid off the place in a year. After acquiring 1300 acres he
               suffered dry years and finally moved to Oaksdale and tried to start over. After the
               Settles married they lived out their lives with them. Father could have gotten a prairie
               homestead if he'd known about it.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Timber claims in Bovill</title>
            <synopsis>Timber claims in the Bovill country. Mr. Wilson
               (of the seed company) got his start by proving up
               on a timber claim.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7140</time>
            <title>The Wells family didn't pick good farm land</title>
            <synopsis>The Wells family didn't pick good farm land for
               their homestead. They may have wanted to be on the
               route to Collins for the halfway house.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Experience in a segregated unit in Europe during World War I. Acceptance in high
         school. Brother's career in Virginia; father-inlaw's pioneering. Family hay baling
         operation. 7-7-75 2 hr 38p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This second interview with Eugene Settle takes place at his home in Moscow, Idaho
         on July 7, 1975. (Sam Schrager)
         
         EUGENE SETTLE: Well, I was pretty young.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: Well, how old were you?
         
         ES:   Well, I was abo.ut twenty-two, twenty-three when I went in. But I
         was real small, I only weighed about a hundred and twenty-eight
         pounds, stripped. So, you see, there wasn't much of me, at that age.
         
         SS:   How did you happen to enlist?
         
         ES:   I was drafted. Yeah, I went to Spokane to enlist. I had a friend who
         was in the navy, he was a fireman. He enlisted as a fireman and after
         he went in, he kept writing to me to come on and enlist in the navy as
         a fireman and we might be lucky enough to get on the same boat. So .
         in October f17, I went up to enlist, and they took me alright, but they
         couldn't put me in what I wanted to get in, because I wasn't heavy
         enough. I think you had to weigh a hundred, I think a hundred and thir
         ty-five, stripped, to enlist as a fireman, and I only weighed a hundred
         and twenty-eight. But they told me I could go in in what branches there
         was, and (if) I gained weight, why then I could transfer
         But I didn't do it. I didn't do it, I just thought well, I come on home
         and waithfor the draft about six months later. And I was in Camp Lewis
         about, long enough to get my shots. I was there just about a month,
         six weeks maybe. And I was transferred to Camp Funston.
         
         SS:   Camp what
         
         ES:   Camp Funston, Kansas to help make up another outfit that was ready to
         go overseas. And so we went over there from Camp Funston to Camp Merrit
         and was there about three days and we went overseas. Then we went
         overseas and went up to Verdun. The Battle of Verdun was over with but
         it was still smoldering around there. And that's where they split us
         all up. Some of the boys moved over to a replacement outfit, some of
         the guys they put in the ammunition train and some went in— transfer
         red to different branches of the service. And you take— there was a
         hundred— about a hundred and sixty of us guys that went to Camp Lewis—
         we hadn't had any training you might say at all— that is, we drilled
         alright, but a lot of the guys hadn't been on a rifle range. Some of
         those kids out of the city, you know, they never saw a gun, you might
         say,until they got out there. But they divided us up. They'd take some
         of the guys and some of them they sent to ammunition train and one
         thing and another. Of course, I was one of the guys— they sent me
         and about fifteen or twenty other fellows, we went out to a little town
         to do some advanced training. And so we went out there and took our
         gas mask training and some rifle and pistol training. And then along
         about in October, the latter part of October, then they called us up.
         They called us up to join our outfits. We was just getting just about
         towards the end of the war,
         bogged down up there,ater, rain and mud, tney needed reinforcements
         and they was calling up everybody behind the lines then. So that s
         when I went up. And I didn't have to go then, my lieutenant told me,
         "You don't have to go." But, I wanted to go, so I went. And we got
         up there in the Argonne Woods, and we was up there— we was supposed
         to have got up there on the evening of the 10th— no, I guess it was
         the 9th, because the next day we was in there, they dispersed us ammun
         ition, tents. They issued us ammunition and inspected clogtags and ev
         erything, and we was supposed to go in on the night of the 11th. And
         the morning of the 11th the Armistice was signed, so you see how close
         I missed it. Instead of going in, that night we turned around, they
         turned us around and started us— well, it was on the night of the 10ththe
         evening of the 11th, they turned us around. We was to go in tnat
         night, and instead of going ahead, they just give us about face and
         started us on back again, and the Armistice was signed the next morning.
         
         SS:   How did you feel about missing the combat? Were you relieved?
         
         ES:   Well,I kind of wanted to get in. I got under artillery fire, but I nev
         er got under I'd kind of liked to have got under fire. I was glad
         I got as close as I did. Htfhen I got'in the army, I wanted to get in
         combat, and I wanted to get wounded, so I could have a Purple Heart.
         That was my desire, I never did think I was gonna get killed. I didn't
         feel that way about it, I never did think they was gonna kill me! But
         I wanted to get wounded and that's I could get a Purple Heart!!
         
         SS:   Were the chances pretty good of that if you got in combat?
         
         ES:   Oh, yeah, I think so. Pretty good. 'Course, when we was up there, when
         we was up there just before the Armistice was signed—it was a running
         battle, you know. The Germans was all in retreat and we was after 'em.
         And in the Argonne woods there, they would put a machine gun nest
         over here and one over here, just behind 'em to hold us back, see, while
         the main army was getting away. That's the way they did it. They'd
         have probably five or six men there fighting a whole company with machine
         Armistice was signed
         guns. And, of course, they tell me that we was losing about six men
         to one at that rate, because they was covering so many of us with so
         few of them, with machine guns. So, I don't know, I might have got a
         not ever have Of course
         Purple Heart and ver been able to wear it!! lots of them got
         rifle wounds too, as far as that's concerned, but the biggest majority
         of the wounded was from shrapnel.
         
         SS:   What was it like in the camps there? The army camps in Europe?
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you. We got into Brest,France and it was raining and
         they put us out there just building the camp there at Brest when I got
         in there, September. And it was just a mud hole. We got in there one
         evening and we slept in the mud that night and the next night they had
         the barracks finished enough so we could get in out of the mud. And
         we just got into it and got our wet blankets spread out on the floor
         and then the officer stepped in there and said, "Be ready to roll in
         half an hour." So I didn't get to spend no night in no camp. But after
         the Armistice I came back as far as Brest— not Brest, but Longuyon,
         France. We followed the Army of Occupation that was going up on the
         Rhine, we followed them back to Longuyon, France, that's just out of
         Belgium. We camped there,and that's where I spent the winter of 1919.
         I thought I was gonna get to come home, but I didn't. So, there was
         one company of— 139th Infantry there— there was a veterinary company
         there, they had a lot of wounded and gassed horses there they was doc
         toring. And there was a company— there was three companies there—
         two companies of American soldiers, one infantry outfit, one veterinary
         outfit and one French company there. But the French company didn't
         stay there all winter, they just stayed there 'til after Christmas and
         I imagine they went home. That's about the only camp I was in. I spent
         the winter there. It was pretty good. We had pitched barracks and it
         wasn't too bad.
         
         SS:   What about the time when you were on advanced training?
         
         ES:   When I was on advanced training over there, we stayed in a little French
         village and where we was, we slept in sheds and barns there in the coun
         try. My quarters was up overhead in an attic over a French home, where
         I stayed. Four- of us stayed there. We did guard duty every night there.
         The road went right through this little village and we had to guard the
         entrance to the village all the time. He just had to walk from one end
         or it to the other to see what was going on, you know, feach guard post
         l every hour. And so that's all we did. And then they praca
         ticed putting on gas masks.We had a chamber full of gas and then we'd
         have to put on our gas masks and go through it and train that way. It
         was a pretty soft life.
         
         SS:   For the middle of the war.
         
         ES:   Yes, for the middle of the war.
         
         SS:   Was the company integrated?
         
         ES:   No. No, it was all black.
         
         SS:   Were the officers black, too?
         
         ES:   No, most all of the officers were white. All white. About the only
         black officers I saw while 1 was over in France, they were on the med
         ical staff or dental, something like that. Doctors. But the officers-
         I don't believe— I know there wasn't any in our outfit. There was—
         I think in what they called the— what they called the Quartermaster
         Corps. I believe in the Quartermaster Corps, I think they had black
         officers. They didn't do nothing, they unloaded ships and stuff like
         that, you know. I think there was some.A.officers in the Quartermaster
         Corps.
         
         SS:   Where did most of the guys come from? Were they Westerners?
         
         ES:   Well, no. The outfit I was in, most of 'em were from Texas. I went
         from here to Camp Lewis, and of course, the boys I was with in Camp
         lewis was from Montana, Idaho and California. Most of 'em was from
         California. And then when we left Fort Lewis and went to Camp Funston,
         Kansas; that s when the Texas, from Camp Travis, Texas was up there.
         They were ready to go over,Athey wasn t up to fighting strength, you
         know, so they took a hundred and fifty of us up here at Camp Lewis%to
         fill 'em in. And then after we got filled in— we just— We started
         out on rifle range there one morning and we hadn't got very far —and we
         back to get ready to sail got  we went from there to Camp Merritt, New Jersey.
         
         SS:   Did you know when you were going in there that that's the way that it
         was? That it wasn't going to be integrated?
         
         ES:   Yeah, yeah, I knew that. I knew that before I went in. When I was
         drafted here, it came out in the paper that I would be sent to— I
         be able to they had me
         wouldn't go with the Moscow boys because sent to some camp
         in the South. Some of 'em tried to do something about it, but it didn't
         work out. So it worked out pretty well for me, anyway. I got in a
         pretty good outfit, the 139th Infantry, what little time I was up front.
         And then when that was over, a bunch of guys come in from the last draft
         they brought them over there,
         I guess, and they were dismantling airplanes and stuff like that and
         tearing down buildings. And so I was transferred over there in the
         spring. The main division that I was with, they came home the first of
         the year, you see, and these guys like myself that got in there late—
         and I was a sergeant—. That s one thing there—they needed noncom
         officer with this new bunch that come in, so I got pulled into that.
         then we went out to Romainesv-France, had a big German prison camp there,
         guard duty- And when I was out there— I was not there but a little
         while and I was a pretty good athlete in school, and then they started
         to get up a track team and so I got on the track team. From March 'til
         the First of July I didn't do nothing but just travel all over France,
         wherever there was American troops, this track team went. On Decoration
         Day in 1919 I ran in a relay race from Chateau to Paris and the race
         ended at the Arch of Triumphe in Paris and I ran the last three miles
         That was on Decoration Day, 1919. And so, they called us back about
         the First of July. They was gonna release the prisoners. I went back
         to the company and on the fifth of July, we broke camp and started home.
         And I got home— landed in the United States, back American soil on
         August the fifth, 1919. That was quite a year to remember.
         
         SS:   What kind of impressions did you have of the French? What did they
         think of us?
         
         ES:   Well, (Laughter) some of the soldiers they didn't think too much of 
         Well, of course, they had plenty of money and they was kinda— I
         think they thought they was a little better than anybody else. But
         they treated us good. I liked the French people.
         
         SS:   You say our boys did, or the French thought they were better?
         
         ES:   Our boys did. 'Course they thought the American army was the best paid
         army in the world to them. The French didn't get anything. They'd
         get pretty rowdy sometimes. We got along pretty good, though.
         
         SS:   How did the family feel about having people living in their attic?
         where I was anyway,
         
         ES:   Oh, they didn't object to that. They was very nice, very nicey We
         didn't have to go through the house, they just put a ladder up on the
         outside and went up to the attic. nights when I was on guard duty-
         I noticed there was always —I see a little light in the back of the
         house all the time— and they didn't allow much light there, you know.
         We was back of the lines quite a ways, but we had to be awful careful
         with the lights, you know. I'd have to walk right past this place
         where I was staying, and seems like I could see just a little dim glow
         I wondered what it was all about
         of light back there. And that night, the early morning, when I got
         off of guard duty and I started up the ladder, this old French lady
         she come out and took me by the arm and took me in the back end of the
         room there, she had some milk and bread for me when I got off of shift.
         Very nice old lady. That old French bread was pretty hard to beat.
         
         SS:   What about the guys that you were with in your unit?
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you. I had more trouble with them than anybody. I just
         couldn't— hard for me to adjust myself to their way of doing things.
         I take a drink but I'm not a drinker and never was. And never was a
         rowdy. I was always taught to respect. So they was kind of out of my
         kind of Me being a black,
         line. It was  to adjust myself there.. I never was around 'em any
         I left— my parents came out here when I was five years old. So I nev
         er was around any black people outside of my family until I was—
         Oh, I guess I was in high school, I went to Spokane a time or two and
         to try to get on.
         met some people up there, but— So it was quite a shock to me. And then
         I'll tell you another thing that I found out after— there was always
         a division point— After we went over, these hundred and fifty that
         went from Camp Lewis to Camp Funston, Kansas, met these guys from Camp
         Travis, some of 'em had been in the army over a year—they were all black
         but there's always kind of a division point between the Western boys
         and those that come from the South. And I found that out. My brother,
         my youngest brother, he finished college here in '29. He left high
         school as soon as he got enough credits to get in college— he didn't
         really graduate, he just as soon got enough credits and he quit, went
         to college and took a short course, dairy course, and then he went out
         and worked in creameries all over the country. Worked up at Sandpoint
         for quite a while and after he worked at that two or three years, then
         he decided to come back and finish college and he come back and finished
         college. And he finished in '29. And then he got a job at Virginia
         State College at Petersburg, Virginia. They took him on as assistant
         professor there, he just had a BS. And so he came back the next year and
         went to WSU and got his Masters, and then he got a little better job.
         Then the next summer he went to Cornell, started to work on his PhD.
         He never did finish his PhD. He finished everything but his thesis;
         He never did get his thesis. They call him Doctor Settle all the time,
         But he never did get his thesis wrote.
         
         SS:   That happens to a lot of people. Get everything done but that.
         
         ES:   He passed away before he ever got it finished at Cornell.
         
         SS:   He stayed there at Cornell?
         
         ES:   No, he just went there in the summertime, worked on his PhD. No he was
         teaching at Virginia State College at Petersburg, Virginia. But he went
         to school in Cornell in the summer months, that's he was working on
         his PhD. at Cornell.
         
         SS:   But when you started talking about him you were talking about the dif
         ference between Southerners and Westerners.
         
         ES:   Oh, yeah. Then he bought a big ranch down there at Petersburg,
         Six hundred and sixty-seven acres, I believe it was in this place. And
         he was quite a stockman. Course animals was what he was teaching, see.
         And he had some purebred stock. And don't you know it was hard for him
         to get help out on his farm there? Because he was a Yankee. Yeah they
         that's the truth
         didn't like him. Well, I was down there, I guess it was 1962, I was
         down there. That was my first trip down there,he had a stroke in the
         spring, so that fall I flew down to visit him. I was out there on his
         farm and a couple of old Virginia Mountaineers— he raised shorthorn
         cattle on his farm out there— and they come down there, they wanted
         to buy a heifer out of his strain, and they came down there, and I was
         there and he hadn't got out there yet, I was out there. He was having
         some work did on his house and he had me out there, I was kind of super
         vising it for him. Two old bachelors, they came down out of the hills
         up there and they wanted this heifer, they was looking for Doctor Set
         tle, and I told 'em he wasn't here yet. I said, "I'm his brother."
         "Well," he said, they didn't think I would know anything about it, but
         he had a heifer that they were interested in, they wanted some of the
         same bloodlines. And so, we talked there a while and my brother came
         and they went out to the barnyard to look at the heifer— cattle. And
         of course, my brother'd been down there— that was in '62— and he's
         been down there since '29— and one of these old guys asked him who I
         was He told  was kis brother from— "Well," he said, told him
         if he wanted to do any business with rid of him.
         You go dox-m there as soon as they open their mouth, they know you
         don't belong there. They knew I didn't belong there. It's kind of
         surprising, but it's true. And he tried to get different families
         to move out there on his place and work for him, they didn't want
         to do it.
         
         SS:   'Cause they knew he was a Yankee?
         
         ES:   Yeah, uh-huh. When I was down there, he didn't have no trouble 'cause
         he was a Southerner then. (Chuckles) And you stay there very long
         you'll acquire that drawl, too, My brother did a they had ad
         opted him by that time
         
         {End of Side A)
         
         SS:   When you were over there in Europe did you find that you had a harder
         time with the guys in your troop because you were a Westerner and not
         a Southerner?
         
         ES:   Well, as I say, there's kind of a little division, I had a little
         rough time,a know tha- way. I had a rough time in this way: I had
         two strikes against me. I was  the company. outfit. I was
         a Westerner and I was about one of the smallest guys in the outfit and
         I was a sergeant, too, and you know— it kind of made a difference.
         They didn't like me giving 'em orders too well, but that didn't bother
         me any. I didn't let that worry me. I give 'em just the same and I
         got 'em done, but there was some of 'em didn't like it, but there was
         n't much they could do about it. I wasn't overbearing to anybody. I
         just did my job and that was it. Whether you was from the South or
         whether you was from the West, it didn't make no difference to me. I
         treated 'em all alike, I didn't show no partiality to nobody, just did
         And for most cases I was pretty well liked.When
         my job. they told me I didn't have to go to the front, 'Course I wanted
         the guys that-were with me
         and that gave me a pull to go anyway went. r they just put up such a
         howl about me not going.
         
         SS:   Why were they saying you didn't have to go?
         
         ES:   They thought I was too young. They didn't was  sixteen.
         
         SS:   Did you think that the Westerners were more independent than the South
         erners? Or wasn't there any difference like that?
         
         ES:   Well, I don't know that there much difference. The only thing I would
         say, it seemed to me that it was just the other way around. I don't
         know whether it was the general attitude of the Southerners, but just
         because those guys from Texas, he figured if he was from Texas, there
         was nothing that compared to Texas,no way shape nor form. If you're
         from Texas, why you're a top cat!! (Chuckles) As fiscae. Idaho, they
         didn't know Idaho was on the map.
         
         You say anything about Washington, they'd say Washington, D.C.. It's
         a funny deal, they know about Montana, but Idaho and Washington they
         don't know nothing about it. Idaho was just a complete loss. If
         you'd say anything about Washington, they'd think you were talking
         about Washington, D.C.! But they all knew about Montana. When you'd
         say about Montana, they knew about Montana, but they didn't know about
         Washington and Idaho. Washington was Washington, D.C, and Idaho just
         didn't exist.
         
         SS:   That doesn't surprise me, it's still pretty bad. In the East they don't
         know.
         
         ES:   Yes it is. 'Course I always knew about it. When I was down there, I
         guess it was in '62 I was down there. I wanted to buy a pair of shoes,
         My brother and I
         and we was up in Richland, Virginia, a big department store there, and
         I was getting a pair of shoes, and of course,as I say a while ago, as
         soon as you open your mouth they know you don't belong there.^ About -
         the next thing they want to know is where you're from. So I was buy
         ing a pair of shoes there," and the fellow, I paid him for it, and he
         says, he asked me if I was an educator and I told him no, I'm just
         here— was I from the college down there and I told him no. 'Course,
         naturally— you just down here visiting are you/ and I told him, "Yes,
         that's my brother, down here with my brother at the college over there,
         and I'm down here visiting him." Then he wanted to know where I was
         from. I told him I was from Idaho. "Oh," he says, "my son-in-law isn't
         from Idaho, but he's right close to it." I said, "Where's he from,Mon
         tana?" And he said,"no." "Washington?" And he said, "No.""Oregon?"
         and he said, "No." "Wyoming?" "No." He studied a little while and
         then he said, "He's from Nebraska." (Chuckles) "Well," I said, "he's
         got quite a little ways to go yet to get to Idaho." (Laughter) Well,
         I'll tell you, after you cross the Mississippi River down there, you
         lose a lot of those Southerners. You're in wide open spaces.
         
         SS:   Well even Texas is the West as much as it's the South.
         
         ES:   Yes, it is, yes. Texas is considered as the Southwest. Yes, that was
         twelve months-- quite an experience for me.
         
         SS:   Did you feel that you grew up a lot while you were over there?
         
         ES:   Yeah, I did. There was a kid in ouroutfit, he was from Baton Rouge,
         Louisian a, and he was a mixture of Negro and French, a Creole, they
         called themselves, and he spoke French, but he didn't speak the— the
         French could understand him, but it wasn't quite the way they speak
         it as their native tongue— the Creole, they spoke it in a little dif
         ferent tongue than they speak in France. He was on the track team,
         too. And he and I we was walking down the street one day, and so we
         made a stop at a French cafe, sidewalk cafe, and there was a black
         girl setting at a table there, and of course, we thought, this kid he
         ^she could stand some company,if
         could speak French, and he asked her if we could sit there. And
         we sit down there, And, of course he got to talking to this girl in
         French, you know. And pretty soon come to find out that she could speak
         better English than he could! (Chuckles) She'd been educated in
         London; she spoke very fluent English, so we talked there quite a lit
         te while, and she told us that she felt that she was superior to
         us— to the American Negro, she was from Algiers, she was from Africa
         anyway, but anyway she told us, that the African blacks, they felt that
         they were superior to the American Negro for the simple reason that
         the American Negro'S parents had been slaves. I wanted to tell her, but
         I didn't, "The only reason your s wasn't, they didn't catch yours."
         She thought she was pretty hot stuffJ Well, I don't begrudge anybody
         that's got any pride, 'cause I think pride1's the spice of life, If you
         don't have any pride there's not much to you. Yeah, that's a year
         for me to remember, that year in the army.
         
         SS:   Its too bad that you had to feel superior to somebody else.
         
         ES:   Yes,
         
         SS:   Sounds like the same old story.
         
         ES:   But there's very few people, I don't care, black or white, that
         spent a year in France and got away with it as easy as I got it. I
         pretty near got what I wanted to get, and then didn't get— Oh, I had
         my . hardships, nothing like a lot of the fellows had. 'Course,
         it was educational-
         
         I got lots of travel— saw what it was like on the front and I saw
         what it was like all over France. I got a good education. I can
         tell you what it's like on the front lines, I wasn't right up in 'em,
         but I was close enough I knew just what was going on there, and behind
         the lines, and about getting the ammunition up there. And how the
         French people back of the lines were living in villages and towns^'and
         I just got a good history of the whole business. As I told you before,
         I was hoping .. I'd get on the line and get wounded so I could get—
         have a Purple Heart, but I didn't do that. But after I retired and
         went down here to Boise to take my examination for my army pension, I
         had a wart on this hip here, on this side of my buttocks here, and before I went In
         the service but anyway The 'doctor noticed
         it there and he says, "Well, you watch that and if that starts to grow
         you'd better have it taken off" So when I got out of the service I
         thought it had growed some; anyway I went down there to the Veterans'
         Hospital for examination, I thought well, might be a good time to
         have that taken off. So they was x-raying me all over and they found
         that wart there and I told 'em I was going to have it taken off. Wanted
         to know— there's something in my hip there—wanted to know if I'd been
         wounded and I told 'em not that I knew of. "Well", he said, "there's
         pretty close to the hip,bone,
         something in there maybe we'd better take it out, find out what it
         is, because if it works into your hip socket there it's liable to cause
         a lot of trouble." So when they took that wart off they just went on
         down and got it, and it was a little piece of steel. And I don't know how 
         when I got it. But I remembered after I got back out of the Argonne,
         and on that hip there was just a little patch of blood in my underwear
         about as big as a quarter there, but I didn't think much about it,
         'course we was always getting in bobwire (barbwire) and one thing and
         another. But that night after we left—when they turned us around
         and started us back — going up to the front in the night— they turned
         us around— marched back and stayed all night in little place,
         a little old village there—and there was a big crater there that
         was full of water there where a bomb had dropped, and so there was live
         ammunition and hand grenades all around the place there, so we* .taking
         the hand grenades and throw in that water know hand gren
         ades is deathly in a radius of sixteen feet any direction from it
         that's what we was taught in the army. You was just about the same as
         a dead man if you were within sixteen fet of one and it explodes. We
         was throwing them in that pond, exploding them see, and I just think
         that probably I got a little piece of shrapnel from that is where I
         got that in my hip. And I know a feller got hit just above the eye
         there and if it had been just a little bit lower it would have been
         right in his eyeball, got hit right in the eyebrow there. And so I
         think that's where I got that steel in my hip. I think I got just a
         little fragment there.
         
         SS:   Would that have qualified you for a Purple Heart?
         
         ES:   Well, (Chuckles)I'11 tell you though. The first thing we got in up
         there in the woods and they kept us over to examine our dogtags and
         give us our final rundown before we went in see that we all had the
         right amount of ammunition and we all had our dogtags and all that—
         that evening we got in there and we wasn't going in— the next night's
         when we was supposed to go in—and a shell dropped in camp that night
         not too close to me, but close enough to me so that I just got a—
         when the mud come falling down I just got a big shower of mud. But
         it wasn't close enough to our company— I think there was one or two
         boys got hurt pretty bad. If I'd a been in that outfit, been close
         enough to get a piece of shrapnel from that shell, that would have
         qualified me for a Purple Heart. But the only thing I got hit with
         was mud!
         
         SS:   Well, I got to ask you why you wanted a Purple Heart so bad.
         
         ES:   Well,I just felt like that was something to show that I had been in,
         the service. That was it more than anything else. But I'm telling
         you though, since I've been out of the war, and there's another World
         War, and I have heard so much about this Purple Heart business, the
         way they give 'em for this thing and another— and some of the guys
         wearing Purple Hearts from self-inflicted wounds, you know, they got
         'em, I don't feel that wav any more. ButI see a guy with a Purple
         Heart the first thing I you get it, did you shoot yourself
         in the foot, or how." That's the way I feel about it now about a
         Purple Heart.
         
         SS:   Did the kind of work that you guys did in your troops, was that dif
         ferent than— was it different in kind from the work that the white
         troops were doing?
         
         ES:   Well, of course, they were— it's like I say—the Quartermaster Corps
         there at Brest— I think there was some white there, too— that's all
         they did, they unloaded ships. See the 92nd Division that I was sup
         posed to^efrn, they're engineers—they were not combat engineersthey
         were stationed there at Brest— they was the ones that was build
         ing those barracks there for the Quartermaster Corps,and they was un
         loading ships and building barracks and doing all that kind of work.
         And then there was Labor Battalions. There was .coming-Wfor Bat
         talions—well,they called 'em Pioneer Infantry, was what they called
         'em—of course, they was some black and they had some white, too. Pion
         eer Infantry. They worked behind the lines doing different things
         and building roads and such as like that. And then they had— the
         French had Chinese battalions working, they was on their own, I guess
         for the money that was in it—they wasn't in army uniform though— they
         was just working for the French. They built roads and that. But the
         139th Infantry and the 92nd Division that was all black combat outfit.
         The 92nd—outside of the 91st Engineer?— the 92nd Engineers— they
         werencombat engineers, they was road building and stuff like that—
         engineers— carpenters and such as that. They did that, they wasn't
         in combat. But the rest of the and the 139th Infantry, where they
         put me into after I got through my basic training, that was all com
         bat. And outside of those two outfits, that's the only two outfits
         that I know of in France that were combat— the 139th and the 92nd Div
         isions— excluding the engineers. They wore the same insignia as thethe
         92nd Engineers, they wore the same insignia— they never went to
         the front, they stopped there at Brest and they started building bar
         racks and unloading ships and they got a nice place after we came back
         home through there. They sure built it up awful nice. And where they
         went from there— whether they left there and went home or not, I don't
         know. I imagine they did.
         
         SS:   Did local fellows really make a try for you to be able to stay with
         them in troops? fheir troop? Did you say that?
         
         ES:   Oh, yes, that is the fellows I was working with, when I got my final
         training over there, before we was called up— they didn't want to see
         me leave the outfit, they wanted—
         
         SS:   I was talking before, you were saying that in Moscow before you went
         in—
         
         ES:   Oh, yes, yes, they was some of the fellows they tried to get a petition
         up for me to go with the kids I went to school with here. We had a fel
         low—in the Courthouse, Deputy Assessor up there— he went to bat for
         me—tried to get— they didn't like it— But, of course, in the high
         school here I played football wiffe the kids and one thing and another.
         And they thought it was no more than fair —why that I should, have to-being
         raised here^-why I'd have to separate myself-why I couldn't go on and fight
         h But that was the law, so—" with the rest of the boYs:
         
         SS:   I wonder during the Civil War if it was that way for the Northern troops?
         Do you know?
         
         ES:   Well, I don't know. That's something that I don't know and I've thought
         at this time.
         of it too, quite a bit, To tell the truth about it, I don't really
         believe that there was— there was lots of blacks in the Civil War,
         but I don't know whether there was any special company or special regi
         ment or not. Now that I don't know. That's something to look into.
         I just really don't know about it.
         
         SS:   I don't know either.
         
         ES:   I just don't know.
         
         SS:   Well, one thing I've heard in Moscow, in the early days, which sur
         prised me, was that the hotel was segregated. You know, they wouldn't
         let blacks stay in Moscow Hotel.
         
         ES:   Yeah, th ti Well, that's, of course— I wouldn't doubt that a
         bit. Course as long as I've been around Moscow
         but in the early days I imagine it was- Probably could have been
         it probably was,I don't know to find out?
         when we first came here—r!Course, we didn't live in town lived out
         in the country and I didn't know what was going on and I never heard my
         folks say anything about it. But I know this— I know here— oh, this
         was in, I believe it was in the '40!s, think it was in the '40's—
         when I started to work for Latah County Grain Growers here, I know
         there was a fellow here, he was a railroad man— and I can't figure
         out why it was, but, anyway, he had three or four black fellows work
         ing for him, on whatever he was doing, I don't know what— and I know
         that he was a veteran and he had been to one of our veteran meetings
         and I had met him. And after that he was through here again, and he
         had these black— he was working for the railroad, now what he was
         responsible for his men
         doing, I don't know, but he had two or three black boys of course he was 
         He came around here where I was at work one afternoon, when I was
         working— and he asked me, he says, "'Gene, where do you eat at here
         in Moscow?" And I said, "What do you mean?" "I mean, which resta*nuant
         do you patronize when you go out for dinner?" "Well," I says, 
         first one then the other, I don't have no particular one." "Well,"
         he says, "why I asked. I sent the boys to I don't know which one-
         Varsity was running then or, not,it was
         along in there. And,he said, "they served them but they acted liked
         they just as soon not serve them." And that was in the '40's. I think
         that was in the '40's 'cause I started to work the Grain Growers in
         imagine there was, prejudices that way
         reached a lot further than the south.
         But, 'course here in Moscow, as far as I was concerned I never
         did experience any of it. Because, as I say, by the time I came to
         Moscow and started I never went to the— The first time
         that I was ever in the Moscow Hotel, that is, upstairs— I think I
         was telling you before, about that colored boy come down here to go to
         school and that his mother was about the first black woman to
         from the University of Idaho
         graduate and then sent her son down here. Well, the first time I bemother
         lieve I was ever up, there was after this kid died,his .came down after
         the body, and she was staying at the Moscow Hotel then. So my sister
         and I, we went down to the hotel and saw her. I think that was the
         first time. 'Course, I didn't get a room there, but that's the first
         time I was ever upstairs. So, I wouldn't be surprised.
         
         SS:   Have there ever been times in your life here or out the country
         when people have given you a hard time because of it?
         
         ES:   No. I've never— Now you take it when I started to high school here
         I was the only Black in the school system. Well, of course, the first
         morning I went to school, all the eyes was focused on me, naturally.
         That I expected. But I met one kid that I knew— I met him the first
         day,* and then when we went un for assembly, the principal was a man
         by the name of Otis Randa , and he lived out northeast of town here
         and he had a little farm out there, just the other side of where we
         did, and I knew him casually; I knew who he was, you might say. He used
         walk Past our Place and talk to some And so he got up, and he
         assembly that morning and he spoke about getting along with people
         and treating your fellow students, something about regardless of race
         or creed or something— (End of side B) The fellow that was teaching
         that, Iknew him, he used to teach out in the country and Iknew him, and
         so Imet this kid that Iused to know- that Ihad met previously- and
         so we got along. And it seems like as soon as the kids found out that
         I walked and talked and breathed just the same as they did, why, then
         I got to be a very popular student in the Moscow High School. They
         invited me out for track and I did pretty well in football. And I got
         along just real good. Just as soon as they found out that I walked and
         breathed the same as anybody else, why, of course, there was always
         some kind of but there was so many more that didn t, that I never
         noticed it, so I got along real good in school here. And always have
         in Moscow here. After coming out here in the early days as we did, we
         never had any particular trouble that I know of. The worst setback that
         I got ever in my life since I've been old enough to know anything, and
         that's when I had to go to a segregated, unit. That the worst setback
         I've got since I've been black was that. That really got under my skin.
         It's like I tell my wife now, 'course the army isn't segregated now and
         they have trouble once in a while, I tell her I think that's— I tell
         her I don't think that would ever bother me any, I could go in an all
         white army, I could get along with But, of course, you
         take these Southern guys, they have a chip on their shoulder, and they
         have a little different attitude than I have. So, in a way, I blame
         those for it, just as much as I do the whites,just as bad. Because I've
         lived here all my life, nobody but whites all my life, and I can't say
         that I've ever had trouble. The same as if I went into the army, all white
         army, I don't think I'd have any trouble. And I've never let nobody run
         over me either. But I don't go around with a chip on my shoulder. I
         see a letter from  bank, I m wondering if maybe I got a check in here.
         
         SS:   There's no harm in trying. (Laughter) But I would think that in the
         South where it's been all segregation for so long, it would be pretty
         tough. It would seem that you wouldn't have a very good chance if
         you were black.
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you, I've thought of that too. Now, as I told you, I've
         got a brother who was born in the West, never been out of Moscow, you
         might say, until after he went South to teach in that school, down there
         in '39. Now he was a Western black boy went down in the deep South to
         teach. He bought himself a farm and he taught down there until he died
         worth anyway
         in '67. And he left an estate down there a quarter of a million dol
         lars. And he went down there when you drive into a gas station and they'd
         fill your gas tank and take your money, but they wouldn't put your gas
         cap back on. If Vouwanted the gas cap on you had to get out and put it
         on you elf. There was just that much prejudice. In spite of that though—
         he went down there
         he was a Northern Black, and made himself a fortune. In spite of this.
         And I was down there and that was '62 when I first went to Virginia, and
         I was back down there— I went down there and buried my brother, this
         same brother in '68, and I heard some of those professors in the South
         then talking about it. They figured that the South was the best place
         in the world for a black man. They liked it so much better there, they
         said now if you're traveling— just after the Civil Rights Act passed
         that is good hotels,
         in '64—there was very few hotels that you're not welcome^ And they
         said the same way about restaurants. The accommodations were so much
         better now, they thought it was a wonderful place to live now, since the
         Civil Rights Act was passed. And when I was down there— the first time
         I was down there, I'll tell you what I saw with my own eyes— The main
         road up from Camp Lee, not too far down the road from where my brother
         ranch is— the kids'd get on weekend passes, they'd go right past his
         farm either going to Petersburg or Richmond, Virginia for a weekend pass.
         And I saw a truck load — army truck loaded with black and white soldiers
         come by there from Camp Lee,Virginia. And just down the— a little ways
         from my brother's place there is a service station. And pretty near evdown
         ery service station has a lunch counterA most of 'em on the highway
         and these kids they stopped at this service station the white boys
         on the truck they went inside and s»t at the counter and the black boys
         they handed their sandwich out of the window there on the side 
         and ate theirs. They couldn't go. to the counter
         they stood out there in the ram, they couldn t go in. I saw thas.
         because they were 
         with my own eyes. Talk about segregation, I saw that right there. black.
         
         SS:   I've read that the feelings of the black people in the South were very
         divided about whether it was worth going through all the trouble, the
         suffering to get integration. But then I think a lot of people felt they
         had gone through a lot of trouble and suffering all ready.
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you— you can say what you want to, but, how many good
         things that's happened to any race of people any time, taking clear back
         to Bibical time without bloodshed? What great thing have they accompli
         shed, any race of people, any nationality, without bloodshed? Just name
         me one.
         
         SS:   Seems like most of the integration though, has been accomplished by non
         violence in the South.
         
         ES:   Yes, it has. But there's bloodshed— I mean, they just didn't go to war#
         Martin Luther King he believed in nonviolence, but he did more for the
         blacks than anyone. Anyway, they're pretty proud of their accomplishments.
         It's so much better now than it was years ago.
         
         SS:   Well, the Northern cities seem to have a lot of their problems, still,
         they got nothing to crow about.
         
         ES:   That's it. There you are. Yes sir. And of course, lots of this segre
         gation in the Northern cities though and places like that was caused when—
         by residential barriers. It's just like— I don't know if you can say
         what caused it— but I guess it's probably caused by poor people, more
         than anything else in lots of cases. It's just like lots of these big
         cities where the black people immigrate from the South— they're usually
         poor people, very little money. So they look for a cheap place to live
         and, of course, that's where the slums get started. The slumlords' ^ these
         old hotels and old buildings and just make 'em liveable, and of course,
         that's why slums get started. And, of course, when they get a bunch of
         'em together, blacks together, why, naturally in that vicinity, you've
         got a segregated school, you might say, because every in that 
         goes up andit goes up,
         rict is black and naturally that school is going to be black. ,And then
         on the other side of town, why theres all white, why then that's the way
         then I guess
         they get theirselves segregated, that way. And after so many years
         of that, they figured— "Why should I bus kids across town, 
         to balance the segregation?" Well, I can see why that's not
         so good, I wouldn't really like that — my kid done the same way either.
         But that's just a barrier that just happened— and it didn't happen by
         law. I guess it happened by fate, I guess that's the way you'd have to
         put it.
         
         SS:   Do you think that there were people around here that didn't know you,
         who didn't like you, because you were black?
         
         ES:   Oh, yes. I imagine there's a lot of people right here in Moscow that
         don't like me for the simple reason— just because I'm black. Yeah, I
         believe that.
         
         SS:   I can't imagine myself it'd be that way now. But I was thinking maybe
         forty years ago when you were a young man, back in the early days—
         when it was still more a legacy of the Civil War—.
         
         ES:   I have to agree with you there. I believe when I was a younger man back
         years ago, there was more of it then than there is now. I feel now it
         still exists, but there's not as much of it.
         
         SS:   Nobady'd ever come up to you and insult you or anything? Or give you
         a hard time?
         
         ES:   Uh-huh.
         
         SS:   I imagine that if anybody had, there'd be other guys that had been friends
         of yours that would have laid 'em out pretty good.
         
         ES:   Uh-huh. Yeah, I remember when I was a teenager, or a kid anyway, guy; that
         kind of didn't like me very well for one reason or another, jie wouldn't
         say nothing to me, but probably get a couple of drinks under his belt
         and then he'd come u? and try to insult me, you know, figured he could
         I'd figure he was drunk.
         get away with it, you know.because that fact that I have* servedup a
         few guys in this town pretty damn fast, just on that account. So they
         kind of found out that didn't work too good either.
         5fou didn't
         
         SS:   just turn the other cheek, huh?
         
         ES:   HUH?
         
         SS:   You didn't just "urn the other cheek?
         
         ES:   No, I didn't. I just held 'em by the collar and pushed 'em up against
         the wall. They all knew me for one thing, they knew that I wasn't a
         very big man, but I was a damn good little man! My dad always told
         us boys never to start no fight, he never wanted us to start no fight,
         but he didn't tell us to run either. About the last incident I had of
         that kind, was down here— up there on Third Street, right above where
         the post office is, right in that shopping center there, there was a
         hall that called Eggans Hall. We used to have a roller skating
         rink there in the bottom part there. And so we used to go down there
         in the evenings to roller skate, I used to go down there once in a
         while to try roller skating. I was a pretty good roller skater. So I
         was down there one evening, several of us were down there roller skating.
         'Course, I knew a lot of those kids, lot of high school kids, I knew a
         lot of em. And another kid come in there, I knew him, Rolland, he come
         in there; he had a girl with him. And he wasn't a very good skater any
         way, and he was trying to teach her to roller skate,you know. And he
         was on the floor more times than he was on the skates. There was two
         of us boys together. Now this Rolland, he said, "Gene, give me a lift
         here. We are in a lot of trouble." "Yeah,  you're
         kinda holding up the parade." He said, "Yes, we are." So, this other
         kid that was with me, anyway, I got aholt of him^and he got her up there
         so we went around there and sat 'em down. After he set down there they
         weren't skating and we were.Then this kid,Dan Holland, he motioned us to
         come over there. I went over.there and he said;"Why don't you and your
         friend take her around some.
         
         If she could learn a little better, I think we could make it.
         I can t skate too good and she can't skate  says, If it s
         alright with her, why, I'll take her around." So I did, I took her around
         the floor a time or two, and I turned her over to this other kid and he
         took her around a time or two. And, so that was alright. I don't know
         whether it was the next Saturday night or the Saturday night after that
         why this Rolland kid he was in— this same guy walked in the hall there
         and he was drunk od he^Uiad a drink or two in him, you know. I don't
         think it was the next Saturday night,it .two weeks after that. And he
         was standing there in the hall and I walked in, I don't know who was with
         me that night or whether I was alone— anyway, he was talking to some
         other kids there and he says,— anyway, when I walked past, he says,
         "Well, Goddamn you, you tried to take my girl away from me the other
         night." I just turned around and I just walked up to him and I just got
         him right like that, and I just shoved him up against the wall, and I
         said, "Say it again, and I'll knock every Goddamn tooth you got right
         down your throat, you lying bastard." And if you ever see a man sober
         up now— he come over arrapologizef and he did to me. He sure did. And
         I made him tell them like it was, and he did. No, I was good to every
         body and I didn't pick no trouble, but I don't let nobody try to push me
         around, big or small. Therefore I think that's one reason why I get
         along good with everybody. I'm not overbearing, I treat everybody right,
         but I demand my respect.
         
         SS:   Myself, I was born Jewish.
         
         ES:   Are you?
         
         SS:   Yeah. And when I went to school, I was the only Jewish kid in the school,
         And every once in a while, you know not often, every once in a while,
         some kid would throw that up to me. Just didn't like me and was using
         that as a way to get at me.
         
         ES:   Yeah, I know what you mean. My daughter taught school in Oakland down
         there for ten years, and I heard her say the same thing. She said the
         black kids they get it throwed up to them too, she said, and then Jewish
         kids. — they run into the same problem down there.
         
         Do you know this Barbara Freeman that works down here at the Crossroads
         Book Store?
         
         SS:   No.
         
         ES:   She's a little Jewish girl from Detroit. She was born, Jewish was her
         faith and she turned Christian. (noisy)
         
         SS:   Oh, I was wanting to ask you about the haying that you did. About the
         hay baler you took around the country. I guess that was George Johnson
         was the guy that told me— wanted me to say "Hello" to you for him, do
         you remember? George Johnson.
         
         ES:   George Johnson? There was so many Johnsons— I know so many Johnsons—
         
         SS:   He was the one from Juliaetta. I guess he used to live right here in
         Lnville or not too far from there, 'cause he said that— I don't know
         if he worked with your crew or if you baled on his place, or something
         like that.
         
         ES:   My dad run a hay baler all over the country, when I was a young man.
         When I went to the army, I left the hay baler and went to the army,
         and when I came back they was baling, too. He baled hay for years and
         years all over the country. George Johnson— did he gro up around
         Genesee? Or do you know?
         
         SS:   I know he was living near Linville when you were out in the neck of the
         woods. But I don't know him very good, I just met him at a friend's house,
         it was a friend of mine he was visiting.
         
         ES:   I know George
         
         SS:   I'm pretty sure that his name is George. He's the only— one of the
         only Johnsons right around Juliaetta. But anyway I was going to ask you
         about the bay baling and what kind of an operation you had there and how
         that worked.
         
         ES:   Well, It worked just the same as— we went from farmer to farmer and
         baled hay, whenever a farmer had any hay to bale, he usually contacted
         my dad or Bad'd contact him. Just like we used to do in farm
         to farm is what it was, all over the country. then he baled hay
         for Pullman college and he baled— straw, rather. In--the fall of always
         of straw to bale for Idaho college or WSU. Animal Husbandry
         department used lots of straw, and he baled straw for both colleges.
         And he custom baled all over the country from Palouse up here, I don't
         think we ever went beyon^ Palouse very much, From Palousei all out around
         Pullman, Colton, Uniontown, Genesee and clear down to the breaks before
         you started down Lewiston Hill there. We just baled all over the country.
         And my father and there was three of us boys and he hired about two or
         three fellows. Let's see, what did we have? Yeah, there was about six
         of us on the crew. And he had a farm out here northeast of town where
         us kids grew up. He raised lots of berries of different kinds and garden
         stuff. Sold mostly strawberries and that. Then he had this hay baler
         and this hay baling was a sideline.
         
         SS:   What was the season for baling?
         
         ES:   Well, we started along about the first of July and then we baled up until
         snow come because we baled straw. usually had a contract for either
         the Idaho college or WSU, and that was straw. And in those days the
         stationary thresher, they blowed
         the straw in big stacks, you see, and then we come along and baled
         it. Then thes colleges would buy these stacks, buy this straw, and then
         we'd go down and bale til pretty near snow fly, sometimes. Way up tw
         November. We usually started along the first of July, up here. And, of
         course, we did that for years. 
         
         (End of side C)
         
         SS:   because some people thought he was doing good?
         
         ES:   Yeah, thought he was making too much money. It was hard work. 'Course
         now-a-days, there's no hard work to baling. They just go out in the
         windrow it and
         field and pick it up and bale it right out in the bale is
         and the hard work there is following along and picking up the bales.
         But those days we sent tne baler tft the hay field, then the farmer that
         we was baling for, he hauled the hay to the baler and he about half a
         dozen one-by-twelve planks nailed together,we you might say,
         then they'd load it on those planks and have about four horses to the
         plank, they'd pull up along side the baler then they'd put rope right
         in front of the load, fasten one to the wheel of the baler and
         an other to a post out here and then drive up and the boards slip right out
         from under the hay, you know, arid load of nay right there offKthe baler
         and then you'd have to hire a crew to get up and pitch it off into the
         A pretty slick rig.
         baler. See there was about six of us on the baler and then the farmer
         he'd have to have about three men — about two of those slips, unless he
         already had it stacked, he'd have to have about three men to haul it in
         on two slips. One fellow stayed out in the field-snd pitched,two fellows
         could drive the slip.
         It was quite an operation. And i think ^un'd §et hotter around an
         old hay baler than anywhere else.
         
         SS:   Well, would you just do— would you be able to do very much in a day?
         
         ES:   Yeah, we baled around about fifteen, twenty ton a day. I think that
         most of the time it only run about three and a half a ton, we got
         for baling it. So there was no big money ain it Then you had to buy
         your wire.
         
         SS:   Would you sleep out doing that, just like if you was a threshing crew?
         
         ES:   Yeah, once in a while we did, we used to, but most of the time we came
         home at night. We come home at nights. When we first started though
         we stayed out. Slept in the farmer's barn, or something like that, vou
         know. Usually baled the straw— that's pretty late in the fall "We us
         ually came home from baling the straw, but, of course, when we baled hay
         lots of times, we would sleep right out in the field, right out wltil the
         baler there. And lots of times we'd get up in the early morning and
         probably bale probably a hour before we went in for breakfast.
         
         SS:   You started doing this before you went into the war?
         
         ES:   Yeah. Started doing this before I went into the war. Well, I'll tell
         you, my father started baling, I believe it was 1912. He bought an old
         baler at a sale. Fact of the matter, he just bought it more to do his
         own baling than anything else. It was an old thing, old wooden thing,
         and he got it for little or nothing. He bought it at a, sale and started
         baling for himself, and by golly, his neighbor across the fence out
         here, a fellow by the name of Nelson, why he said, "John, why don't you
         over and bale mine?" So Dad did. Before he got through that, why,
         somebody wanted him to bale his, you know. Seme other neighboring farm
         er right there. Wanted him to bale his, so by golly, you know, he
         did quite a little baling with that old baler that year. And it started
         out the next year. "John bale my hay!" So, he run tit that first year
         gradually and piling jup on flim
         and the second year and business kept piling up on him, so he just went
         and bought him a baler! (Chuckles) Bought him a new one, new outfit,
         and that started it. Then he run that one for I don't know how many years,
         that was a horse power, too, and he run that I don't know how many years.
         Then he got rid of the old horse power and bought him one with a gas mo
         tor on it. And I think he had about two of those.
         
         SS:   Did you boys make pretty good money, as far as wages go, on the baler?
         
         ES:   No. we didn't get very much. Couldn't pay very much— I think it was about
         three or three and a half a ton what they baled for. iabout twenty
         With expenses there profit in it
         ton a day. Wasn't very muchA But we made a little. And then he ^usually had
         to hire about two men.
         
         SS:   Did you get to know the country pretty good when you were doing that?
         
         ES:   Yes, oh, yes, I'll say so. Yes, sure knew the country. Yes, we knew
         every place where we baled where they'd bring out lunch about the middle
         of the forenoon, too. (Chuckles) They sure knew that, places where we
         baled where we got lunch.
         
         SS:   Just some places would be good enough to feed you? While you were there?
         
         ES:   Oh, yeah. They usually fed us, while we was there. Oh, some places, why
         or some old couple, board,
         they'd rather pay a little more for the baling and let us ourselves
         than to feed us. We did that, too.
         
         SS:   Do you remember much what those places were like as far as— was it peo
         ple every hundred and sixty acres those days?
         
         ES:   Yeah. Well, I'll tell you— of course when we first started out, the
         farms wasn't as large as they are now. There was lots of hundred and sixbecause
         ty acre farms and two hundred— it was mostly horsepower. There wasn't
         very many tractors when we started out. So that's what put my dad
         out of business, is when they got this tractor business and combine bus
         iness. And then they got these power balers, they'd cut the hay and then
         windrow it, and then just go right out with the baler and pick it up and
         bale it right out in the field and just drop the bales along^there. My
         dad, he was an old man then, he was through with the baler by that time.
         But that's what came long. They just started doing that a little bit be
         fore — the last year or two that he baled, they started doing that.
         He was about done anyway.
         
         SS:   How were these farms doing in the teens, when you started baling? Were
         most of them in pretty good shape, or were the farmers struggling to get
         by?
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you—it was a struggle, ju : like it is now. Most of
         'em, seemed like 1 they never had too much money then, the farmers
         didn't. That was along about 1912.
         
         SS:   I've heard it said that after World War I, that it never did come back
         for the farmers. That the '20's were hard years.
         
         ES:   That's true. I come back in the '20's there— I only baled, I guess
         a little while after I came back. A couple of years, then I got married
         and then I went to farming by myself. And then I never did help on the
         baler only— lots of times in the wintertime, some fellow'd have a barn
         full of hay and they'd want to bale it, you know; 'course that takes
         extra help, and I used to go out and help when they'd get a job like that.
         But people didn't seem to have after the war, as I say, it seemed like
         everything went up before the war, machinery and stuff, and the price
         never did come down. And then they had substitutes; flour*, so it never
         did come back. When we first started, everything was horses, there wasn't
         any tractors in the country then. Everything was horsepower. And there
         was lots of hay, we had baled alfalfa, baled timothy, and we baled grain
         hay. We had all kinds of hay to bale, lots of it. So's you might
         say, every farmer— most of 'em always had a little hay to bale. Some
         of 'em'd fill their barn and then if they had any left, why they'd bale
         it and so forth. And then if they had a patch of wheat that had too
         many wild oats in it', They'd cut that to sell. Hay at that time sold
         about fifteen, twenty dollars; good hay. Now it's— just last winter it
         got up to eighty, ninety dollars a ton.
         
         SS:   Were most of your jobs small ones, then?
         
         ES:   No, we had some pretty good jobs; big jobs. That is, what I mean, we
         had several— I know we had quite a few jobs, alfalfa probably thirty or
         forty acre fields, something like that. Some of it. Most of it was five.
         ten acres,. Very few farmers had too big a field of alfalfa. Some
         Wad quite a little bit. 'Course when they had horses a lot of the
         farmers didn't like to feed alfalfa to the horses, they figured it was
         too washy. They thought it was good cow feed, but they didn't
         like to feed it to horses. And then before harvest, they'd take the
         mower machine and cut about four swaths around the wheat field, you see
         they they'd bale that.
         
         SS:   That's what they'd give horses?
         
         ES:   Feed that to the horses. And feed the cattle alfalfa.
         
         SS:   Did many, of the places still have the homestead cabins on them?
         
         ES:   Yeah. You betcha. A lot of 'em along that time had. I don't know a
         place in the country now that has a homestead cabin. I dont believe
         I do, since you mention it. wien we started to bale hay, there was lots
         of places that had old homestead cabins still there. But I don't know
         a one of any more.
         
         SS:   Most of the families big? Or were there all different kinds?
         
         ES:   Well, I'll tell you, in those days— most of the families were pretty
         fair size. You know this country, where I grew up and then around Moscow
         here, it's principally Scandinavian country, you know. Now you take
         over the hill where I grew up, that was practically all Scandinavian
         and all of 'em had pretty good size families. And over across the hill
         here towards Blaine country in there, and then on a little further this
         way, a little further west down Thorn Creek country that was— around
         Uniontown, and Colton that's German settlement in there. And there's
         where you saw your good horses and your larger farms and good crops,
         around Uniontown and Colton, in around there. They had some nice farms
         down there. And they had some nice stock.
         
         SS:   How was it that they got ahead? Was it because they were on the prairie?
         some of the go. That's choice country down through there. 'Course you take out this
         way, Troyf that's mostly timber. And that didn't amount to anything until
         here in the last— since World War II, you might say. Then they got to
         using fertilizer. You take up there at Troy, when I worked for the
         Latah County Graingrowers, " for twenty years, and they got
         a warehouse up there at Troy, they had a little old warehouse there, and
         if those fellows up there got twentk thirty bushels to the acre,1 they got
         a big crop. And since World War II, they've increased that warehouse at
         Troy and Deary both about three times—now- fertilizer up there
         and they get seventy-five and eighty bushels crop just the same as they
         do down here. Yeah, that fertilized sure has did something for the coun
         try, out this way. Course the country this way and this way, that's all
         prairie country. That timber soil, you take the timber off of it, I've
         heard oldtimers say that it leaves a certain amount of turpentine in the
         soil, and it takes years before it gets out. It don't produce
         too since they got to using fertilizer on it, though, ii will 
         just as good a crop as anywhere.
         
         SS:   Was it easy on the prairie country to start farming right away? Was
         it hard to clear that brush?
         
         ES:   No brush on the prairie. Now you take my wife's dad down here, he came
         from South Carolina to Madeira, California, that's down in the Fresno
         country. He started working for a big cattle baron(too--no-isy to hear)
         that run cattle clear across the state there.
         He owned thousands and thousands of acres of land, so they leased—and
         dad farmed there,him and his brother.
         they couldn't get along, they was farming to-
         gether, so she wanted to get out of there. So Stella's dad got out of
         what he could—mhis brohkers selling out to he came up in the
         Walla Walla country. And you know in the early days the railroad company—
         the government give the railroads every other quarter section of land
         when they built the railroad; through here. Well, came up from the Walla
         Walla country, 'course he didn't have no money, but he had a promise of
         getting some more from his brothers back there. He bought a hundred and
         sixty acres from the railroad company down here at Dodge, Washington—
         you know where Dodge is, down below Lewiston— between Dodge and Pomeroy
         was no brush on it.
         well, that's where he bought. It was all bunchgrass. You've heard of
         bunchgrass? That's what the buffalo lived on those days. And he bought
         this hundred and sixty, it was all bunchgrass. And he talked the bank
         in the notion of loaning him some money to get it plowed. He didn't have
         a team or nothing. And he got some plows in there early in the fall and
         they plowed there all winter; plowed that hundred and sixty up. And then
         in '— February- he seeded it to wheat.
         
         SS:   The whole thing?
         
         ES:   The whole thing, hundred and sixty acres. And that next year, that fall,
         he got enough off that, he paid for his and sixty, that he had
         borrowed money to buy,and all his debts, for plowing it and seeding it.
         And he did pretty good the next year. And then he kept on building,
         kept on buying and he had thirteen hundred acres of land in his name
         at one time. And then after his boys grew up and they was big farmers
         down there. And then they got a couple of dry years in a row down
         there and just about broke the old fellow. And his boys got sick on him
         and he sold off— got rid— I think he lost part of it,sold what he'could
         left and went there up there by Oakesdale. He lost both of his boys.
         
         SS:   They died?
         
         ES:   Yeah, lost both of his sons. Then they were getting old. My wife and
         her sister was the only two kids that was home. And when they got out
         of Walla Walla down there, they wanted 'em — let the kids shift for them
         selves and then, buy a small ranch that they could take care of, the two
         of 'em, you know. Get 'em a cow and chickens. He wanted to farm. He
         was a big farmer and he thought he «eould do it again, you know. So he
         lost his boys. And so about the second year that Stella and I were mar
         ried, they had to quit and so we took 'em over. We took 'em in with us
         til they died. Kept 'em til they died.
         
         SS:   Did they stay for very long?
         
         ES:   Yeah. She passed away at eighty-five and I think he was in his eighties
         when he died, I think he was eighty three or four.
         
         SS:   When did he get that prairie land?
         
         ES:   Well, they came out here— they must have came out here right after we
         did, along about 1902 or three, I think we was here a little ahead of
         them. out here about '98. 'Course, when we came to Idaho my dad
         could have got some homestead land up here in Nez Perce County, up here
         around Nez Perce. But he started farming he looked into it, it
         all— there was nothing by mountains. Alright for cattle, I guess.
         He never tried. But if he'd aknown it when we first came here— when he
         was gonna homestead up in the Big Bend country, if he'd known it when we
         first stopped then, he might have looked into it.
         
         SS:   What? That there was still prairie country that was ?
         
         ES:   It: was homestead land up there. I know a party that got a
         homestead there just about the time we come here, a little after we come
         here, that was good land,
         
         SS:   This was around Nez Perce?
         
         ES:   Yes, it was around Nez Perce.%tQuite a while after we got here, up in
         Bovill, up in that country around Pierce and up back in there you could
         get those stone and timber claims, they was available at that time.
         
         SS:   Weren't some of those where the lumber companies was paying people to—?
         
         ES:   I don't know, I don't know about that.
         
         SS:   I've heard that from several people.
         
         ES:   I know that we'd been here several years and my dad and another guy moved
         a widow woman up in there above Bovill, and she had took up a stone and
         timber claim up there, out of Bovill, somewhere there. And she was
         going up there to spend the summer on it to get proved up on it. I know
         he Shoved her up there, I don't know who brought her back.
         
         SS:   Was she at all concerned about going up there alone?
         
         ES:   I guess she was a widow and she wasn't married to this guy, but I guess
         they was fixing to get married, and he went with them up there. He had
         his team and rig. He didn't stay up there all the time, but I don't know
         what he was doing in Moscow,
         what his business was, but he went up there with them. And Dad left him
         up there. I don't know just what his name was, Dad knew him, got acquain
         ted with hinu on the way up there, but I think he told my father that he
         kind of went back and forth up there in the wintertime. And in the summergoing
         time while she was up there they was to get married, but they wasn t
         married then. She had two or three kids, seven or eight year old kids.
         My dad said there sure was some swell timber on that place up there.
         
         SS:   Pretty good timber, but she couldn't farm it probably.
         
         ES:   Couldn't farm it. But I know a fellow that built this seea outfit, his
         name was Homer Wilson, he came here and he started working in a grocery
         store here for a man by the name of Washburn. And Old Man Washburn he
         sent him up there,he went up there and hefiled on a stone and timber
         claim. He lived up there and proved up on it and then he married Old
         Man Washburn's daughter. And then he sold his stor\e and timber claim,
         then him and his father-in-law built this Dumas seed company down here.
         That used to be Washburn-Wilson. His name was Wilson and he married ^
         Washburn— they built that big outfit.
         
         SS:   I wonder if he sold that land to the timber company?
         
         ES:   I don't know. I don't know who he sold it to. I don't know whether he
         sold the timber off— I know Potlatch eventually got it. Whether he sold
         it to Potlatch then, I don't know. But that's where he got his start
         ana money and went in with his father-in-law and they built this Washburn-
         Wilson seed company.
         
         SS:   That's really where he got his start.
         
         ES:   That's how he got his start. But the Wellses up there, I'm pretty sure
         they homesteaded their's. What they had there. I don't see why they
         didn't homestead. Go back out on the ridge there and get some good land,
         instead of taking up there in the timber
         But, I guess they thought that was the best part of it. Anyway
         they could get logs to build the house.
         
         SS:   Most of those ridges out there must have had timber on 'em, too.
         
         ES:   I think a lot of 'em did.
         
         SS:   People at first just didn't realize that that was going to be better farm
         land.
         
         ES:   But you take way out on that Driscoll Ridget I doubt if there was ever
         any timber out there to amount to anythings5,n the drawls there might have.
         Ouitside of the canyon..,But he could have got £ a homestead "; had
         some farm land on it anyway. I think that wa-.; all timber what he got
         there. But, I guess they did pretty good. They built that house and
         they had kind of a halfway house. They made quite a bit of money off of
         travelers going back in there on these stone and timber claims
         and one thing and another. Stopover place to eat, I guess they could put
         'em up for the night, I suppose, I think they did. They had such a big
         old house there, I think they did. Anyway, I know they fed a lot of
         people there. I guess they figured they did just as good.
         
         SS:   I've heard said that it was the main stopping place. Troy and Collins.
         Did they keep that business for quite a few years of having people stop?
         
         ES:   I don't know. I never knew too much about 'em. I wen^-^herenthe winter
         of 1919, worked with them in the woods. But it wasn't going at that time.
         I think it had been stopped quite a little while. Their main trade was
         when people had those stone and timber claims up in there, that was when
         they did their biggest business. People went back and forth up there to
         file on or proving up.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13555</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Settle1</previous>
      <next>Settle3</next>
      <disp_name>Settle2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
