<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">9/22/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Nellie Wood Smith, 1975-09-22, Interview #3 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:30:21</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Smith, Nellie Wood</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #3</intnum>
      <occupation>Homemaker</occupation>
      <birthyear>1892</birthyear>
      <residence>Bovill, McGary Butte</residence>
      <origin>Came from Missouri with parents, settling in the area c.1900</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#CCC"&gt;CCC&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crafts"&gt;crafts&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#clothing"&gt;clothing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sewing"&gt;sewing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pregnancy"&gt;pregnancy&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#childbirth"&gt;childbirth&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#doctors"&gt;doctors&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hospitals"&gt;hospitals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#babies"&gt;babies&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#nurses"&gt;nurses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sewing"&gt;sewing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#crafts"&gt;crafts&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homemakers"&gt;homemakers&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#McGary Butte"&gt;McGary Butte&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13510</file_name>
      <mp3>13511.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13511.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Belief in keeping women's hands busy; needle work; using leftover CCC twine; knitting
               while watching sports on tv
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Women's hands were always busy; different kinds of needle
               work. Using twine left over by CCCs from ribes (plant) control
               work. An old lady who liked to knit while watching sports
               on TV.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Nell's first stitching as a child; played with sewing</title>
            <synopsis>Her first stitching as a child. Mother gave her sewing to
               play with.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1140</time>
            <title>Nell's ability to make clothes without patterns</title>
            <synopsis>Her ability to make clothes without patterns. She took to sewin&lt;
               more than many others did.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Sister Edna tried to sew pants from a flour sack, Nell accidentally wore them to school;
               making clothes for others
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Sister Edna's attempt to sew pants from a flour sack. One
               morning Nell wore those pants to school by mistake. Making
               clothes for someone else, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>making clothes; her first sewing machine in 1913; buying material from tralveing Italian
               lady; making dresses for reciptal week before giving birth
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Making clothes. Her first sewing machine - 1913. Buying
               material from a travelling Italian lady. Making three dresses
               for a piano recital one week before the birth of her first child;
               description of the dresses.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Waited at home expecting labor to begin; doctor arrives, concerned due to feet first
               birth; Nell delivered the baby so quickly that doctor told her to hold back
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>She waited at mother's home, expecting labor to begin at
               any time. Arrival of the doctor. His fear of trouble because
               baby's feet came out first. She delivered so quickly the
               doctor told her to hold back.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3480</time>
            <title>Story of neighbor lady giving birth, being slapped by doctor to get her mad enough
               to bear down
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>A neighbor lady had so much trouble in labor that doctor
               slapped her in the face, getting her mad enough to bear down
               harder. Doctor dreamed he had a baby. Belief in laying in
               bed ten days after delivery.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Nell's only baby girl had malformation at birth; operated on at six days old; Nell
               at hospital when baby worsened, doctor never came; baby died and they brought her
               home; never heard from doctor
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Her only baby girl had a malformation in her large
               intestine. She was operated on at six days, because they told
               Nell that was the only chance she had. Nell was at the hospital
               when the baby worsened. She asked the nurse to call the
               doctor but he never came. She took the dead baby home, and
               never heard from the doctor. Complication from the
               operation.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>Baby care information handed down from mother to daughter and midwives; lots of babies
               born near Bovill; superstitions around baby care; colic
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Precautions for baby care handed down from mother to daughter;
               midwives. New doctor joked about there being so many babies around Bovill that it
               would make Teddy Roosevelt
               happy. Knowing by a baby's cry when to pick it up. Idea
               that cats could steal baby's breath. Had to be careful about
               baby getting colic from fresh air; hot water bottle treatment.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5220</time>
            <title>Story of baby being raised on mare's milk; mother's needlework for pleasure, not income</title>
            <synopsis>She heard of a baby raised on mare's milk, crossing the
               plains. Mother's needlework was for herself, not for income,
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Birth of first child; lore of childbirth. Death of baby daughter. Learning sewing
         and needlework. 9-22-75 1.5 hr 33p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         SAM SCRAGER: This interview with Nell Smith was made at her home in Bovill
         on September 22, 1975.
         
         NELL SMITH: ...most of it before I came here, then I began to learn it when I was
         just
         a little kid. Mother always did that work, so much. Their mother and their grandmothers,
         you know, were always doing something like that. They never sat down with their hands
         empty or idle. They er going all the time they were visiting or talking, their hands
         went income kind of work. I tried to get that pillowslip - I just laid it out here
         the
         other day...
         
         SS:  Now what were the different kids of work again?
         
         NS:   Well, there was embroidery, and knitting, crochet, tatting, and this weaving
         - they
         had a little frame board, you know, that they the twine went on to. They made so many
         tidies and hot mats and things - hot dish mats. And it was at the time that the CCCs
         were
         here - then, that we made those. Maybe you've heard of them - the CCCs?
         
         SS:   Un-huh. You made them for the CCCs?
         
         NS:   No. We made 'em. But after they'd - you know, they had balls and balls of twine
         -
         great big balls of string that they'd mark out the spot that they had cleaned from
         your
         wild gooseberry - what's it called?
         
         SS:   Ribes.
         
         NS:   Ribes. I had forgotten the name. And then stake it off and the next fella would
         work up to it and they would try to clean all the Ribbes around that area.
         
         SS:  So they had a twine that they brought into the area? And that's what you used?
         
         NS:   Well, then they'd go on to the next one and probably they'd forget, they'd get
         lost
         with their twine or go to lunch or to supper or something. And the next time start
         in some
         place else. And I know a lot of the folks found balls or half balls of that string
         in the
         woods where they had been working.
         
         SS:   Well, would they use that, for - for macrame or what?
         
         NS:   You mean the people here?
         
         SS:   Yah, what would they use the twine for?
         
         NS:   No, we had frames, whatever size we wanted. I think that's what they call
         the macrame now. But we just called it mats, I think.
         
         SS:   What'd you make out of that? Place mats or what?
         
         NS:   Anything you wanted. Placemats and the things for the back of your chairs, for
         protection, hot dish mats for an the table, and lots of them. They even
         made bedspreads of it. And those were all - you see, they were strings put across
         and then was put the other way - would cross.
         
         SS:   Would people ever dye the material first? Or just use it as the color?
         
         NS:   No, they used the white bedspread. And, I don't know, there was one lady
         that her husband, that made an awfully pretty bedspread but I've forgotten whether
         they had it trimmed in any color - a touch or it or not. But then it was made of
         a ball of that twine. He found it cached in - stuck into the woods.
         
         SS:   What color was the twine?
         
         NS:   Well, it was supposed to be white, but it was kinda a beige white, or eggshell
         type.
         These strings, you know, were put across at nails at each side, and you hooked them
         on these nails back and forth. And they were oh, about - well, it all depends on how
         big youViant your squares between them. You could make them quite a ways apart
         or you could make them just very small, whatever size you put your nails in there.
         And then that one diagonal - I mean the logitude and the latitude of the thing. Then
         you go along and hook across the corners of each place they crossed and tie that
         knotted. And tie that good and strong and onto the next one. And keep on until you
         tied that all solid. And then you would go to work with the scissors. When you got
         through, turn it over and take about half of it and clip it with the scissors and
         that
         made a puff ball where each one of those crossings was. Now isn't that what they
         call macrame now?
         
         SS:   I'm not sure how macrame is done. I think, it's similar. It sure is
         similar, anyway.
         
         NS:   Well, I haven't seen any of it. I haven't had any experiences yet - I haven't
         been out anywhere lately where they have been sewing or doing that kind of work.
         No sit still Ernie, OK? You sit still now. Don't run around. Where are you going
         Ernie? Are you going tn the kitchen? Oh. Well, lets - now that's not the way to
         the kitchen. Well, oh, sometimes they would scarves of it or they could make, you
         know, the
         bonnets or anything like that, you know. There was so much of it that, oh, it seemed
         like the woods were full of the twine. And everybody was making something of twine.
         
         SS:   Was that partly 'cause there was so little money at the time, during the
         depression?
         
         NS:   Well, it was just something just laying there and probably going to waste.
         In time it would all weather - it'd be weather-beaten and everything if it layed there.
         When they had finished that certain area and left it and gone to the next, then the
         CCC
         had gone then, about that time. After they left, why, of course, it layed there,
         and anybody that found one, a cone of it, would pick it up and bring it on in. And
         well,
         the people were thrifty enough that just looked like a shame to leave that lay there
         and go to rot, you know.
         
         SS:  Well, what do you think was the most popular of the different handwork? Was
         knitting the most popular? Is that what people did the most?
         
         NS:   Well, a whole lot depends on the person. Some people took to knitting, some
         took to embroiderying, and.like that. And some people can do all those things. I
         could, I know. I could embroidery and knit and crochet and tatt. I could do all those
         things myself. This drawn work too. All this drawn work - they draw the threads
         in a piece of material, and then you embroidery into those things. There's an old
         lady here, she was getting up in years, but she didn't let it bother her any. She
         was a live-wire, just up and going, you know. Busier than a birddog. She was a
         German lady and that counts for part of it. But she said that whenever - when she
         was little
         her mother taught her to knit. Gee, I think, it was about four years old she learned
         to knit. Anyhow she said anytime that their hands were empty, that they had nothing
         to do, they got their knitting out. And they knitted their own socks. Most of them
         had big families and that's quite a job for one person to knit socks for - well, their
         husband and the rest of the kids too. So she had learned to knit and so she just
         kept it up. And she'd knit socks for her grandkids and all the little ones and every
         once in a while she'd knit a pair for somebody else, that wanted some of that done.
         Oh, she was quite a hand to watch sports on TV. And she'd get her knitting and get
         out and get herself all fixed up, you know, and she'd turn on TV. And then she'd
         watch, the - oh, what is it they have their games, or - well, she wanted to he sure
         to
         find out who - and she'd sit there and just be knitting to beat the cats a fighting,
         you
         know. Her hands just flew and knitting an intricate pattern of a bedspread,
         a knitted bedspread.
         
         SS:   Without looking at it?
         
         NS:   Un—huh. She just never looked at it. She just knew what she was doing and
         once in a while glance down but she didn't never miss a thing that was going on on
         that
         I was over there one afternoon when she was sitting, working at it. She was
         talking to us too, at the same time, you know. Visiting with this other lady and I
         that went there. Here now, listen Ernie, now sit down or else...
         
         Ernie:  .. .an that end.
         
         NS:   Well, now come on, sit down somewhere so you won't bother us.
         
         SS:   What did the work that you did- when you were young and doing handwork - what
         would you do? What kind of things would you make?
         
         NS:   Well, I had- I started with hem stitching when I wasn't old. Yes, I
         was just about that size because we were at Grandmother's just before we came out
         West. We were at grandmother's - or at great-grandmother's and visited with her
         a while. I suppose Mother was kinda making the rounds before she left for the West
         because we didn't expect to ever get back. I had forgotten about it though, but I
         had left a little handkerchief at great-grandmother's house and I just had forgotten
         it. And when I was about 13, I think, about 13 when I was living out at Troy. We were
         looking through her trunk one day - she was living with my aunt - right there at the
         mill. So we lived at the mill too. Dad was working at the mill. And we would be
         kinda bored and she would say, "Come on,lets go in there and see what you need. I
         think I've got so-and*-so" and she'd be talking about, "in my old trunk in here. Lets
         go in there and see what we can find it." And that was just my keen delight to
         look through something like that. But we went in there and she was talking and
         explaining everything to me as we went. And she came across this handkerchief
         and said, "Here, this is yours. I'll give it to you now. I've had it long enough."
         And she said, "You left it when you were to visit us that time in Marceline." And
         she said that Mother had that I had made that handkerchief when I was six
         years old. And I had pulled threads and then hem-stitched it. You know what
         hem-stitching looks like, don't you?
         
         SS:   Um...tell me.
         
         NS:   Well, there would be little - you know, the threads are all even crossed at
         the
         place that they have pulled the threads. And then you take a little bit at - oh, you
         can do it several ways, but you can have little straight up and down things by the
         time
         you take little bite with the needle and tie it off and go on to the next one and
         tie,
         you know. Or you can tie that and when you put the bottom of it, you don't take the
         same bunch, you take half of each one and that makes it go zig zag. And mine was
         that zig zag kind.
         
         SS:   At the age of six?
         
         NS:   Um-hum. I can't see how I did it but Grandma said I did, you know. And
         she said that Mother said that I had made it. I know I can remember sitting beside
         Mother when she would be sewing and when I wasn't more than oh, 3, I think or
         something. But like lots of little kids I was always right at her side. "And I
         want to do it too" whatever she was doing. So she went. one day - I think, Dad
         had made me a little doll cradle - and she whipped up, she made me a little feather
         bed for that cradle and then she fixed it with a pillow - or bo Isters it was, in
         those
         days it was bo Isters. And she gave me some scraps, you know, and she had made me
         a little quilt. And I played with those doll things. I can remember my sewing
         machine was just like it was sitting there, and I sat against the wall right by her
         at her side and she was busy sewing and I was right by her close. And she'd, of course,
         she'd have handwork to do too, with her buttonholes, and all. And so she'd give me,
         to keep me out of her hair and to keep me from pestering her, I guess, why she'd give
         me something to do. Some sewing or something, like make a doll dress or something.
         So, I would sew those things and I can remember that. I can remember the scene.
         Say, now, listen Dad, sit down and sit still. Well, money's foot, you haven't got
         any so it hadn't oughta worry you any.
         
         SS:   You can remember the scene?
         
         NS:   Um-hum. I can just remember Mother sitting - I don't remember much
         about it. Well, there was a bed over behind, but I can remember that picture in my
         mind of her working at the sewing machine and I was down there beside her. And
         I was sewing whatever little trinkets I had to sew. She'd give me some things - maybe
         cut out the doll dress or something like that for me. And I was trying. And I don't
         know what that looked like at the time. But I was sewing too, anyway. It was
         probably mussy, sewing up those things, I don't remember them.
         
         SS:   But this was even before you were six.
         
         NS:  Oh, yes. That was when I was just a little tyke. Just in her hair all the ti
         to sew too. But then - so I know that I was doing the other, fancy work. Well, she
         let me do that, of course. I was learning to use my needle and thread and all. By
         working there with Mother so much, I had - anyhow, I was just learning - like. It's
         clumsy for a little kid just starting, you know, and their needle doesn't go where
         they
         want it too and all. I guess, eventually I kept on and I suppose improved on it and
         I got so I could sew it. I have that little old handkerchief here yet. Grandma gave
         it to me. I didn't remember it atall.
         
         SS:   Do you remember doing much work as you were growing up out here in the
         West?
         
         NS:   Handwork?
         
         SS:   Yah.
         
         NS:   Oh, yes. We had it in school on the first - the first school we had here.
         
         SS:   In Bovill?
         
         NS:   No. It was the second school that we had had here. And every Friday afternoon
         why we'd have sewing. The first year, we had Mrs. Bovill in and she read
         books to us. She read those books that would be most interesting. And, what's his
         name, who wrote Freckles and the - some of those books. And she'd come and read
         as many chapters as she could before the time was up. And she read those books
         clear through to us that way. And that was interesting.
         
         SS:   But did you already know how to - when you took up the handwork in school -
         you already knew how to do it pretty well?
         
         NS:   Yes, by that time because I was making a lot of my own clothes by that
         time. Well, that picture out there this morning was lying over there under the
         blouse. I noticed it. I was looking at it and there's my blouse. But I was getting
         pretty
         catty with the sewing machine and cutting and everything then by that time. I had
         a
         white Indian linen blouse I had made and it had little tiny fine tucks across the
         
         these little patches of them. And then kinda puffedpie sleeve with the little puff
         here
         and lace at the end of it. I that's about all.
         
         SS:   Did you need a pattern to make something like that?
         
         NS:   I did at the time, but I soon got so I didn't need any pattern, after
         I was married and got to doing more of it all the time. Well, maybe some before
         I was married, but.... (I don't know what's a matter with me.) Before that
         I had cut my own patterns mostly because I'd kinda size up about what I wanted, and
         maybe take measurements if it was for somebody else. So I'd take the measurements
         with
         a tape measure and I would cut that and cut some of those patterns myself. But
         most of them I just went kinda by guess or, well, not exactly by guess either.
         Maybe I'd kinda lay down a garment that did fit and was just about what I wanted,
         and then I'd cut it by that. But you can't get an accurate pattern by that unless
         you're
         pretty catty with the pins and the scissors. I made all the wedding clothes for one
         of my granddaughters living here with us. See, her parents had separated and I
         inherited the three kids. She wouldn't let him have them and he wouldn't let her
         have them. But they agreed to let me have them. So, anyway, I made all of her
         clothes as she grew up. And everybody always said, "Why, Nell, that kid just looks
         like she just stepped out of a band bolCor something like that. You make those things
         look so tailored, like they're from the store." "Well, heck," I said, "It's no trick
         hardlv. Just whack them out and an at it me to do than them. I suppose it was because
         I'd practiced it for a long while.
         And I liked it, that's one thing.
         
         SS:   When you were growing up, was that usual? Did most of the kids have their
         clothes made at home? Or make them themselves?
         
         NS:   Oh, most everything was made at home. Mother,I know,used to do sewing
         for one of the ladies in town. She had quite a large family and they were awfully
         good friends of ours. And she was always sending over a bunch of material for Mother
         to make up. She would try to do it herself sometimes but goodness!, she would -
         I don't know - instead of making a felled seam or something like that, you know, a
         nice smooth seam, she would have it a half dozen different thicknesses piled up
         so it would make a knot , you know, where all the seams would cross and all. She
         was trying awfully hard and she was doing the best she could but she didn't know how.
         She hadn't - she wasn't as used to it as I was. But I just kind of grew up knowing
         because Mother was that way and I was in the midst of it all the time. But now, my
         sister wasn't. She didn't take to it so much and, I guess, maybe Mather didn't - she
         probably didn't bother Mother so much about it. And Mother's have to kind of
         give her some rags to keep her out of her hair - like she did me. I guess, because
         Edna, my sister, was well - we told a joke on her that - they used to use a
         lot of flour sacks. Mother made me a whole outfit. She made me the underskirt,
         you know, the underskirt had a band around the waist, and then the skirt went on
         down and there was a flounce - a gathered ruffle - went onto it about at the knees,
         like
         that, and it was gathered full from there on down. And that had little tucks in that
         flounce and I think she had crocheted lace on the bottom of it, too. I don't remember
         if it was crocheted lace or if it was some store lace. But, Edna and a little girl,
         a
         neighbor to us, took a notion that they were going to sew something. And they
         laughed about - well, they didn't laugh about it now. My sister passed away but the
         other one, every once in a while - I -saw her at the picnic not so long ago, and she
         asked me if I remember the sewing that she and Edna did. And I said yes. And I
         just carft forget it yet. She gets a big kick out of it, she just laughs.
         
         SS:   Well, what happened?
         
         NS:   Well, they said they were going to sew. They were going out to the playhouse
         and they were going to sew. They asked - Mother wanted to know what they were going
         to do . They each had a flour sack. Well, they didn't want to tell her.
         They'd wait and show here when they got through. So she let them alone. And I
         don't remember whether they had any pattern. I think maybe mother cut out
         a kind of a half pattern out of a newspaper for them. I'm not sure but anyway she
         gave it to them. And they were supposed to be a pair of panties and they had the
         hems at the bottom and the gathers on the belt at the top. So they worked real hard
         and, of course, they had a piece of material then about that wide at the top that
         had
         to be gathered up so that it would fit the belt - be smaller. So they gathered it
         up
         and when they got it through, why they had just put it on plain and when they got
         to the
         end of it, all those gathers went in one bunch. Instead of making it even all the
         way around, the gathers, they put it all together plain and then had a whole bunch
         of gathers right at the one side. The joke was - that was pretty funny. Well,
         anyhow, they came in fussing about it, "Well, what's the matter with these things?"
         She hadn't asked any questions before and she didn't know what to do about it. And
         they didn't look like she thought they ought to. And I was in a hurry from school
         one
         morning and I grabbed those pants and put them on. I was in a hurry to get to school.
         And I came home a fussing at noon. I was just about to have a fit. And mother said,
         "What's the matter with you?" And I said, "These pesky pants that Edna made."
         I said, "I had to walk crosslegged and they'd fall down halfway." And I got those
         off
         just as quick as I could. I reached in the cupboard and got a hold of, I thought they
         were my pair and was in such a hurry. I thought it was mine. And Mother and Edna
         just laughed until they were sick, pretty near. I told 'em what a time I had with
         those
         things. And I said I was afraid I'd fall down everytime I took a step. And Georgie
         was the other girl, she just laughs everytime she thinks of it, how her sewing turned
         out,
         
         SS:  The way they were set up, they would really just fall down off you all the time
         you weren't careful.
         
         NS:   Yes. Of course, if you could get the band pinned but whatever it was, why
         they were safe. But here were all the gathers in one place and the rest was just
         plain around. So - I can say, when I was 16 or 17-16 I think - when Mother
         was sewing for other people quite a lot and the girl worked up at the restaurant,
         her
         mother r||n the restaurant. And her name was Bean, Ernie Bean, Ernestine Beam.
         She brought up some material and wanted Mother to make her some dresses for her
         to wait tables in. She helped her mother in the restaurant. Well, Mother thought
         she just didn't have time, she had so much on her hands she just couldn't do it.
         Just then, anyhow, she couldn't. And I was showing her one my dresses that I had
         just finished and sha said, "Why, you made that?" and I said, "Yes." Well, she
         said, "Why don't you make my dresses then?" Well, I had never been sewing for
         anybody else, I was scared too. Well, she said, "You just go ahead and make them"
         she said. "That's good enough for me." I made her - she wanted the dresses made
         out of black sateen. And they were trimmed, around the edge of the belt there was
         a little piping. You know what piping is? The edge of it show«?just like a fitting,
         you
         know. 
         
         (break) END OF SIDE A
         
         NELL SMITH: Well, like this would be and that edge of it was bound, with a little
         -
         like a little binding and then the little blue edge was showing. You know that little
         streak of blue. And the other was two suits. I can't remember what the other
         was, but anyhow, she wanted them made shirtwaist style and with plain skirts.
         And the button holes from the neck to the bottom, that was the style then. And I
         used to make all those button holes by hand. And I'd hate to have to do it now. But
         that's what she wanted so that's what I made. I took the job and made her two suits
         and she liked to have a fit about them. She thought they were so nice. They were just
         what she wanted.
         
         SS:   How long did it take you to do something like that?
         
         NS:   Oh, well, I guess, a few days.
         
         SS:   Did you have your own sewing machine?
         
         NS:   No. It was whenever Mother wasn't using it, I would. We just had her sewing
         machine. That one he bought for me in 1913. And that was the first year we were
         married. And that's the machine that he bought. The machine agent came along and
         we proceeded to get one. We were going to move to ourselves. We were still building
         this house and we were living with Mother. We were at her place yet until we could
         get
         our house finished. I was pregnant and was doing up a lot of sewing and he bought
         the
         machine for me. And it was the 5th of August that we got it and my baby was born
         the 30th of August. It was just about not quite a month after that. But I was just
         a
         sewing up a storm there because Mother was - and my sister were going to - my
         sister was taking music^at the time - had been from Mrs. Klickner. Her husband was
         depot agent here and they lived up on that hill by McDonalds. And she had been teaching
         this class quite a while and she had arranged for a recital that Saturday night, I
         think. So my Mother and my aunt lived near us over there and she was to go with
         her to the recital that night. So they were supposed to go at 9 o'clock. There used
         to be an old Italian lady, I think she was, or some foreign person, that used to pedal
         things through the town. Here she'd coma every once in a while with yards and yards
         of dress materials and all fancy tidies and paintings and things to sell.
         
         SS:   Paintings?
         
         NS:   Yah. They were, I suppose, done by machinery or something. Dora, I think
         we called her. I think that was her name. But she'd just come with the biggest
         suitcases you ever saw. You wondered how in the world she could possibily carry them.
         But she came. And she liked us. She'd been there before, several times. So we
         always stopped and talked to her and looked at all of.' pretties she had. And sometimes
         bought. She was real keen about just felt at home at our place. So anyhow, that
         was just a week before my baby came that I started out - that she came there. Well,
         I picked it out and I said, "Now that way you can have your new dress, you know, for
         the recital up there." I pitch in and make them. So I pitched in and made those
         three dresses for them.
         
         SS:   Three dresses?
         
         NS:   Un-huh.
         
         SS:   For your sister, for your-
         
         NS:   Mother and - oh, one, two, three - yes. My sister Edna, and aunt Mary and
         Mother. And Aunt Mary was a large one, about 225 or 250. And she had a light - rather
         light - blue, a p retty blue dress. It was the full length dress. And it had - oh,
         I guess it was just about, you know, where they were. About that length then.
         I don't remember so much what it was made of but I think - oh, I know, - they had
         that kinda of an apron like thing - a tunic affair that was pointed in front and
         then shaped up toward the back.
         
         SS:   You did this one week before you had your child?
         
         NS:   Yes. And, but I was having fun. I was just hurrying like everything because
         I
         was afraid I wasn't going to get those three dresses out.
         
         SS:   I'll bet. Was that the only - the main way to get material then from this lady
         or did they have much in toown?
         
         NS:   No, they didn't have anything like that. She carried quite a lot of fancy materials
         and that was a part - it had a silky flower woven in, you know, fine flowers.
         
         SS:   Did she go from town to town, this lady?
         
         NS:   Yes, she went all over this part of the country. Everybody knew her.
         
         SS:   Did she stop by the house and say ? Is that how?
         
         NS:   Yes. She came right to the house and we always welcomed her. We'd say ,
         "Come on in" And she felt at home so she would come in and talk and laugh. But
         she didn't talk real plain, all of it, but we could understand her. But that dress
         I
         made for Aunt Mary, I think hers had that little silk, kinda edging on it.
         
         SS:   On the tunic?
         
         NS:   On the tunic, un-huh. And I got hers done and made Edna's and she
         was kinda slender, tall and slender. Now hers was a tangerine color. It was made,
         I think, with the eeam went down the side and was puckered up here with
         kinda a slash.
         
         SS:   In the front?
         
         NS:   In the side, front. And this piece was gathered up here and that one straight.
         That was - a lot of them made that way then. And there was some kind of a droop there.
         The collar affair of it cme across this way and then the other piece lapped through
         like
         that. And hers had the lacy fringe all around that collar.
         
         SS:  Sounds very fancy.
         
         NS:   They were. Real sssy dresses, and...
         
         SS:   Did you have patterns for those?
         
         NS:   Um-hum. Just had the common pattern that we all would use for things like
         that. Whenever I wanted something else, well, I just put it on without that.
         
         SS:   Did you have a pattern for each - the size - that each one was? Or did you know
         the size?
         
         NS:   No. I'd just take their measurements with the tape measure and then add to or
         take from. Maybe pin it big and then if it was going to be too large for them, add
         to it.
         Edna's was that kind that had the surplus -
         
         SS:   Surplus in the top.
         
         NS:   Un-huh. In the top. My mother's then - her's was black taffeta. It was made
         with these, kinda a panel in the front, here. And those panels were placed in there
         like that.
         
         SS:   Pleated right in the front.
         
         NS:   Un-huh. Just across here -
         
         SS:   Across the chest. . .
         
         NS:   But his piece here was lacy, some kind of a lace front.
         
         SS:   Lace in the collar?
         
         NS:   Well, this was across here and down to the waistline.
         
         SS:   Oh, I see. Across the front.
         
         NS:   Un-huh. It was,I think , white lace in there. But these others - the edge of
         her - the other thing - where it met the lace, had a pleat like your shirt front.
         Like that
         that went down on each side of it. Well, that was piped in deep rose color to kinda
         shed off so much of that black. And that was piped in that rose color and piped on
         the sleeves,on the cuffs, and on the belt.
         
         SS:   Well, now, where did you get the ideas for the design? Were they just dresses
         that were being worn at the time?
         
         NS:   Yes, it was. We would pick up a magazine or catalogue or something and
         saw something I like, well, I would copy it usually. I do yet, go quite a lot. I
         find something I like in a catalogue I like, why I go ahead and make it. I don't so
         much anymore. I never get time to sew and I' m about to forget how.
         
         SS:  Did you make all three dresses before you had your kid?
         
         NS:   Um-hum. I got mother's all done and I was working on it the day of the recital.
         I was working right up to the time and I was scared I wasn't going to get it done.
         I
         was hurrying like everything. So part of it I didn't get stitched solid or something.
         I know I had to almost leave part of it. I had to leave it to be finished afterwards.
         
         But I got pret-near everything - oh, I know - the hooks
         and eyes. I had to leave those off. I had to put pins in for the recital. But I got
         enough so she could wear her dress and her hair fixed. I sometimes had to help
         with that. I think she probably did it herself that time. But anyhow, she wore the
         dress in and went to the party.
         
         And along about twelve o'clock they came back home and I was sitting by the fire.
         I had started a fire. I had started to have a party myself at that time. And when
         Mother came in the door, she said, "Well, what are you doing up here this time of
         night?" I said, "Oh, you folks like to go to parties so well, I thought I'd maybe
         give
         you another one - party .." I just kidded with them. "Why,are you sick?" I
         said, "Nope. Never felt better in my life." But I had indications that showed there
         was liable to be trouble and that it wouldyprpbably be - probably things would finish
         up
         all right. She want - my, she wanted to hussle around. And she turned back to Edna
         and said, "Run back up to" my aunt just lived two-three doors up the street. "Run
         on up there and fetch Aunt Mary before she gets in bed and tell her to come on down.
         We
         might need her here." And I was laughing and kidding with them. Every once in a
         while I'd have a little kink that wasn't so good didn't pay any attention to them.
         And I said, "I'd had lots worse pains than that when I was five eating cabbage and
         vinegar."
         
         SS:  When you were what? Five and when you were what?
         
         NS:   I told them I'd had lots worse pains than that - than I was having then. I
         said, "for eatiing cabbage with vinegar on it."
         
         SS:   What do you mean "eating cabbage with vinegar on it?" That was a worse pain?
         
         NS:   No, that would sometimes give people cramps - yes, I had lots worse
         from just eating supper. So, I figured I was gonna know when I got the real thing
         because I had heard others talk about it. And one lady - one of our close neighbors,
         had just had a baby two-three weeks before that and she said she called the doctor
         in and he said, "Well, in this case it was a good thing she hollared when she did."
         'Cause he said whenever you began to have those regular pains five minutes apart,
         you
         can look for a youngster within the hour. And I think she said it worked out that
         way
         too, with her. And, listen now, well, when I thought that sounds funny a doctor
         , because that can't be my deal, the way I would be, because I thought I'm
         not ready yet, I don't think. They kept wanting to go for the doctor. "We'll send
         Ernie for the doctor." And I said, "Well, I don't need him. There's nothing now -
         I
         don't think I need any doctor now, I feel fine." Well, they were all standing around
         having
         a fit 'cause - "You better go get the doctor." Well, finally I - begin to get a
         little tougher. "Well, if it'll make you folks feel better, well, go ahead and get
         him."
         So they did and about the first thing about it. There was like a door there, and he
         came in that side door. And he was taking off his gloves and set his little black
         bag down on the chair near by there. And my bedroom's off here. It was just a
         across the door and there was a lamp, lit in there, no electricity then, you
         know. And so she had the light lit in that room and he was standing facing that way
         talking to the bunch of them. And I was standing over this side, over here where the
         stove was. And I was standing in behind the stove. Just room enough I could
         squeeze through between the stove and the wall., 'cause I got so I was chilly then.
         I
         was freezing - it was working on me all right. But I was getting shakey and chilly
         so
         I got in there where it was warm. And he stood there talking to them and he started
         to
         pick up his bag and on in. And I snickered. It struck me funny. I kinda giggled and
         he turned to see what had happened. He looked so funny and I said, "Well, I guess
         I'm the one you're looking for." Well, "All right." he said. And he wanted to
         know how I was and all and I said, "Well, fine - so far."
         
         SS:   He hadn't really noticed you?
         
         NS:   Oh, he'd seen me before. He had been expecting that youngster for two months.
         He told me he thought it would be about the fifth of August.
         
         SS:   So what did you say to him? You said... ?
         
         NS:   "I guess I don't look like the one you're looking for- but I guess I am." Or
         something like that I said. Anyhow, he came back then and stood there and talked to
         me. He said something then about pains, how far apart and everything. And the
         severity and I said, "No, they weren't bad at all." I had gone in and sat in the
         rocking chair in frortcf the stove. And he was watching me and finally he said
         something about the timing. How the time was and I said They were about
         a minute or two minutes apart or something like that. And he looked like he didn't
         believe it. So he took out his watch and began timing me. And once in awhile I'd
         kinda screw my face up, kinda little more severe and he watched that for awhile.
         He thought I didn't know the time but I was sitting facing the clock on the wall.
         And
         I did happen to notice the timing all. And after he had checked two or three of
         those and there wasn't any intermission between 'em hardly. And so he said, "Why,
         I think we better get you in here and find out what's going on. So clean the bedroom
         there. And they came out just on high. How long will it take to get some boiling
         hot water? Get these things going." She said, "It's already boiling." And he said,
         "Well, good. Get these instruments on to cook just as quick as you can." And he was
         hurrying on like everything and the baby was already on the way then. So - he gave
         her a lecture,then he came back to me and he said, "Now, I'm going to tell you. I
         see
         trouble on my hands here but we'll 'avoid it all we can." And he said, "You're going
         to have a buttocks presentation."
         
         SS:   A what?
         
         NS:   A buttocks presentation, he thought it was going to be. Something he had. And
         he said, "One foot is appearing now." I said, "All right." And he told me he'd give
         me a little lecture. He said, "Once this all starts," he says, "I'm sorry to tell
         you,
         we cant give you a speck of ether or anything." But he said, "Once this all starts,
         you have to work just fast and hard, 'cause once this starts we have five minutes
         to get this over with or we'll probably have a dead baby." So I said, "All right,
         I'm
         game." I said, "I'll do what I can."
         
         SS:  Were you afraid?
         
         NS:   No, I wasn't. I thought - well, I used to be kinda in the first part of it,
         but I
         thought, "Well, there's been thousands of them born before my baby so I'll
         make it through too." That's what I thought.
         
         SS:  When you say "the first part of it," do you mean when you were first with child?
         
         NS:   Yah. Then I was kinda thinking then, "Well, how can it all be?" But then when
         I finally figured, out, I said, "Well, there's been thousands of 'em and hardly any
         of
         them ever died in childbirth. "
         
         SS:   Were you in pain at this point when you were laying in bed there? Was it
         hurting you pretty bad?
         
         NS:   No, not bad. There would be intermission and some, but anyhow, he said he
         wanted me - just five minutes to spare during that time for trouble. And I thouaht
         "I
         don't want that." I'd a done most anything because I was so afraid,, I knew I might
         have
         a dead baby and that baby was pretty precious to me. And I was wanting it to be all
         right. After awhile, we were boarding - we had some boarders that were staying in
         a little shack we had on the back. It was a perfectly good little house but it was
         just
         a small place. And they had rented it. They were taking pictures or enlarging pictures
         or something like that. And they rented that for it. I was so scared that I'd
         make a lot of fuss. And I'd heard of people just screaming and yelling that were in
         the hospital and making such a fuss. And I was just scared to death I'd do that way.
         And I didn't want those fellers to hear me hollering around. So anyhow, he went
         back then to tell Mother something and when he came back in here ,why the - he
         said, "Hurry". And then he said the feet were presenting. And he had someone to
         help get his garters on and tie his apron and get his gloves and I don't think he
         ever
         did get the gloves on. He just - the baby came just right now! And then he began
         to say, "Well, wait a minute Mrs. Smith. Now wait a minute." So - but it was coming
         too fast then, but that was easier said than done. So in about two minutes why the
         baby was there. And it came all right. But there was another baby born just a week
         later up at this end of town, a girl. Born in the same position, the same, you know.
         The same thing happening and they broke her collar bone, her arm was I kinked up
         someway or other. So they kinda had her taped up for quite awhile. But mine came
         fine - just wonderful.
         
         SS:   It sounds like he was more nervous than you were.
         
         NS:   Like what?
         
         SS:   It sounds like he was more nervous than you were.
         
         NS:   Yah. Well, the doctor - he was a good doctor and all. He just told me the
         bare facts. Well, I think he knew too that I was pretty much out and out - whatever.
         
         SS:   Was this Dr. Gibson?
         
         NS:   Um-hum.
         
         SS:   Do you think that it was different with some women? Did some women have much
         more trouble? I mean facing this kind of a thing?
         
         NS:   Yes. Yes, they do sometimes. Some of them 25-30 hours sometimes in
         labor and that's no fun.
         
         SS:   In those days when they were having babies at home, it was the same way? Long
         labors sometimes?
         
         NS:   Well, some of'em. In fact, I shouldn't be telling you all this stuff. I don't
         suppose it's very proper conversation.
         
         SS:   Well, that's the way people lived in those days. I think its important to know.
         
         NS:   But another one of our neighbors lived over there. She was quite a chum of
         mine and she was expecting. And she did have a twelve pound baby in the long run.
         And the doctor was there and she had worked and worked and she was worn out. And
         it had been quite a long time - stretch. And he had told her now she must work hard
         with this next pain. And she must bear down and she just had to work hard for that.
         And she just give out and she finally said, "Well, I can't. I've done all I can do."
         You know. And she just kinda relaxed, you know. And give up. And finally he just
         up and slapped her along side of the face. Give her a good sound slap. And she got
         so mad at him she - if she could of done it - she'd a got up and tried to throw a
         shoe
         at him. And she just got so mad and he let it go. And she went to work then. Oh,
         she was all stirred: And the baby was there in a little while, had it over with. After
         it came,
         he apologized to her and he said, "Now, my apology, now to you but I had to do that."
         He says, "With some people you have to do that They just get worn out and just give
         up. You have to make 'em mad with a good slap or something. You have to make 'em
         good and mad and then they'll tend to go to work stronger." And she said, "Well,
         you don't know how it hurt." He said, "Oh, yes I do." And she says, "Yes, like fun
         you do." And he said "Yes, I do." He says, "I dreamed one night I had a baby - a
         youngster and I was never in such misery in all my life as I was in that dream."
         So she got over her mad spell.
         
         SS:   Was this the same doctor?
         
         NS:   Yes, it was the same one I had.
         
         SS:  Was that the way most all the women had their kids - at home in those days?
         They didn't use the hospital then?
         
         NS:   Yes, Well, they - some of them did. But I didn't want to go to the hospital.
         I
         just wanted to have my youngsters at home and I had them that way, the whole six of
         them.
         
         SS:  Well, when the baby was born then, he just stayed with you at home and you just
         were supposed to lie in bed and recuperate. Was that how it worked?
         
         NS:   Yes, you were supposed to stay in bed for ten days,anyhow. But you know, why
         that was the day that everybody considered - that had been kind of a hand-me-down
         idea
         from way back. Sometimes 12 days, but they were supposed to stay anyhow, 10 days
         in bed. And the tenth day, why, everything was supposed to fall back in its place
         and
         IT would all become normal again. But I said, "Well, of all things. Why
         everything isn't going to wait until the tenth day and just jump back into -
         
         SS:   Well, I would...
         
         END OF SIDE B
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: You get weaker than the dickens not doing anything.
         
         NELL SMITH: I laid there, I think, it was the full ten days that time. But I didn't
         feel like it. I felt like getting up and going to work or something. But that was
         the rule
         at that time, you were supposed to stay in there. And then when I had the last - no
         not the
         last one - the next to the last one, I just lay- I was in bed six days and then they
         picked
         me up and took me up to the hospital. Took my baby girl up there and - because it
         had
         trouble with her and they were going to operate on her. She had - oh, I don't remember
         now the name they used - but, anyhow, it formed an ostome - I can't think of it -
         but
         anyhow she had a malformation of her bowel. And she'd been laying there - a
         beautiful baby, and a sweet little cozy, cuddly little thing, you know. Beautiful
         child. But she didn't have the - well, I don't know whether it was - something was
         missing. They thought it was either a malformation near the rectum - it was either
         a
         disconnection or it was knotted or something, because nothing Could pass. And she
         had
         been lying in bed there with me and - that's here at home - she had been taking her
         feed all the time, but again the last two or three days, burping it up. And it was
         some kind of a stoppage there that prevented it going on through.
         
         SS:   So they took her and you both to the hospital?
         
         NS:   Well, they took her up here - up there to operate. I think that was one of the
         hardest things I ever did, to let them take her up there to operate. Little tiny thing,
         six days old. I thought - well, they said that she only had a 50/50 chance of
         success if they took her there. And she would have to have another operation
         later - when she was maybe five years old. When she was old enough, you know, to stand
         it. So there I was, deciding whether to send that baby up there and let them cut
         into her and thinking probably there was no chance for her. And then I'd think, well,
         if there was a 50-50 chance, maybe I better lean on the little bit of hope. And they
         took her up there and she was just six days old, I think, when they took her
         up there. And they came down and got me. I sent mother up to the hospital with
         her - when mother was here. I said, "You go and stay right there with her and
         see that everything is done right. Take good care of her." Mother went up there
         and then that evening she came down then and said that - the hospital was right up
         there where that building is, up there where the Hall Apartment House, was the
         hospital then - and she came down. She said, "Well, you know, I'm not doing a
         thing up there but just sit there with my hands folded. There's nothing I can do for
         the baby." So she said, "Why don't you go up there and stay with her and let
         me be down here? And I can be doing some work down here." I said, well, I
         didn't know. The doctor - she said the doctor said that would be all right. I
         could do it. So he came down and got me in a car and took me up there. She died
         on the day she was eleven days old.
         
         I held a grudge kinda against the doctor from that time because the morning
         that she took worse, of course, I wasn't suppose to pick her up or do anything
         for her really. But, oh., I could give her a sip of water or something like that.
         So I was watching carefully. I was following orders. And I noticed that
         morning ahe was having more trouble breathing and all. She was worse. And I
         called the nurse and she came upstairs and said, well, she's. . .yes, she's - I know,
         I said, "Does she need anything more to eat now?" I said, "She acts like
         she's awfully worked up and nervous. Acts like maybe she might be hungry. Maybe
         if she had a bit to eat it might calm her."
         
         (Ernie: i thought you were going to shave me this noon?)
         
         NS:   What?
         
         Ernie: I thought you were going to shave me this noon?
         
         NS:   Well, I shaved you awhile ago.
         
         Ernie: What?
         
         NS:   You been a dreaming. I just got through shaving you before you ate.)
         And so the nurse went back down and said, "No. She don't need anything now."
         She said, "Regular time for her feed, on schedule. When it comes time, we'll
         give it to her." So she left me and I thought, "Well, that was very consoling." But
         I sat right by her and watched her closely. Finally, I asked her if she wouldn't
         call the doctor then, he just lived up the next place above it. And she went
         and called the doctor to see if there was something he could do, maybe, in a
         pinch, you know, something in an emergency. She was supposed to have called
         him. I don't know whether she did or not, she said she did. But he didn't come.
         It was about 4 o'clock, I think, in the morning. And I asked her later on if
         she, you know, - why he wasn't coming or if he couldn't. I was expecting him
         to come right on down, considering it an emergency. And she said that - he maybe
         had to eat his breakfast first before he came down,
         
         SS:   He had said he was going to wait and see if the baby would eat or she
         wanted to wait and see?
         
         NS:   No, I want to see if the baby could have something to eat and she
         said no, it wasn't time for the feeding. She was going by that. It wasn't time
         for it. But the time came then she got it. But I asked her then, you know, to call
         the doctor and have him to check her - her condition in general 'cause I could
         see she was worse. And so - he didn't come. I waited and waited and he didn't
         show up.
         
         SS:   This was the second time you'd asked her?
         
         NS:   Um-hum. And he didn't come. So it went on to about 7 o'clock in the morning
         or
         something like that and he never even showed up. And I finally - the baby had
         died. I didn't ask him the second time again, until I could see she was going
         fast then. And I took the baby up and held her in my arms and kind of elevated, you
         know, - kinda gave her better room to breathe by elevating her head and holding
         her in a slanting position. He didn't come. So I asked the nurse then, I said,
         "What do they usually do in a case of this kind here?" I said, "She's gone
         now."
         
         Well, first, when I saw she was bad and was going, the nurse looked at her
         then and oh, said, "Oh, she needs changing now, let me carry her in and
         change her then." Or fix her up or something like that. And I said, "No.
         Just let her alone." I said, "She's suffering enough as it is just now." I said,
         "It will soon be over." And I said, " hat little bit of mussed diaper isn't
         going to hurt her at all." And I said, "I'd rather you don't. You just let her
         alone. Let her be as comfortable as she can." And, well, "All right, if
         you say so." And I said so. And I said, "What do they usually do?" afterwards,
         when she was gone. I siad, "What do they usually do here in cases of that kind?"
         And I said, "Do we just let her lay here on the bed until he comes or what?" And
         she said, "Well, no. They usually take them down in the basement." And I
         just thought, "You're not taking my baby down in the basement." I didn't say
         anything to her but I just asked her to get the janitor there. He was, had
         known  me for a long time. I had gone to school with him, I think, known him for
         a long while here.
         
         And I said, - I sent Joe down - I said, "Would you go down and tell Ernie to
         come up. I think the baby is dying now." And he just hustled right down and got
         Ernie. And she was gone by the time he got back. That's when I asked Peggy
         what they usually did. So I sat and waited a little while. Ernie sitting there
         with me, when he came in. I took her things and packed up a suitcase. Finally
         when, I think, it was about 7 o'clock came, I said to Ernie, "If you can carry
         these suitcases, lets go home." And I said, "I can carry the baby." It was
         only eleven days after and ordinarily when in those conditions they would of thought
         But anyhow, I carried my baby in a blanket, walked out from that hospital,
         and carried her home myself. And you know, that doctor never did see that
         baby after she passed away. He didn't know whether she lived or died. Except
         the nurse said so. He had the nurse's word for it. You'd of thought, he'd have
         made some apology to me or some bit of condolance of some kind. But never a
         word. So, we just brought her down to the house here and laid her out here at
         the house.
         
         SS:   Had the baby's condition been pretty stable after the operation?
         
         NS:   No. That was the trouble. The two days after the operation they had had
         to go in there again and they said they had made too large of an incision and
         they had to go in there and, I don't know, close that a little, I think, or
         something like that. And they had to give her - what is that - it wasn't
         ether but it was some other anestectic they had given her. And they thought she
         was too delicate and too tittle to - too much of a strain - the whole thing in
         general.
         
         SS:   It seems really - it must have been very hard on you during that time.
         
         NS:   Um-hum. It was. And deciding whether to send her up there knowing
         what they were going to do and knowing it was serious - that probably no chance.
         I felt like you were leading a little lamb out to the slaughter.
         
         SS:   She's the only girl that you ever had? All the rest were boys?
         
         NS:   Only one. Five boys and one girl.
         
         SS:   When you had babies at home, when they were first born, were there
         certain precautions you were supposed to take about the first days and the first
         weeks? Were their certain ways of doing things that the mothers were supposed... ?
         
         NS:   For her? Or for myself?
         
         SS:   No, for the kids. For the average baby that was born in those days at
         home. Since the baby wasn't in the hospital and they didn't take care of them
         for you, were there certain rules that the mothers were suppose to follow?
         
         NS:   Well, they all kinda grew up knowing that, I think. You know, it was
         handed down from mother and grandmother and all. And many of them were
         born with a midwife in attention and that's all there was to it. The midwife
         would - took care of the case.
         
         SS:   The midwife would stay at the home?
         
         NS:   Well, no. She would just go and come, I think. Sometimes if it wasn't
         handy or if they lived a long ways away, then she would stay in. But I didn't
         happen to run into any of those. Of course, he was here - the doctor was here
         at the time when I had ... She was my fifth one and then I just had
         one more and that was a boyand he wasn't here for that one. He had gone,
         been transferred to Potlatch, I think. And he had given his -turned his book
         and all to the doctor that was in charge, Dr. Onsborg. He was, I guess, a
         big Dutch man or something but he had been in charge of the naval hospital for, I
         think, he had been in the Navy for about twenty or twenty-five years. I think
         it was twenty-five. But he had been a Navy doctor. And when he got here, why
         Dr. Gibson had his book all filled up with - oh, there were an awful lot of babies
         were born that year and he had it all filled up with that. And I went up one time
         for a check-up when I was expecting Lloyd and I went up to see him the first
         time. And he said something about Dr. Gibson leaving him - he said, "I never
         saw so many babies in one place in my life!" He said, "Oh, Teddy Roosevelt ought
         of been in this town, I can just see his big old grin a-coming-shin ing yet." 'Cause
         he was always pictured him as a big, shin iy grin.
         
         SS:   He'd be grinning because there were so many babies?
         
         NS:   Un-huh. And he was always rather in favor of large families and loved
         kids, I guess.
         
         SS:   Teddy Roosevelt?
         
         NS:   Un-huh. But he couldn't help - him saying he thought Teddy ought to be
         here at that time.
         
         SS:  Did they have the idea then that if a baby cried you were supposed to
         pick him up?
         
         NS:   No, they didn't want you to hardly. But I kind a did as I pleased. If, you
         know - you're armed against it at all. Know your youngsters, know a few things about
         'em,
         why, you're going to know when they cry if something's a matter with them or whether
         just hungry or something else. It's a different cry and you learn to know that cry.
         Sometimes they have cramps in their stomach and need you. You turn them over
         on their stomach and pat them a little while - that helps them or else hold them
         over your shoulder and brings up the burp or two. And sometimes it'd heal the whole
         thing. They don't like it if you pick 'em up. Well, there is such a thing as picking
         up a baby everytime it moves, and spoiling it to death. And they'll cry then just
         to get up. But you got to kind of learn that - know whether - the different tone of
         voice and all, generally.
         
         This woman over here - she's getting hers spoiled now, I think. It' s only four
         weeks old now. She was over here the next day or so after the baby was born. And
         it was born in a hospital over there, but she was up and going around here, had the
         baby on her arm, doing fine. They just let her come home the second day. Things
         have changed considerably. And I t hink the girls are really healthier. They
         don't loose their strength, you know, like they do if you just have them lay down
         and lay there for ten days. They get up the next day or two after the baby's
         born or something like that. Or maybe if " born during the night,
         they get up the next morning and go to the bathroom and then go back to bed
         and just up and down and they don't loose their strength at all, hardly.
         
         SS:  I know there used to be - oh, I've heard people say stuff like - one of the
         old ideas was you had to be careful not to let a cat near the baby because the cat
         could
         really hurt the baby. Is that something that you learned when... ?
         
         NS:   Yes, I've heard that a good deal. Never let them - the cat they say
         will purr and, you know, how they'll work with their claws...
         
         SS:   They knead.
         
         NS:   Kinda kneading like and they say they can stop the baby's breath because
         the little chest ia tender and gives a lot. They said - that's what their theory was,
         anyhow. But I always, seen them - to watch 'em close to see that the cat
         didn't get to the youngster. We dorft want a cat up there with a youngster anyway.
         But this woman over here she picks up her baby, throws a.blanket around it
         and comes over here. She's been over here two - three times now since her baby
         came. Just the other day she was here and the baby was a month old then, four weeks
         old. And she had it on her arm with a blanket on it, just wrapped in a little
         sheeting blanket. And a little cute baby, cute as a bug's ear. Just pretty and
         plump and , you know, even features, and just real pretty. And never says a
         word. Never. Just as contented as can be. It never seems to - the other day
         whimper a bit and fidget and cry. And she said, it's time for eating
         again. It's dinner time,she knows it. So...
         
         SS:   Did mothers used to be careful, when you were a mother, did mothers
         have to be careful about taking the kid out? And that sort of thing or would you do
         that with babies - take them with you when you went places?
         
         NS:   We were pretty careful right in the beginning because a little wiff of
         air - fresh air - they weren't used to it. And they'd give 'em a little wiff or two
         of that fresh air or wind in their face and they'd have the colic. If they got colic
         it would be bad. If you put a good warm pad, a hot water bottle or something, you
         know, on the blanket right under them, and turn them on their stomach and
         something warm on their feet, they'd generally get over it in a little while. Or
         sometimes a little bit of- oh, just a drop or two of peppermint or something
         like that in a little sweetened water. But generally just give 'em a bottle with
         warm, just as warm as they can stand, with warm water. A good big drink of
         that would generally do it.
         
         SS:   Well, I wanted to ask you about that fire that came down from Beall's
         Butte and almost took the town with it.
         
         NS:   Well, that was, I was just thinking, I got kinda sidetracked on th*
         doctor's business.
         
         SS:   Oh, I enjoyed that very much because it helps you understand how different
         things were in those days. Now, its all so different. The mother that wants to
         have her kid at home is looked at as being pretty -
         
         NS:  Backwards or something, I guess, kinda back-woodsy.
         
         SS:   Well, I think its the way everyone did it, but still it's history now, that
         way
         they had a child.
         
         NS:  Yes, a good many of them had the - the youngsters were born in the
         covered wagon on the way out West or something. Or sometimes the mother
         died or she didn't have milk for feeding it. I don't know. Someone I heard talking
         about that they were raised on mare's milk on the crossing the plains. They had a
         mare and her colt that they were taking along there and the mare furnished the
         - or the mother got sick or something. I don't know, but it was an emergency
         anyhow, and they got along fine. There's a lot of things a person can do in a
         pinch if they just know about it.
         
         SS:   Was your mother tended by a midwife when she had her kids, do you know?
         
         NS:   I don't know. No. Because she said the doctor's name who took care of
         her when I was born was, I think, Dr. Brosish in Missouri. So that's all
         I know about him. I heard her mention him, Dr. Brosish. I don't know
         maybe Grandmother had - probably - a midwife there when mother was bron. I
         don't know. That was back in 1868.
         
         SS:   I was going to ask you, when you talked about all the work - the needlework
         that your mother did. Now, did - she got an income for doing that, or a small
         income from doing? She just did it.
         
         NS:   She did that for her own self. And she made a lot of things. All
         her doilies and things, you know, she had 'em trimmed up and did the work
         on them and all. An d then if anything she made was for anybody else - I don't
         think that she did that kind of work hardly for anyone else. But if she did it was
         a gift or something she was planning on making for them.
         
         SS:   Was that sort of a skill really prized skill, was that something that was
         considered... ?
         
         NS:   Well, now you scratch up some of those old pieces from that time and show
         them nowadays and they're prized. They're something to hand-me-dawn. Something
         worth - that's one reason I was going to show you the pillowslips that I started
         to make. I got one of them finished since I was 80 years old. So... and then
         the other one I haven't even gotten started, yet. I have too many - I sit down and
         if I don't et busy, I'll run out of time. But now you take some of those old
         fashioned things that are on display in museums and things.
         
         SS:   Well, you know, what I was thinking when I
         
         END OF SIDE C
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13510</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Smith2</previous>
      <next>Smith4</next>
      <disp_name>Smith3</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
