<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2/24/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>William Stowell, 1976-02-24, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:47:45</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Stowell, William</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>Lumberjack</occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Clearwater River, Bovill area</residence>
      <origin>Came in the mid-twenties; father had a farm and sawmill in Quebec</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gambling"&gt;gambling&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#cards"&gt;cards&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumberjacks"&gt;lumberjacks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#log drives"&gt;log drives&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#accidents"&gt;accidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#reading"&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sports"&gt;sports&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gyppos"&gt;gyppos&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#strikes"&gt;strikes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#working conditions"&gt;working conditions&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Clearwater River"&gt;Clearwater River&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Clarkia"&gt;Clarkia&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13498</file_name>
      <mp3>13499.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13499.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Differences in logging between Idaho and Michigan</title>
            <synopsis>Difference between logging in Idaho and Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Better conditions
               in Idaho camps than Michigan's.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>What the IWW accomplished; the democracy of the IWW</title>
            <synopsis>The IWW's accomplished wonders with direct action. The strike in 1923 was for the prisoners
               in jail; the 1936 strike for better conditions, which were improved after they broke
               the strike. Democracy of IWW made it much better than the CIO. IWW's strike for better
               conditions, not money. They were revolutionary and are dead.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Lumberjacks are single; the work was all done by hand; lumberjacks were mostly older
               and came from the east
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>People have changed. Lumberjacks were single, footloose, and had the world to gain.
               Gyppo system was supported by many to make money, and was opposed by the IWW. The
               work was all by hand and hard. Older men learned shortcuts. Lumberjacks were mostly
               older and came from the east.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>His father had a sawmill in Quebec, Canada</title>
            <synopsis>His father had a sawmill in Quebec, Canada.</synopsis>
         </point>

         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Fights among lumberjacks; Aberdeen was roughest town on the coast</title>
            <synopsis>Fights among lumberjacks. Aberdeen was the roughest
               town on the coast.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1500</time>
            <title>Staying on the job; working with good foreman</title>
            <synopsis>Staying with the job. The foreman rarely checked on gyppos, or bothered working men
               on the job. Most foremen worked for the company. Malker Anderson was a very good foreman.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Consolidation of the Potlatch Lumber company forests; taking horse teams to Headquarters;
               the ground around Bovill
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Consolidation of Potlatch Forests. The Potlatch Lumber Company woods operation had
               better conditions than the Clearwater; quality of Potlatch horses. The home meadow
               at Bovill. Taking horse teams from Elk River to Headquarters. The ground around Bovill
               was almost all accessible to railroad.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>The death of Art Henderson; early logging camps on the Clearwater; cutting the road
               on the river
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Death of Art Henderson. Early logging and camps on the Clearwater, and foremen from
               Montana. Cutting the road on the river.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>

         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>First Clearwater river log drives; construction of early wanigans; Gust Piper took
               the first drives; Silent Joe trapped on the North Fork
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>First Clearwater River log drives. Construction of early wanigans - cedar timbers,
               vine maple binders. Gust Piper was a log "pirate" who took rafts down to the Snake;
               he took the first drives because he knew the whole river. Silent Joe trapped on the
               North Fork in different cabins and rarely spoke.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Navigating the wanigans; finding places to land</title>
            <synopsis>Navigating the wanigans. Swinging athwart the current. Need to keep rafts together.
               Finding places to land; setting snublines.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>A raft that missed the landing and the foreman was let go</title>
            <synopsis>A raft that missed the landing went thirty miles to Big
               Island and the foreman was canned.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4740</time>
            <title>Discussion about rear and center crews on the drives; lining the batteaus upstream</title>
            <synopsis>Rear crews and center crews on the river drives. Using powder. Lining the batteaus
               upstream.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5100</time>
            <title>Working in the riving; the drowning of three men near Lenore</title>
            <synopsis>Working in the river. Drowning of three men when their boat swamped near Lenore. Fitting
               searched for his brother's body.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>Taking up collections by the men in camps - a day's wages</title>
            <synopsis>Taking up collections by the men in camps - a day's wages.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5880</time>
            <title>Discussion of Pierce, Idaho and Clarkia; how the Pierce hotel started</title>
            <synopsis>Pierce, a lumberjack town with everything. Tent living in town. Pierce Hotel started
               as a bootleg shack. Clarkia, a wide open town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Incline on Marble Creek; Working for Wood 'Em Up George</title>
            <synopsis>Incline on Marble Creek - 57% grade. Working for Wood 'Em Up George - he lost money
               with race horses, he liked to fire men.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Moving from camp to camp; Oscar Sturgill's camp; death of a superintendent</title>
            <synopsis>Going from camp to camp. Getting jobs. Oscar Sturgill's camp. Tramp lumberjacks and
               family men. Death of a superintendent in a wind storm.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Old time lumberjacks are gone</title>
            <synopsis>Old time lumberjacks are gone.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>IWW Strike of 1936: murder of pickets; arrest and blackballing. Strikes on the job.
         Lumberjack sociability. Picking timber on river drives; fluming. 2-24-76 1.5 hr
         42p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This conversation with "MICHIGAN" BILL STOWELL, took place at his home in Lewiston,
         Idaho on February 24, 1976.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: I was wondering about this in the old days with the lumberjacks.
         They'd stay in the woods for a pretty long time before they'd get to
         go in town?
         
         WILLIAM STOWELL: Oh, yeah. Three, four, five, six, seven, eight months, you
         know.
         
         SS:   That seems like a hell of a long time to be out in the boondocks.
         
         WS:   Oh, God, yes. I used to do it. But there was always— there was no
         TVs, of course, there was poker games. And sometimes if you played
         poker you might have to stay. You know, they'd keep you there, if
         you weren't winning. See what I mean?
         
         SS:   You could lose your stake pretty easy in a game.
         
         WS:   Yeah, there was a good game there all the time. I used to play all
         time, but sometimes— well, you go six to eight months that you
         wouldn't win, you'd lose. You wouldn't warm the chair even, when you'd
         on it. But then again, you'd get lucky and win a thousand and
         away you went!
         
         SS:   Were the games pretty honest?
         
         WS:   Oh, always, yeah. Once in a while a slicker would move in, but, oh,
         1 he'd win of course, but they were easy games to win in, you know,
         never^iose, free and easy, you know. Four or five hundredApot, you
         might win on a high card, you know: Queen, King, Ace, something like
         that. No pairs or nothings they just tried to bluff their way out.
         
         SS:   Did you usually play the same kind of poker?
         
         WS:   Mostly stud, yeah. Five cards. That was the going deal.
         
         SS:   That's a good game.
         
         WS:   Oh, Yeah. Fast game.
         
         SS:   Well, how did they pay you then, in the woods? Would you get paid by
         the week or by the month?
         
         WS:   No. Some camps paid when you quit. If you stayed one month, two months,
         three months or six months, or no matter how long, they'd pay when you
         left. Otherwise it was every month, like the Potlatch did. They paid
         every months. And they insisted on you picking up your check, you see.
         You know; payday. You could stay, of course, as long as you want to
         but they didn't like them checks laying around, you know. Pick it up
         every month. That's the way they worked it. But some of them gypos
         you could work as long as you wanted to without that, you see. Get it
         all when you left. One check.
         
         SS:   But if you were going to be gambling, you need some money.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, all the time. You could draw, you know.
         
         SS:   Draw off your pay.
         
         WS:   Well, the Potlatch had a draw day; the fifteenth. That was a pretty
         strict deal. You couldn't draw otherwise. You could draw once a month,
         besides your regular payday. That's the way that worked.
         
         SS:   Did everybody get in on the gambling or was there a bunch of guys that
         wouldn't touch it?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. Some didn't gamble at all. Just— well, there was a regular
         bunch that— 'course there'd be some that'd drop in an lose what they
         had and then they wouldn't play again, you know, for another month
         unless they borrowed or got some. But there was a bunch that played
         all the time. They were the old, you know—well, they were lucky to
         have money and they just played every night. Sometimes like Saturday
         night they'd play all Saturday night and all day Sunday, and then fly
         at her again, Monday morning. But them games, they don't— there's
         no more games now. Not when I left there even. There was a little
         game at Headquarters, but it didn't amount to nothing. They— oh, a
         few had money, you know. But a small game, didn't amount to nothing.
         I never played there.
         
         SS:   Would you figure, that when you gambled, would you figure you'd come
         out even, or better, or did you come out flat more than—
         
         WS:   Well, I think I broke about even. But sometimes I'd go for six to
         eight months I wouldn't — as I said— I wouldn't warm the chair
         you know. I'd drop everything in a pot or two, you know. We wasn't
         getting much, well, a hundred and fifty dollars was a big months, you
         know. But that was years ago, you know. That was a real, real good
         month. A couple of hands'd take that sometimes if you happened to
         get mixed up right with 'em. But I didn't borrow, I'd quit. Wait
         for another month. (Chuckles) Go at her again! But I usually come
         out about even.
         
         SS:   What about the honesty in the camps? I've heard that lumberjacks were
         honest as the day is long.
         
         WS:   Yeah, they was. You could— well, you could leave a thousand dollars
         lay on your bunk and go to work. Someone might come along and put it
         under your pillow or something, but they wouldn't take it. I don't
         know how it is now. I imagine it has changed some, but... But I don't
         know how— the lumberjack as a rule is a pretty fair guy.
         
         SS:   What about debts? Paying back money that you owed?
         
         WS:   Well, they--
         
         SS:   Men pretty good with that?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. Yeah. They were good pay, all of 'em. Might take a little
         time, you know. But they'd get it. Might be five or six hundred
         miles from there, further, but they'd either send it or see that you
         got it, if they owed you. Lumberjacks traveled around a lot them
         days, you know. On the coast and back here, Montana and all over.
         Gallivanting around.
         
         SS:   Did the men have places that they liked specially that they'd stay
         at mostly?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. They'd run around for a while and then they'd come back to
         this spot, you see, where they liked to work. Where they liked the
         crew and one thing and another, and settle down. They'd
         quite a hitch, as a rule, that's the way it works. Way it always did
         with me. I'd run around a while and then I'd finally go back to
         where I liked the best. This Potlatch usad to be a good outfit to
         work for— still is, I guess. I worked for 'em well, when they was
         building Headquarters. I'd been out in this country quite a while
         before that, but I was on the Coast quite a bit then. Montana. But
         when they started up, I used to always work here sometime during the
         year I'd be here for a while. (What are you doing? Writing a book
         or something?)
         
         SS:   We're hoping to, eventually.
         
         WS:   Someone else beside you?
         
         SS:   Well, I kind of work for the county; Latah County. But that's what
         I'm hoping to be able to do that eventually. 'Cause we've talked
         to a lot of people, about the interesting things from everybody.
         
         WS:   Yeah, see what you mean.
         
         SS:   Because you know, you look at it from all the different angles, all
         the different kind of people, you know. It's a hell of a story.
         
         WS:   condense it down,
         
         SS:   I've been working for instead of the Coast, and what made this
         look—
         
         WS:   Well, all those different reasons. awful heavy on the Coast,
         And I never followed no machinery They had machines on the Coast
         when I went there. But I never drove no machines. I always worked
         on the ground rigging and like of that, you know. I don't know, they
         eliminated camps over there first. They were the first to eliminate
         the camps, see, like here, they kept 'em, you know. And you could go
         to camp and stay there in camp. Over there, they got to drive a long
         ways, and married. So, that was one reason why I left there. But
         the Rainier, has still got camps over there, but that's about all. And
         there's camps in Alaska, too. But, this country here kept the camps
         the longest of any.
         
         SS:   What about the men? Did you find that the men around here— I mean
         did you get to know 'em pretty good? Feel, you know, like they were
         friends?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. Sure. But, well, I had on the Coast, too. They were
         tramps, like myself, you know. They were here and there and every
         where. But, of course, there's good people wherever you go. And
         then there is some that's not so good, but I never had no connections
         with them. You know, if I didn't like 'em I didn't mix with 'em
         that's all. But they were all good guys. Very good. I don't know.
         I always catered to the short log, I mean I was— river driving, you
         see. There wasn't much of that on the coast. Very, very little driving.
         It was all rafting, you know. And ere was long logs there
         when there was shorter logs here. Always donkey work and I didn't go
         for that too much, you know. I liked this short log country; horses,
         camps and driving, you know. I used to work on the Coast and I'd come
         over here every spring to drive someplace, you know. And you'd meet
         guys you hadn't seen for a year. There was several drives in this
         country.
         
         SS:   Besides the Clearwater?
         
         WS:   Oh, Chtist, yes,, lots of 'em.
         
         SS:   Where were they driving?
         
         WS:   Well, there was the Coeur d'Alene River, Priest River, Wenatchee Riv
         er and the Blackfoot in Montana. Priest River. Oh, I can't remember.
         
         SS:   Gee, I didn't know there was that many.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes.
         
         SS:   Clearwater is the one you always hear about.
         
         WS:   Yeah. Well, that was the last one, you know. You see, years ago
         there was no roads in them camps, you know. You hiked in. They were
         flume camps. You know, there was no trucks or cars or nothing, and
         they flumed everything. You've seen a flume, of course.
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   Well, they flumed everything into the river and drove it in the
         spring. That's the way they did that. But lately, of course, rail
         roads and trucks; it's all trucks now course.
         
         SS:   Were you in on that Beaver Creek flume?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah, I helped build it. 1928.
         
         SS:   How did they organize that whole job there? It looks like a big un
         dertaking, when you see what's left of it.
         
         WS:   Yes. Five miles to start with and they extended.it, of course, later
         on. But the original flume was about done for then.
         
         SS:   There was an older flume in there?
         
         WS:   Well, from Beaver Creek Dam to the river. That was five miles. That
         was built first, then there was flumes and chutes into that, you see.
         Into the pond, from different camps around there, you know, P, and N
         and W, J, and all them camps they all went into Beaver Creek, you know
         and flumed from there to the river. But that's been quite a while
         ago. I worked there on that Beaver Creek plume in 1941. That's the
         last time they used it. They had about, oh, I don't know— we were
         in there right after Christmas, and they trucked to that flume. They
         had a bunch of Chev y trucks and they trucked to the flume. And that
         was just before the war. And we flumed 'em right in, too. 'Course,
         there was always lots of water in Beaver Creek, the flume, you know.
         You never had trouble with that, even in the summer? They flumed there
         all the time?
         
         Yeah, any time. That's a big creek, you know. You been there?
         
         Yeah, I've seen it. It is a big creek. The feeders are pretty good
         too.
         
         Yeah. Well, they'd back that water up and hold it, you know. They
         had, one, two— two big dams, Beaver Creek Dam and Dam. That
         was a way up, 0 and P and them camps come into that. That was above
         camp M. That was probably ten miles from the river, or eleven. But
         they had a big dam there and they held water there, too.
         
         SS:   How much water—? I've never seen a flume running. How much water
         would you keep in the flume?
         
         WS:   All you could get.
         
         SS:   Just fill it right up to the top.
         
         WS:   Yeah. 'Course they knew when they built 'em, how much they'd need,
         and all this and that. But sometimes in the summer— Beaver Creek
         never was that way. There was always water, you know, you could flume.
         But, of course, it would take more water to sluice a log through a
         dam than it does to roll it in, you know. It takes ten times as
         much. But, I worked on them flumes, like Camp T, in the summertime
         in mid August or so, you'd get about four floods a day, and no sluicing
         except through one dam. They'd Kabout three minute floods, you see.
         You had to get that timber in— and you'd maybe flume three hundred
         thousand a day, you see, that's board feet, you know. But you'd have
         to get that in in twelve minutes. Four three minute floods, two
         in the morning and two in the afternoon.
         
         SS:   Well, you could have all the timber right by the flood—
         
         WS:   Right there, yeah.
         
         SS:   Ready to go.
         
         WS:   You'd have what you was going to flume. They're all ready. And
         then call for the water, you see. They opened the dam and give you
         the water.
         
         SS:   Gee, they must have moved fast.
         
         WS:   Oh, boyl There'd about six, seven men rolling in, you know. On the
         average landing where there was maybe seventy-five or aliundred thou
         sand each fluming, you see. That's about what you'd have. But there'd
         be four or five of them landings, you know. Maybe trucking to some
         of 'em, and some of 'em they'd be skidding to.
         
         SS:   During that three minutes when it was open you'd have to roll the
         lumber right onto the flume right then?
         
         WS:   Right then.
         
         SS:   How many guys would be working on one landing?
         
         WS:   Oh, five or six.
         
         SS:   Would they have peavies?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Must have been a scramble.
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. You had to watch your step, too, you know. Short water,
         you see, and you couldn't double 'em up or nothing, you know, or they'd
         jam and there you are and you'd lose the flood and everything. You
         had to keep 'em singled out. Oh, yeah, it was quite an undertaking,
         but of course, everybody knew this business,^there was nothing to it.
         
         SS:   How big were the logs?
         
         WS:   Oh, they'd average maybe three, four hundred feet. Course, they'd
         be some with a thousand feet in 'em, you know. Some with a hundred
         feet in 'em. The average log maybe three hundred feet. They'd just
         leave the minute they hit that flume, you know. You concentrate
         that water there in one small spot you know, and it's got a lot of
         power. You know how them flumes was built.
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   See'a log there was five hundred feet in the chute, get another
         one right behind it, and that would be gone a long ways. Yeah. I
         Used to like that kind of work.
         
         SS:   Would you ever run into trouble with timing with other landings?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, well, they had to watch the ones below, you know. They
         had to watch real close. The guy on the upper end^ he didn't have to
         be too particular to let 'em go, but the guys down below f they
         had to watch or they'd be in trouble. But there never was much trou
         ble. They all knew their business.
         
         SS:   How much of the season did they flume? Did they keep that going right
         through the spring and summer?
         
         WS:   Yeah. Well, in the wintertime, when they worked in the wintertime,
         they would— there was no water in the wintertime, it would freeze up.
         They'd deck it. Pile 'em up, you know. And they'd go in the spring
         before the drive started and flume 'em. Yeah.
         
         SS:   On these river drives— now, I was thinking about that working in
         the water— cold in the spring— I imagine that'd be really rugged
         work.
         
         WS:   Yeah, it's tough. Sure.
         
         SS:   You got all them wool clothes on and everything, too.
         
         WS:   Yeah. The deeper it got the colder it got. Well, some guys could
         wade deep, you know and some couldn't. Just a matter of— there
         wasn't a hell, of a lot to know about it. Just get in there and go.
         'Course, there was something, too—you had to savvy a little bit
         about it in order to do it, but that was just plain old work. That's
         all that was. I didn't care much for that part of it. I'd rather
         work on the timber, you know, like a center or^that work.
         
         SS:   What?
         
         WS:   Like a center, you know, something builds up in the middle of the riv
         er, and you got to pick 'em off, as a rule. Like this river here,
         down along the highway here, the main river, you know, you had to
         take all that stuff off by hand, them timbers, you know, on account
         of— well, they used machines late years, but you couldn't use pow
         der on account of the highway on one side, you know, and the railroad
         on the other.Well, it was machine work or handwork, depends on the kind
         of water it was. Good big water, why, they'd take 'em off by hand.
         Just get their side picking, you know, and loosen em up, get
         slack in it and pretty soon she'd all go, you know. You had to 
         for the boat then. Yeah, that's the way that worked. Used to be a
         lot of centers in this river here. All kinds of 'em.
         
         SS:   When you say you pick at it; you just tried to separate— just tried
         like to— get them logs untangled?
         
         WS:   Yeah, that's it. That's just it. Get 'em unraveled. The center al
         ways builds up against something, you know. It depends upon what kind
         of water that goes on. Different stages of water will cause centers
         and some it won't, you know. But, it'll build up on something. It'll
         start like on a rock, or an island or a bar or something and it'll build
         way back, you know. Well, maybe back fifty feet from where it start
         ed there's twenty feet of water, but everything that hits it goes
         under, you know, and it keeps raising it up and it'll get built up
         til it looks like a mountain, you know. But you get on there and—
         four or five men and get slack in front, you know. Oh, maybe the
         width of this room, or something like that. Then if it does take a
         notion to go it'll leave the crown on piled higher, or swing and go
         off. That's the way that works.
         
         SS:   What about them jams that don't want to untagle? I know that hap
         pens now and then, you'd get one that would just build up real big
         and—
         
         WS:   Well, you stay with her, if you couldn't use powder. If you could use
         powder, use powder. (Loud knock at the door- Visitor: Bill, I don't
         know if you've read these or not. If you haven't, why, look 'em over
         and if you don't want 'em, throw 'em in the garbage.)
         
         SS:   Well known fellow around here.
         
         WS:   Yeah, he used to run camp for the Potlatch.
         
         SS:   I didn't know he run Camp 2. 
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. He run some of them donkey camps. He was . Pot
         latch Lumber Company, you know, before they consolidated with this
         Clearwater Timber Company. That was the Potlatch Lumber Company,
         you know.
         
         SS:   He was a foreman besides being a—he had a poolhall there?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah, he a joint there. His wife run a restaurant and he run
         the bar, and the poolhall. Just beer, but he drank whiskey all time,
         he always had a bottle of whiskey there, two or three, I don't know
         how many. But I wouldn't want to ride with him that day, I was coming
         over here I had been working in some of them camps there, Camp
         7 or 5 or maybe, some of 'em. And I quit and. in there in there
         in Bovill, and I was coming over here and I was gonna ride with him,
         but I didn't get up that morning, and by God, he got killed that same
         day.
         
         SS:   Driving?
         
         WS:   Yeah. The door flew open and he rolled out right under a big semi.
         Going around a turn, you know and he maybe leaned a little bit; an
         old pickup and the door flew open and he landed right under the
         wheel. Yeah, he was a good guy, that guy. But there was some guy,
         I can't think of his name now, that run that joint, he isn't there
         no more, he's around town, but he— there's someone else running the
         joint.
         
         SS:   I forget the guy's name, but there's still quite a few people go in
         there. People go drink at Bailey's, too, you know.
         
         WS:   Bailey's, that's the place. Yeah, that's the place.
         
         SS:   Well, there's Bailey's and then there's—
         
         WS:   Bailey don't run that no more, does he?
         
         SS:   No.
         
         WS:   No. Well, that's the guy, an old feller, big, old feller. Drank a
         lot of whiskey. Yeah, that's the guy I knew. Yeah, Bailey. Has the
         Potlatch got shops there yet?
         
         SS:   Gee, I don't know if they got— they got a little operation there,
         but I don't know how much of a shop there is, or how big it is. I'm
         sure it's nothing like what it used to be.
         
         WS:   Oh, no. Used to have an office there. Chet Yanjel did he die?
         
         SS:   He's still there.
         
         WS:   He retired.
         
         SS:   Yeah. Do you know Byers Sanderson?
         He's still there and his brother, John, is still there. John is
         quite old. Ernie Smith just died. Did you know him?
         
         SS:   Ernie Smith was in the shop all the time.
         
         WS:   I didn't know him. Some of those railroaders I knew. I see where
         one of 'em died here maybe six or seven years ago, the one I knew
         best.
         
         SS:   The depot agent was Joe Holland, he's still around. He's still around,
         He was the depot agent for about forty years.
         
         WS:   Old Pat Malloy.
         
         SS:   Did you know Pat Malone?
         
         WS:   Pat Malone I'm thinking of.
         
         SS:   That old sheriff, did you know him?
         
         WS:   Yes, Put me in jail there one time. I stayed in there four or five
         hours and he- come over and let me out. They was having a council
         meeting there that night, and I had to walk right through where it
         was. I don't know, I said some foolish Goddam thing, and I went on
         out the door.
         
         SS:   Well, Pat was kind of a joke.
         
         WS:   He didn't bother anybody, Christ you - fall right down in front
         of him to get pinched.
         
         He drank a hell of a lot. He had quite a reputation.
         
         Drank, you say?
         
         Yeah
         
         Oh, yes. Yes, he used to be drunker'n somebody he'd punch, you know.
         Oh, yes, he would tell a guy, you know, he'd tell 'em, "Go on over
         there and lie down for a while." That's all he'd say. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:   Was he better than most of these town
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, Christ, he didn't bother nobody.
         
         SS:   Yes, I kinda thought that.
         
         WS:   Christ, there used to be a lot of lumberjacks around there then.
         Right after this whiskey was legalized, you know. Things started to
         pick up a little bit, you know. And there was several camps around
         there. Horses. That's about the time they was changing then. Pot
         latch had some awful good horses, you know. Jesus, they were wonder
         ful. Old Nogle was the horse buyer. Is he living yet?
         
         No, he's dead but one of the sons, but one of the sons died not long
         ago. The son named after him.
         
         WS:   Yeah, Clare, He died on the Coast.
         
         But his other son's still on the Coast.
         
         WS:   What's he doing? Still in the lumber industry?
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   Some kind of a ?
         
         SS:   I don't know what he was, but his other son is still there;
         'em. Did you ever know this Dick Ferrell?
         
         WS:   Who?
         
         SS:   Dick Ferrell, a lumberjack?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. I knew him well. Yeah.
         
         SS:   What did you think of him?
         He was alright. He was a good guy. I don't know whether he was sincere
         or not, but he He come to camp every once in a while,
         Didn't make any difference who was hiking on the trail when he come
         along, he'd take your packsack and go. If you was, you know, half
         drunk or something, he'd take your sack and carry it right into camp.
         And he'd get up at night and give a little speil. Everybody'd go
         you know, because they liked him. I think maybe he had some other
         means of support, but that's all I know of, is what he got around
         camps. He was an expug.
         
         That's what I heard. I wonder if that's why people, you know— guys
         listened to him a little more, because they knew he'd been there.
         I don't know. I guess that's something he just picked up. I don't
         know whether he was sincere about it or not. But he talked it any
         way. He talked like he was sincere, you know.
         
         SS:   Was he fire and brimstone? Or was he ?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. Yeah. (Chuckles)
         
         SS:   I'd think he'd be talking to the wrong bunch if he (Chuckles)
         wake you of
         
         WS:   Well, they listened to him. He'd come around if you was asleep, tell
         you, Come on, come on over. 
         
         SS:   When you guys were in camp did you have— was there much reading mat
         erial around?
         
         WS:   No. No. Not years ago; there was nothing, except what somebody brought
         in there. You take like Bradbury, Howard jury, he was awful good, he
         was superintendent up there, you know. He always come in with a load
         of magazines and stuff like that, but otherwise there was nothing. No
         body brought anything with 'em when they come in. Daily papers, that
         was out, you know. There was no such a thing. The mail'd come in, oh,
         once a week maybe or something like that. Packhorse, you know. Pack
         string. And, if you had any mail you'd get it, and of course, if
         you didn't, of course you didn't. I never had no mail come in or
         anything like that, but I used to like that old paper once in a while,
         of course, everybody did. Like sports, you know, or something. Christ
         I used to be lost in the summertime. I liked baseball, you know,
         and I used to follow that pretty close. But, everything'd go right
         by me.
         
         SS:   There'd be a World Series and-
         
         It's be over with. Yeah.I used to take time off at the Series some
         times and come out.
         
         You could do that pretty easy, I nean, you could leave if you wanted
         to.
         
         Oh, Christ, you could leave anytime.
         
         SS:   That's a pretty good deal.
         
         WS:   Well, there's some of them guys didn't stay over ten days anyway. Just
         enough to make a road stake and move on. But I never that way,
         if I got a job that I liked and making money, I'd stay with it, you
         know, for quite a while. But then, when I went to town after after
         I went broke I always go someplace else. You know, move around a
         little bit. See how they done things other places.-
         Well, when do you figure on completing this book?
         
         SS:   Oh, it's probably going to be a couple of years.
         
         WS:   Oh, quite a while. Well, there's more than you working on it?
         
         SS:   Nope. Just me.
         
         WS:   Just you? Well, I'll be damned.
         
         SS:   That's why it takes so long. Just going from camp to camp now. That's
         something that you didn't like to do. But did most of the guys like
         to move around like that?
         
         WS:   Oh, probably, half of 'em, yeah. Some of 'em used to stay, but.
         fifty percent of 'em that was what they called jumping jacks, you know.
         They'd work a few days and go. Yeah, there were lots of them.
         
         SS:   Was it always by yourself, or did you chum around with— would you
         go with another guy?
         
         WS:   Well, when there was different ones come out— that was when I come
         to this country— you always had a pardner, you know. If you were fall
         ing, you had a pardner. You usually travel with them or pick somebody
         else up. Or you went into camp alone, the push would mate you up
         with somebody, you know. If he wanted you to go to work. I'd travel
         around with some guy, oh, maybe two or three years at a time, the same
         guy, you know I'd work with. Some guy you'd like. Good man
         you know. I would stay with him. And someone you i get along
         with you, know. That way, it matte work a little easier. You knew
         what he was going to do all the time. That way, why, you'd keep your
         pardners you see. I've waited in town for several days for a guy
         to get sobered up to rk. Or he'd wait for me, or something like
         that.
         
         SS:   Well, was it—Were there other gyppo jobs besides falling that you'd
         need two men?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah, skidding.
         
         SS:   Two men?
         
         WS:   Teamster and a swamper.
         
         SS:   Did you do a lot of both of them?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Both falling and skidding?
         
         WS:   No. No. I didn't do any falling.
         
         SS:   Oh. But you did the skidding and swamping?
         
         WS:   Yeah. That's about all I did. That is, for years, you know. There
         was pretty fair money in it. Oh, I don't know, I liked horses, so I
         stayed with it.
         
         SS:   You did that by marking out strips, and you took a strip?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   And you did that for so much for the whole strip? Or did they do it
         by the thousand?
         
         WS:   Well, it was by the thousand, but the way it used to be, they'd— a
         strip would be all blazed out, you know. Up this draw, or some place.
         And it would run back to the and it depends on what the timber
         was and everything. It would all be felled, you see ahead, you know.
         And they'd set a price on it. You'd go out and look at it. Like you
         come into camp this afternoon. And the push d comeA and say, Want
         to go to work?" You'd say, "Yeah." "Well, come on then, and I'll show
         you a strip." So he'd take you out. He wouldn't go over the strip
         with you, but he'd take you down the flume or up the chute, or where
         ever the hell it was, and say, "There you are." A line here and
         other lines up there— "Look it over." Well, then you would, you see.
         And he'd already told you the price, you see. Then you'd go back to
         camp and probably the next morning, he'd say, "Well, you gonna take
         that patch?" "Well," you'd say, "you gotta raise the ante a little
         bit." Something like that, you see. "I can't go no higher." Well,
         then you'd take it or leave it, you see. And probably leave it, and
         go. But, if he'd raise it two-bits or something— say the price was
         two and a half a thousand or three or four or five or something—if
         you wanted four-bits or a dollar or two-bits more, why, you'd tell him.
         If he seen fit to give it to you, he would, and if he didn't, he
         wouldn't. You could go or take it, one or the other; whatever you
         wanted to do.
         
         SS:   You could size it up pretty good without doing it on how much it
         would take you to make good money on it? You could just tell from
         looking at it.
         
         WS:   Yes, if you had a pardner that you knew and you knew what he could do,
         you could tell just about how close you could come. You know, just
         about how you could come out. Yeah.
         
         SS:   What was the difference?— Did it vary a lot, how much money you'd
         be able to make on gyppoing? I mean, did it change a lot? Or was it
         pretty much set?
         
         WS:   No. No. Like this Potlatch, it was pretty much of a— they'd let you
         make so much. If you went over that, they'd cut the price, after you
         started on . Some outfits didn't.
         
         SS:   They'd cut it while you were still on the strip? Sounds like—
         
         WS:   You signed a contract, but it didn't mean nothing, you know. Except
         if you killed a horse, or something like that. You had to pay for it.
         A team of horses was valued at five hundred dollars. That was standard
         value. But, if you killed one or both of 'em— that hap
         pen very, very seldom. But if you broke a leg or something— like I
         mean a horse's leg or something— they'd naturally destroy 'em, you
         see. But that didn't happen very often.
         
         SS:   It sounds like — I mean, they change the price in the middle of the—
         doing a strip, it didn't pay for you to work too hard or you wouldn't—
         
         WS:   Well,-
         
         SS:   You worked too hard and make too much money—
         
         WS:   You take like at Bovill— at one time you could make about a hundred
         dollars a month; a hundred five, a hundred and ten, or ninety, something
         like that, just stay in between that. There was nobody
         went over that, regardless of the price. But when this Clearwater
         started up, they were a little different. Nobody majle the same. You
         could— you got a good strip, a big enough strip that you could lay
         it out properly and go ahead, you see and figure it to your best advan
         tage, you know, leave some shorthaul and take the long with the short
         and keep it mixed up you could come out with a pretty fair average.
         That's the way I always did it. And most of 'em did it that way.
         
         SS:   What's this idea that— to mix short and longs?
         
         WS:   Well, there was some long skidding, you know. Maybe— well, we skid
         ded three thousand feet, thirty-five hundred feet, you know, and some
         of it would be a couple of hundred feet.
         
         SS:   You'd mix 'em.
         
         WS:   Uh-huh. That's right. Like, if you didn't time to make a trip, you
         see, maybe you was skidding four trips a day, maybe, using dogs, you
         see— You know what them dogs are?
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   Well, you maybe— say it was steep ground and you was using maybe
         twenty-five dogs— well, you was making four trips and you couldn't
         get— you'd get caught short some day and you couldn't make four—
         Well, you'd wn on the short haul, leave the swamper up in
         the woods, let him stay there. You'd pick up some handy stuff, enough
         to keep your average up. That's the way that worked.
         
         SS:   Did they pay your bonus on the— if you hit a certain amount every
         day?
         
         WS:   Yeah, yeah. The Winton Lumber Company, they were Coeur d'
         Alene, they set a price and didn't change. They might raise it if
         you weren't making it and they wanted you to stay, they might raise
         it. But, otherwise it didn't change, and if you made a hundred dol
         lars a day, they paid you. But nobody ever did that, you know. Re
         gardless of what you were making they'd leave the price after they
         set it.
         
         SS:   That sounds really bad to me, changing the price in the middle. I
         mean if they make a deal, it ought to be a deal.
         
         WS:   I know, but, I didn't say they cut the price, but they'd raise the
         price, if you weren't making it on a strip. I never knew 'em to cut
         any.
         
         SS:   Are you talking about Potlatch?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Oh. They raise it?
         
         WS:   Yeah, if you weren't making it.
         
         SS:   That's different. That's Okay then.
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   I've heard it said that if you made good on one, that's when they try
         to cut you back, so that you wouldn't—
         Well, you — when you took another one.
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   Well, they all tried that. Yeah, that was customary.
         
         SS:   That'd be a good reason for leaving to go to another place, wouldn't
         it?
         
         WS:   Yeah. That's usually what they did. Most guys quit after they'd
         put a strip in anyhow of any size, say a couple of months, you know.
         
         SS:   That much.
         
         WS:   Yeah, when they'd get the strip in, they'd go. And when they got
         ready to go, why, they'd go back to maybe someplace else, or maybe
         back there. It didn't make any difference.
         
         SS:   Well, how big a strip are we talking about?
         
         WS:   Oh, some were a hundred thousand and some were a million.
         
         SS:   How many acres?
         
         WS:   Oh, I wouldn't know. I wouldn't know about the acreage.
         
         SS:   It sounds pretty big. Couple of months is a lot of work.
         
         WS:   Yeah. But, I know a guy that went into camp and took a million feet;
         all summer, all summer long. Maybe he wouldn't get it ain, but they
         knew who they were giving it to, see. They were pretty steady guys.
         They wouldn't give it to somebody that was just going to dig in a
         little while and then and then wheel, you know.
         
         SS:   How big— how many men would be in these camps, guys working on the
         strips?
         
         WS:   Oh, a hundred and fifty.
         
         SS:   In camp?
         
         WS:   Yeah. That's about the average.
         
         SS:   Were these camps tent or car camps, or what?
         
         WS:   Both. Frame, tent and cars. Railroad camps, sometimes was car camps,
         but like the but like the Jrhmt camps, they was all either rag camps,
         either tents or frame. Potlatch had a couple of log camps. Built a
         couple of log camps.
         
         SS:   Were they just the older camps that were standing there? I mean, them
         early camps were—
         
         WS:   What?
         
         SS:   Them early camps were log?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, sure, they all were. But, no, they built Camp G up there on
         Silver Creek.
         
         SS:   And that was a log camp?
         
         WS:   Yes, that was built in '31.
         
         SS:   Well, what did you think of the Was there any one kind of the camps
         that was usually better, or better to live in?
         
         WS:   Yes, yes.
         
         SS:   — than others? Which was the best?
         
         WS:   Well, the way it worked, wherever there was a good cook, that's where
         I'd go. I used to kind of keep track of the cooks. There was a lot
         of bum ones and a lot of good ones then, you know. The good ones
         were well known, so were the bum ones. I used to kinda keep track
         of the good ones and go where they were.
         
         SS:   Did you know Shorty Justice?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes.
         
         SS:   I talked to him in Spokane.
         
         WS:   Is he living?
         
         SS:   Oh, sure.
         
         WS:   Jesus Christ, he cooked the last time I worked, he was cooking at
         Camp 5 Bovill on the highway, on the highway. 
         
         SS:   He was supposed to have been a pretty good cook.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. He was a good cook, yes. Sure he was. Hell yes. I ate a
         lot of his chuck. He's living?
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   He must be pretty old.
         
         SS:   Oh, he's about eighty.
         
         WS:   Yes. You talked to him in Spokane?
         
         SS:   Yes. After he left this country, he went and he was purchasing agent
         for the Ridpath there in Spokane. For that big hotel there. That's
         what he did.
         
         WS:   He bought the chuck?
         
         SS:   Yeah. Bought for 'em.
         
         WS:   That was just a sideline for him, he wasn't doing that with his full
         time?
         
         SS:   I don't know what else he was doing.
         
         WS:   Probably wasn't doing nothing else. That's after he was retired?
         
         SS:   Yes. Well, was there really a big difference between the good chuck
         and the bad?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah.
         
         SS:   World of difference?
         
         WS:   Yes. Yeah, a bum cook, you know, he wasted so much. Garbage can's
         full all the time. But a good cook he'd take the leftovers and he'd
         do something with 'em, and they'd be good, you know. Fred Thomas, he
         lived in Coeur d'Alene— he must be dead— he was an awful good cook.
         He used to cook on Marble Creek on the drive. You know where Marble
         Creek is?
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   I drove there for quite a few years. The Rutledge Timber Company.
         And I seen him poach eggs right on the bank of the river for a hun
         dred and fifty men in the morning. That is something, isn't it?
         By Jesus! He was a dandy cook and a good guy. I haven't
         seen him since he left over here.
         
         SS:   What kind of outfit did they have to cook on? On the river drives?
         They didn't have a full camp cookout? Did they have to move the damn
         thing?
         
         WS:   Well, yeah. Well, you'd either throw everything in a couple of boats
         or put it on a packstring.
         
         SS:   Did they have a big heavy cookstove?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. Sure. Like this river here, you know, the cook had it good
         here. A lot of 'em didn't like it. They had everything right in front
         of 'em all the time. It was only thirty men, you know. But— why
         they could bake bread while were moving. You take like Marble
         Creek and the Coeur d'Alene River and them— Priest River and them,
         they would. Well, they'd throw everything in a boat and move maybe
         five miles, six, miles9 three miles or something, that depends on
         the down the river, and then the cook would have to come and
         have the supper ready for a hundred men maybe, from three o'clock
         on in the afternoon to set that camp up. That was something. 'Course
         the push, he'd always give the cook lots of help, you know, off of
         the river crew, you know. And the guys liked to do that, too, you
         know. Change. You take like— well, after you've been at that old
         drive— I drove a hundred days one time. One hundred days without,
         well, just every day the same Goddam thing. And we had the camp on
         the banks. We'd move five or six miles, packstring. Well, we got to
         take that stove all apart.
         
         SS:   Oh, yes. Huh.
         
         WS:   Well, they'd have to put that on a mule. Pretty hard to get it bal
         anced up, you know. You overload the poor old mule. You know what
         a big stove'll weigh.
         
         SS:  Yeah.
         
         Well, he used to have packsaddles built like a sawhorse, you know,
         take everything off of the stove you could and put it right on top of
         them, and lash it down, you know. But they were big, strong mules;
         good mules. Just like the government had in the Forest Service, they
         got good mules. But, Jesus Christ, that was an awful job.
         
         Moving that camp?
         
         Yeah.
         
         Every day.
         
         Not every day. No.
         
         No, that's right, you'd move it -
         
         Whenever you needed to. Whenever you got too far away to hike. It
         was all hiking. Fact, lately here, the last few years I was on here
         they had jet boats on this river. Christ, you didn't hike no place.
         Jump in one of them' go up river, down river, anywheres. Nothing to
         it! And them fellers kicking!
         
         It must have been a whole day's proposition to break the camp down
         and move it and set it up.
         
         Oh, yeah. You'd take a lunch that day, you see. Cook would have a
         lunch ready for you in the morning in a paper sack. You'd take that
         lunch that day. That's the only day you took a lunch, otherwise you'd
         come in. But that day you took a lunch. As time went on, you know
         and two or three moves and four or five moves, pretty soon there was
         only two or three more moves to make, you know. That's the way I
         looked at it.
         
         Would it be maybe once a week or twice a week that you'd move that?
         Depends on the water, —
         
         How fast you're moving on the river?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Well, now like on the drive, when you worked a hudnred days— would
         you be doing much work from day-to-day, or would it wind up being a—
         would you tive one job— would you be set on a— the same job on the
         whole trip? How did they break 'em down? You'd be a peavey hand?
         
         WS:   Yeah. I never run boat. I'd just ding around a little but, but
         I never— I was always peavey. I don't know why I— I never cared
         to run boat. Well, there's too much responsibility. They swamped
         them boats, too, you know. Lose men, Jesus Christ! No, I never
         wanted nothing to do with that.
         
         SS:   Well, working on a peavey, did you have much— wouldn't it have
         been pretty tricky when you were breaking a jam?
         
         WS:   Yeah, you had to know your business. If you wanted to drift you
         had to be able to take care of yourself, you know. If
         a chunk broke off or something and the boat couldn't get to you,
         why, it was up to you. The crew might scatter, you see. Might be
         a man here and a man here. Well, you can't get 'em all. There's
         somebody got to ride her out, you know. They'd usually pick up the
         ones was least capable, you know, and to hell with the other
         son of a bitch, let him go. He'd make 'er. That's the way they fig
         ured it.
         
         SS:   Well, what would you do if you got cut adrift like that? You'd be
         on a log?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Just have to hang on to it?
         
         WS:   Well, you'd stay with it. It didn't seem to bother them guys much.
         I was the same way. If you went adrift, you went adrift. That was
         up to you then. Lot of 'em did it apurpose to get out of work. Sure,
         ride around a bend or two and jump off. If it's a nice sunny day,
         lay down. Sure, I've done it myself, too. (Chuckles) I've done it
         myself a thousand times, not a thousand times, but I did it quite
         often. If I didn't feel like working. But, I don't know, I kind
         of liked to work. I'd stick around and bullshit, you know. (Laughs)
         
         SS:   Well, I think about having to— about living in a camp of ahundred
         and fifty men for months at a time, I think about that— I've never
         had to live that close, you know to men all the time, and get along.
         Used to short period of time, you know. It's a little like the army
         that way. All be in one place together all the time. I was think
         ing about that. You'd all have to be able to all get along pretty
         good or it would be pretty easy to get a lot of tension going.
         
         WS:   Well, nowa days, I there would be, but at that time there
         wasn't. But nowadays, I believe that people are different. I don't
         believe these young fellows could do that. I don't know why, or
         what makes me think that, but I don't believe they could. I think
         they'd be more fistiicuffs going on and the likes of that, you know.
         
         SS:   Maybe they're more selfish, I don't know. It seems like if you're
         not as used to thinking about considering other people maybe. May
         be that part— I don't know.
         
         WS:   I don't know. I couldn't say, but I've often thought about that.
         I believe if you put them in together for six months at a time —
         Of course, they work every day. They get rid of their energy that
         way, you know. But otherwise, I don't know - how it
         would work out. Well, it'd be more or less as bad as being in prison,
         wouldn't it?
         
         SS:   Well, if a person is in prison, you can't go ride a log around—1
         
         WS:   no, but I mean— be the same thing every day, every day, every
         day, you know. Of course, you might come home at night and you
         can relax, play poker, wash clothes, and you're tired anyway, you
         know from working all day. First thing you know it's bedtime and
         down you go. Of course, I don t know, these young fellows now,
         I can't see 'em doing that. It seems like— well, they don't work
         as hard, when they do work. And it seems like they always want to
         go someplace, you know. Go. Go. Go. They've all got cars, you
         know.
         
         SS:   That's got to be part of it— to be back there and isolated for a
         long time, that'd drive guys crazy. I don't mind it. I've worked
         on lookouts and that kind of thing and been up there for months
         and I kind of enjoy it, but then you're kind of by yourself, too.
         
         WS:   Oh, Jesus, I don't like being alone. Do you?
         
         SS:   Well, you know, it's been a while since I have been. It's hard to
         know. Back for a while I didn't mind it. But I don't know how I'd
         feel about it now.
         
         WS:   Yeah, it's kind of hard to say.
         
         SS:   You weren't alone in the woods at all.
         
         WS:   Oh, Christ, there was always something going on. And at night there'd
         always be some new guys come in, you know. Guys that you knew and
         you'd get to talking to them and find out what's going on here and
         there and around the country, you know. Sure, I always)used to look
         for who come around in the evening, you know, other guys. with
         'em. If they didn't go to work, you'd always slip 'em a little money
         you know. Ten or twenty or something you know to go on, see. You
         know. They'd pay you back maybe five years from then, or whenever
         they met you and had it, that's when you'd get it.
         
         SS:   But they wouldn't forget?
         
         WS:   Oh, no, no. nc! Christ, no. If you ever met 'em and they had it you'd
         get it. And if they didn't have it, you wouldn't, that's all there
         was to it. Simple as that.
         
         SS:   What about these kind of guys that— I'm sure there must have been
         some guys in the camp that were really jerks. You know, guys that
         just there must have been guys that were just no good.
         
         WS:   Yeah. Sure.
         
         SS:   What about them guys. Did they get kicked out of camp?
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. Them old-time pushes would get wise to one of them right
         quick, you know. There was some of 'em, they would try 'em at dif
         ferent jobs, trying to find out something they could do, and even
         tually they'd either let 'em go or find something they could do.
         Them old-time pushes was pretty fair. A lot of 'em were tough, you
         know, too. Out, you know! But a lot of 'em were good
         They were reasonable men. I knew a guy on Mica Creek, a push, you
         could go and lean up against an old stump all summer and he wouldn't
         fire you, but he wouldn't hire you back the next year. You could
         stay there as long as you want to, but, of course, you had to do a
         little something, but no matter how ma ch it was, if you were work
         ing by the day, he'd leave you there. He wouldn't never tell you to
         go. He might make it a little miserable sometimes for you, but he'd
         never can you. But the next spring, of course, no use acomin' around
         to him. He wouldn't hire you.
         
         SS:   So, he was a pretty nice fcuy?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, sure.
         
         SS:   What was his name?
         
         WS:   Fife. Steve Fife. That was Mica Creek.
         
         SS:   What about a guy that got a— Did some 'jacks get bad reputations
         with the— with other men? Did they get an idea that this guy was
         no good? And to stay away from him?
         
         WS:   Yes, Yes. He was pretty much a loner then.
         
         SS:   I'd imagine.
         
         WS:   They wouldn't have anything to do with him. Didn't want to work with
         him. If they did they'd do something to drive him off the job, you
         know. Try to kill him, maybe. Can't tell.
         
         SS:   What would a guy do to get a reputation like that? Steal, or lie?
         
         WS:   Just no good. Don't pay your bills; pay any debts. Never give any-
         body any help, that needed it, you know. You were in a position to
         help him or something like that .would put the injun sign on him.
         
         SS:   You know, I've been thinking about the Wobblies since we talked before
         and this is really interesting to me - that union. It just sounds
         like a good union. I like the sound of the way they were democratic.
         The way they really seemed to be out for the men instead of themselves.
         
         WS:   Yes, they were real good. The only reason the IWW's isn't in force
         today - it was revolutionary. You see, they believed in the over
         throw of the government by force. That was right in the preamble of
         the constitution, 
         
         SS:   Trying to overthrow the government, but trying to improve conditions
         of the men.
         
         WS:   Yes, that's exactly what they did. But that was in their, as I say,
         in their preamble to the constitution: overthrow of the government,
         by force, if necessary. But, of course, it never come to that, but
         they had some awful hard battles, you know, the IWW's. In the mines,
         you know, and on the Coast, here. They were run down by practically
         everybody except those that belonged to 'em. All these civic organ
         izations was against 'em, you know. American Legion was was deacon
         'em. They lined right up in front of the hall there in Centralia
         and opened fire on 'em! There was four or five killed that time.
         Of course, the Wobblies, they shot back, they had arm, too, you
         know. There was some of 'em, I don't know whether there's any of
         'em left in jail yet, or not. Wesley Everetts, he was one of the last
         ones. They were all tried for murder. Five of 'em I think there
         was that time. But the last stand the IWW made was right here in
         this country; '36, that was Diane Everetts.
         
         SS:   What happened that time? Did they get very far?
         
         WS:   No. Well, the company wanted 'em out. They wanted to break the
         strike, which they eventually did. They got a bunch of gunmen, you
         know and started the shooting works, you see. They killed three that
         time. That night. They tried those guys that— they only got two
         hundred and fifty dollar fine. Eight or nine of 'em.
         
         SS:   Where did this happen? 
         
         WS:   Well, the shooting happened up here Pond, just out of Pierce.
         We were coming off the picket line. I was in the bunch. There was
         about twenty-four of us in the truck, I think, an old flatbed with
         with stake rack. And it was just about dusk, they were up on the
         sidehill, you know; nine of 'em, I think there was, nine rifles in
         the bunch, And they just started blasting, you see. Just
         in discriminately, you know.
         
         SS:   Into the back of the truck? 
         
         WS:   Yeah. I baled outfand (Chuckles) They shot through
         the windshield first. Stopped the truck, you know. But the law
         come, the state troopers, you See Pierce was under martial law
         then. The troopers was— I don't know how they happened to get there.
         They must have been planted or something around there, because they
         come right now; eight or nine of 'em. They broke it up. And they
         pinched quite a bunch. It was dark I hid out. I didn't want to
         go back to Pierce. I knew I'd get pinched. So I started hiking
         come daylight the next morning. I was going to Missoula. I made
         Missoula. I had maybe a hundred dollars in my pocket and a ranger
         picked me up that was going in the general direction, you see.The
         second day he picked me up. He had an old pickup of some kind. He
         knew right where I come from and everything. The pickup was parked
         along this old— just like an old skidding trail, it was— and I
         come along. I didn't go by it, I stopped and waited, you see. I
         knew there was someone around there. 
         
         I see the sign on the— US
         Forest Service, so he come pretty quick. He said, "How's everything
         in Pierce?"  was a hundred and fifty miles from Pierce then!
         I said, "Alright, I guess." So he said, "You going to Missoula?"
         I said, "Yes." So I jumped in with him. And we got to talking.
         He give me a couple of sandwiches, and he let me off in Missoula.
         Really, he knew; I told him where I was from and everything. 
         knew that he knew it, "Sure, I come from Pierce." Well, we had a
         hall in Missoula then, the IWW. Or, I didn't go there when I first
         got to town, I stayed a day, I think it was, and then I went down
         to the hall. They knew I was in town. I went down. You know how
         the word gets around, grapevine business and one thing and another.
         Someone had seen me, of course. I knew a few around there, not too
         many. It was a long time since I'd been there. But I went down to
         the hall and got to BSing with some of them guys. They told me the
         FBI was around there.
         
         SS:   Pierce or Missoula?
         
         WS:   Missoula. So, the next day I got picked up. I was in a bar. I
         was sober, but I was having a drink or two and this guy— I looked
         in the mirrotf—was watching me, you know. And everytime I looked
         he was watching me. He was standing back next to the wall. I fig
         ured I'm going back and ask him what the hell he sees about me that
         looks so funny. I turned to go back and he met me then, you know.
         Showed me the business; FBI. Took me down to the sheriff's office
         and I stayed that night there and he brought me back to Orofino.
         Didn't take me to Pierce, took me to Orofino jail. The rest of our
         crew was in there, you see. Seven or eight of 'em, I guess. So
         that jail filled up so they brought me down here.
         
         SS:   Lewiston?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   What did they hold you for?
         
         WS:   Inciting a riot. That was the charge.
         
         SS:   Was that supposed to be because you encouraged those thugs to shoot
         the guys in the pickup truck?
         
         WS:   I don't know. I don't know how you could incite a riot out in the
         woods! Well, of course, I didn't contest it. We got a lawyer from
         Spokane. I got eleven months. A year.
         
         SS:   Did you serve it?
         
         WS:   Yeah. Right here.
         
         SS:   In town? What about the other guys? Them, too?
         
         WS:   Well, yeah. iey : a few months Let's see, who was sheriff then?
         Dent. Dent. Oh, yes, I was a trustee. I used to go out, get
         half drunk, go back again. But I served about eleven months, I think
         it was. Then when I got out, of course, they were all back working
         and they'd called the strike off long before that. Oh, they called
         the strike off in August, I think. That's just a few days after
         the shooting match. They had to, you know, they was broke anyway.
         But the company did clean up a lot of things, during the strike
         and afterwards, see. Well, we never had sheets on our beds before.
         They put sheets on.
         
         SS:   This was in '36?
         
         WS:   Yeah. Every week you could get sheets, or twice a week, if you wanted
         'em. It made a difference. But I didn't go back to work here for
         five years.
         
         SS:   What did you do?
         
         WS:   Well, I went to the Coast; California, Montana, all over. But I
         was blackballed on the Coast, same as here, you know. I'd work about
         ten days and they'd get word, you see. Call me in— well, I'd know
         what it was. So I went down to Crater Lake, I knew a guy down there,
         he was running camp and it was getting along towards Christmas time
         and I thought, "By God, I'm going to make a Christmas stake somewhere,
         so I'll go there." went there. His name was Gaffney. He used to
         be superintendent for the Rutledge, that's how I knew him, you see.
         He was running a camp there. So I went in there, went right to work.
         I'd been there about ten days when the clerk came in one night and
         he says, "Mr. Gaffney wants to see you over at his house." He lived
         in a house. He was a married man, you see. So, I didn't go over.
         I knew what it was, you know. So I just packed my sack and went to
         bed. The next morning, why, the clerk come in again, says, "You
         didn't go over to see Mr. Gaffney?" I said, "No." "Well, he wants
         to see you." I said, "I know what he wants." So he came in the
         bunkhouse after the crew left, and told me, "I gotta let you go."
         
         And he showed me the list; there was about a hundred names on it.
         That's the only time I ever seen that list. I was about the fourth
         or fifth name I think on it. But they got new labor laws in then,
         about discrimination and all this and that. I come over here to
         Orofino and was skidding poles for Charlie Clark— he lives over
         in your country. Palouse it is. He's in Spokane now, he's
         about ninety years old. I heard about him the other day. I was up
         there to skid poles for him on Orofino Creek, and this Nelson, they
         had an office there, you know, personnel office where they hired.
         And this Nelson, he was the hiring agent, and I was in the City Club
         and he come in there, and he looked all around him and tapped on the
         window, and I went out. He said, "Do you want to go to work?" I
         said, "Where at?" I knew him, you see. He used to be postmaster in
         Headquarters. He's a graduate of Moscow, up here. I said, "Yeah."
         He said, "Go up to -bwl ." I said, "Alright." So I went up
         the next day. That was in '41. And I left in '36; just five years.
         
         SS:   And you didn't get canned?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. I set right in again solid and I've been there ever since.^
         You see, I didn't go any place after that.
         
         SS:   Well, did you lead the '36 strike?
         
         WS:   Oh, no.
         
         SS:   Is that why they put you up so high on the list?
         
         WS:   No. No, I was an active member, is what I was. Just a member. I
         never held no position or nothing you know what I mean: I was
         never on a strike committee. I was just a member. But I happened
         to get involved, you see at certain times. Certain things happened, happened to be
         there. Like that shooting match, see.
         Ordinarily if it had happened at any other time, I wouldn't have
         been there. And then running away, you see, and all that I guess
         padded up, 
         
         SS:   Well, when the '36 strikes started did (it) come from out of Spokane?
         Or did it start from around here?
         
         WS:   No. It started here.
         
         SS:   Was it from meeting and guys deciding to do it?
         
         WS:   Yes. You see, the IWW is different from the IWA or the CIO or some
         thing like that, you know. If there was enough here for a meeting,
         say five or seven or whatever it was, you could hold a meeting here,
         right in the camp, you see and decide on what to do there with that
         particular camp. You didn't have to send to no executivabranch or
         international orfolace, you could act on the job. And that's what
         happened here. Individual camps and then they just all come together,
         you know and elected a general strike committee and set
         date and presented our demands and they were turned down, of course
         and the strike was on. That's the way that happened.
         
         SS:   Was this '36 strike then the whole thing just Clearwater Timber?
         
         WS:   No, it was general.
         
         SS:   Potlatch's over North Idaho and Eastern Washington?
         
         WS:   Yes, Winton, and Diamond and Long Lake and all of 'em. The whole
         works. And that was it. It lasted two months. And the companies^
         they had to shut these mills down, you know.
         
         SS:   In Lewiston?
         
         WS:   There was no logs. And the mill wasn't out, you see, the mill didn't
         belong to us.
         
         SS:   The woods? They couldn't get no logs down to the mill?
         
         WS:   Yes,.no logs. The millpond was empty. And they wanted to start that
         mill, you see. It was affecting too many people. So that's the cause
         of the shooting. See, they started this bullet throwing deal, you
         know, in order to get the law in and break it, you see, is
         what happened and what they wanted. They don't care much for human
         like, you know in a case of that kind.
         
         SS:   Not if it's going to get in the way of profits.
         
         WS:   Oh, no. That's it. Yeah.
         
         SS:   Well, the men that did the shooting—were they Potlatch men?
         
         WS:   Yeah. They were working for Fromos, most of 'em.
         
         SS:   For who?
         
         WS:   Frank Fromos. He was a big, big gyppo for the Potlatch.
         
         SS:   What about the men that were killed? Did you know 'em pretty well?
         
         WS:   I knew 'em just as well as I knew myself. Yeah. One of 'em was
         paralyzed, he didn't die right away, he died in the hospital in Orofino.
         The other two died, in a matter of days, three.
         
         SS:   Do you remember these guys, who they were, their names?
         Country
         
         WS:   Old Mike's the only one I can remember. I can't remember the
         rest of them.
         
         SS:   County Mike?
         
         WS:   Old Country Mike.
         
         SS:   Old Country? That's just bad. That's bad.
         
         WS:   Yeah. But it's the only way you could get 'er agoin', because we
         had no money, you know. The organization was broke, you know. But
         there was money coming in all the time from— a lot of it anonymous,
         you know. A hundred dollars, two hundred dollars and so on, you.
         There was quite a bit of it, enough to keep the thing going. We had
         to eat, you know. And, of course, a lot of 'em pulled out, you know.
         See, the Coast wasn't on strike, after the strike was six weeks old
         or so, a lot of these guys pulled out, went to the coast, went to
         work. Which was the only thing they could do. But we still kept
         a picket line on here, you know. And the railroad company, the emp-
         loyees, they recognized our picket lines, they wouldn't cross
         
         SS:   Were many loggers crossing the picket line around here?
         
         WS:   No.
         
         SS:   They weren't crossing it either? They'd respect it.
         
         WS:   No there wasn't a Goddam wheel turning. No.
         
         SS:   Do you remember the demands? I am sure that sheets would have been
         one of them. One of the demands. Right? The sheets.
         
         WS:   Yes. Oh, the camps were filthy then.
         
         SS:   That's funny, I thought they— You know they like to say they cleaned
         'em up after 1917.
         
         WS:   They did. But outfit wasn t started then, you know. This Potlatch,
         it didn't start until '26,- '25.
         
         SS:   So these camps down here never—
         
         WS:   Well, they started out good. Not sheets, but good chuck, good camps
         and everything. But they just seemed to deteriorate. Everything
         went to hell, you know.. Then they would build an old rag camp for
         you to sleep in. First thing you know it was full of holes and ev
         erything and no floors. Some of the bunkhouses right on the ground.
         And double bunks, you know. They'd settle down and the springs
         would be on the ground on the lower bunks, unless you shimmed up
         under 'em. Oh, it was awful. Yeah, there was a few concessions any
         way. Not directly to us, but that was the result.
         
         SS:   Could the— Could the IWW's guys fight back? Was there anything that
         they could do besides just run a picket line?
         
         WS:   That's all. The law was not with you.
         
         SS:   Sure.
         
         WS:   They were strictly against you. It ain't like now— These guys on
         strike now, they got certain law protection in lots of cases. And
         they go beyond that, too; get in trouble.
         
         SS:   I guess maybe partly because they don't think of- like the Wobblies
         they thought they were threatening worse than they were. These
         unions these days are pussy cats, you know. They're not about to
         really break things up.
         
         WS:   Oh, no. Once in a while— like when they were reorganizing the CIO,
         they got rough. ..Ford Motor Company, they had all
         kinds of gunmen hired for them. Special police.
         
         SS:   Yes. Well they kicked a bunch of - they kicked some of them unions
         out when they— it was going on. And some of the better ones, too.
         The Longshoremen. The West Coast Longshoremen;/kicked out. You
         know the philosophy — the revolutionary philosophy in overthrowing
         the government— what was it that the Wobblies figured would be the
         new— I mean, what would take its place?
         
         WS:   Well, I can't explain that to you. I used to have an idea what they
         meant.
         
         SS:   I was sort of figuring it would be some kind of workers control of—
         
         WS:   Well, yes. Like the different industries, you know, they were an in
         dustrial organization, the IWW. They have a head for the automobile
         industry, for the lumber industry and a head for transportation,
         and they'd all centralize in that— then they'd create a government
         that would function over all. I think that's the way it worked out.
         I can't think of any other way.
         
         SS:   So that the union would run the industry.
         
         WS:   Yeah, that's right.
         
         SS:   You know, there s an old-timer.Potlatch in a sawmill town you know,
         milltown, that I talked to — it's funny, 'cause he was telling me
         how in the 1917 strike how the company— all the propaganda that
         they laid down, all the propaganda about how bad the Bolsheviks and
         bomb throwers.were. And he said to me, "We believed that stuff."
         And he said, "That at some point, maybe a couple of years," he said,
         "I figured out just what they were doing." You know what the com
         pany would do and what the newspapers were doing, what the lawmen
         were doing. Just how we'd been had. They had given us a whole line
         of bullshit all along. And he said, "It just taught me that you can't
         believe what you read in the newspapers."
         I guess those guys in the sawmills and in the milltowns were—
         the company kind of controlled them pretty well.
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. The sawmills they were always apart from the woods until
         now. Now they're in with the woods. They all belong to the IWA.
         But that's what I argued, in this strike in '47, you know. I argued—
         You see, the mill is what put us out on the strike in '47. They went
         on strike; the mill. And that's what put us out. I argued to keep
         the mill out of our business, you know. 'Course, they couldn't be
         cause they all belonged to the same organization. Only different
         locals, you know. Our local's at Pierce and their's is down here
         at Clarkston. I think that's where the mill local is. So they fin
         ally went out first, you see, ahead of ours. Three or four days.
         So we had to go. You see the mill that was here long before
         we did. And the was right in behind our picket lines
         trying to organize those that were working at the time. Can you
         imagine that? Oh, it was a mixed up, Goddam, bolixed up affair.
         Potlatch Rose, they called her around here stumping around the street
         and talking in parks and everyplace. You know she was a woman.
         She was company hired, of course. She was a good talker. Oh she
         had a line of shit. She'd get an audience spellbound listening to
         her, you know.
         
         SS:   Was she good looking?
         
         WS:   Sure. Hell, yes! Well dressed. (Laughter) I had to laugh, i thought
         to myself, ''You Goddamned old son of a bitch, you're alright, tool"
         I heard her talk. I was in the mill. A bunch of us came down there
         one time. This picket line at the mill wasn't functioning very
         good, so they wanted some of us to come down, so we come down here.
         And she was out there and she talked right there. Why, Jesus Christ
         she could make you believe the Goddam river was running the other
         way! (Chuckles) Yeah, I liked her, I thought she was alright, you
         know. didn't believe it; she couldn't. She sure boosted that old
         Potlatch! (Laughter)
         
         SS:   It sounds like they were pretty crafty in knowing how to try —
         
         WS:   Ohhhhh! Jesus Christ, some of them personnel managers, you know,
         they're pretty smooth operators. And^they got their publicity men,
         This Beardsmore, that attorney,
         you know. Did you know him?
         
         SS:   No. I've heard about him.
         
         WS:   He was great. Yeah. I talked to him. We struck on the river here
         at different times, you know. Five times, I think we struck on this
         river. Won every time. Every time, we won. Strike for a dollar,
         you know. Something like that, a dollar a day. Get 'er every time!
         Might have to hang up a couple of days, or something like that. But
         Beardsmore always come up.
         
         SS:   Would this be during the drive?
         
         WS:   Yeah. Mutiny Bar, we struck there three times.
         
         SS:   Mutiny Bar? (Chuckles)
         
         WS:   Yeah, that's right up here. Oh, it's a rock bound son of a bitch of
         a place. It's above Junction a ways. Jesus! it's an aw
         ful place. Everybody'd be tired and half pissed off, and somebody'd
         quit or something and^someone'd say, "Let's go for four bits or a
         dollar? It's a good chance." So we'd stack arms, get 'er, you see,
         right away; next day. Some of them bigwigs'd come up from the mill,
         "Go ahead." That's all there is to it. But it's easy to win on a
         drive. I've never seen a driving crew lose yet. No. I've been on
         a lot of strikes on drives, you know. But I never did see one lose.
         
         Would these be— you wouldn't go through the union for that, would
         you? I mean, that'd just be a bunch of guys.
         
         Well, this is a wildcatter here, yeah.
         
         What was the union? Was that CIO then?
         
         Yeah. The last time we struck.
         
         I guess that's kind of a deal, if you strike when you've got the
         cards in there, you can win.
         
         That was the only way. That was the Wobbly theory, "Strike when the
         they argued, iron's hot." But, by Jesus— well, this last time, of course,"We
         got a contract. We got a contract." I told 'em "To hell with the
         contract!" I said,"I've drove on this Goddam river for three dollars
         a day, and ten dollars a day and fifteen dollars a day," and I said,
         "my labor's worth twenty dollars a day now, before I go another God
         damn inch!" Yeah, you could always win on a drive, but them camps,
         oh, Jesus, they'd always have a big supply of logs out here every
         time we struck, you know. By the time they were used up we were
         starved out. Ready to go. See how that works.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13498</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Stowell1</previous>
      <next>Stowell3</next>
      <disp_name>Stowell2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
