<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/29/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>William Stowell, 1975-10-29, Interview #1 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:56:09</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Stowell, William</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #1</intnum>
      <occupation>Lumberjack</occupation>
      <birthyear>1903</birthyear>
      <residence>Clearwater River, Bovill area</residence>
      <origin>Came in the mid-twenties; father had a farm and sawmill in Quebec</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#strikes"&gt;strikes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#lumberjacks"&gt;lumberjacks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#gyppos"&gt;gyppos&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#sawmills"&gt;sawmills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fighting"&gt;fighting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#foremen"&gt;foremen&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#working conditions"&gt;working conditions&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rivers"&gt;rivers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#death"&gt;death&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#bootlegging"&gt;bootlegging&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html# "&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Michigan"&gt;Michigan&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Bovill"&gt;Bovill&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Clearwater River"&gt;Clearwater River&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13654</file_name>
      <mp3>13655.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13655.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Differences in logging between Idaho and Michigan</title>
            <synopsis>Difference between logging in Idaho and Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Better conditions
               in Idaho camps than Michigan's.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>What the IWW accomplished; the democracy of the IWW</title>
            <synopsis>The IWW's accomplished wonders with direct action. The strike in 1923 was for the prisoners
               in jail; the 1936 strike for better conditions, which were improved after they broke
               the strike. Democracy of IWW made it much better than the CIO. IWW's strike for better
               conditions, not money. They were revolutionary and are dead.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>720</time>
            <title>Lumberjacks are single; the work was all done by hand; lumberjacks were mostly older
               and came from the east
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>People have changed. Lumberjacks were single, footloose, and had the world to gain.
               Gyppo system was supported by many to make money, and was opposed by the IWW. The
               work was all by hand and hard. Older men learned shortcuts. Lumberjacks were mostly
               older and came from the east.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>His father had a sawmill in Quebec, Canada</title>
            <synopsis>His father had a sawmill in Quebec, Canada.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1320</time>
            <title>Being able to read in camps but missed following baseball; working on strips; and
               fixed rates for certain people
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Lack of reading material in camps; he missed following
               baseball season. Men gyppoed with partners, often of
               long-standing. Choosing and working on strips. Rates
               were fixed despite gyppo contracts.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point> 
         <point>
            <time>2160</time>
         <title>How he chose camps; the sociability of loggers; ostracism of bad loggers</title>
         <synopsis>He chose camps with the cook in mind. Cooking on the
               river drive; moving camp. Cutting adrift while picking was a good way to take a break.
               Sociability of loggers - easy loaning money. Foremen's attitude towards men who
               didn't work. Ostracism of bad loggers.
            </synopsis>
      </point>
         <point>
            <time>3180</time>
            <title>IWW's gone because they were revolutionary</title>
            <synopsis>IWW's gone because they were revolutionary</synopsis>
         </point>
        
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>First Clearwater river log drives; construction of early wanigans; Gust Piper took
               the first drives; Silent Joe trapped on the North Fork
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>First Clearwater River log drives. Construction of early wanigans - cedar timbers,
               vine maple binders. Gust Piper was a log "pirate" who took rafts down to the Snake;
               he took the first drives because he knew the whole river. Silent Joe trapped on the
               North Fork in different cabins and rarely spoke.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3840</time>
            <title>Navigating the wanigans; finding places to land</title>
            <synopsis>Navigating the wanigans. Swinging athwart the current. Need to keep rafts together.
               Finding places to land; setting snublines.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4440</time>
            <title>A raft that missed the landing and the foreman was let go</title>
            <synopsis>A raft that missed the landing went thirty miles to Big
               Island and the foreman was canned.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4740</time>
            <title>Discussion about rear and center crews on the drives; lining the batteaus upstream</title>
            <synopsis>Rear crews and center crews on the river drives. Using powder. Lining the batteaus
               upstream.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5100</time>
            <title>Working in the riving; the drowning of three men near Lenore</title>
            <synopsis>Working in the river. Drowning of three men when their boat swamped near Lenore. Fitting
               searched for his brother's body.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5700</time>
            <title>Taking up collections by the men in camps - a day's wages</title>
            <synopsis>Taking up collections by the men in camps - a day's wages.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5880</time>
            <title>Discussion of Pierce, Idaho and Clarkia; how the Pierce hotel started</title>
            <synopsis>Pierce, a lumberjack town with everything. Tent living in town. Pierce Hotel started
               as a bootleg shack. Clarkia, a wide open town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6060</time>
            <title>Incline on Marble Creek; Working for Wood 'Em Up George</title>
            <synopsis>Incline on Marble Creek - 57% grade. Working for Wood 'Em Up George - he lost money
               with race horses, he liked to fire men.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6540</time>
            <title>Moving from camp to camp; Oscar Sturgill's camp; death of a superintendent</title>
            <synopsis>Going from camp to camp. Getting jobs. Oscar Sturgill's camp. Tramp lumberjacks and
               family men. Death of a superintendent in a wind storm.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6900</time>
            <title>Old time lumberjacks are gone</title>
            <synopsis>Old time lumberjacks are gone.</synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Clearwater River log drives: wanigans, pilots, drownings. Tramp lumberjacks; wide
         open towns. IWW's and direct action. Foremen and gyppo logging. 10-29-75 2 hr
         43p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
          
         
         This conversation with WILLIAM STOWELL, who is known by most people as,
         "Michigan Bill", took place at his home in Lewiston, Idaho on October 29,
         1975. The interviewer is SAM SCHRAGER. (There is some technical difficul
         ty with this tape.)
         
         WILLIAM STOWELL: I come from Canada, but I worked all over upper Michigan.
         I was born in Canada.
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: I've heard that upper peninsula there in Michigan was some log
         ging country.
         
         SS:   How did you wind up in Michigan?
         
         WS:   In Michigan?
         
         SS:   Yeah, how did you wind up there?
         
         WS:   Oh, just tramping around,I job, you know. Finally wound up
         there. Spent a few years there, not too long. Maybe six, seven years,
         
         SS:   When?
         
         WS:   Oh, in the early twenties. Twenty, twenty-one, twenty-two.
         
         SS:   I've heard something about that country. Were there a lot of Finns?
         
         WS:   Oh, Christ, yes. That, was all Fins, that mining country. That was
         copper. Yeah, that was ninety percent Finns. Yeah. I knew some of
         'em. I didn't never work in the mines, though. I was arouild 'em a
         lot. They worked in the woods, too. Yeah, there was lots of Finns
         there.
         
         SS:   Did you come out here from there?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Was this country very much like that as far as the what the logging
         life was like? Was it similar?
         
         WS:   Yeah, practically the same when I came here, except it was steeper
         ground, you know. There it was all level. But here it is pretty
         hilly, steep. Its a little different logging, you know. Of course,
         they used horses both places But they used dogs in this country,
         you know. Nailed together, you see. And long trails of, well,
         twenty, twenty-five at the most, you know, logs. And then chutes
         and flumes. They'd chute 'em to the flume and then flume 'em to the
         river. That's the way they done it here. Too steep for railroads.
         There was no trucks at that time, so, that's the way they did it.
         You know a chute?
         
         SS:   Uh-huh.
         
         WS:   Well, that's the way they went.
         
         SS:   Was it the same thing for the loggers? Same kind of guys out here
         as there was back there?
         
         WS:   Well, there was more foreigners back there than here. But, other
         wise it was the same. Camps, you know. Conditions were different here,
         they were much better, much better.
         
         SS:   Were they better here?
         
         WS:   Oh, Lord, God, yes. Yeah. Well, they eliminated the to^p bunkswell,
         that was later years that they done that, but there was double
         deck bunks. Two in a bunk. Uppers and lowers.^ And that is bad bus
         iness. That is one reason I got out of there. Not much chance to
         improve it. But this country here was a way different.A Clean linen,
         you know, every week for your bed. It got to be later years all bot
         tom bunks, you know. They was no top. Oh, yes, much better here.
         
         SS:   Did you hear much about the the work they did to improve the
         conditions?
         
         WS:   Yes, Yes, they accomplished wonders.. Yeah. They did. They was
         kind of a rough and tough outfit, but they got the work done. They
         got that job done. Direct action is what it was. There was no po
         litical harum-scarum mixed up in it. It was all direct, on the job.
         That's how it worked. Yeah.
         
         SS:   About what year was it, you got here? In Idaho. Came to Idaho?
         
         WS:   '27.
         
         SS:   By that time, now, the way I've heard it, is was about back in 1917
         or '18 that the IWff s cleaned up the camps.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, yes. And up until '23— the last big strike was in '23—
         general strike, for ten days. That was all. It was for the prisoners
         that was in jail, see. Those that were put in jail during these strikes.
         
         SS:   During the earlier ones?
         
         WS:   Yeah.
         
         SS:   Was it to get them out?
         
         WS:   No. no. They didn't make it but they shut everything down, see, that's
         all it was. They couldn't get it. But they did make a little up
         rising here in '36, again, if you remember that. Don't you?
         
         SS:   I've heard that.
         
         WS:   Yeah, that was for conditions, mostly, and wages. Well, they wanted
         a minimum of five dollars a day. And clean out the camps. The camps
         were getting pretty scroungy, you know. I don't know whether it was
         won or lost. We were out a couple of months. I was working for the
         Potlatch, then, but we were out a couple of months. I don't believe
         we lost anything. They cleaned the camps up. And raised the wages.
         But they didn't do that til after the strike, you see. They broke
         the strike, that's what happened.
         
         SS:   Well, you know that's the story that I've heard before. That way the
         company says that it wasn't the IWW's that mad because they
         ended the strike and then they made But it's all one
         and the same thing.
         
         WS:   Yes, I look it that way. They didn't do it til after the strike,
         but they did it. But that was the last feeble attempt of the IWW's
         that they ever made, in this country.
         
         SS:   I was surprised when I heard about the '36 stike that they were still
         kicking around all that time. Because these others,the AF of L and
         those * were getting in and the CIO, too.
         
         WS:   Yes. Well, the CIO wasn't too husky yet, in this country, you know.
         They come in afterwards. The AF of L got booted out and the CIO took
         over by a large margin, you know. But, I don't know the AF of L, I
         guess they were— Well, the CIO was political, too, but the other
         was moreso. I belonged to the CIO, but I never did belong to the
         AF of L in the woods. I belonged to the piledrivers and the like of
         that.
         
         SS:   I had the idea that the AFof L was more like a craft union than it
         was a real industrial union.
         
         WS:   Sure, it was, that's what it was, yes. It was a craft union.
         
         SS:   That way it'd make more sense. To me the CIO would be in the lum
         ber industry.
         
         WS:   Yeah, yeah. It was the lesser evil of the two, but I don't know, I—
         beings that I had belonged to the IWW, I couldn't see much to either
         one of 'em.
         
         SS:   What do you think made the IWW's so much a better union than the CIO?
         
         WS:   Well, you could act, more or less, without all these executive boards
         and the like of that, you know. You could hold a meeting and youCoul*
         decide to do something, and majority ruled. Take a vote, and if
         the majority wanted it, why, that's the way it was. It went, as far
         as the crew was concerned. We didn't always win, but it was an ef
         fort, anyway. So, that was what I liked about it. You got an organ
         ization, there's too much politcal. High salaries. Big shots. All
         that. It don't work with the common stiff, you know. I don't fig
         ure it does.
         
         SS:   Most of these unions it never gets down to the workingman. I mean,
         he never really has any say-so about it. Those decisions are made
         up there and—
         
         WS:   Yeah. Yeah. That's right.
         
         SS:   Were you ever in camps that you guys took a vote and then went out
         on strike?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes.
         
         SS:   What kind of reason would make you decide you had to do that?
         
         WS:   Oh, well, different reasons. Mostly— especially the IWW's. They
         were mostly for conditions. Working conditions and living oonditions.
         Get away from them old double bunks and lousy camps and bum chuck
         and all that. They were trying to get something better— well, bet
         ter living. Is what it was, really. They never did strike too much
         for money, because they take that away from you anyway. That money.
         Oh, I don't— I think there are IWW's never come back, you know.
         The IWW, they're done. They were revolutionary, you know. And a re-
         volutionary organization at this day and age don't get along very
         good.
         
         SS:   Do you think it made more sense in the off days than it would make
         nowadays?
         
         WS:   Well, that's kind of a hard question to answer. I wouldn't attempt
         to answer it. I don't know.
         
         SS:   Conditions have changed a lot. I sometimes wonder, whether it's
         changed all that much, or whether—
         
         WS:   People change, you know. People have changed an awful lot. Oh yes.
         That's what makes it, I think. Is the people, themselves. You see
         the lumberjack was always a single man, a footloose man, you know.
         He didn't give a Goddam for anything. He had nothing to lose. And
         the world to gain. So that's what made him that way, I believe.
         I'm pretty sure that's the way it was with me. Say a hundred and
         fifty men in a camp, they might be two percent married, or maybe one
         percent. All single. And they had no responsibilities except them
         selves. Anything they could gain, was for them. Now, you see, they're
         all married. They got responsiblities. Payments on cars and homes
         and TVs and whatnot. Those days, all a man had was his packsack.
         Just what was on his back, that's all.
         
         SS:   It seems so different than it is, as you were saying then and now.
         I can't even think of how the situation would arise, so many men
         would be single and not be tied down by anything.
         
         WS:   It's hard to figure that out, isn't it?
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   I don't know why they never got married. I can't figure that out.
         Well, I never did. I was just from job to job, you know, and I didn't
         have no responsibility. Couldn't afford to have many, unless I
         wanted to settle down and take less money for some other job, you know.
         We always made a little more than the town workers.
         
         SS:   Why was that? You guys could go anyplace where there was a job?
         
         WS:   Where the money was, yefrk. Well, then the gyppo system come in. Of
         course that changed everything. There was a minimum wage but it was
         awful small. Everybody wants to gyppo, gyppo, gyppo. And they al
         ways made it so you could— well, you'd come out a third above the
         regular wages, anyway, you see, by going the limit, you know. Doing
         the utmost, your very best, every day, you had to. That's the way
         that was.
         
         SS:   Was that a good deal? I mean it sounds— they must have got a lot
         more work out of the men.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. Sure. No,that wasn't a good deal for us at all. No, we
         tried to abolish it, but you couldn't. There was too many that
         wanted it that way. You know, really wanted it that way. Right down
         in their hearts they wanted it that way. I mean, good militant union
         men, too, they were. But, if there was any trouble at all there were
         always ready to help out. Most of 'em wanted the gyppo system. Lit
         tle more money. You know, that's what drives people on, is that money.
         
         SS:   Sure, for a few years a guy can break his back working if he's young,
         and really can put out the work, but seems like it's gonna catch up
         with 'em after while.
         
         WS:   Well, it does. Naturally it does, sure. You may think you can do
         it, but you can't. You'll poop out pretty Goddam sudden like when
         you get older. That's awful hard work in them olden days, you know.
         Everything was handwork. The sawing was all handwork, bucking was
         all handwork, and the skidding was, oh, well, the horses, you know,
         but peavy work, you know, you had all that to do* and that run into
         work.
         
         SS:   Did the IWW have on that? Did they say gyppo was no good?
         
         WS:   Yeah. That's the stand they took. Absolutely no good, no.
         
         SS:   If you really believed in the union, then the gyppo would be very
         unequal, because the guys that could put out the work could make a
         lot better than the old-timers, who couldn't do it. Is that right?
         
         WS:   Yes, but when you got old enough, you quit gyppoing, though, you
         couldn't. You had to quit. (Chuckles) That was the way that worked.
         Well, you were good up til fifty years old, you know. You knew a
         lot of shortcuts, by that time, that you didn't know when you were
         young er.
         
         SS:   What?
         
         WS:   Well, just generally speaking, you know.
         
         SS:   The way to do the work — you mean, like you learned, you really
         mastered the whole job.
         
         WS:   Yeah, sure, that's it. Yeah, that's my idea, yes. It's just as I
         say, you learn a lot of tricks and shortcuts. It all help out at the
         end of the day, you know. You have accomplished a little more than
         than the absolute greenhorns would, and done it just about as easy.
         
         SS:   I heard that most of the early lumberjacks that were out in this
         country were old men. Older men. Is that true? As far as you knew,
         in the early days?
         
         WS:   There were a lot of old men, yes. They were a lot of 'em pretty old
         when they come to this country, you know, from the East. They were
         all from the East, practically. Eastern Canada and the Midwestern
         states, Wisconsin, Minnesota and Michigan. That's where most of 'em
         were from when I came out here. And they were all men along in iheir
         years,
         
         SS:   You were one of the young ones?
         
         WS:   Yes. Yes, sure. I was only about twenty-three, I think, when I
         landed here. But, all I'd ever did was work in the wood?, you know,
         when I was a kid at home. Well, the Old Man had timber, you know.
         The old sawmill.
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   Yeah, old waterpower sawmill.
         
         SS:   You must have seen it ever since you were old enough to see things.
         
         WS:   Yes, sure.
         
         SS:   Did he let you work on it?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. No, I just was around it, you know. I never done nothing
         around it. Piled a little lumber, something like that. Worked
         on the pond a little bit. I was going to school then. I didn't do
         much work.
         
         SS:   Where was that in Canada?
         
         WS:   In Quebec; the Province of Quebec. Little small town about the size
         of Pierce, I guess.
         
         SS:   
         
         WS:   Oh, no, he had a sawyer, that's all. The neighbors, they helped out.
         Do a little work for a little lumber. Work a day or two and get some
         lumb er.
         
         SS:   Did you come down to the States because there was more work here?
         
         WS:   No. No, I come down to go to school.
         
         SS:   Oh!
         
         WS:   Yes.
         
         SS:   You were still just a kid?
         
         WS:   Yeah. I was about seven, I guess.
         You know in the Midwest— those lumber towns were really tough towns.
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah. Of course, they had calmed down some, when I got there.
         They used to fight for the fun of it. But, I don't know, they kinda
         cut that out. People change, you know.
         
         SS:   Fights were just over — when drinking and that.
         
         WS:   Well, yes. There'd be one tough guy and the other A think he was
         tougher, and he'd maybe go over to the camp where the other guy was
         working just to challenge him. That's the way that worked. And
         they were rough, too. Lot of 'em done all their fighting on the
         floor, they'd chew and bitin', and if they were on their feet they
         were usin' their shoes.
         
         SS:   Cork boots?
         
         WS:   Yeah, they went in to win, regardless.
         
         SS:   Did any grudges go on for a very long time?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. They were forgotten. Sometimes they weren't, but most of
         the time they were. Have it out and over with and go back to drink
         ing.
         
         SS:   Well, was that the same out here, too? Were the towns pretty tough?
         Out here, the logging towns?
         
         WS:   Some of 'em were, yes. Like Aberdeen and Hoquiam. Aberdeen was a
         rough town. Washington. That was about the roughest on the West
         Coast, I think. Well,they was longshoremen there and lumberjacks
         and everything, you know. Timber was close to town. And that made
         a difference, and it was still the single men that was working then.
         
         SS:   Did you usually stay with a job for very long?
         
         WS:   Me?
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   Yeah, I have stayed six to eight months. And I've stayed two days.
         Varied, it depended on how the job was, or something. I usually
         stayed pretty good. Well, it all depends on how things go. If it
         suited you, you'd stay, if it didn't, you'd go.
         
         SS:   The different bosses, you know, formen, did that make a big differ-
         ence?
         
         WS:   Well, it would, yeah. Sometimes. But some people— with me
         it didn't make any difference who I worked for. I could work for
         anybody; long as I get along with 'em. But never inter
         fered with you much. If you were gyppoing you wouldn't see 'em,
         maybe, from the time you started until you quit. You'd see 'em in
         camp, you know, but you wouldn't see 'em on the job. But if you
         were working by the day, you'd see 'em. They'd be around then ev-
         ery day But they didn't bother you much. No.
         
         SS:   Do you think there was much difference between them? Were some
         foremen really working for the company and others working more for
         the men?
         
         Well, you can't be both ways. You couldn't be both ways. Some
         lean a little bit towards the crew, if they come up from the crew,
         you know what I mean. If they were picked out of the crew, or some
         thing like that. They would lean a little towards their fellowman,
         but, ordinarily, of course, he was working for the company. But, you
         can't hold that againsit him.' And in order to hold the job, they had
         to be. That was my idea, always. Generally speaking, they were pret
         ty good bunch of guys.I never seen any of 'em that weren't, anyway.
         
         Axel Anderson, do you know him?
         
         Oh, yeah. I worked for him. He's living yet. In Spokane, 
         
         Yeah, I talked to him up there. Oh, I talked to him for hours and
         hours.
         
         Gosh, he must be old.
         
         About ninety-one, maybe.
         
         And did you know Maler, his brother?
         
         No, I don't know him. I've heard of him.
         
         He was a good guy. Real good guy. Axel's alright too, but, Malker
         was a really good fellow. 
         
         He was a foreman, too, wasn't he?
         
         Yes. Good one.
         
         What would make a good foremah like him? What did he do, that made
         him a good foreman?
         
         Well, I don't know. He mixed with the crew, in town. on the job.
         And he drank with 'em. Just generally speaking, he got along real
         good with 'em. He give 'em a good price for their work, and he got
         a lot of work done. That was the whole sum and substance of that deal.
         
         SS:   Axel said that he thinks the push was in a mind, between the
         company and men. He said he used to like to try to do good by the
         men and every once in a while he'd get on the carpet with the company.
         
         WS:   Sure, sure. I imagine they did. I know they did. I never was a
         push, but— I kinda imagine that some of 'em would get called on the
         carpet for being a little bit too lenient, or lean a little bit towards
         the-^ you know. I know they do. Sure they do. Bound to.
         
         SS:   Was Malker a big man, like Axel?
         
         WS:   No. He was tall, but— a little taller than Axel, but he was slim
         mer. He was a little different man than Axel. I don't know why,
         but he was. Axel was pretty much company. But Malker, he didn't seem
         to lean that way too heavy, but he was a good push. He was goodreally-
         good for both sides. He got a lot of work done and he was
         good with the crew. I always liked him real well. I worked for the
         both of 'em. I used to work for Malker whenever I was on that side.
         See, this outfit here, what time did they consolidate? Tell you
         what—
         
         SS:   Something like that.
         
         WS:   I remember I was working up here at Camp H, and we got our September-
         October checks and they had a little strip of paper up in the cor
         ner— white strip of paper— They used to be the Clearwater Timber
         Company, you know. The cheks was made out that way. And there was a
         little piece of paper pasted onto the check— it said Potlatch For
         ests. I think that was in '31. I'm pretty sure it was. I know I
         was working.at Camp H for Old Brooks.
         
         SS:   Malker was on the other side?
         
         WS:   Yeah, he was always over there.
         
         SS:   Was there mu«h difference between the two sides? The camps and the
         men?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. Yes. That other side always had better chuck, better camp
         conditions and everything. That's before they consolidated, you
         know. It was Potlatch Lumber Company.
         
         SS:   Right.
         
         WS:   That's what it was. And they had awful good horses. I used to like
         to go over there on account of the horses. They was good and they
         took good care of 'em. You couldn't abuse a team of horses there,
         you know. You wouldn't stay. Them pushers were all pretty much
         horse lovers, you know. And that old Nogle, you know, he was horse
         crazy, that guy. He'd sleep with 'em, I think.
         
         SS:   Didn't he do most of the buying for them when he was a push?
         
         WS:   Nogel, you mean?
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   Yeah. Sure, he did. Him and the vet. But Nogle did the buying. I
         don't know where the hell he got 'em then. Oh, this outfit here
         used to get pretty good horses in Oregon.
         
         SS:   I know in the early days, they bought quite a few from the farmers.
         WSi Yeah, that's true, that's where they bought 'em all. And then
         "praised 'em, that was their business, raising horses. They bought
         wherever they could. This man here on this side, White, he died,
         he was fifty when he died, I think. I went with him a couple
         of times buying horses. He'd hear of a team of horses someplace,
         you know, he'd hear about 'em; he'd go and look at 'em. If they
         weren't too old and looked good to him, why, he'd buy 'em. If they
         were well matched, you know. But they used to buy 'em, oh, they'd
         buy one here and one there and a half a dozen here and so on. Match
         'em up themselves, after they got here. Bovill has a nice big meadow
         over there, you know. And, gee, I used to go over there and look
         at them horses, right in grass up to their knees. Fat and slick.
         Nice big barn. I used to like that.
         
         SS:   Gee, they had a lot of horses, too. Probably two hundred and fifty,
         three hundred head of horses in that barn?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. See, I've been in that barn. I brought horses out of there
         one time over here. That was in the fall of '32. I don't know how
         many teams had. must have had thirty pair, anyway. We
         brought 'em to Elk River, stayed overnight and then come across the
         North Fork, there was a big island, and into Headquarters. Old Nogle
         hated to see them horses leave.
         
         SS:   How did you take 'em? Was there many guys on a run like that?
         
         WS:   There was about four of us, I guess, or five. 'Course I knew the
         route, too, but there was a guy that knew the route, that is, from
         Elk River to Big Island. And, I don't know, maybe six, but we had
         a wagon with a load of harness in it. They were unharnessed. Unhar
         nessed 'em all, you know.
         
         SS:   Just drove 'em?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. Put the harness in the wagon and then led them behind in
         twos, you know. Had four horses on the wagon and then lead them be
         hind. And there was a guy with a saddle horse, he took a big bunch,
         too. That way, we got 'em over. They were alright after they'd be
         on the road a little while, you know, they'd kinda calm down, But,
         otherwise, when we first started from Bovill, why, they were all har
         nessed then, you know. Had the harness on 'em. They was tangled up.
         Lose a team once in a while have to stop and pick em up. But, we
         made her, I think in three days.
         
         SS:   How many horses?
         
         WS:   Oh, they must have been thirty-five pairs, anyway. I can't remember
         exactly.
         
         SS:   That's a pretty big job. Not an easy one to do.
         
         WS:   Yeah. The Bovill side wasn't running , and this outfit didn't
         run nothing that summer.
         
         SS:   You mean this is when the Depression was on?
         Yeah. '32. They started up a couple of camps here in the fall.
         That was that rainy fall, the bridges washed out and everything, be
         tween Orofino and Headquarters. They quit at New Year's, that time,
         Christmas was the high water. I think there was fourteen or fifteen
         bridges went out between Headquarters and Orofino on the railroad
         to Camas Prairie, I guess it is.
         
         SS:   Well, I've heard up there, said that it was a lot rougher up there.
         One or two guys have said to me that they had the idea that the log
         ging over on this side was a lot rougher.
         
         Yeah, it was. The ground was rougher, steeper. There was some rough
         ground at Elk River, too, you know at the tail end of their operation
         there, but to start with, they had a lot of nice ground. Them camps
         all around Bovill was real nice ground. Two, Four, Five, Six, Seven,
         they was all nice, well, just little rolling hills, you know, little
         humps here and there. You could lay steel anyplace pretty near, very
         little grade. Lot of nice, big pine.
         
         SS:   That's probably why they didn't do so much with the stuff like that.
         
         WS:   They didn't do any. They laid the railroad right to the stump.
         They had quite a big railroad crew working. They all had them steam
         rigs loaded with tongs, you know.
         Did you know Art Henderson?
         
         SS:  - No. I've heard of him, though. Who is he?
         
         He was a— He loaded cars for years, and then he got to be a push.
         Got killed up here at Camp Y. He was running that camp then. But
         he come up below a bulldozer, you know. Bulldozer working above
         and he come up from below, it was shoving over trees and snags and
         everything else, you know, and he got underneath one. He was a good
         guy. Damn good guy. I think— Do you know ? I can't think of
         his name, but he married Art's daughter, anyway. He was some kind
         of a wheel over there.
         
         SS:   Where?
         
         WS:   Bovill. They haven't got much going over there, have they?
         
         SS:   No, they got. They got some work there.
         
         WS:   They're on the East Fork of Potlatch Creek, I hear. Aren't they?
         
         SS:   I don't know. I haven't been out there— I haven't noticed they're
         logging around there lately.
         
         WS:   They used to have a big camp right in town.
         
         SS:   Did they?
         
         Yeah, right there— well, old Camp 8 was there. That was years ago,
         that's before my time.
         
         SS:   Yeah, old Camp 8, I've heard of that quite a bit.
         
         WS:   This other camp, was set up right there where Camp 8 was.
         
         SS:   Well, do you think that country was more— it seemed to me—I have
         the idea that a lot of the people— more people, maybe in the woods
         there were people who had families.
         
         WS:   Yes, they did. Lots of 'em.
         
         SS:   Did that make the camps more settled than on this side?
         
         WS:   I don't know. This was always just kind of a- when it first started
         up was kind of a hurly-burly outfit, you know. All tramp lumberjacks,
         all of 'em working there. There was no married men like in Bovill.
         'fhere was a lot of married men working in Bovill
         in the camps.'"you could tell on Sunday, you know, the camp would
         thin right out, you know. And here, it wouldn't make any difference.
         Tommy Kinrw was tne superintendent then and he come over here from
         Montana and took over. There was several pushers come here from
         Montana. Tommy Stevens. Dave Herman,  Henerson And
         Kinney, of course, Kinney was superintendent here until '36, then
         he went to the Winton outfit. And he was down in California for a
         while, for River Lumber Company. But he's dead now, Kinney when 
         is. Bradbury took over after him. He's dead, too.
         
         SS:   Well, when you first came out here in the twenties, was there much
         there was supposed to have been
         going on this side in the way of lumbering, up around Bovill and that
         country?
         
         WS:   Oh no. Well, this mill started in '26; in August of '26.
         
         SS:   So they were just getting going pretty big then?
         
         WS:   Yeah. They hadn't got into the river yet, but there were railroad
         camps here out of Pierce and Headquarters. Oh, yeah, they put in a
         lot of timber here '27. A hundred cars a day. Then they got in to
         the river, see. They was cutting a strip the river and they
         built a road, and then they started up them river camps; B, C, D, 
         F, G.
         
         SS:   Was that before the Depression started here?
         Yeah. Yeah, well, the first drive was in '28, so you see they had
         to get in there— they logged there in '27. Camp B and C. Yeah,
         B and C. Camp A, that was at— Camp A was right there where that
         dam is built now.
         
         SS:   Right there near Orofino.
         
         Yeah. All they took out of there was piling for bridges and stuff
         for the mill, you know. Had a little mill there.
         There wasn't no timber there much except— (Blanked out with noise)
         Lot of people never knew where that camp was. Camp A. 
         
         SS:   What that first one was like, they had on the river?
         
         WS:   Sure, I do, I remember all about it. Who the hell had that? Webb.
         Joshua Webb. I think he must be dead, though. But they drove from
         it ma Big Island then, you see. That Big Island, that B and C and them
         camps put that timber in, all flumed. And then the next spring, they
         drove from Beaver Creek. They had dug in to the river and started
         camps up there. And Old Brooks brought that drive down as far as
         Big Island and Webb took it from there on in. But then the next year
         Old Brooks went all the way through. He— they had wanigans, you see.
         Well, Webb had wanigans too, but Brooks had to build 'em, too
         way up the North Fork. But his were just kind of a skimpy affair
         compared to what Old Webb had. Webb had regular, I guess- wccold 
         They were all square timber together. But the ones Old Brooks
         built, they were- there was no bolts or spikes or nothing in them,
         just all made out of wood, you know. They were different lengths of
         cedar, interlocked this way, you know. And they real flexible.
         Stuff about eighteen, twenty inches on the butt, it was. Forty and
         sixty feet long, they were. They were held together by— they were
         about eighty-five feet long, possibly, about twenty-two feet wide.
         I helped build 'em. They were held together by what they call widthsthey
         was wild cherry. And they laid these binders across-
         
         SS:   What?
         
         VS: These binders, you know. They was mostly maple, and they was bored,
         you know, these timbers, this stuff here that the raft was built out
         of, was bored, you know, and they put this width in and a
         square peg with it, you know, in the round hole, was the size
         And that's what held it together. This over this maple,
         this binder. If you wanted to dismantle 'em you had to cut 'em up.
         There was nothing come apart, otherwise.
         
         SS:   So, it was pretty solid.
         Oh, yes. Sure. But flexible, you know. In rough water they oscil
         late, you know, up and down, so there was no breakage in 'em that way.
         
         SS:   This was for the first drive?
         Yeah, they used them all the time after that.
         
         SS:   The same kind?
         The same kind, right up til the last drive. Except they put rubber
         on. They had rubber, you see, the last. The last ten years, maybe
         they had pontoons.
         
         SS:   Well, this first drive, were they well constructed, well made? Were
         they serviceable? Did they do the job?
         
         WS: Yes. Sure they
         
         SS:   How did the first drive go? I take it they had never drove down the
         Clearwater before? It must have been a new experience for 'em.
         
         Well, there was an old guy by the name of Piper, he's dead years ago,
         he run the first rafts. And, he knew the river, he lived on the river.
         He was an old prospector. But he rafted cedar poles on that river
         when he used to, I call it pirating or highgrading or whatever the
         hell you want to call it, before this dam was built, you know. They'd
         make up wood rafts, cedar rafts and run 'em down into the Snake and
         on down and sell 'em, you see. But he used to do that. It was his
         business, he done that. But he knew every pebble in that North Fork.
         And he run the first rafts down for the company. Helped build 'em.
         He built 'em. He was the supervisory element, building 'em. He showed
         'em how to build 'em and run 'em. So that's how they made 'em at
         that time.
         
         Did they hire him on just for that job? Was he working for them
         before? Or was he an independent gyppo?
         
         No, he was just independent. He used to make up three or four
         and run them,
         cedar rafts a year, you know. That's before the company started, 
         driving.
         
         So this pirating? Was this really company timber a man was taking?
         
         Anybody's. On the bank of the river, you know. Standing close to
         the bank. Well, they done a lot of it, yes. Everybody was doing it.
         Woods and cedar.
         
         Could a guy make a living that way?
         
         Oh, Christ, yes. Cedar you could, yes.
         
         You had to come down on your raft to be sure it made it?
         
         Oh, yes.
         
         I wonder where they sold it; how far down did they have to go?
         
         Oh, I don't know. A lot of 'em was sold— made up in posts, cedar
         posts, you know. They're at a premium down the river, you know.
         There's no timber down there, down that Snake. You know where that
         is?
         
         Oh, yes. Probably wouldn't have to go too far.
         
         Tumbleweeds, is all it is. But, yeah, they made a livin' at it.
         
         This Old Piper was a fine old guy. They found him dead in his cabin.
         He was a funny old guy, he'd never come to town. He'd land out here
         at the mill with them rafts, that is, when he was driving for the
         company, you know. And he'd charge back up river. And he was a rag
         ged old thing, you know. I don't think he ever went to a barber or
         anything like that. He was just an old hermit, is what he was. But
         a good old guy.
         
         Did you ever talk to him and know how long he'd been in this country?
         
         WS:   Yes. He'd been here for years. I don't know how many cabins he
         built on that North Fork. He trapped some, too, you know. And he'd
         get-, well, he'd wander off, you know , going looking his trap line
         over and he'd have a cabin to stay in. He built just leantos and
         cabins of all kinds up and down that North Fork. There was another
         guy come along after him: Silent Joe. Truckee, his name was. He
         built a half a dozen cabins, too, but he But ne made
         a living trapping. And he'd work on the drive in the spring. He
         was a good driver. French Canadian. Real good. And he died up
         there right on the Goddam flat.
         
         SS:   What did Silent Joe come from? He didn't talk?
         
         WS:   Yeah. 
         
         SS:   At all?
         
         WS:   Well, he'd say a word or two, of course. But he wouldn't try to keep
         a conversation or nothin' going. He'd just sit there. I used to go
         up and see him after he had quit working. He was too old to work.
         And I used to go in a little earlier than the driving crew, you know,
         there'd be five or six of us to go in and build them rafts. And he
         lived about a mile from where we'd be building, and I'd go up to see
         him. Well, he'd sit there, he wouldn't talk. I'd keep on talking,
         you know, "Yes,", "No", is all he'd say. And there was nothing in
         the shack, an old frying pan and a couple of old kettles of some kind.
         And an old wooden bunk. I said, "Well, I'm going to do, Joe." "Well,
         sit down." So I'd have to set another half hour. He would never say
         nothin'. I'd finally get out of there. But he died right there. He
         never come out.
         
         SS:   Same thing as this Piper. He trapped and he did the river drives, too?
         
         WS:   Gust Piper. He didn't drive too long. He was down there about five
         years.
         
         SS:   Piper, you mean?
         
         WS:   Yeah. He was back up there one spring and they found him dead in
         the doorway of his shack. They don t know whether it was t4"&gt; or
         foul or what happened. I don't think it could be foul, because
         there was nobody ever around there. I think he just died. He was
         pretty well decomposed when they found him.
         
         SS:   This Piper?
         
         WS:   Yeh. Gust Piper. Let's see, who took them rafts then? Frank
         Larkins. He's dead, too, now. He run 'em then. He wasn't near as
         good as Old Gust. And then they had different ones after that. I
         used to work on 'em all time, help move 'em, you know. But I never
         did run 'em.
         
         SS:   That first year, how many of 'em did they have?
         
         WS:   Rafts?
         
         SS:   Yeah.
         
         WS:   They had, one, two, three. They had a sleepin' raft, a cook raft,
         and a chuck raft. You see they couldn't get no in. There was
         no roads in there then until they got to Big Island. See, there was
         sixty miles there, I guess. And rtf the river was heavy and you were
         movin' slow, you know, that is, say, a mile a day or something like
         that, it took a lot of chuck, that's why they had the chuck raft.
         They had a regular crew. Well, there was one man that run the rafts,
         and then he'd pick up men out off the crew to help him move. And
         they usually got a day off for that. Well, it took a day. There
         was a lot of hiking. Say you moved five miles, you had to hike fifteenmiles
         back, three different times. And then if you missed the
         landing or something, which we did, that caused more complications
         then.
         
         SS:   What did you do if you missed the landing? You had to rope it back
         or something?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. Impossible to do that. That was out of the question. No,
         you went to the next one, or you got in someplace where you thought
         you could. This Old Piper knew every bend in the river, you know.
         And so did Frank Larkins. They were lucky that way. They always
         had someone that knew. But later on, when they got motors on them—
         they put motors on them rubber rafts, them were the first ones they
         put motors on. Big seven horsepower motors, and they didn't draw
         that much water; pontoons. You could go up river in places with 'em.
         You could come to a dead stop anyplace. That is.not anyplace, but
         if the water wasn't too wicked, you could fetch 'em right to a halt.
         Yeah, that simplified everything.
         
         SS:   How many men would run that raft in the old days ? How many men would
         move it?
         
         WS:   Oh, there'd be usually five.
         
         SS:   Did they use poles?
         
         WS:   No. Sweeps. Long oars, you know. There was an eighteen foot blade
         on about a forty foot stem. The butt oar'd usually have three men.
         You run and back and forth across with it. The guy run from the stern,
         the pilot. He would call the shots from the stern. If he wanted to
         go over to the right, why, he'd holler, "Right!" And you was always
         in position anyhow, you see, then you would dip your oar and give
         her a gut to the right, you see. Your oar would be about this high.
         
         SS:   Above your head?
         
         WS:   Yeah. That is, the back end of it would be. The shorter man would
         be—
         
         SS:   Down close to the edge.
         
         WS:   Yeah, he'd be reaching . But you could bring it to time.
         Take quite a few dub6 you know. Landing was the worst part of it.
         They'd run through an ordinary eddy, you know, they was so heavy.
         If you went into the upper end of the eddy they'd either swing on
         you or run through. If it was a really strong eddy, why, they'd swing
         on you. They load up with water in front, you know water'd be up
         to here, and they'd swing. And there you were, you were in a hell
         of a shape. trouble.
         
         SS:   What would you do?
         
         WS:   Well, try to straighten it out. You couldn't run from the stern beway
         cause the stern was loaded, it was down. The stern was in the water,
         there was water over the stern. It was too heavy to handle, you had—
         the bow was up, you know. You had to work it from the bow.You'd turn
         it again if you could, get the bow ahead. And then try to land. If
         you got— If you had two rafts, say, the sleeping raft and the cook
         raft and the chuck raft, well, you had to have 'em together. At
         night when the crew come in. If you didn't have they be a mile
         apart, you know. If you missed with one, you'd have to pass it up
         with the other one, and go where the first one was. And then maybe
         you'd have to hike three or four miles back to the rear in the morn
         ing. That was no good. They used to try to keep 'em as close to the
         rear as possible. That was the idea. Eliminate that hiking, be
         cause when you're marching, you ain't fightin' (Chuckles)
         
         SS:   What kind of a spot did the pilot have to pick out on the river?
         Did if have to be a real sizeable cove?
         
         WS:   Yes. That would be the best. And the bank you know, they try
         to get a place— he wouldn't run into a brush pile or nothin'. You
         had things and stuff to set out on the bank and build fires for
         the crew at night. tHey had places, you know, after the first couple
         of years. They had places, regular places, where you landed, as a
         rule. If the river's moving fast, they'd miss one of these or one
         or two of 'em, otherwise they'd run in there and tie up, you know.
         We used to have snublines, and we had a boat, and old batteau. We'd
         go ahead and set this snubline, see. It was just a long, they were
         two inch lines, I think, with a in it, you know. And you'd set
         that a put a stick or something under it, so you could see it. A
         guy had to bail off of that raft, 'cause it would be tootin' right
         along. And you had a sort of a line on the raft, maybe thirty feet
         with a big snap in it, you see; a big iron snap, that long, with a
         spring in it, you know. Well, you'd grab that and bail off, the
         guy that was supposed to do the snubbing. There was always one good
         active man done that, you know. And you'd grab this line with the
         bone in it, and there was one on a tree, one wrap as a
         rule, a tree or stump or something. Well, you'd make the joint then
         you see, with the big snap in the bone, and then you'd drop that
         and grab the other line, and pay out a little slack. If you snubbed
         around real tight, and it was in straight water, it would take the
         stern of the raft down and probably break the line. That's happened,
         too. Just give it a little slack on the stump and you could snub
         it any time you wanted to, as far as the— you had the hitch,to do
         it with, you know.
         
         SS:   That spring cushioned —
         
         WS:   No, no, that spring was just to keep the lines together. It wasn't
         a coil spring. It was just a spring that kept the lines together.
         After it got in the snap, you know, it couldn't fly up. No, it was
         no coil spring.
         
         SS:   It sounds like you had no time to play or something like that.
         
         WS:   No. No. It had to be done. If you missed you was looking at it
         going around the bend. And there you were, you didn't know
         where the hell they were going. And you made kind of a day for your
         self, too (Laughter) That was part of it. They'd kid you about
         that, and maybe find someone else to do it, if you missed too often.
         
         SS:   Now the deal on this was that they'd take one raft at a time down
         and then go back for the next one?
         
         WS:   Yes. But when they got the rubber, you know, that's just a few years
         that they had that rubber. But that was all in one. That was a hun
         dred and eighteen feet long. Motor on each end. Cookhouse in the
         middle , the sleepers on each end. three sections. They
         was awful flexible. But, they was rough to ride, you know. Rough
         water they'd be just like a bronco, jumping around. But when you
         landed that thing everything was there. You didn't have to go back
         after nothing.
         
         SS:   I'll bet the old-timers must have really thought that was quite a
         change.
         
         WS:   Oh, yes.
         
         Because you fellows on a drive never could imagine what the old days
         were like.
         
         No. I remember one time we missed with the sleeping wanigan at Robison
         Island, that's just above the Little North Fork, and we never
         got tied up til we got to Big Island. I don't know what in hell the
         idea was. It was thirty miles there; I was new on there, too. HI
         didn't know where the hell we was going. But the others did. Larkins,
         he knew. Nobody ever did find out, he got canned, anyway.
         
         SS:   For that?
         
         WS:   For that. When we got to Big Island there was another raftsman
         there. But I hiked back up. I don't know, we had to sleep on the
         bank then. Well, we was twelve days on that barge, and we slept on
         the bank. We had the cookraft, you see, we landed the cookraft.
         Another crew moved that. They landed with no trouble, I guess.
         
         SS:   It took twelve days to get the sleepingraft?
         
         WS:   Yes. Sleep on the bank every night, and no blankets, but they built
         a big fire, oh, as long as from here to that house. Had two or three
         men cutting wood all day. Keep your feet warm. There was snow on
         the ground up there. Howard Bradbury was keeping time that spring.
         That was in '32. That was the year Roosevelt was elected, I think.
         Yeah, 1932, in the spring, it was. 
         
         SS:   Well, that's a hell of a thing. Was something wrong with him or some
         thing, that he didn't ?
         
         WS:   Well, I never could figure it out. Nobody ever did. Everybody tried
         to, but he missed the landing, alright, and after that he didn't—
         oh, he had tried a couple of other times, but he didn't make much—
         I knew myself, he was going to miss them other ones. But the line
         broke, you see is what happened at Robison, the first landing, see.
         Broke the snubline, and lost a man off of the raft, you see. The
         guy that went ashore, he couldn't raft, he was there. Broke
         the line. However, that didn't make any difference, he could a got
         in someplace. The water wasn't too high, it was up pretty but
         hadn't had the big water yet, it still came after that. I never could
         figure out why he But he got relieved of his command as soon as
         that old push caught up him.
         
         SS:   Without the snubline, how would you stop it?
         
         WS:   Well, you'd have to improvise.
         
         They had more line?
         
         Oh, yes.
         
         You could pretty much rig up another?
         
         Oh, yes, sure. Anything. Well, there was places where you wouldn't
         need one, you could step off, you know. If you had you could
         get around something, you know and get stopped.
         
         You were new so you didn't know where— what was going on too good.
         We was all new.
         
         You guys were waiting for your orders.
         
         Yeah. They was except, well, Old Bill Akins and
         this Larkins, he was supposed to be the big shot. But, I don't know,
         he never made a success of it that I could see. But, that's the way
         it was. But after that they, well, — Oh, Bill Akins took 'em then
         and he run 'em for years.
         
         Do you remember how long that first drive took?
         
         By gosh, no, you see, it was split up, you know; changed pushes at
         Big Island and another push went down from there. Oh, you mean the
         first drive.
         
         Yes. The very first one.
         
         Oh, I don't remember at all. Lasted way into the summer. No machin
         ery or nothing, and the water got away. The river was new to 'em.
         They got late water that year in June, but it didn't— it helped, of
         course, but it dropped right away again. We were down on them big
         bars in the main river, cranking them logs off a there by hand! Hot!!
         That's not very interesting.
         
         These logs drives, I never did see one, myself. And up north there,
         of course, we never had any. The men working in the water on the
         logs; what was the techniques they used? What did they do to keep
         them logs moving? What did they have to do?
         
         WS:   Well, take like the river crew, they'd gang up around a log and roll
         it in the water, roll it in the river, that's all. That's all they
         could do. Just keep rolling it til it went afloat. Then there was
         another crew, more experienced— well, they weren't young men and
         they weren't old men, they were men around thirty-five, they were in
         the center crews. They would take the floating stuff, you know, you
         know like— they land on the center— like the center of the river
         and it's held there by something, you know, a rock, or something,
         and they'd pile up. They get to be real long. But you make space
         in the front; get slack in front, you see, that's the first thing
         you gotta do. It all depends on the water and general conditions.
         You get slack, and then it'll start to peel off, you see. Well,
         sometimes it'll go and sometimes it'll hang again and pile up more.
         That makes it bad. When it starts to go you hang on to it4as long
         as you can, you see, unless there's a shot or something in there.
         Then you've got to get the hell away from it.
         
         SS:   What?
         
         WS:   A Shot. You know, powder. A man to use powder, you see. But with
         these motor boats, you could always come back. But
         you couldn't. You have to line 'em back. That took a different
         length of time, of course. Sometimes that was an awful job,
         depends on how fast the water was and how far down river you went,
         and you had to line it back. The crew would line it back up, up
         way above the center so you could land on it again. That's why they
         didn't use so much powder then. You had to get away from it when
         you put a shot in, you know. And they didn't want to leave it. They
         wanted to stay and pick on it until it unravelled, see. If they 
         sure it was gonna go, they'd leave it. And, oftentimes they did,
         most of the time, after you got slack and started picking it a while
         they'd peel off, you know.
         
         SS:   When you say line 'em back up— would you explain that? What do you
         mean?
         
         WS:   Well, they all got what you call a painter on 'em, you know a rope
         in the bow, and it's a small rope 5/8's maybe. Well, the boatmen
         stay in and they'd pole, keep it off shore, and the rest of the crew
         would grab it and get ahold of that line on the bank and crawl along
         the bank and pull the Goddamn thing back up. Nobody likes to do that.
         That's why they hang on the center so long. They'd stay right on
         there, you know. They'd land in a place back pretty well from the
         front, you know. Get in between the logs, you see, so they could
         stay there until it went. Then they'd go. But I don't know, I've
         drove there three days and a half, one spring, that's as long as it
         took. And I've driven there a hundred days.
         
         SS:   How could you do it in two and a half days? What were the conditions?
         
         WS:   Well, the river's at Elk Creek. You know where that is?
         
         SS:   Yes.
         
         WS:   Well, that's where the river was, and that was in '48. And we stayed
         in town. We only had one boat. There was only four, five, six of
         us. Six, I think there was. But the water come up til, Lord God, you
         couldn't keep up to the rear, We had dinner at Ahsahka that day
         from Elk Creek, you can figure that out.Then out into the main river
         we went. The water was in the highway, you know. The water was right
         in the highway. Webb was the push that year. Young Webb, Bill Webb.
         That s old Webb s son. He worked on the pond there. And on a
         Sunday we finished up, we were at— I don't know, I think we left it 
         at Lapwai, or something. - Three days and a half.
         
         is he still alive?
         
         Oh, yes. He was the push on that drive, a good push. He lives on
         Third someplace. I know where he lives, but I can't—
         
         How old is he? Is he retired now? here-
         
         Yes. He's retired. He was foreman on the pond there for years. He
         was— You going to be around tomorrow? No, I can't tomorrow.
         This lady that tends bar down here, she lives at— two houses from
         Profitt.
         
         Where? At the Silver Dollar?
         
         Yeah. In the morning. She's just there in the morning. Not tomor-
         row ming, but she s there on Tuesdays, Wednesdays—
         
         I'll come back here another time and I'll find out.
         
         I haven't seen Profitt but once since he left the woods. He run
         Camp Two, you know. Yeah, he's a real guy. I didn't think he was
         that old. I drove with him on the Coeur d'Alene River. Oh, Christ,
         I was just a young guy. He was, too, he isn't as old as I am. He's
         about sixty-six, I think.
         
         What year was you born in?
         
         1903. Seventy-two last April.
         
         How much of the work when these guys were working on the river, on
         the drive, on the logs? Standing right on the logs? Was that a rare
         thing? Or was that pretty often you did that?
         
         Oh, depends on what you were doing, you were or
         something like that, you'd be working on timber all the time. But
         the rear crew, they weren't out on logs, unless they wanted to be.
         What I mean, once in a while they'd get in a slough or something
         and get to fooling around, but,no, there wasn't too much work on
         loose timber, except them centers. They get in a jam once in a while
         you'd get on the stuff, you know.
         
         SS:   Most of the time they worked from the batteau?
         
         WS:   Well, they'd be out of the batteau, of course, they wouldn't be in
         the batteau. They'd be out working on the timber. But the batteau'd
         be there to pick 'em up, see, in case they went a drift, or you know,
         got hurt or got dinged up some way, you know, or anyway incapacitated,
         they'd pick 'em up. Unless they got scattered, that's one thing a
         didn't like, if they got scattered around, you know, too much.
         Like a center breaking up, and the crew gets scattered and they
         couldn't pick 'em all up. Maybe someone wasn't capable of handling
         himself, in that position, you know. Get excited and get out of hand
         like. But mostly they got along pretty good. lost about four men
         on this river. Oh, yeah, that's all.
         
         SS:   Did you ever see anybody go? Get lost?
         
         WS:   Well, yes, I see them three at Lenore that spring. We went to pick
         'em up but we were too late. We were just above 'em. They were on
         the right hand side of the river going down, just above the bridge.
         And there was trees there, there was half a dozen bull pine trees
         scattered around there, and the water was maybe six feet deep, but
         awful strong, you know. It was smooth, but running fast. Strong
         water, you couldn't commence to swim against it, or nothing like that
         you know. You couldn't row a boat against it. Well, there was a
         boat working just below us on one of these trees, you know, taking
         this timber off the tree, and when the center moved out, when they
         and everything else, why, course, it just picked up and left
         and there was a big sweeper, big steer, oh, like pulling a stump,
         pull tree lengths, stump and everything, you know. Underneath that
         you couldn't see it. And it come up under the boat, you know, and
         swamped the boat. It come up under the bow and the stern went down
         you know, and it just rolled her right around underneath. Well,
         these guys that drownded were in the boat. But there was four of
         'em went up this tree. 
         
         Well, of course— I seen it. I was frosa here
         to that house, I guess, upriver in the other boat, we was working on
         a little center there. Someone said, "They're going to swamp that
         boat." They seen it coming back, you know. So we all jumped in. The
         boatman hollered for us to jump in. There was only four of us, we
         had the forward boat, and we took after 'em, you see, we left the guys
         in the tree, we didn't stop for them at all, we could see one guy,
         his head just going under the bridge as we got as close as we could
         to him, and he disappeared. The water was high and awful dirty, you
         know. You couldn't see nothin', you know. So, I guess, I don't know
         we landed at Cottonwood Island. And there was some guy going down
         along the bank, he was in the water, too. His name was Chase. There
         was Fitting, Chase and Anderson. There was the names of the guys that
         drownded. This Anderson, his daughter works in the liquor store here,
         that little blonde. She's forty-two years old now. But anyway, we
         landed at Cottonwood Island on the highway side, and it was on a Sun
         day and oh, quite a bit of traffic. I got up there and stopped an old
         flatbed truck that come along, And we put the boat on it. It was a
         way longer than that old flatbed, but three or four of us sat in the
         bow of the bow and held it down and tied it on. And we had to come
         back up and put that boat in the water and land on that tree where
         them guys was. That was a tricky proposition, but we made her. pick
         ed 'em all off: the four of 'em. This Tom was one of 'em. He lives in
         Orofino now. He works for a construction outfit. He's sixty-three
         I think now. But he was one of the guys up the tree.
         
         SS:   What year was that?
         
         WS:   Forty-nine Because me and this gal over here in the liquor store, you
         know, I get whiskey for the Silver Dollar you know. But anyhow, I
         used to talk to her, you know, she's a nice gal, said, "You knew my
         dad." That's when I first started getting whiskey there, three or
         four years ago. I said, "Yes, sure." But I didn't know who she was
         talking about. I was in the dark, I was going to wait to see if she'd
         volunteer some information, which she did right away, you know, she
         said,she was Walt Anderson's daughter. I knew Walt very well.
         
         SS:   So these three guys never had a chance, really?
         
         WS:   No, no, not after they got in the water, they didn't have no chance,
         no. Unless— the only chance they had if they had stayed with the
         boat. The boat didn't really swamp until it hit the pier, you know.
         It hit the bridge pier, and then it went under. We found that down
         Cottonwood Creek, washed up on a bar. But it was not serviceable anymore.
         But, I don't know, there was spare paddles in that boat and
         everything underneath the seat. I tied them in there myself when we
         started out. I had two paddles tied underneath. They was not in the
         way or nothin'. They could have grabbed one of them. Them boats they'll
         be just about ready to sink and they'll still pack three or four men,
         you know. But they could have done something if they'd a stayed with
         that boat. They could have stayed off a that pier; grabbed them pad
         dles, 'course, the oars and everything was gone. Oh, I don't know,
         excited, I guess.
         
         SS:   In a situation like that, you can really lose your
         
         WS:   They found 'em all but one. They found Chase and Anderson, but they
         never found Fitting. His brother, this guy that drowned was Ray, and
         I can't think of the brother's name, but I know him real well, he
         was on the police force here. He was chief of detectives in Cheyenne
         at the time this happened. He come up, he and his wife, and he stayed
         here all summer. He went to work on the police force here then, and
         every Sunday they'd take a boat and go up to Lenore and put the boat
         in the river and she'd drive the car down and he'd go up every Sunday
         all summer long, and they never found him. I suppose he got sanded
         in, you know someplace and buried.
         
         SS:   When that kind of thing happened, death or a bad accident, was there
         any protection for families?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, oh, yes. You mean insurance?
         
         SS:   Yeah, from the company?
         
         WS:   Well, I don't know about the company. The State, I know pays. Them
         guys got around eight thousand dollars, I think is all, but we took
         up collections in the ftamp for them. We got damn near that much in
         the camp. After the drive was over, you know.
         
         SS:   Eight thousand bucks for the three of 'em?
         
         WS:   Yeah. But they got eight thousand apiece out of the State. They kind
         of hung off on Fitting for— maybe they haven't paid it yet, but they
         claim that in seven years, they gotta pay it. So I suppose that's
         paid now.
         
         SS:   That was pretty good, getting that much money. That sounds like a lot
         of money to come out of the camps.
         
         WS:   Oh, yeah, but them guys are all pretty easy in a case of that kind you
         know. They got about that much for the three of 'em, you know. But
         it used to be customary — a collection taken up on a drive, you'd
         give a day's wages. Whatever the wages were— but, of course, I never
         paid any attention to that. I always hit her a little heavier. I'd
         spend it anyway, you know.
         
         SS:   What do you mean? A collection on the drive, if somebody was killed?
         
         WS:   Yes, or hurt, or sick, or something. They'd take up collections, you
         know. It used to be way more so— they don't take up many collections
         in these camps anymore. But, when I was a young guy around here, every
         day, there was someo taking up a collection.
         
         SS:   If you'd give to every one of those, you wouldn't have any salary left.
         If you'd give a day's work every day.
         
         WS:   I know. But, I mean, it wasn't every day, but there'd be every couple
         of months, or somewhere around that. But they was all worthy of it.
         
         SS:   You know, up North there, it seems like whenever the lumbering shut
         down the men all went to Spokane. Was that the same here?
         
         WS:   Oh, yees. Yes. Until  When they started up,Pierce was the town.
         Some guys never got by Pierce, for years, unless they come out the
         other way by Elk River. But I was in Pierce, I don't know, I musta
         been there twenty years, anyway, and I never got by there either.
         Everything there you wanted. Women, whiskey.
         
         SS:   That's pretty good. I didn't know there was any small towns that had
         that. I thought you had to go to a big city.
         
         WS:   Oh, no, Pierce always had 'em. They haven't now, but, there was always
         something like that there. I don't think there's any there now.
         
         SS:   There was a lot of lodging then, too? Lots of places for the 'jacks
         to stay? The houses, I imagine were places that the 'jacks could stay.
         
         WS:   Well, when I first went there— Have you been at Pierce lately?
         
         SS:   Yeah,
         
         WS:   Well, you know where the Clearwater Hotel is? There was a big tent
         there when I first landed there. There was I don't know how many men—
         The railroad was up at JP then, as far as JP, it wasn't into Headquar
         ters yet. But, I don't know, there must have been three thousand men
         around there. I don't know how many, they was coming and going, you
         know. And they had all kind of camps along the railroad; the railroad
         company, you know. Building that railroad up there. But that's where
         it was when I went up there at JP, didn't take 'em long to shoot in
         to Headquarters from there. But that old Clearwater Hotel was a big
         tent, and them army cots to sleep on. No floor in the bottom at all,
         just on the ground. I don't know what they charged; a dollar, I guess
         to sleep on one of 'em. I forget who built that. Old Chris Johnson
         built that Clearwater Hotel. Then old Snyder he built the Pierce Hotel,
         That was after that, too. There was just one old shack there, he was
         bootlegging there, and he just built on around it and he made a hotel
         out of it. It's still there. No! it burnt down. There's a bank
         there, by gosh.
         
         SS:   Were there many of the whorehouses there?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes. There was always about three. Four or five gals in each
         one. And the last year or so it got down to two and then one. The
         Pierce Hotel, that was always one. That is, after it changed hands,
         The Hotel, that was always— It isn't no more.
         
         SS:   In Bovill—
         
         WS:   There was never any there, was they?
         
         SS:   Yeah, there was, but they were gone by the time you came here. They
         were gone by about 1915, or something like that. I understand Clarkia
         stayed pretty wide open—
         
         WS:   Oh, Clarkia was— was hell, bing-bang. Everything. Same as Pierce.
         
         SS:   It was never so big, though, was it, as far as—?
         
         WS:   Oh, no. no, no. Well, they used to go in that way, you know, on that
         drive. Used to go in from Clarkia, you'd think that they was comin'
         out that way, the way they'd perform, you know.
         
         SS:   You talking about Marble Creek?
         
         WS:   Yeah. But they never come out that way. See, Marble Creek run in
         at the St. Joe below Avery. It's Marble Creek station, is what it is.
         That's where it runs in there. But you'd think they was comin' out
         that way, the way the bootleggers treated 'em. Give 'em everything
         they wanted. Gals and jugs and corks. And the girls were very free
         with their wares, tool (Chuckles)
         
         SS:   Well, what were they doing on Marble Creek? The logging there on Mar
         ble Creek— what kind of thing did they have going there? Didn't
         they have an incline there?
         
         WS:   Yeah, they had an incline coming down to the main line of the Milwaukee.
         Yeah. Did you ever see that thing?
         
         SS:   Uh-huh. Just hear about it.
         
         WS:   Well, that was quite a rig. That was a double track layout. Empties
         come up and the loads went down. No, it wasn't double track, they had
         an automatic switch, that was it. I've rode up on it. They had a
         donkey sitting on the top. A big donkey, I don't know, a big—
         or fifteen, and they used to drop them cars down.
         
         SS:   Must have been steep.
         
         WS:   It was 57 percent in one place. That's just exactly what it was, be
         cause I asked old whats-his-name, the first time I went in there. I
         asked him how steep that place was. He said fifty-seven percent, and
         I thought he was lyin' to me. That was Bill Gaffney. he was the sup
         erintendent then. I thought he was lyin' to me. I didn't say anything
         but I asked several others; all said fifty-seven percent. I guess it
         was.
         
         SS:   Did they flume in there, too, before they had
         
         WS:   They used chutes.
         
         SS:   Yeah, that's right.
         
         WS:   They shot 'em to the railroad, you know. Put 'em on skids and loaded
         'em out.
         
         SS:   Was there some kind of a fire there that they built an incline?
         
         WS:   A fire?
         
         SS:   Yeah. Was there some kind of a— can't remember what I heard now.
         I heard something about—
         
         WS:   Oh, there was a fire in 1910.
         
         SS:   Yeah, I heard about that one, yeah.
         
         WS:   The whole State of Idaho was burning then. They didn't try to put it
         out! I know they didn't. They couldn't. They had no way to get to
         it. But, I don't know of any fire there lately. Well, let's see, that
         was the Rutledge Timber Company, yeah. And then the Potlatch took it
         over. They didn't do much there. By gosh, they truck there now.
         They landed right in Clarkia, yes. When I worked up there, there was
         several different creeks- Hobo Creek, JG Creek. I don't know
         how many. I worked there at Hobo for a guy Em Up George, they
         called him.
         
         SS:   I've heard of that name.
         
         WS:   You have, eh?
         
         SS:   Sure. Well, what was he like?
         
         WS:   Oh, boy, there was never nothing like him. He was a divil, that fella!
         He got killed down in Oregon. I knew him real well. I knew the whole
         family. He had two boys and a girl and his wife. Yeah, he gyppoed for
         himself on Marble, that's when I first caught up to him. He went broke
         there. He had pretty fair outfit; fourteen teams of horses. All the
         riggin' to go with 'em, you know. Then he went to work for the Diamond,
         And he worked there for years, running camp. But I guess they didn't
         like his style, or something, because they dumped him, anyway. But
         he had quite a bit of money, you know. He owned a dandy home in Spokane.
         He lost everything. He went for the racehorse, you know. He bought
         a saloon, he run that and he was making money hand over fist, but he
         bought three old plugs and he started running 'em around and following
         em around from Seattle to Portland and Tacoma, First thing, you know
         he was on the rocks and had to go back to word in the woods. He could
         n't work himself, he was too old then to work. But then everything
         had changed. He never changed with conditions, you know at all. Never
         did. I know when 'dozers first come out, the Diamond bought 'dozers,
         he wouldn't use 'em. He'd skid them logs a hundred miles instead of
         building a truck road, and the 'dozers sitting in the camp yard. That
         didn't pay. I think that's one reason why—
         
         SS:   This Wood 'Em Up, I heard he got that name because he was always try
         ing to get one more log on there. Is that true?
         
         WS:   Yeah, that's it. Wood 'Em Up. And he was— he liked notoriety. He
         was an awful man to fire men, you know. I've seen him fire thirty
         men one morning. Thirty! There was them labor agencies in Spokane.
         Van Camp and Featherstone,^but he kept them busy.
         
         SS:   What did he fire 'em for? No reason?
         
         WS:   No. no. Hire 'em back the next day. No, he'd just get mad and start
         cannin' 'em. He'd can one, he might have a reason for canning the
         first one, but if you happened to come along right after that, you
         was gone, too. I was working for him five months and never got canned.
         I never did get canned. He never did can me. I,don't know why. If
         I thought it was coming, Id quit, you see! (Chuckles) he was
         a good guy, you could always go along and stay over night in his camp
         and sleep and eat. He might come in and tell you, "Nothin' doing to
         day, stick around for a day or two." Or something like that, you
         know. Yeah, he had a lot of good points. One of his boys is a contract
         or, now, you know. Yarno and Company. Yarno is his name, Y-A-R-N-O.
         But he is, an oh, a construction contractor. He built them sewers in
         Weippe, I know that, i haven't seen him since.
         
         SS:   You know, talking about this guy, or you know, staying overnight to
         find out if there's work. I've heard— One guy was telling me about
         these camp inspectors. Was there any guys that went around to campsto
         try them all out?
         
         WS:   Oh, yes, sure. Why, you see around Bovill, I've met thirty men between
         Camp 7 and Bovill, on the railroad track. They never said nothin'.
         They had to set up extra tables for 'em, them guys, sometimes. I
         never did go that route. I'd go to a camp, you know what I mean, when
         I was lookin' for work, that was customary then. You'd go into camp
         and if the push wanted you, he'd come around and tell ya. And if he
         didn't, why, he'd come and tell ya anyway. That was alright, then
         you could go. Or go to work, one or the other. I usually went to
         work. I don't know, I was pretty lucky. I knew a lot of 'em, you know.
         Andaa lot of the crew, you see, the crew would put a plug in for you
         once in a while. Like over on the Bovill side here— like Sturgils
         you know. I guess he's living yet.
         
         SS:   Oscar Sturgill? He died, recently.
         
         WS:   Moscow.
         
         SS:   Yeah. He's been dead, just this year. Recently.
         
         WS:   He always had tramps working for him. Tramp lumberjacks. And he al
         ways had the best horses. And if a guy come along, you know, there'd
         be some guy in the crew, of course, maybe you might know half of the
         crew, but there'd always be someone that'd whisper to old Oscar,
         "There's a pretty fair hand. And put him on you know, and
         then, you'd go to work. If he didn't know you, you know. That's the
         way that worked.
         
         SS:   When you say tramp lumberjacks— you mean the lumberjack that went around
         to a lot of different places and didn't stay in one camp?
         
         WS:   Well, yes, he stayed sometimes; sometimes he didn't. It all depends
         on, as I say, conditions, and sometimes they'd be real bad, but
         you'd stay anyway. I don't know what the hell the reason was.
         
         SS:   When you're saying tramp— figure there's a difference between a
         tramp lumberjack and what— in a family man?
         
         WS:   Well, yes, sure there is. The family man, he does stay. He's anchor
         ed to his job. The other guy he's just a kind of tramp, see. I don't
         mean he's a bum or nothing. Just a tramp, is all. Likes to keep mov
         ing. To see how they do things other places, or something like that.
         Well, you ought to go up and see this profit. He's a nice guy to
         talk to. He's amarried man, he's got-
         
         SS:   Was he on any of them early drives on the Clearwater River?
         
         WS:   First one.
         
         SS:   Was he? And he got so he'd run 'em?
         
         WS:   Yeah. Yeah, he run that drive— he must have taken it out seven or
         eight times, anyway. That was before the war, he started in. He run
         camp first. Then he took the drive. You see, this Boots— Did you
         ever hear of him?
         
         SS:   I don't know. What's his name?
         
         WS:   His name was Edelblute. He used to live in town here. He was married.
         He married Howard Bradbury's sister. Well, he took this drive after
         Old Brooks died. That was in '38— Old Brooks died. Well, he took it
         he finished it that spring and drove from then on until— I don't
         know— just before the war. And he got killed, in a windstorm. He
         was a superintendent then. But there wouldn't be much doing in the
         spring and he'd take that drive down. He liked that kind of work,
         you know. And a hell of a good man. He was from that Rathdrum,
         Coeur d'Alene country. Profitts, they grew up together. But
         there was a windstorm, you know, and he was in his pickup, and in
         stead of parking some place, he just kept a driving, you know and
         the wind a big snag over and just crushed him. Fell across
         the cab, just flattened everything. I was in Camp X. They worked
         on him all night. Doctors come in there, two doctors come in there.
         They come in there in a place— they come to Elk River in a plane.
         They brought him in there in a truck or something, I don't know.
         
         SS:   Well, I'll get going. What time you got?
         
         (tape turned off for a while at this point)
         
         WS:   I believe they're all  I don't know of a single one.
         
         SS:   I figured there must be some old-timers in Spokane someplace.
         
         WS:   They're awful scattered. I know of one, that's all now. 'Cause I
         hear from there every week. There's some guys go through here that's
         working up in camp. One of 'em. He goes to Spokane. I don't know
         what the hell, he plays the horses, too, that's what he goes there
         for. Harry, Harry the Horse, they call him. But he tells me about
         some people in Spokane.
         
         SS:   Guys that he knew from the old days?
         
         WS:   Well, he knows 'em. Not from the old days, but he knows 'em. From
         Spokane. The only place I ever seen him work was in, I never did see him anyplace
         else.
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13654</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Steffen1</previous>
      <next>Stowell2</next>
      <disp_name>Stowell1</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
