<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">5/17/1976</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>George Torgerson, 1976-05-17, Interview - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:04:02</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Torgerson, George</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview</intnum>
      <occupation>Ran drayline; did road maintenance;farmed</occupation>
      <birthyear>1892</birthyear>
      <residence>Park, Elk River</residence>
      <origin>Father was a Norwegian homesteader (c. 1890)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#chores"&gt;chores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#timber"&gt;timber&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#homesteads"&gt;homesteads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#roads"&gt;roads&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#threshing"&gt;threshing&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pioneers"&gt;pioneers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#languages"&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#churches"&gt;churches&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#fires"&gt;fires&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#stores"&gt;stores&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#post offices"&gt;post offices&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#logging camps"&gt;logging camps&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#IWW"&gt;IWW&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#strikes"&gt;strikes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#African Americans"&gt;African Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#drinking"&gt;drinking&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#banks"&gt;banks&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#moonshine"&gt;moonshine&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Prohibition"&gt;Prohibition&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mills"&gt;mills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#brothels"&gt;brothels&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mills"&gt;mills&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Park"&gt;Park&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Deary"&gt;Deary&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Elk River"&gt;Elk River&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13526</file_name>
      <mp3>13527.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13527.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Early morning chores</title>
            <synopsis>Early morning chores. Father grew up in the timber and
               wanted to stay there.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>240</time>
            <title>Many at Park sold their homesteads to Potlatch for little and moved out; parents worked
               hard; short lifespans
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Many at Park sold their homesteads to Potlatch for little and
               moved out. Land ownership Park. The bad roads for cars:
               building the old road. Parents worked hard; life spans were
               shorter. Most was grown; little was bought in stores.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Neighbors who met on the road always stopped and talked; few pioneers left the country</title>
            <synopsis>Neighbors who met on the road always stopped and talked.
               Very few pioneers left the country. Father had a threshing machine
               which they used on the ridges.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1020</time>
            <title>Learning English; Park Church ruined by not getting re-roofed</title>
            <synopsis>Learning English; school terms. The Park Church was ruined
               by not getting re-roofed. The minister came from Deary.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1380</time>
            <title>Their house burnt down at Park in January; he owned Deary bank for a while</title>
            <synopsis>Their house burnt down at Park in January; neighbors helped.
               He owned Deary bank for a while. Family ran store and post
               office in Park.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Potlatch didn't bring much money in because people who sold left; bad conditions in
               the camps, IWW strike
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Potlatch didn't bring much money in because people who sold left;
               some worked for the company. Low farm prices. Bad conditions
               in the camps; necessity of IWW strike, although he was
               against striking. Bad situation with rising prices now. Pay
               wasn't enough to get ahead much.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2340</time>
            <title>Parents could make a living at Park, but couldn't get ahead</title>
            <synopsis>Parents could make a living at Park, but he couldn't get ahead,
               so joined his brother in Elk River. Father had a meadow seven
               miles towards Elk River.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>The Trumballs, moneyed people, ran post office at site of Elk River; Torgersons put
               homesteaders up on their way to Elk River
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>The Trumballs, moneyed people, ran post office at site of Elk
               River and bought up surrounding homesteads. The Torgersons
               put homesteaders up on their way to Elk River. Trumball looked out for himself. Selling
               hay when mill started up.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3120</time>
            <title>Joe Wells' story to the new Potlatch crew; completely accepted by local people</title>
            <synopsis>Joe Wells' story to the new Potlatch crew. He was completely
               accepted by local people. He died by drinking the wrong bottle.
               He said when he scrubbed that he was still as black as ever.
               Drinking has always been common for many.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3540</time>
            <title>At Elk River credit would always be paid up at the end of the
               month at their business, (continued)
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>At Elk River credit would always be paid up at the end of the
               month at their business, (continued)
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Reliability of Elk River people; helped each other out when needed; social life was
               most enjoyable, circulation of the latest stories
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Reliability of Elk River people. They helped each other
               out when needed. He and his brother were stuck with houses
               when the mill went down all of a sudden. The social life
               was most enjoyable - circulation of the latest stories.
               Comparison of Park's independence with Elk River's money
               and fun; people were as close in Elk River a s Park. Judgement
               of new people at Elk River; the bad ones were forced to leave.
               He always handled Mrs. Bloom's trunk.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4140</time>
            <title>His dray line hauled supplies for moonshiners and wouldn't give information to town
               sheriff; moonshiner camps
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>His dray line hauled supplies for moonshiners, and he wouldn't
               give information to town sheriff. Moonshiner camps. A
               black moonshiner made the best in the area. Few were caught
               in the area. He supported prohibition at the polls, but made a
               mistake.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4560</time>
            <title>At first Elk River houses were company-owned; they sold them to the public shortly
               before they shut down
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>At first Elk River houses were company-owned; they sold them to
               the public shortly before they shut down. His dislike of the mill
               in Lewiston. In winter they told the people they'd open in
               spring. He stayed with the business until then despite his
               inclinations because he'd been doing so well. The went down
               the drain. The brothers tried mining with J.P. Jones, but
               there were too many people involved.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5040</time>
            <title>No more life in town; worked for Clearwater Highway District and the state for fourteen
               years and finally quit
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>No more life in town. He worked for the Clearwater Highway
               District and the state for fourteen years. Finally he quit
               because the state wouldn't supply materials to fix the road.
               Mr. Birchneyer asked him to work for him in Moscow and he
               continued as streets superintendent for twenty years.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Having to leave for Moscow; dray business in Elk River</title>
            <synopsis>Having to leave for Moscow. The dray business in Elk River.
               People's predicament when the company pulled out; the company's
               lack of concern.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5940</time>
            <title>Outstanding Japanese pool player at Elk River; picking up bad-smelling shipment of
               food from China
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Outstanding Japanese pool player at Elk River. Picking up
               bad-smelling shipments of food from China. The children spoke
               fondly of China. Three Chinese families - the women and one
               man worked in a laundry, the other two men in the mill.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6240</time>
            <title>Social events before the mill went out; various nationalities mixed freely</title>
            <synopsis>Social events before the mill went out. The various
               nationalities mixed freely; it made no difference. Elk River
               was hard on bad people; "deadbeats" had a miserable time.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6720</time>
            <title>Outdoor activities around Elk River; old road to Elk River from Kendrick; Elk River
               businessmen moved out; mill was modern
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Outdoors activities around Elk River. The old road to Elk
               River from Kendrick. Elk River businessmen moved out. The
               mill was modern. They were never told why the mill went out,
               and got no warning. Extra equipment was smashed with a
               sledge hammer and sold as scrap.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Homesteaders around Elk River. Prosperity of Elk River; devastating impact of mill
         removal. Settlement at Park. Moving from Elk River. 5-17-76 2 hr
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13316_lcoh_13316.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13526</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Thurtle</previous>
      <next>Tribble_Hershiel1</next>
      <disp_name>Torgerson</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
