<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">11/14/1975</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Emmet &amp; Anna Utt, 1975-11-14, Interview #5 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>2:19:51</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Utt, Emmett &amp; Anna</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #5</intnum>
      <occupation>Sawyer in Potlatch mill; farmer;Teacher; farm wife</occupation>
      <birthyear>1906</birthyear>
      <residence>Harvard, Hatter Creek</residence>
      <origin>Parents moved from Spangle, Washington (1911)</origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#teaching"&gt;teaching&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#world wars"&gt;world wars&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dating"&gt;dating&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#automobiles"&gt;automobiles&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#winter"&gt;winter&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#weddings"&gt;weddings&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#shivarees"&gt;shivarees&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#mills"&gt;mills&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#immigrants"&gt;immigrants&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#schools"&gt;schools&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#dances"&gt;dances&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#poor"&gt;poor&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Great Depression"&gt;Great Depression&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#electricity"&gt;electricity&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#boardinghouses"&gt;boardinghouses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#colleges and universities"&gt;colleges and universities&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#hunting"&gt;hunting&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#presidents"&gt;presidents&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#politics"&gt;politics&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Potlatch"&gt;Potlatch&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13530</file_name>
      <mp3>13531.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13531.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>60</time>
            <title>Their meeting; her years of teaching</title>
            <synopsis>Their meeting and her years of teaching.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>300</time>
            <title>Gas rationing during World War II</title>
            <synopsis>Run-ins with gas rationing during the Second World War.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>780</time>
            <title>Anna bet a girl she couldn't steal Emmett from her; Emmett bought a motorcycle</title>
            <synopsis>Anna bet with a very forward girl that she couldn't steal Emmett from her. Emmett
               decided to forget about women and bought a motorcycle instead.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1200</time>
            <title>Anna riding his motorcycle; motorcycle sidecars</title>
            <synopsis>Anna's first and last ride on his motorcycle. A motorcycle ride for a tramp. Motorcycle
               sidecars.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1560</time>
            <title>Driving to Woodfell</title>
            <synopsis>Driving to Woodfell to get Anna in the winter snow.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1680</time>
            <title>Entertainment for dating couples; getting around stopped cars</title>
            <synopsis>Entertainment for dating couples. Getting around a long string of stopped cars.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Raising cane at Harvard; Anna's father liked Emmett</title>
            <synopsis>Emmett raised cain with his Velie at Harvard, so the people up there didn't like him
               but Anna's father did.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1920</time>
            <title>Getting married; setting up a house; bridal showers; Emmett almost shot</title>
            <synopsis>Getting married and setting up house. Anna was a crack rifle shot. Shivaree and bridal
               showers. Emmett almost shot during a shivaree.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2400</time>
            <title>Working in the mill; rumor about foreigners getting promoted</title>
            <synopsis>Working in the mill in the early years. The few whites used to tease the Greeks for
               speaking in Greek among themselves. Rumor that foreigners kicked-back to their bosses
               to get promoted. A Greek sawmiller who became a millionaire in business.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2880</time>
            <title>Concentration camps during the war; Gus Demus gave money to the poor in Greece</title>
            <synopsis>A Japanese janitor sent to concentration camp during war, suspected of being an agent.
               A Japanese worker who told Emmett Japan was going to lick the U.S. Gus Demus gave
               much of his money to the poor in Greece. Dago Mikers yellow Ford.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3300</time>
            <title>Emmett turned water hose on full blast; town kids feared country kids</title>
            <synopsis>Emmett turned the water hose on full blast, surprising men in the mill. Town kids
               feared country kids.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Working as a "servant girl"; high school in Potlatch</title>
            <synopsis>Anna worked as a "servant girl" on Nob Hill in return for board and room so she could
               go to high school in Potlatch.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3720</time>
            <title>Making "Eskimo pies"; Potlatch pool hall owner; smoke bombs at dances; working for
               a doctor's wife
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Making "Eskimo pies" with their inventor, the Potlatch pool hall owner. Country kids
               went to high school by living in Potlatch. Working for the rich was a hardship. Anna
               was promised but never given a dollar a week. A boss's car was drained of gas when
               he didn't pay his bill. Anna got in trouble because her girl friend ate candy at the
               house she was working at. Her "employer" bragged on her. Smoke bombs at a dance for
               the "upper class." Working for a doctor's wife who was kind but tight. Speaking when
               spoken to.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Working for Emmett's aunt; aunt was spoiled</title>
            <synopsis>Anna worked for Emmett's aunt, who later had to accept her into the family. How aunt
               was spoiled.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4860</time>
            <title>Millionaires like common people; local boy who became rich</title>
            <synopsis>Millionaires can be like common people; difference between them and the "two-bit millionaires."
               A local boy who became rich.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>5400</time>
            <title>Forced retirement; walking to work; repossessing cars at Potlatch during the Depression</title>
            <synopsis>Forced retirement and getting ahead at Potlatch. Poor people walked to work, they
               didn't use cars. Repossessing cars at Potlatch during the Depression. More concern
               with possessions in Potlatch than in the country. Country people working in Potlatch.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6000</time>
            <title>Moving out of Potlatch; their country place during the Depression; swapping among
               farmers
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>Emmett moved out of Potlatch when he was forced to pay electricity costs for people
               who weren't working. Getting by in their country place during the Depression. Beans
               for the neighbor. Swapping among the farmers.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6360</time>
            <title>Land purchases; dances at halls; drinking at dances; early movies</title>
            <synopsis>Emmett's land purchases. As a boy he had to return five dollars to a lumberjack who'd
               given it to him while drunk. Dances at halls around the country. Drinking at dances
               - young people didn't very much. Decline of old entertainments, Early movies.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>6840</time>
            <title>Working on Nob Hill</title>
            <synopsis>More about working for the well-to-do on Nob Hill.</synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7200</time>
            <title>Family wanted care during the flu; father helped through school; boarding in Lewiston</title>
            <synopsis>Her family wanted her to go home and care for them during the flu, but she didn't
               want to give up school. Father helped her through school as much as he could. Emmett
               was led upstairs to see Anna in her Lewiston boarding house by mistake. Boarding in
               Lewiston while going to Lewiston Normal.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>7620</time>
            <title>The Depression; wife starved to death; popularity of Roosevelt; opposition to Truman
               election
               
            </title>
            <synopsis>During the Depression, a young married wife starved to death. Shooting deer and leaving
               much of the meat. Popularity of Roosevelt. Boomdays of the twenties. Opposition to
               Truman election among mill management.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Her work as servant girl on Potlatch Nob Hill. Class snobbery and self-made men.
         Dating and marriage. Depression days. Gas rationing. Relation of country people to
         Potlatch.
         11-14-75 2.3 hr 58p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript>&lt;a target='_blank' href='https://objects.lib.uidaho.edu/lcoh/transcripts/13328_lcoh_13328.pdf'&gt;Download
         the PDF Index&lt;/a&gt;
         
         No transcript available.
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13530</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Utt_EmmettAnna4</previous>
      <next>Vine</next>
      <disp_name>Utt_EmmettAnna5</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
