<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT>
   <record dt="2015-01-03">
      <version>4</version>
      <date format="yyyy-mm-dd">10/3/1974</date>
      <date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format>
      <cms_record_id>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</cms_record_id>
      <title>Lela Grace Jain Wicks, 1974-10-03, Interview #2 - MP3 Recording</title>
      <accession></accession>
      <duration>1:31:36</duration>
      <collection_id>latah</collection_id>
      <collection_name>Latah County Oral History Collection</collection_name>
      <series_id></series_id>
      <series_name></series_name>
      <repository>University of Idaho Library</repository>
      <repository_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/</repository_url>
      <subject>Latah County -- Idaho</subject>
      <interviewee>Wicks, Lela Grace Jain</interviewee>
      <intnum>Interview #2</intnum>
      <occupation>County commissioner and civic leader; homemaker</occupation>
      <birthyear>1906</birthyear>
      <residence>Genesee, Coyote Grade</residence>
      <origin>Father's family came from Wisconsin (1878), mother's from Michigan
         (1892)
         
         
      </origin>
      <keywords>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#pioneers"&gt;pioneers&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Native Americans"&gt;Native Americans&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#food"&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#rattlesnakes"&gt;rattlesnakes&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#farming"&gt;farming&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#animals"&gt;animals&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#women"&gt;women&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#families"&gt;families&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#trapping"&gt;trapping&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#horses"&gt;horses&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#electricity"&gt;electricity&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#telephones"&gt;telephones&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </keywords>
      <locations>
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Genesee"&gt;Genesee&lt;/a&gt;
         
         &lt;a href="/digital/lcoh/index.html#Coyote Grade"&gt;Coyote Grade&lt;/a&gt;
         
      </locations>
      <interviewer>Sam Schrager</interviewer>
      <file_name>13534</file_name>
      <mp3>13535.mp3</mp3>
      <sync>1:|0(1)</sync>
      <media_id></media_id>
      <media_url>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/latah/13535.mp3</media_url>
      <mediafile>
         <host>Other</host>
         <host_account_id></host_account_id>
         <host_player_id></host_player_id>
         <host_clip_id></host_clip_id>
         <clip_format>audio</clip_format>
      </mediafile>
      <language></language>
      <index>
         <point>
            <time>0</time>
            <title>Place of birth and growing up a pioneer</title>
            <synopsis>Her place of birth was incorrectly recorded as Latah, not Nez
               Perce County. Growing up with a pioneer heritage*
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>180</time>
            <title>Stories from living on the farm</title>
            <synopsis>Watching an Indian get fruit from the Reuben place.
               Reuben family. She asks Eddie Conner an embarrassing
               question. A dispute over the farm's boundary is settled
               by a grove of trees.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>480</time>
            <title>Fruit, produce and animals</title>
            <synopsis>Her father's knife is lost in a tree. Kinds of fruits
               from the family orchard. "The William Nixon Bare
               Spot" in the raspberry patch. Her father wins a bet
               with a neighbor about the size of his strawberries.
               He loved to give neighbors garden produce, and to keep
               Gersey cows in town.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>900</time>
            <title>Dogs and animals</title>
            <synopsis> Dogs. Gack, their first, a stray from a covered wagon,
               was shot by neighbors when roaming. Stubb, the cattle
               dog, and Missy, who knew how to get petted. Grace kills
               her puppy by mistake.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1260</time>
            <title>Dealing with rattlesnakes</title>
            <synopsis> Snakes. How children took care of rattlesnakes. The
               mate returned to the spot where his partner was killed.
               Where rattlesnakes were found.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1440</time>
            <title>Birds on the farm</title>
            <synopsis> Birds. The pigeon problem on the farm. Swallows,
               hawks, and other welcome birds. Destructiveness
               of English sparrows and sparrow hawks.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1620</time>
            <title>Pigs on the farm</title>
            <synopsis> Their pigs were great snake killers. Missouri razorbacks
               ate chickens. Her mother fights off two enraged sows
               who were attacking a piglet caught in the fence.
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>1800</time>
            <title>Women's work and survival </title>
            <synopsis> Her mother's frailty. She used to tell Grace that
               while men worked six days, women worked seven, and that
               women conceived when they were physically weakest.
               (An unwanted child became a leading citizen; nature took
               care of the human family before family planning.)
               Her mother's isolation was lightened by joining the
               Golly Gokers, an international club of people who wished
               to correspond: gifts and letters came from everywhere,
               and the children learned of geography. Her mother enjoyed
               giving a meal to travellers and talking with them; they
               housed the school teacher and hired hands. Winter breakfast.
               
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>2520</time>
            <title>Native Americans in the area</title>
            <synopsis>Indians. Peo-peo-ptalkt, and hollyhock in Indian
               yards. Charlie White's mother, an Indian, was put aside
               for a white woman after the country was settled; the story
               was told that she camped in the new wife's yard when she
               was angry. Grace's Indian friend had tragedy in her
               family when her son was killed in a fight.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3000</time>
            <title>Stories of women in the area</title>
            <synopsis>Brocky Gack, mistress of a rancher, had pride in dealing
               with a dressmaker. Gane Silcott, an Indian, was buried
               by her husband Goseph at the confluence of the Snake
               and Clearwater. Goseph never took his sister home to
               meet her.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3240</time>
            <title>Trapping animals for bounty during war; coming of the telephone</title>
            <synopsis>She trapped squirrels and weasels for bounty while the boys
               wjuri at war, and bought a ukelele with the proceeds.
               She learned songs from early records, some of which
               her mother worried she'd sing in town. The telephone
               came; a night call of distress from the Spokane county
               jail.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3600</time>
            <title>Stories of Nez Perce</title>
            <synopsis>Her brother Ben was often asked for a little money by
               the Indian he rented from. He witnessed a Nez Perce
               funeral, which ended with the widow giving away all the
               family possessions.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>3900</time>
            <title>Bunkhouse and reading books</title>
            <synopsis>The bunkhouse covered the storage cellar. Mother discouraged
               her from reading westerns, forbade Horatio Alger, but
               permitted mild love stories. Reading Topnotch while
               herding cows. They named cows after the wife of the
               man who sold them, or after movie stars.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4260</time>
            <title>Horses and dogs</title>
            <synopsis>Horses. Prince always stopped when one child tumbled off
               his back. Madge lived on white bread through a winter;
               Ben mourned when she died and was dragged away. A small
               boy was bitten by a rabid coyote, and the family dogs were
               muzzled.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4620</time>
            <title>Electricity and going to town</title>
            <synopsis>Electricity came to the farm. Dressing to go to town
               to trade, and wearing dusters. Mother told stories
               on the way to town; Follow-Me's rest stop. The pleasure
               to come back home.
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
         <point>
            <time>4980</time>
            <title>Trees, shrubs and bees on the farm; first job; working as telephone operator</title>
            <synopsis>Trees and shrubs on the farm. Mother hived bees for
               honey, and once nearly died from a dead stinger. The
               family children didn't hire out, which was her mother's
               pride. Her first job was embroidery for ten cents an
               hour. Working weekends as the Genesee telephone operator
               for nine cents an hour; she was afraid of the switch
               board in thunderstorms, and handled all kinds of requests.
               
               
               
               
            </synopsis>
         </point>
      </index>
      <type>interview</type>
      <description>Growing up on the family farm: reading, music and pen-pal club. Farm animals and
         orchard. Mother's frailty as a pioneer. Nez Perce families. Jane Silcott; Brocky Jack.
         10-3-74 1.5 hr 30p
         
         
      </description>
      <rel></rel>
      <transcript> 
         
         
         
         SAM SCHRAGER: Grace Wicks was very observant of life on her family's farm in the
         Genesee country side when she was a girl. She enjoyed it all: from the fruit
         garden, dogs and horses to exciting town trips, their Indian neighbors and a
         club that brought the geography of the world to their door. She rem
         embers difficulties as well, especially her mother's frailty and loneliness
         the strenuous pioneer life and also the danger of rabid dog, rattle
         snakes and the nuisance of certain birds. She also tells of operating the
         Genesee telephone switchboard- on weekends.
         
         MRS. WICKS: I am Lela Grace Jain Wicks. I was born in 1906 at the top of Coyote
         Grade in Nez Perce County, State of Idaho. I was the youngest of five, and my
         mother forgot that this after-thought child of hers was born in Nez Perce County
         because her other four were born in Latah County. So she registered our births
         in Boise, the State Capital, as having all been born in Latah County, and when I
         discovered this I pointed out the error. We wrote to the State Capital and we
         found out it would take an act of God, even though Mother and the nurse that at
         tended her were still living, to get that location of my birth changed. So that's
         the way it is in Boise. Since I was born in 1906, I have many early day memories
         and since I was a later child in the family I spent much time alone with my par
         ents. Which meant that I adopted or by osmos_is or capillary attraction, or what
         have you, acquired a great deal of their thinking, so that I feel very at home in
         this period. I loved my home and I loved my family and we all loved our friends^
         so there was great empathy that went on around our table on the
         back steps that went to the kitchen over any tasks
         that were shared. 
         
         And since the help that was employed in the home was always a
         neighbor or a neighbor's child, or somebody who homesteaded next door, or some
         body who was connected in some way by place with where we lived, we were very
         polite to them, and they were very polite to us.and we were on an equal, or near
         ly so, social basis. I'd like to talk a little bit about the Indians I have
         known. One of them in particular, was my father's landlord. His name was Steven
         Rueben, and he was a fullblood who had inherited or been given by the government,
         ajlotted, I suppose I should say, a large tract of land which was across phe canyon
         from our house, but adjacent to my father s land, which was also across the can
         yon from where we lived. The Rueben ranch was a choice place, and Father ran it
         for many years. It was distinguished by having a large orchard that I don't have
         any idea who planted, but it certainly wasn't an Indian- because they weren't
         along in our culture enough to provide in that way for fruit. But someone had
         planted a large orchard there, and the Indians would come and pick fruit from
         time to time, particularly the squaws. lee they were unobtrusive and didn't bother
         anybody. SiFt I remember one day, a lone rider came up the road from the Clear
         water River and down through our gate and down our driveway a**d?~past the house and
         past the barn and 6tit through the corral and down across the canyon over to the
         Rueben ranch. Now I watched him the whole way with my father's good field glasses
         because I was a bored little girl and had lots of time on my hands. Sor anything
         that was moving, that was a little out of the ordinary got full attention, 4m lie
         went over to the Rueben ranch and ndpne was there. So he took the woodbox, emp
         tied all of the contents on the kitchen floor, tramped it down a little, and
         went out and filled the woodbox with apples. Then it was a little large to put
         on the back of his saddle, and a little large to balance on the front, so he had
         great difficulty in getting it back (on horseback) to where he wanted to go.-3-
         I watched this procedure and was a little amused because, of course, Mother
         interpreted what had happened, and I don't know how many apples he got home
         with, but that made a very entertaining interlude for me.
         The Ruebens were a , fine family, and Steven Rueben was an ordained Presbyterian
         minister! so when he came to dinner on went the white tablecloth and
         a good meal was provided, Imean a company Sunday dinner. 4fM the Reverend Steven
         Always said grace. We were accustomed to grace when our grandfather came, but not
         when our dad presided.
         
         Now another Indian whose land bordered us on the north was Eddie Connor.
         Eddie I think also was a fullblodded Indian, and a handsome large man. who had
         a very round head. one time I embarrassed my mother greatly by saying
         to Mr. Connor, "Mr. Connor, what makes your head so round?" And of course, he
         laughed and Mother laughed, but she could have killed me. (chuckles) 
         Connor performed a nice service for us later in life because there was a suit
         brought regarding the boundary line, of the home place, and it was said that we
         had forty feet of someone^land, the full west border of the place, which was
         on a straight line and which had a few locust trees on it, and several walnut
         trees that Dad had planted along our driveway. Those trees and Mr. Connor's
         testimony saved that forty foot strip of land over this long space for our
         home place. It seems that the law recognizes a border if it has living growth
         on it that shows length of time. And since both the walnut and the locust trees
         were of large size, they knew that that land had been paid taxes upon and farmed
         by the owner of our place who was/Walter F. Jain^for all those many years.
         Also, Mr. Connor testified at the trial that he had known my father for some
         years and that indeed in all that time Walter had farmed this land. I have an
         other tiny story about the locust trees One time at an early period when Dad
         and Mother were out working in the garden, they finished what they were doing,
         and Dad put a case knife up in the crotch of one of the trees. Now a case knife
         is a full-sized dinner knife w. ith a wooden handle. It was used by early day-4-
         bachelors and that sort of thing, but it never was used in serving food at my
         mother's table*, however, I suppose that's the kind of cutlery that my fatker
         had when he was a bachelor before he was married. .... fit any rate, it was in
         the family possession, and was the handy tool that day. 
         
         Well, wz(one came along
         to finish whatever th job had been going on, and so the knife stayed in the tree
         and in due time the tree grew around it and further, completely covered it. -feSi
         I have tried to find it since: There is not one blemish on the trunk of that tree
         which still, sixty years later, is right there and the knife is completely gone,
         incorporated in the middle of that tree. Dad took great pride in his orchard
         and all of us savored the delicious fruit that came to our table from time to
         time. Dad felt that fruit or vegetables were to be had in their season and he
         gave very little time to winter strawberries or winter tomatoes. What he thought
         was good was what was picked and brought immediately Mto the table, and indeed
         there never was a better taste when it was accompanied by homemade well jjpjig
         butter and good thick separated cream, jEhat was ambrosia/ In his orchard he had
         early peaches, and Ja$4 peaches, silver prunes and plums and purple prunes. He
         had peach plums, which I see now at an exhorbitant price in the market, and which
         we didn't care for and there were tree of, so the children were put to taking
         these to the pigs. I never see them on the market at fifty cents for about
         six that I don't have a little of my hair curled, (chuckles) Dad also sum
         mer apples. fall apples and winter apples. And how we did enjoy those.
         Mother made wonderful sauce and we also had three kinds of black cherries; Lambertsy
         Bings and Black Republicans. -Agtfsince we ourselves were black^Republicans, those
         had spectial empathy. In that garden was anjsnormous patch of red raspberries.
         These were the bane of the women's existence, because they never could keep all
         of the dratted things picked in season, and when my brother finally brought his
         bride there she thought she'd never had such a burden placed upon her. "9t it
         had, in the middle of this patch a bare place which was wrought by a large-5-
         young man, probably about fifteen, named William Nixon, whose father and
         mother were very old friends of the family, and who came to pick raspberries with
         the family and who sat down in aconvenient area and pulled the raspberry vines
         to convenient distance and filled his pail. Of course, the patch never recovered
         from his picking, but we always called it the William Nixon garespot, and it «emained
         there as long as the patch did. (laughter)
         
         My dad was agreat homemaker. He not only planted those blac^alnuts which
         still line the driveway, long since unused, But he had lovely roses along there
         too. And also, from time to time, beautiful patches of strawberries. Iremem
         ber one time when he had adear friend who^usband was apioneer, John Ha He
         had John and haAsa. Hall in that garden, and bet Mrs. Hal] . no matter what, he
         could find a strawberry too big for her to consume in one bite, and not have
         juice run' t i;; from the corner of her mouth. Well, asnw Mrs. Hall was a very
         beautiful woman, who took great pride in her appearance, and whom we all dearly
         loved, but she took his bet^ and he found an enormous berry which she promptly
         popped in her mouth, and down the corner of each side came the red marker of her
         defeat. (chuckles) We also had blackberries from time to time, but they were
         such space pigs, and took such a lot of room, and were so difficult to pick that
         Dad eliminated them. The garden was a great source of pleasure to Father who
         as a pioneer boy deeply cherished good food, and when guests came to see us, which
         was nearly every Sunday in good weather, he loved to load their rigs, ow it
         wasn't a buggy, and it wasn't a wagon and it wasn't a Model T— whatever anybody
         came to our house in was a rig, and he loved to load up their rigs with delicious
         things from the garden. It swelled his heart to be able to do it) he felt just
         warm and loving and provident and so rich when he could do this. Aff lis long as
         I can remember my father as a host he continued to do this, even when he retired
         to and kept Jersey cows because they were fun. He told me one time,
         "I like to go up to the poojihall and play a little solo with my best friends, and
         maybe win a hickey, and bring you home a chocolate bar, and then go out to the
         barn and feed something." He had Jersey cows because their
         cream content was so high. 
         
         And there was just one terion about a
         good Jersey. She had to have long enough so a man could get his hands on
         them because: be damned if he wanted to have that milk sprayed all over the
         lower part of his palm when he tried to milk a short teated cow-- he wouldn't
         have her. (chuckles) Dad and his dogs were a great pleasure to me, too. The
         first dog in the family that I remember, was a character. I the story goes
         was a baby in my cradle on the south porch, and my arm was just long enough so
         that my hand could poke out between the slats at\ the side of the cradle; 
         Mother . working in the kitchen with the door open between us, heard a little
         thump, and a little sigh and looked out to find a most engaging black dog with
         white around his muzzle and a weariness to his body, a worness to the pads of
         his feet, contentedly licking the hand of "MM baby. They named him Jack, and
         figured that probably hiL had grown so tired he no longer could follow the cov
         ered wagon which had gone along the road that morning. I am sure the family that
         lost him were sore of heart, but he was our great good friend from then until
         when he died, which was many years later. The trouble with Jack was that he
         liked to roam at night, and the neighbors didn't caee for his visits. So the
         man on the horth, who was farming the Connor place shot him in the right hind leg
         and somebody-we never knew who- shot him in the l^fi1 hind leg and the right
         foreleg, so poor Jack had to hobble around in great misery, and no one ever thought
         of taking out those bullets. They just left Jack get along and he lixzked those
         wounds from then 'tilj he died, and of course, must have suffered terrible pain.
         These days we'd have him in to the vet in a minute, but those days to take an
         animal to the vet meant that he had to be an animal that paid his way, and, of
         course, Jack was the best stock dog in the world, but after he became impaired
         he was a beldtved pensioner. Along with him was Stub. warned for his short,
         bobbed tail. He did all the work after Jack was incapacitated, and since my
         father always had cattle to some extent . little "jag" of cattle they were
         called, then he would be the mainstay for corraling them, for gathering them
         for a driveJaa just bringing them home at night. A man with stock can't get
         along without a good dog because if he does he v wasteSan amazing amount
         of time. Another dog we had that was my father's dear friend, was MiSy. She
         was an Australian Collie, and a spayed female,, «ffli .she accompanied us always
         to the toilet which was out to the north of the house, ad as we went to and
         from, a nice little dog let us know her presence by leaping and touching with
         her cold nose in very gentle, but insistent fashion our right elbows. Of
         course, she got many a pat and all kinds of lovely visiting, both going and
         coming, and we enjoyed it. and she enjoyed it. (chuckles) 
         
         My father, it fell
         to his lot to have to shoot each of his dogs when they became so old that they
         had to leave this world and it was kinder to do it thus, and each time it was
         a major, major operation for him, and one which he could hardly bear to do, but
         he was always Sffeftt with himself as with the necessities of life.
         One time when I was a little girl, during World War I, and my father had
         returned to the farm, because my big brothers, who had been running the farm,
         and who were about nineteen and twenty-one almost, v^nz.' beirw occupied by World
         War i; Trimima. we went back to the farm to grow food. "Slit during that time my
         dad came home from riding down on the river, and he found along the way a little
         cur puppy^, .aflft-" it had been put out of a sack, I suppose, somebody figuring it
         would die, and they wouldn't have to have the pain of putting it to deathj and so
         they put it out to starve to death or a coyote to get it. jft Dad, of course, he
         couldn't stand that, so he gathered it up and tenderly brought it home to his
         little girl. I thought it was yummy; it was the sweetest little old pup--as
         every pup is—and so I carried it every place I went. And I'd m had it in bed
         with me if Mother would have allowed, but that certainly was beyond the pale, we
         had no animals in the house; none whatever, ever, though we dearly loved them
         them and had 'em as part of our lives, just outside the door. This little dog
         and I had a traumatic experience. I carried it, as I said, every place I went,
         and one night I was feeding the chickans, and I had a big pan of feed, and I was
         holding it in my left hand with the doggie balanced on the pan, and then with my
         right hand I strewed the wheat, a«d the dog became impatient with this and jumped
         or fell to the ground stumbled over the the little soft belly, and my foot
         came right down on it and broke it^s back. Oh! Ithought I'd die that was
         one of those things. We learned on a farm that you never think too much of an
         animal or anything, because you have to kill your own 
         had rattlesnakes on this place, so that everywhere a child's foot would set
         down-in wheat, in weeds, in grasses, in any growth you watched where your foot
         went. This was also helpful so that you didn't step in a cow pie! But in the
         main, it was to protect us from snakes. I learned to tell a rattler from a bull
         snake, which was protect^., a rattl We were given great
         instructionrrm instruction, as to what to do when we found a rattler. We were
         to send somebody in the party, if there was one, to the house, while someone who
         had spotted the snake kept it in vision. nd that way a big person could come
         with ahoe, the twenty-two )Qr an axe and dispatch the snake. We were never to
         let it out of our sight. 
         
         then in that area we were to be exceedingly wary
         for the next several days because the mate would come to hunt it_s partner and
         would be found in-.fchearea. This happened invariably. Apparently snakes are
         monogomous and mate for life. Nov, I don't know whether this is true or not,
         but certainly we got snake after snake after snake because it came to follow
         it s dead partner. We found one right at the door of the barn coiled ready;
         we found two, that I know of, in the raspberry patch. One time years later,
         in another canyon, working for my brother, my husband had a snake slither down
         the handle of his hay fork as he pitched a bundle into the wagon. Of course,
         these snakes were complete enemies, and no one protected them, ever. There
         were good snakes, of course, who killed blacksnakes and water snakes and harm
         less garter snakesan. that were protected because they killed varmints
         too, but for the deadly snake, we were ' very, very busy dispatching them,
         and the same in the bird world. We were taught the good ones and the bad ones,
         had large flocks of pigeons, and my mother made delicious pigeon potpie. 
         "Zhese pigeons, however, were dirty creatures, and Father had to finally kill
         them all off because they roost high, they are very prolific, and their drop
         pings are very bad for hay; animals don't like to eat it after it has been pol
         luted.  droppings on machinery is damaging they have the poorest
         of domestic instincts- in that they'll lay their eggs with one or two sticks on
         a two by four shelf, just a stud going along in a shed, so they don't bother
         much about their eggs rolling off or their young rolling off. An amazing number
         of them didn't, ^nd the birds were beautiful as they flew and beautiful
         as they walked. There's nothing prettier than the streamline of a lovely pigeon,
         and their coloring is out of this world. So many varieties and such a lovely
         sound to their wings and to their cooing. We loved them. ~WMDad had them first
         in a cote, but they outgrew that in short order and then took over, first the
         machine shed and then went into the barn. im When they began destroying the hay;
         ( Dad had to take action. Now, we had pillions of swallows, who built their sweet
         little mud nests around. We had lots of bluebirds in those days, and yellow canaries,
         and we loved them and protected them in every way we could. Jtet the English
         sparrow began to invade, and that sparrow was really a destructive animal. It
         was almost as bad as a magpie~-both of which are predators of other animals nests
         and both homes that are made by other birds; kill their young, scratch
         out their eggs and take the places themselves. We were taught to destroy if pos
         sible vboth species of birds. A hawk now was a somewhat protected animal, part
         icularly if it was a large hawk—a redhead or a barnhawk. They sailed so beauti
         fully in the clouds against the wind. Sometimes they couldn't make any headway
         at all with the breeze they tried to go against. And those amazing eyes of those
         creatures way up there in the air/ wo^lA see the movmment of a mole or a tiny
         squirrel or a little mouse, way down in the hog pasture, and ZOOM, they'd come
         down and feM it. Now, a sparrow hawk was another thing. We killed sparfow hawks
         religiously. That's what the twenty-two was used most for-^-to hit a sparrow hawk
         square in the eye—that was the goal. Because a sparrow hawk ate baby chickens.
         We had a little flurry with our pigs, too. Our pigs were in a pasture north
         of the house, out back of the toilet, and off to themselves where their
         noise or their odors didn't distress the household. They were great snake killers.
         Apparently the layer of fat under a pig's skin protects him from the venom, be
         cause they could kill rattlers or any other kind of snakes and they were great to
         help keep down the population of snakes. time we found He kind of pig
         that was new to us. 
         
         It was a Missouri Razorback that had been shipped in in a
         government project, and those razorbacks were indeed high along their backbone,
         and they had hair straight up along that area. Now our Poland Chinas and Duroc
         Reds were nice, round, flat-backed pigs, and they were domesticated and we could
         live with them nicely, but those wretched razorbacks ate Mother's chickens! And
         I tell you, it was the chickens life if it got into the hog pasture. So we couldn't
         get rid of those creatures fast enough. The only time a red sow or a black sowoh,
         we had a few New Hampshires, too, with the white band around their middle-
         -/lie only time those were dangerous was when one of their little pigs got caught
         intA,:fence. Now, a baby pig is tiny, like any other animal for ±ty species
         when its young, and so it will go through a crack in the fence, and in due time
         it grows and it gets so big it gets stuck in the hole that it has been using all
         this time^ Ugl it'll squeal— oh! It's being squeezed, and it doesn't like it
         and it raises a r«^er a the mother sow gets very excited, and she nip
         the pig to increase it s efforts, and if she draws blood, which she easily can,
         she becomes very excited, and she'll cew the pig up— to death. Mother,
         being a town girl didn't know about all this, but she was game, art She took the
         axe one day and got in a pigpen and fought off two enraged sows who had a pig
         that they were just dispatching. Ad he took the axe with her (laughter) and
         I remember seeing that axe flailing and Mother's apron flying and her determined,
         beautiful little face set in lines of complete combat and she was whaling away
         at the hog with the sharp end of the axe, meaning, of course, to hit 'em with the
         dull but she got a little confused. Well; anyway, she scared off the women--
         (Ifiqghter) and saved the piglet. Bat fcity mother didn't often take any hand
         in the operation of the farm, however^ outside the house, never. She never gath
         ered an egg, she never picked a pea- she sometimes did fruit, but not other things.
         
         (End of Side A)
         
         Mother was never well. I have known long periods of time when she lived on
         parched bread and cocoa. She was a dear, charming, loving, intellectual woman,
         and she didn't fit the diet— the sstringent diet of salt meat and hotcakes and
         winter vegetables, such as cabbage, kraut, and roots. About the only one
         I imagine she could consume was carrots, and in the days before we processed vege
         tables r and that was not done until World War I in our home, at least Mother's
         diet was so limited, She'd had her babies fast and without aWeat deal of care.
         So Mother was never well, and the Sunday visitors many times were a great burden to
         her. She always said two things that stuck in my mind: One of them was that a
         man had six days of work and on the seventh he did chores, and he went maybe to
         the neighbors on special errands like castrating the calves or something^ 'cause
         that"could be done on horseback but to a woman there were sexgn days of work, be
         cause on Sunday she had company in good weather and in bad weather it was not
         suitable to go any place in the rain or snow or cold. The other thing she said
         was that a female animal before giving birth or even before conception, was given
         a little time to rest and be ready for her inner chores, but a woman had her child
         ren when she was depleted physically and conceived most easily. She thought the
         reason for this was nature's way of perpetuating the race. If this female was
         going to die, she could surely repooduce first. By weakest, I think she felt-12-
         that she understood it as the fact that she seemed to conceive when she was, in
         her words/'run down! When she was tired and least physically fit to handle the
         business of having a child, then was when she conceived. And she had her first
         three children in about five years, less than five years. Then there was a space
         of three and then there was a space of four, and she prevented, she felt, con
         ception by nursing her children overlong; because as long as she nursed a child
         she cUfc't conceive.  course, in those days of no restrictions of any
         kind on reproduction, a woman just lived as best she^ could. father said
         to me one time, "I never felt anything but a welcome for one of my children."
         Well, now whefe. children just came whether they were planned for or invited, then
         I think that was quite a statement of character on his part, And it's been greatly
         reassuring to me; because certainly as number five, when it took my mother forty
         eight hours to bring me into the world with the longest and most painful of del
         iveries, I would not have known life had it been a planned family. I have known
         more than one offspring that was the flower of the flock that was born lafeer. My
         mother, of course, was just thirty when I came, but there is an illustrious fam
         ily in Moscow- whose name I shall not give because I'm going to tell some sec
         rets. -?M this dear lady was to have_her fifth child and she did not want it.
         But here she was pregw -again. In the family way; they called it then. Well,
         she went club of 8 nice lady friends here in Moscow on a picnic down
         to Kendrick. She climbed a tree and jumped off. She did it repeatedly. She
         thought maybe she'd miscarry. Arte fci this day and age where abortion is sup
         posed to be fully accepted, I do want to say that the Lord kept that baby for
         her and he went on to be. probably as illustrious a son at this community has
         ever produced, having later been president of the Ford Foundation, Dean of the
         Business School at Harvard and presently lives in New York. I speak of him
         only with admiration. Jfttil I tell this story only because one of her peers told
         it to me as an illustration of what nature does for the human family when therec
         is no planning.
         
         I would like to go back for a moment and talk about my mother as a lonely
         woman on the farm. She could see no light in any window o- another white woman
         from her house. She could see way across the Clearwater River over toward Ruebens
         and Look Out^and sometimes we could see a light from over there and with the field
         glasses we could distinguish buildings. But the Rueben ranch house was hidden
         from ours by the trees, and besides that, it was never inhabited by anyone but a
         hired cook during harvest. No Indian woman ever lived there and no white woman
         ever lived there, during my memory. This had occurred earlier, but during my
         memory. Up north of us on the Connor place from time to time there would be a
         woman, but the house was just up around *, bend, so it could not be^seen from our
         place. SIR Mother was accustomed to daily company. Her father had had a grocery
         storg,and meat market and later a'factory back in Gladwin, Michigan^before theyJ
         migrated West. She was accustomed to people. So, the other day I ran onto a
         catalogue which was, I think called the Jolly Jokers, , no,that isn't the correct
         name— I'll hunt it up one of these days. This catalogue was of a club of lonely
         people who wished to correspond with each other over the whole surface of the
         globe. tggdmSQ Mother joined it— it cost a big fat ten dollars! But she joined
         the club and geography came alive for us children^, because there was Mr . Jones
         down in Quito, Ecuador^, who sent her gifts and sent her interesting letters,' and
         the gifts would be such things as the carving of the local water carrier, or a
         lovely embroidered doily, that if enough such doilies were put together, a pretty
         hand-embroidered hart" could be made. Or such— this was sent as a sample of the
         handwork of the Indian women ?- the area. Or there might have been* a girl whose
         last name was Magna laughter, and she was from Denmark. jsbA c^he sent Mother
         a piece of handwoven linen which I still have, and which is as heavy, almost, as
         foil, for thickness and strength of texture. Or. there was a young man in Tunis.
         There various people who sent her the sands of local fivers so that she had anc
         enormous collection of the sands of the rivers of the world. SliSSaRlTf Ve knew
         about the Dnieper, we knew about the Amazon, we knew about the Ganges, we knew
         about the Marne, we knew about the rivers on the surface of the earthy because
         Mother had a little sample ofjsand'taken from right alongside that flowing water.
         This was delightful for us all, and it made the mail such an.important thing because
         scarcely did Dad get on horseback and go to town (because there was no rural
         j delivery in the early timej and get the mail and inside would be all of these delights.
         My mother's mind was always alert and curious and enjoying. And no mat
         ter if it was a stray of any kind who tied his horse at our front gate and came
         up to be fed ""because of course you fed any human being who came to your door^
         because, otherwise they would have to go hungry because there were no restaur
         ants around, of course, in easy access. So anytime somebody needed bed or
         board, any human being gave it to em. you gave them what you hadj aaak if
         it was very limited that was never questioned. 4ndScarcely did anyone ever of
         fer to pay. This was beside the point. The point was, that Mother would have
         somebody to visit with for a while. Anil no matter who it was«if there were some
         that she just couldn't find mucts of interest in, but mostly Mother could find
         something to visit with . .in this traveling person.  usually
         housed the school teacher who taught about half way down the Coyote Grade, what
         they later named Rattlesnake College. Aflt she usually had one or two hired men
         at her table. Her htcake griddle could bake six large cakes at a time, and of
         course, the main staple of any good workingman's breakfast was something that
         stuck to his ribs—called a good hotcake. Dad always had smoked, cured meat so
         it would be bacon or ham, hotcakes and fried eggs for breakfast with lots of
         homemade syrup. ^SM. That was a good enough meal for anybody. And all the
         people could work on it, go to school on it, $er starve to death on it, if her
         name was Le[a Jain.~) that's the way we lived as for diet in the winter
         timei. I knew at the time it was difficult for Mother, but now that I'm a grown
         person, how much more I empathize with the maladjustment in which she lived,
         and how hard it must have been on my father who held her dear and had to witness
         all this and at the same time, never could have a shoulder-to-shoulder companion who
         earned with1 egg's and butter and produce, and who also was a constant
         drain for doctors' bills.
         
         I'd like to talk a little more about the Indians I have known, because I
         left that subject. Just over from our farm was 
         three 'ps' in the pron unciation because that's the way I was taught. He was
         an Indian man who came up to his eighty— that's eighty acres alloted by the gov
         ernment—with his two squaws each summer. His place, the Connor place the
         Rueben place, like all Indian homes had a dooryard utterly alive with hollyhocks,
         which only allowed for tramped-down paths to and from the door, to the house and
         to the toilet and to the barn. Otherwise, they grew all over the place. And
         hollyhocks, to me are Nez Perce flowers. Peopeqtalk but we said Peopeopatalik
         however it was, he came up in the summer and once in a while he'd come up and visit
         with my dad who was great friend^ of all the Indians. Another Indian who came
         to visit us was Charlie White. He was a halfbreed and a handsome large man who
         was a great baseball catcher in later timesy and played on the same team with
         my husband, who was a kid from Gifford, and at sixteen was a hired second baseman.
         Charlie played for free with the Lapwai. or Spalding teams on Four of July and
         stock shows and such celebrations would come through the warm weather, and
         my husband,Guy Wicks,would be hired to come down and^'given twenty dollars on
         the Fourth of July to beef up the excellence of the hitting staff, (chuckles)
         Charlie's background is illustrative of the scarcity of white women who came
         West. Men were more adventuresome and they came first, and then there were no
         women around, save Indian women. Well, Charlie's mother was a maiden of great
         worth because she not only had two children by this early day settler- who later
         married in full legality the daughter of a lovely white family that came West,
         and had another family that was housed and still lives'in Lewiston. They are-16-
         a distinguished family and I shall not identify any further. But this Indian
         woman was put asid^ when her husband fell in love and could marry this
         lirtjpp white girl. This silly story was told and I don't believe it for a minute;
         but it does carry a certain punch— that when the Indian woman didn't get proper
         care, or had a disagreement, she just mosied down the river with her tepee and
         pitched"in the yard of the white woman, and things came her way, but quickly.
         Now, I think that's just a good story, but it is a funny one.(laughter) The
         imagry is very good, isn't it? Well, Charlie was one of two of her children.
         Later she married an army man. who was a very early settler, and had another
         child by him. And I don't think it hurts to tell his name because his father
         was Tom Beall. There's a creek named for him down between Lapwai and Spalding
         and his wife was this same Indian woman.
         
         Now, I've found Indians in their adjustment to our culture in my own way
         n working with PTA "There was an Indian woman who was the president of the
         Lapwai unit of PTA when I was district president and going around and yisimi^
         all the units,, and-she was a high class Indian woman. But she simply couldn't get
         to meetings on time—forty ..minutes late was par. She had her problems. Her little
         daughter whose picture is still a lovely thing on -ee postcards and is emblematic
         of beautiful Nez Perce maidenhood, broke her mother's heart by running away during
         high school days and going up to Coeur d'Alene with her boyfriend and distres
         sing her family no end. Her son came to the Uniersity and pledge^Tau Kappa
         Epsilon- and was a star basketball player for some time, but he didn't get a
         degree. He married well, however— he married the daughter of a fine white fam
         ily from up the road always * who nearly died at the match. But in due time this
         young Indian man was in a bar and someone provoked his anger and he took a
         swing at them. Well, the fellow didn't like being swung at, and he swung back
         and hit this chap square on the tip of his chin. The fellow fell backward, dead.
         He'd been hit by a trick punch, which is known to boxers 4Pf the man who finds
         this punch fatal is called a man with a glass jaw. 4Hi ahr friend's son was
         dead. There was a grandchild, and at the funeral of this young man, the white
         in-laws came ,and that was the first time that the Indians and whites had mixed.
         Now this is within the last ten . fifteen years. So the amalgamations and the
         melting of races and the assumptions of cultures is still a very living struggle.
         Now, let's see.what other Indians have I known that are colorful? I told
         you about Rueben and Connor and Peopeotalktp $egp I think those are the main
         ones. There are other stories regarding the scarcity of women. Another man
         who was a big-time cattle man, and who has descendants living, so I shan't name
         him kad a mistress named Brocky Jack. He took her out of a house, and she
         had had smallpox at sometime and her face was greatly pocked, so they said she
         was brockied, which I guess means deeply freckled or speckled. Jack
         was very conscious of her lack of status. We had some friends named Vernon
         who were very proud people, and Mrs. Vernon could sew-* So Brocky Jack, the story
         goes, would bring a pattern, material, thread, etc. and put it on the post of
         thexgate and ride away. Mrs. Vernon would then come out of her house, go down
         and get the dress makings, and take them inside and in due time produce a gar
         ment. I suppose there was a note accompanying rey=*/~d'Tq measurements, or maybe
         the pattern sufficed, I don't know; but then the garment was placed on the gate
         post and Brocky Jack drove back or rode back and picked up the dressr So there '
         never was any personal contact. This, I imagine, was a matter of pride with
         Brocky Jack quite as much as Mrs. Vernon. She was not about to be snubbed. And
         t don't think, knowing Mrs. Vernon, that she would 
         Now there's another Indian story that I wish to tell because it hurt me to
         see this happen. Jane Silcott was the daughter of Chief Timothy, and she was
         married to Silco+t, Captain Joseph Silctt, who was Snake River boat captain. She
         died and he buried her where her grave could look up the Snake River at the con
         fluence of the Snake and the Clearwater RiverS For many years that tall, white
         shaft was there. Mil Ve all thought of the fact that here was a white man who
         had loved his wife enough to mark her grave in such a knowing way. But in due
         time vandals came and ripped down the monument and descrated the grave, and now
         there is nothing but harvest over the place where this touching monument used
         to be.
         
         I have another story about Jane Silcett and her husband. A friend of mine
         was a seventeen year old boy and working around the Raymond House, an early day
         hotel in Lewiston, and from the train one day. came a distinguished lady from
         the East who said she had come to visit her brother; Joseph SilcerH:. Well, word
         was sent to Joseph Silcoft, and he came in all dressed up and took his sister to
         dinner, he took her for rideS, he entertained her as royally as Lewiston afforded
         for several days. And th^A put her on the train and sent her home, never having
         taken her back to his house or having introduced her to his wife. Whether she
         ever knew that he was married to an Indian woman is quite doubtful/ because she
         was made happy as could be, and perhaps there was never a question in her mind.
         Now, let's see what other stories I have here.
         
         Oh, when I was a little girl during World War i, and we were busy growing
         food for those big brothers overseas, I trapped squirrels. Igot anicking a tail
         and a dime for a weasel, and lots of times I got snakes, I never got a rattler
         though. m I learned that I could take a little scout size axe and dispatch
         the squirrels, protesting and fighting for their little lives, caught in those
         traps, mm. I pull 'em by their poor little caught legs from where they'd
         frantically try to stay down the hole; that I could pull them forth and dispatch
         them, because after all, I had to preserve the fcocj for our boys, was a
         terrible lesson for a little girl to have to learn, but learn it I did. I took
         the money from those squirrels' tails and sent to Sears Roebuck and got myself a
         ukelele. I learned four chords, and Oh, my! if I couldn't sing up a storm with
         that instrument, (chuckles) -$d we also had an old fashioned phonograph that
         my parents had bought at Beal-i's store in Gene 5ee. This store had formerly been
         owned by had such delightful records, as Uncle Josh
         and the Chinese Laundry',1 and the Harrigan^'and later I found at my grandparents
         "The Whistler and His Dog" , and"In the Good Old Summertime". J—1B1 having
         learned to play this instrument, I went over to the Rueben ranch and somebody had
         left there another phonograph, and on it was "The Whole Dam Family"?-I-be-dam.''
         and "you* be -dam„. and the whole iaPan?- Family. Jfcftri When it came time for me
         to go to
         town and be sent to Sunday School, and eventually to school, my mother told me
         very carefully not to sing "Old Dan Tucker was a Good Old Man, washed his face
         in a frying pan, combed his hair with a wagon wheel, and died with a toothache
         in his heel." Because I said Old Dan Hailey did this, and Dan Hailey was a very
         respectable and well liked neighbor^ feet ihe hired man had taught me the wrong
         words, (chuckles) And so of course, on the I Be Damned song, I didn't dare
         sing that for Sunday School and it was very hard not too, because they wanted
         verses, and they wanted songs, and those were the only ones I knew, (laughter)
         Can you imagine how my mother must have suffered wondering what I'd do? About
         this time we got the telephone. Now, I hadn't gone to school yet when we got
         the telephone, and the wire came from a rackedcp pole and the pole was just an
         chored so carefully with great boulders at the corner of our field, and then
         that heavy wire swung clear^ across that vast canyon over to the other side to
         another well-anchored pole. There were nineteen people on our J\'.re, and our
         ring was two longs and two shorts, and it din't ring at n^^rtf., or it didn't
         ring for long distance unless there was death or disaster. However, one time,
         it did: It rang at night and my father got up, and I can see him yet in his
         long underweajfand all of us children dashing out of bed, down stairs to find
         outrwhat terrible thing had happened. Well, it was long distance from Spokane,
         ane a young man who was the son of Reverend Stephen Rueben*, litis name was Louis.
         And he said,"Walter?", "Yes." "This is Louis Rueben." "Yes." "I am incarcerated
         in the Spokane county jail." "You are? What'd you get in trouble about?" "Well,
         they have me here— now, Walter, you know I'm the original aborigine." "Yeah, I
         know that. Well, they have me incarcerated for intr ing liquor on the Nez
         Perce Reservation, and I need twenty dollars, Walter. I need it soon."
         (chuckles) Well, of course, any landlord is, from time to time, to have a
         little good will, and public relations demand a little cash from time to time,
         but twenty dollars was enormous. That was'equivalent of a steer, il don't rem
         ember how my father solved this, but I do remember that my brother, who also
         rented from Indians^ several years later had an amusing incident happen to him
         along these very lines.
         
         fen years older than I He was renting this Indian land, and in the sixth
         grade he'd gone to school down at this country school down the canyon road with
         some girls "I thinkthet name was Andrews or Alexander or something, a white name
         anyway, and there were two of 'em, and they were all in the same grade with Ben.
         here'came, years later, as grown people they were the landladies and he was
         a prospective renter and ije wanted to do business with them, to rent some of
         their land, up the Clearwater out of Lenore. WHS. 'the girls couldn't speak
         English, they had to have an interpreter. Well, of, course, what it was, they
         were givmj some of their boyfriends a little government money by interpreting.
         Why, it was just normal, they'd learned white mens ways^-they weren't dumb —
         and so they had the interpreter there. Well, all the business went on through
         the interpreter. But from time to time the girls would see Ben in Lewiston or
         lapwaior Spalding, or some place, and they'd hit him up for a little money.
         WBM he'd give 'em a few dollarsjand good will remained at a high point. 
         rtlftS- Sunday the family was having dinner when rattle-ty-bang into the dooryard
         came this old Ford with one of the girls and two quite high Indian bucks, and
         they were all having a very fine time, indeed. Ben left his dinner table
         and went down to visit with 'em a minute, 0t this Indianfsaid, "Pen" (don't
         make a B sound, it's kind of a P sound) "Pen, Emily would like to have a little
         money." Ben said, "Well, gee, she^shit me up in Lewiston twice this week, (Slat
         ought to be enough for now. I guess, maybe not today." "Oh, she would like it
         very much." "Well, I'll tell you, it's getting a little heavy." 
         looked across this very jovial driver and looked merrily at Ben ami said, "Ah,
         Pen, give me a couple of bucks and scram t hell out of here." (chuckles)
         After that, it just didn't hold to have an interpreter! (Laughter)
         Ben served at a completely pagan funeral while he lived on that place. He
         said that his neighbor died, and he was not a Christian Indian. They hired Ben
         to bring his team and the running gears of his wagon downjand they just laid a
         couple of boards across the* two sets of wheels, you see, the running gears. And
         the old Indian was rolled in his blanket, his good hat, his quirt, his bridle,
         his saddle, his saddle blanket, were all with him, And up the hill they went to
         where a grave was dug and he was laid in the ground. The Indians are very faith
         ful to one of their dead. Arad "the house was full of friends and relatives. The
         women absolutely, just as in the old days. sister-in-law
         didn't go, feefr the widow of the dead man gave away everything in that house, and
         when she didn't have enough possessions to give away, she had some gifts at hand,
         like dress length of new material or something. A dress length of cotton mater
         ial was sent to my sister-in-la^ 4mWBen for what he had done to help with
         the funeral5 was given a beautiful pair of buckskin gloves, made by the widow.
         *Bl When the day was over, she not only did not have her husband amymore, she
         had no possessions. Now- that was a completely pagan funeral, and the only one
         t U*' I ve known of one of the family having a part^f. Most of the Nez Perces were
         converted by Reverend Spalding and his followers. -4flG ithis has an amusing after
         math which I'll not tell today because I'm not going to get all this material
         I had quite interesting experiences with hired men and bunkhouses. Being
         the daughter of the family and just a little kid, I was allowed free access every
         where. And I didn't go up into the bunkhouse too much because in the first place
         it didn't smell good, those unwashed socks didn't leave exactly a pleasant aroma
         And Dad would store his seed corn up there, and the mice'd get in in the wint
         er and they have a distinctive odor. However, up there I learned to braid three
         strand and four strand and six strand, and there were certain seasons when it was
         empty; then, of course, it would be full, and I was not encouraged to go near it.
         i^ it was right in connection with our house. The bunkhouse was connected to
         the house by a breezeway, which Dad eventually built a shed over, and under the
         bunkhouse was a very fine cellar fh5Cf~ he built with walls, oh, eighteen inches
         to two feet thick, J$mt this kept the cream nice and the milk and butter in hot
         test weather, it was always in quite nice shape—properly provided for in the
         cellar. The doors were double and triple a«d with their padding, and so the
         heat was kept out, and the roof v the bunk house. The men^feading in the
         bunkhouse was of a variety that my mother didn't condone. Now it wasn't that
         it was dirty or four letter words used/ because these men were not dirty mouthed
         people at all; but it was a cheap variety of magazine, like the Blue Book and the
         Topnotch, and mostly Western stories, not especially'written, *e*gh there was a
         lot of Zane Grey mingled in with it. which Mother didn't recommend to me, but
         which she didn't forbid me. However, she forbade me to have anything to do with
         Horatio Alger, that was too cheap. Now, Gene Stratton Porter, I read with great
         pleasure. The Girl_of the Limberlqst and the Harvester, were very mild little
         love stories with lots of nature lore that Mother said I could have. JMff I had
         a delightful time the last summer we were there -no not the last summer, but one
         of the later summers -because we had a hotbloaded thorobred. called Ruby, and she
         was such a high spirited animal that I couldn't ride her any place but within the
         field, or within the dooryard. They wouldn't" let me out on the road with her,
         'cause she could take Kbit and go. 4m %o I rode her to keep the cows out of
         some grain. Dad had a strip of spring wheat that he kept the cows in good shape
         with, and there wen fifteen cows and one bull, and I herded them twice a day all
         summer on Ruby. And my dear delight was to get a Topnotch to read while I did-23-
         my little chore. 
         
         And if, by any chance I could have found a nicklja, and could
         have bought a Centennial chocolate it was one chocolate in a box, all by itself,
         and it had the most .delicious cream inside, often with black walnuts, sprinkled
         in the delicious thingTand I would manage to make that last almost an hour
         until it melted in my hands, and then read Topnotch, and still be away and by my
         self like that, and doing my work, why, that was a combination beyond compare.
         fp Of course, stock  interesting. Father did not encourage us to name animals,
         because pretty soon theyd...to be butchered or sold, or something, and 
         they were part of the business, it wasn't welL thsTchildren got their
         heart-strings too attached many times named the cows for the wife of the
         man wo'd sold it to us. Now this made for amusing situations Oh, Rosie got
         in the fence this morning* Ch[, old Minnie had her calf last n|4kt, or something
         like that. And it was a source of amusement to us, a little cruel, but all right.
         This1/summer, I named most of the cows;movie stars. There was Mary
         Pickford, and Norma Talmadge,  Coleen More and Pearl White and just the whole
         gamut of people'I had had a nick to go to the Saturday show and get acquainted
         m We didn't know whether to name the bull Francis X.Bushman or
         Brigham Young, but both names we knew who we were talking ahsut when we named
         them. (laughter) And that's mainly my story about cows. We've got lovely
         stories about horses, however. Prince was the first horse that I remember. He
         was a bald-faced roan, and the sweetest old dumper of a riding horse you ever
         saw. He practically raised my two older brothers and older sister. When the
         little fellows would get to fighting on his back, and one would get pushed off,
         the remaining rider couldn't get Prince to budge 'tilf he had two fellows on his
         back. Hwi that saved many a worry for Mother. Because she knew that the children
         wouldn't get ir.. trouble because Prince would bring 'em home. There was another
         horse that we loved, everybody loved; she was Madge and she was a white Apa-loosa.
         We had bought her from a homesteader who Kftd been snowed in on his claim and had
         kept her alive through a winter by baking white bread. She could eat it she
         couldn't eat flour, but she could eat white bread, and the^l kept her alive through
         the winter. So she was a dear, pink-nosed, light-eyed pet. And of all the people
         who adored her, Ben was the main one. As a matter of ,fact, Ben gave me her
         bridle not five years ago and I have it here'to give to the muse um when we get a
         barn section, laying to me, "Here's something old, Gracie. I never found another
         animal that was good enough to wear it." 
         
         He, as a sweet, tenderhearted little
         boy, aged about ten, fell in love with Madge. Aar %he was his horse, "fefd He
         tended her, he curried her, he babied her with special food, and he loved her.
         Well, one day we went to town for Decoration Day (and 11 speak of Decoration
         Days nexty. mien we got home, there was a little colt, a beautiful Apjaloosa,
         but Madge was dead. She'J had her colt and she hadn't survived. HRQ. Ben told
         me when when he gave*ne. he./; bridle how terrible it had been for him to see Madge
         with a rope put around her neck and dragged out and down into the canyon, which
         was the burial she got. He said, gust like so much garbagerflow his little heart
         had bled. Now Prince was buried, he was buried under a thorn bush}and I can
         find it to this day. He was properly buried, but Madge was just dragged'over the
         edge of the canyon. I suppose Dad was very bus^ or he certainly would never
         have done this that way. MmH ^e never knew quite where Madge was, but Prince's
         place is still marked. There were other horses but few of them that took the
         places of these two. I also have a story of a mad dog—a mad coyote—it was.
         People lived on the Rueben ranch ^md this was before I can remember much about it}
         who were white, named Treutman, fi0t Mr. Troutman went out after the cow one morn
         ing and took his little boy with him. As they went out past 6. straw stack,
         out past the end of barn= which my father owned, to get the cow, a coyote in
         most unusual fashion, loped right up to th^ little boy and bit him an the cheek.
         Before the father could prevent it, or anything, that child was bit^fri the cheek.
         Well, of course he,-dispatched the coyote, and it s mouth was frothing and it ob--25-
         vi.ously was infected by rabies. Well, they took the little boy, who became
         violently ill, to the Toomey Hospital in Genesee, mmh he lived for some time.
         stead ^he wound healed to ascab the size of agrain of wheat, anurse later told
         me, and then he went mad and had a horrible death. Our dogs, at that time
         were Stub and Jack,and i the only times I've ever known that they were kept in
         at night-and this was in the granary-was in that trying interlude, 4MB Wnen
         they were out, they were muzzled for fear they would infect another animal or
         bite one of us children. Because if rabies were rampant, then, of course,
         every living creature was vulnerable. This was a very trying time, as I rem
         ember it. It was only later that I talked to the nurse who was aneighbor of
         ours and learned about how close the little boy had co«ie to healing in the
         course of the terrible disease. %^mm^^^mme t that time there was no
         Pasteur or tta^udlup«b serum or anything— rabies were just fata^ *'you
         got it in a rat population or a squirrel population, or a coyote population,
         you just had to live with it until you could dispatch all^the infected animals.
         Time does march on, and the world does get better in many ways.
         I remember when electricity came to our home. Of course, we just had the
         center cord come down with a light on it, but Mother did insist on some pretty
         shades. *. She 4Bi use/high powered globes, which many of our friends did not.
         «t We were all readers in our family and we had to have light, she felt. **
         ve read a great deal of the classics, so that the fine print of the classic books
         had to be seen to be read. ** so she had the electric lights in that fashion.
         It was, Ithink,^ 1916 when we got electric l4ght^ ^ the man who wired our ho^se
         was named Walter; he was very handsome and he got acrush on my older sister, but
         it didn't last long. State was agreat boon to us, amPSZther wanted an electric
         washer: But how to get an electric washer? Well, she had another horse I should
         tell you about. His name was Follow Me. He had been trained by adear friend-26-
         named Jim Vernon to follow Mr. Vernon every place that Mr. Vernon went as long
         as he carried a whip. And Follow Me was a large Clydesdale, in part, so that
         it gave him large bones and he was about fifteen hands high. Mother didn't have
         a fancy buggy. She had a utility, four-wheeled vehicle that she could take the
         he * cream can and the egg crate and the raspberry crate or the cherry @¥*fee and
         a
         couple of children and go to town, MtSi. . Mother was always dainty and pretty,
         and she would get her face made up mt her false switch on mmm her hat set just
         right and her makeup wound up with Cream d' Camelia , and oh she smelled so
         good and she looked so pretty, -*wd then she'd put on a duster to keep her costume
         nicely free of dust for when she got to town fro die her trading. As a little
         girl I also had a duster that I wore, and oh. I remember getting all tricked
         out ready to go to town, amd then that dust along that dirt road would just %Ht
         on my pretty little shoes and jpa* on my duster.-0k When we'd get to town, we'd
         just have to be brushed and shaken thoroughly, and then we'd leave the dusters in
         the rig while we went down town with our dresses as nicely starched and ironed
         as they could be after six miles or five miles, whatever it was, of going through
         the heat to town. The only thing was. that I was a delicate child, and no matter
         what I ate at my grandmother's at noon, if I had the slightest treat like a little
         icecream cone from the confectionery named Smoltt, all the way home from *MK
         cemetery on ^usually Iaw88*d have to vomit,assi I would have a headache, awd it
         was nothing but nerves from the terrific excitement of getting to go to town.
         this day I love the fact that we have closed, warm cars for transportation.
         . the weather can't keep us home and disappoint the very living daylights
         of us, like it did when I was a child, (chuckles)
         
         Well, Mother was a charming person}and she would entertain us with obser
         vations and human interest stories as we'd ride along. MS Since she was such
         a lonely person she used as companions the ears of her children. And we got allc
         the lore from her former home in Michigan,and when letters came we kept up with
         the births and deaths and marriages and engagements and everythihg else of her
         friends back there. 40fi pn these rides, when there'd be the time just to put in
         while Follow Me took us to town and brought us home, ^Sy she would just regale
         us with one delight after another. Follow Me had a certain area where he was
         king. And that was coming up a portion of the road which still is there, but
         has just a little flat place as you climb rather a steep hill. In this flat
         place, where Mother could easily put her foot on the brake and hold the buggy,
         Follow Me knew that .... he'd get a little when he would approach
         this flat placer" really, swish, swish, swish, would go his tail back and forth,
         remind,ree4: lady driver behind him that it was time, "4mfr~w* she'd put her foot
         on the brake and laugh and give him a rest. Many times as he switched to go
         forward he would break wind mightily, and we would have to protect ourselves
         from anything that was liquid thereof, but up the hill he would go, (laughter)
         not expecting another rest tiU he got to our upper gate. Jdl- then whatever
         child was there -not a little girl like me, but my brother four years
         older ."was the one to open the gate, and then down the road past the locust
         and the walnuts we would gofask then we'd see the light of home and the smoke
         coming out the chimney, and was that A. nice welcome, I'll tell you that was
         home and love and comfort. And-yet, I can remember many times when we came
         home, and all of us were along, and so we came into a cold house. We had to
         light the lighlS, wa-4i«""tre go out and gather kindling and chips, come in and
         build a fire, heat water and Mother;make biscuits, iatft it took quite a little
         while to get the comfort going. How simple it is these days, and how different
         from then.
         
         My father was so sweet about his yard,aiways. He planted lilacs; he planted
         yellow roses; he planted a climber rose; he planted trees for shade; and he tended
         them carefully. Out in the back, near where my play box of sand was, and my
         little playhouse was, was a row of locusts and in front of them— oh, yes,
         many syringas—were a row of beehives, and we had our own honey. Mother didn't
         do outside work, and she didn't have her daughters out in the field or the corral
         or the garden, either. It gave a girl a big^s^feefe- to do heavy work and she wasn't
         about to have her daughters in that realm of activity at all, and we never were
         hired girls to the neighbors. The neighbors came to house, but never did we
         work for anyone else. This was her little pride.
         
         So when, from time to time, Mother would get all bundled up with a wide
         brimmed hat and a veil and one of Dad's coats and long, long skirts and gloves,
         a«d ties at the bottoms of her sleeves, and ties around her neck, we'd know she
         was going to hive a swarm of bees. This she often, and this she did well, imek
         ^he never was stung. This was fortunate, because we learned much later that she
         was allergic to bee sting, venom. This came about whenvshe went back to the
         farm to help harvest the honey, and was just staying all night in Dad's bachelor
         diggings,""^8d hey were working with the honey, and she had a five gallon kerosene
         oil tin which Dad had cut out the head of and had pounded down so that it was a
         lovely big, clean container. 4gg§: they put the honeycomb in the comb
         would stay on top and the honey would drain down into the bottom. it was
         simply delicious with her biscuits made of sour cream or sweet cream and served
         with homemade butter and that good honey, I'll tell you-ambrosia. Well,
         this particular time, Mother was washing a five gallon container, and a dead bee
         .ntSt  clung to the edge of the container from the year before's use, she
         swished her cloth and the sud.s of the water around to wash the container, her
         ring finger on her right hand came in contact with the stinger of that dead bee
         and it gp*ffg her; ohe got the venom from the dead stinger-  and Site was so vio
         lently ill that Dad had to cut her corset strings and bring her to town immediately
         she nearly died. Now the rest of us.we had been stung a pillionc
         times, but Mother should have never been stung. She just wasn't very well suited
         to the life she lived.
         
         Oh, yes, I did too, hire out to the neighbors. It was after we lived in
         town. And what I did, was make a layette for the lady next door, and she paid
         me for embroidering all the pretties on the baby's little nighties and sacks
         and hug-me-tights, and all the little robes and things. I loved to embroider.
         I've got a hankie here that I crochetad on when I was four years old. I have a
         pillow top that I worked on whilA I was younger than that, though I don't know
         how much younger. As wien the big ladies would be doing their needlework, wh ,
         of course I wanted to to^ and I learned to knit and crochet r.aand
         do all the things that I still enjoy doing, if I only had the eyes to do it
         all, just like they did. "Hi I prettied that layette, and then I got so I dusted
         and vacuumed for heranctshe paid me ten cents an hour for all this. I was in
         high school. But that's not the lowest wage I ever got. In the early twenties
         I was night operator.— well, let's see, this was the summer of 1925— I was
         night operator of the telephone company. It was a local company, and my father
         was a director and was able to pull strings to get his daughter a job. I worked
         for thirty dollars a month. And I went on Saturday night to take up my duties
         at nine o'clock, and I didn't leave the place until seven o'clock Monday morning.
         The way the hours worked out I made nine cents an hour. I was terrified in some
         aspects of this job. because in a thunderstorm every key there came down on that
         switchboard. An-if a woman was expecting—a-baby*rand of course everybody knew
         everybodyr I'd get calls saying, "Gracie, what time is it? Is it time to take
         my bread outj The clock stopped." Or they would say, "Will you look up in the
         Sears Roebuck catalogue and tell me what's on page eleven?' The page is missing."
         Or some such thing. Well, I remember one violent thunderstorm when the keys were
         just playing a dance on that keyboard—switchboard— one of the older girls in-30-
         high school was having a baby, and they called for the doctor, and I had to
         plug in on that lively switchboard,, and I was terrified. The electricity was
         off and I had to hand grind the ring, but I got her the doctor all right. My
         bed was pulled up right under the protruding counter of the switchboard and I
         slept right there, and in the daytime I made the bed and %pushed it over next
         to the wall. The sanitary facilities were out back,' and it was an unfinished
         attic that went clear up two stories, and bats inhabited that place. SM at
         night, if I felt the call of nature I was terrified going out there to that
         constantly running little- old toilet. And**?, I would suffer until daylight
         came, if possible. Otherwise, there were many fringe benefits in the job. I
         had a beau who was across the street in the bank.
         
         (End of Side C)
         
         
      </transcript>
      <rights>Digital format copyright: University of Idaho Library. Original Copyright: Latah County
         Historical Society
      </rights>
      <fmt>audio</fmt>
      <usage></usage>
      <userestrict>0</userestrict>
      <xmllocation></xmllocation>
      <xmlfilename>13534</xmlfilename>
      <previous>Wicks1</previous>
      <next>Wicks3</next>
      <disp_name>Wicks2</disp_name>
      <collection_link>https://www.lib.uidaho.edu/digital/lcoh/</collection_link>
      <series_link></series_link>
   </record>
</ROOT>
